He will be a staff for the righteous with which for them to stand and not to fall.
And he will be the light of the nations and the hope of those whose hearts are troubled.
All who dwell on the earth will fall down and worship him, and they will praise and bless
and celebrate with song the Lord of Spirits, 1st denoc, chapter 48, verses 4-5.
The modern world doesn't acknowledge but is nevertheless haunted by spirits, angels,
demons and saints.
In our time, many year into break free of the prison of a flat, secular materialism,
to see and to know reality as it truly is.
What is this spiritual reality like?
How do we engage with it well?
How do we permeate everyday life with spiritual presence?
Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew Stephen Damick, and Father Stephen De Young
host this live Colin show focused on enchantment in creation.
The union of the scene and unseen as made
by God and experienced by mankind throughout history.
Welcome to the Lord of Spirits.
Good evening and welcome back to the Lord of Spirits podcast
and welcome to our first anniversary episode.
It's been a whole year.
My co-host Father Stephen D. Young is with me
from Lafayette, Louisiana.
And I am Father Andrew Stephen,
David and Emma is Pennsylvania.
And if you're listening to us live,
you can call in at 855 AF Radio.
855-237-234
or six, Bobby will be taking your calls tonight,
which we will get to in the second part of today's show.
So before I get to my intro,
Father Stephen and I wanted to take a moment
to mention why our regular engineer,
Matroska Trudy is not with us tonight.
This past Sunday, her husband, Father Anastasi Richter,
known familiarly as Father Stacey,
as he was preparing to serve the divine liturgy
collapsed in the altar.
at St. Elizabeth Orthodox Church in Chesterton, Indiana, where he was the pastor.
He was rushed to the hospital but soon pronounced dead.
He was just 52 years old and leaves behind not only Montesca Trudy but their three daughters as well as a shocked and grieving parish.
If you would like to help the family in this time of sudden grief, a GoFundMe page has been set up for you to make donations.
Now we've shared the link on our Facebook page.
but you can also go to the Go Fund Me website and do a search on Richter that's spelled R-I-C-H-T-E-R
and you should see the fundraiser come up.
Whatever else you can do, please say a prayer for the resting of his soul
and also for the comfort of his family, his friends, and his parish.
Thanks, everyone.
So we've been on the air for a full year now and for this episode,
we are going to be talking about the great biblical patriarch Abraham
And as we...
love to do on Lord of Spirits, we are heading deep into the ancient world to more than 2,000
years before the birth of Jesus Christ for Abraham lived about as distant from that event
as we ourselves do.
Now usually when people think of the ancient world, they might picture time of primitives,
people living in caves, tribes of hunter-gatherers, lucky get a spark of fire from banging to sticks
together and rocks, that kind of thing.
What is that the kind of...
that Abraham lived in, Father Stephen?
No. No.
So, yeah, in Star Trek Picard season two, they're traveling back to the 21st century AD.
We're going back to the 21st century BC.
Right.
So that means we're better.
And you can stream this for free.
Yeah.
So, you can't have that.
Yeah, so it's actually quite the opposite of that.
We tend to not realize just how organized and efficient and interconnected the ancient
world was.
Right.
The giant's episode we talked about the Bronze Age collapse.
This is, we're not going even further back than that.
already civilization is a thing that exists.
And so the period that Abraham lived in is referred to as the Ur-3 period.
Sometimes also called the Sumerian Renaissance.
Right, which makes me kind of wonder, where is the Sumerian renfair?
Like why is there not a...
Yeah, Renaissance fare for...
There's Sumerian.
Sumerian word for his ah, I think.
Is the issue. How do you know that?
not a Sumerian word.
That's why we've discovered.
Yeah, so this period ran from circa 2112
to about 2004 BC.
So this really is sort of as far back
before Christ as we are after Christ.
Right, 21st century BC versus 21st century AD.
And to sort of explain what the or three period is about and this is still going to be
kind of weird and confusing even after we kind of explain what it's about.
But that's what we do on this podcast, right?
It's sort of some basics of ancient Mesopotamian politics.
This is why you come here.
The region of Mesopotamia, right, which is great for between the rivers, between the
Tiger City Freighties room.
rivers as they flow it down into the Persian Gulf. There were two main regions, Sumer,
which was the southern region, really south eastern, near where the rivers meet the Persian
Gulf. And then the northern region, which is really sort of northwest, which is Ahan, a
KAD.
for people to keep a track.
And so these two regions contained some of the earliest city states in the world.
These individual city states were ruled over by
kings who were seen to be gods, so sort of god kings,
who are also the priests of the
of that city, which was worship generally in a central ziggurat within the city we've
talked about ziggurats before.
And then what happens is politically various cities in those two regions, in either region,
would become sort of politically ascendant at different times.
Yeah.
If folks are interested in the big grand sweep of...
the civilization of this era. We both recommend actually a podcast that we are both fans of,
which is the Fall of Civilizations podcast. They did an episode on the Sumerian Empire, which,
I don't know, it's like three or four hours long, which really gives us something to reach for.
But it's just a really, really well done podcast. It's not a Christian podcast, it's just a history
podcast. But yeah. And it's it's available both as the original audio podcast.
And there's also a YouTube version that has some incredibly stunning HD video and photos
Yeah, like on location in Iraq and and so you can see
Some of these things so either way that is that is worth consuming if you want to spend four hours learning about the whole
Sweep of the history of Sumer and let's face it people listening to this podcast
There's probably at least a good 50 50 chance that they are interested in this
Yes.
Yes, so that's a place where you could go get all that because we're just going to be talking about this little sliver here.
Yeah, all right.
Of this one period.
So through the skill and force of charisma, et cetera, of a given, one of these kings at any given point,
his city would sort of become ascendant and be able to project its will over the other nearby city states of the region.
Yeah, I'm sorry.
right, make them function as vassals to him.
And so the Earth 3 period is called the Earth 3 period
because we used to think that it was the third time
that Ura had become this sort of ascendant quasi-capital city.
Now it turns out, apart from their archaeological research,
But this was only the second time.
There was no or two period.
Yes, so there's one and then there's three.
Right.
But they did change the name.
Yeah.
Because changing it from or three to or two I guess would have been too confusing.
Like having someone on the faculty not named Bruce.
So they just left it as or three even though there's no two it goes from one to three.
So there are actually only these two periods where...
was ascended. But what tended to happen was not that it generally it would be a city in
Sumer or a city in Ahad and culturally whichever region had the ascended city would also
become sort of culturally ascended. Because Ahad was populated by Semitic peoples with
the Semitic language.
So, the Canadian is sort of relates to other
subbidic languages, sort of like the way
Sanskrit relates to Indo-European languages.
Right, right. So, you know, for those of you
don't know, that would be stuff like Hebrew and Arabic
and, you know, the Arabic and Syria.
Yeah, Syria. Right, right. Whereas Sumerian
is this language isolate, meaning that it's
related as far as we know to anything else.
And yet, these two language groups and cultural groups existed right next to each other.
And, and barred each other's words occasionally actually.
So that's fun.
Yeah.
And we're also not sure ethnically what the Sumerians were.
So they're kind of this quasi-bestuers group.
But they were not aliens.
I assure you.
Not ancient aliens everybody.
Not at all.
there are not hilly.
So rather than one of the other cities rising up in a revolution against the currently dominant city,
what tended to happen was that the quasi-imperial reign of one of these cities would fall to a foreign invasion.
There were a number of nomadic peoples both east and west of Sumer and Akhad of Mesopotamia.
And you have these city states,
which were gathering wealth from the whole known world
at the time in one place.
And so those city states would start to make tempting targets.
Yeah.
Foromatic invaders to come and pillage.
Generally, when they came and pillaged,
they would kind of take control of the area,
but it usually wouldn't last long
because they weren't like skilled bureaucrats.
Yeah, right.
It's one thing to take over a city.
It's another thing too.
to try to run it.
So usually they would just sort of occupy it,
take the stuff and then leave,
and then the locals would have to kind of rebuild.
And then meanwhile,
some other city in the area would become the city.
Right, right.
And sometimes it would be one of the kings
of one of the other city states would sort of drive them out.
And then by virtue of being the hero
who got rid of the foreign invaders,
their city would end up becoming the next ascended city.
And that's what we're gonna see happen
in the... in the...
or three period because previous to the or three period there was an Ahadian dynasty
and this is the dynasty that was started by Sargat of Ahad.
It was an actual person.
Yes, not the quasi-political YouTuber, but the actual guy, Rahid Abe himself after.
And that, that dynasty.
collapsed through an invasion by the Gideons who came down from the Zagros Mountains and
invaded and managed to basically destroy the supporting infrastructure that allowed the
city of Akkad to keep the other as vassals.
You have this interconnected chain of tribute being paid in taxes and that kind of thing
They disrupted all that.
So they only actually occupied the area though for about 20 to 25 years and then a good fellow named Uduhengal.
We just don't have good names anymore.
Yeah.
Sumerian names.
So cool.
Uduhengal came and defeated the Gudian king at the time whose name was Tyrigan.
And that then led to...
Ornamo, who was the king of Orr, coming to ascendancy and beginning the third dynasty of
Orr which was actually this second dynasty.
Ornamo figures big in the story that is told on that episode of the Fulves of Eversations
podcast.
Ornamo, part of the reason this is called Dushu Mary and Renaissance is he was actually
apparently a particularly gifted
leader at least materially. So he issues a law code that was very similar to the one that
you're probably more familiar with that Hamarabi issued. Hamarabi is about 500 years later.
Yeah, and it's worth probably taking a moment to mention that law codes at this point,
know 4,000 years ago. We're not like the law codes that we have now.
And like the whole theory was different. It was not, okay, we're gonna establish laws and everyone has to sort of obey them and the King's job is to enforce these laws.
No, it was, this is the stuff the King expects of everybody.
You know, the law was simply just his will on paper, so well, Clay tablets, I guess.
Clay tablets, right? Stone obelisks in the group town.
Yeah, they're more like house rules just like you know parents set house rules and you know it you know if you
have kids, you probably had the kids attempt to enforce the rules against the parents.
Like, no, no, no, no, that's not how the rules work, son.
You know, these rules are an extension of mine, your mother's will.
And that's how that's how laws worked, you know, in the ancient world.
It was like, this is what the king expected.
And he could change it at any time.
Now if he was a smart king, he wouldn't constantly change it.
But the king is the king.
And that's the way that it is.
He's not above the law.
The law is part of him essentially.
Yeah.
He is the law like Judge Grant.
just like judge.
Yeah, but yeah, and and this is important because it affects how we see Old Testament law too
That we get into discussions of it
We tend to treat it like a law code like a system of law or a rule of law
There people who try to pull simple law out of
Right to be the Old Testament law, but it was the same thing, right?
This is the king in the case of Old Testament law Yahweh the God of Israel, right?
the king.
says this is what I expect of you as my vassals and my subjects and this is what
I'm going to do to you if I don't get what I expect from you. And this is what I'm
going to do for you if I do, right? If you're loyal and true and faithful this is
what I will do for you, right? And that's sort of the covenant structure, right?
The covenant structure that's used to the Old Testament is not just an Old
Testament thing. This is a pattern that's followed by...
by the fact that the Book of Deuteronomy
follows very closely a particular form of Hittite,
the Susur and Vassal Treaty.
But yeah, right.
But this is the same kind of thing
when we talk about Ernomu's law code,
it's him saying, here's what I expect for all of you
and here's what's gonna happen if I don't get it.
But then also here are the positive things
that I'm promising, that he would help
aid with their protection from invasion,
that he would sort of share the wealth, right?
See what they'll...
with cultivation and expansion of lands.
Because that's what a smart king does.
Yes, yes.
And in terms of expansion over the,
the or three period, the domain controlled from Sumer
expanded to stretch from the southeastern part of what's
now Turkey, Anatolia or Asia Minor, all the way to Iran.
to Iran.
And not only did they control territory over into what's now Iran, but they conducted
trade, they established trade routes with the civilizations in the Indus River Valley
at this time.
Yeah, so this is basically parts of modern Turkey, Iraq, Iran, kind of that whole area.
Yeah.
And then, yeah, that they were able to set up these sort of stable trade routes to bring
things overland all the way from India.
from what's now India.
And he divided the regions around each city state
into sort of imperial provinces.
The remains of the different kings.
Right, and I mean this is interesting because it's
it's a kind of federalism of sorts, right?
You've got this, or I mean may not federalism,
but it's almost, you know,
you're starting to see complexity of structure,
the likes of which we usually associate
in the ancient world only with ROM.
which I mean, that's centuries upon centuries later.
You already have this kind of regional subsidiary,
a real empire, right, with that's held together
with bureaucracy.
And so it's complex, it's organized,
there's a whole system of economy,
tribute and taxation,
and all the marks of a great civilization.
You've got literature,
and this includes stuff like the Epic of Gilgamesh,
a lot of people interested in the ancient world would know about, which includes a flood
story, because of course all ancient mythologies include flood stories.
And the very, as we've mentioned before on this show, the Sumerian Kings list, which mentions
that Gilgamesh is a giant, right?
Yeah, so it's big, and I actually looked this up.
So the population of the Sumerian Empire, it's height, had about one and a half million
people in it.
But the whole world's population at the time was about 27 million.
So that means that roughly one out of 18 people in the world lived in the Sumerian Empire.
So it was gigantic for that time.
You know, it was big.
And all of this is to say that, again, these are not tribes living in caves, right?
these are cities
city states and sort of governance all functioning together in this vast web. And this is the world that
that Abraham lives in. Right. Yeah. Right. This is the period when he lives in. So he
lived came of age. I mean, when his story really begins, he's 75 years old. Yeah. Right. Right.
So this is the civilization he lived in for 75 years.
Right. This is this is his his time and his
era, sort of before we actually meet him in Genesis. And then so then the
or three periods sort of comes to an end by another forum for an invasion. The
eelomites come and invade. They sort of so chaos managed to occupy parts of
Sumer for 20 odd years again. And then the Martu people who you may remember from
the Giants episode.
The Martu means Westerners basically.
They come from Syria essentially and invade.
These are the biblical amurites.
Right.
People get excited when we talk about amurites.
Yes, and out of the Martu coming in and taking over,
ultimately will come the establishment
of the original Babylonian empire,
the original Babylonian
dynasty from which our friend,
Hammurabi, who was a Martu or an Amarite,
was king.
Yeah, exactly.
In Babylon.
Yeah, okay, so let's talk about the city or itself
because this is the actual town that Abraham lived in.
He didn't just live in the empire.
He lived in Ura, right?
So what does that city actually look like in his time
and leading up to that?
Right. This is...
This is the capital.
Right.
And so this is the central hub of civilization
literally in the world at the time.
Yeah.
Yeah, right.
Because even the civilizations that aren't actually a part,
that aren't actually under oors control like Egypt and
the Indian River Valley civilizations are trading with
and through Ours, that Ascetic Empire.
All roads lead to war.
Yeah, as it were.
So this is the center and this is the hub.
And so, Ur was already a very old city at the time that Abraham lived there.
So, the area was initially settled in the period around, and this is very rough,
because they're sort of an initial settlement.
very under a layer of sediment. Say that five times fast. That original sediment, which
is I guess, or or if you will. Wow. I don't know why I didn't see that coming, but I really
should have at some point in this episode. I just I don't know.
against low. So the settlement came into existence because at the time it was
located
at the place where the river Euphrates
flowed into the Persian Gulf, where it met the Persian Gulf.
So it was a coastal settlement.
And because it's sort of in a river delta,
the river would cause it to flood every year.
You had very fertile soil.
Yeah, it's like a museum.
Yeah, or the Nile Delta, or yeah.
And so this was a good place because of the flooding
you could plant crops.
in the fertilized soil that washed down the river.
So the settlement starts somewhere around the middle
of the seventh century BC.
And what first seems to happen is
that there was an agricultural settlement,
they dug sort of irrigation canals within the delta area.
And then the city grew up and was structured
around those irrigation canals
because things like defense.
became needed as it grew.
And now if you go to the remains of ore today,
which is in Iraq now.
And I've seen photos of a number of folks
who served in the US military who were deployed over there
and got pictures next to the Ziggurat.
You can go there now.
And if you've been there, you're probably going,
It's in the
the middle of the desert. What do you mean it's a coastal?
Right. Things change.
Yes. When you're talking thousands of years.
Yes. Yes.
You know, climate change happens.
Yes.
And climate change happens to ur.
It was on the coast and then the Persian Gulf receded
a lot and now it's a long ways from the coast.
The water level in the Persian Gulf since the 21st century BC
has gone down about 10 feet.
Right.
which is miles and miles of land. Right. Yeah. And so it is now very far from the Persian Gulf.
But at the time it was there where it met. And the original settlers of the area were
Semitic people. So more like Ahad. But then the Sumerians showed up from somewhere. They're not
Aliens. They are not aliens.
not saying it was aliens, but it's not aliens.
Still not aliens.
So what out there is going, oh see, they're not aliens.
So they showed up from somewhere, around 3,300 BC.
Yeah, right.
And they sort of migrated in from somewhere.
The only accounts we have of where they came from,
which were written in today for much after the fact.
uh, say they came.
from the sea. Right. And just to remind everybody,
Quneiform is the alphabet that was used by ancient Sumerian and for some
other languages in the area. It's not really an alphabet. Yeah. Okay. Well,
the writing system. Okay. Actually, yeah. Thank you. Yes. Writing
system. Yeah. It's which which evolved from pictographs. But
Quneiform, especially Sumerian, Quneiform, there's like hundreds and hundreds of
It is very difficult to learn kuneiform.
take it for me I've tried.
Later on gets in a cadien, it gets kind of standardized to about 60 characters that are commonly
used.
And that's hard enough.
And when I say characters, I mean, it's different patterns of wedge imprints.
Yeah, and they look a lot alike.
Yeah, they look a lot alike each other.
Three vertical and one horizontal.
Three vertical two horizontal.
Right.
Two vertical two horizontal.
lol
Yeah, right. Yeah, but they evolved from sort of pictographs in the same way that you get like Chinese
Yeah, and hi-ratic in Egypt
sort of
Also pictographs so
But yeah, those accounts they they came from the water
Probably means somewhere to the east
But we don't we don't know where and we're not sure what they were
their language gives us zero clues because it's a language isolate. We don't have
like Sumerian DNA to test it and see what they were ethnically.
But they're not aliens.
They're not aliens.
But they may have been Indo-Europeans, right,
who came from like India, that direction, but we don't know.
And likely never will.
Oh, no, but likely we never will.
So...
They came and they didn't come in like conquer or they just sort of moved into the area and
Intermarried with the the settlement already there to produce the the
Early population of or the the or one dynasty
Which does exist unlike or two started around 2550 BC
So in the middle of the 26th century
BC
The city when Urnamu came to power and started the Ur 3 dynasty, he did a massive building
project in the whole city of Ur to sort of refinalize it and build it up as a capital
and a powerful city.
Most prominently, he built the great Ziggurat of Ur, the remains of which are still there,
although it's been repaired a couple times.
Thousands of years apart, but a couple times.
And that was finished near the end.
actually of the or three period. And that Ziggurat, as we've talked about, Ziggurat's were
the Sumerian good and Diggurat means, you know, gate of the gods. And so this is a sort
of human construction of the Holy Mountain of the mountain of the gods to draw him down
and bring him down there.
And in this case, it was...
because the Sumerian name of the God is Nana,
and A-N-N-A, the Acadia name is Sin, S-I-N.
Which is not related to the English word Sin at all.
No. No. Not connected.
Or Sinah, or anything. Right, right.
A moon God, which is interesting because, you know,
in anyone who studied mythology,
Most of the moon deities you run into are usually...
female, but actually there's a lot of male moon gods depicted as male in the ancient world.
More common than the female gods, I think, in that period.
Remember that far back? Yes.
Yeah.
Right.
And this one is male, even though Nana sounds like a feminine name.
That's actually a male figure.
So that that's the city of Ur is dedicated to this God that is God is the God.
out of the city. As these cities sort of gained and lost power, the gods of these cities
were seen to gain and lose power in the heavens. And there's what often be connected to astronomical
signs because, of course, astronomically, those are the gods too. So those are bodies of the
God too so that
actual moon in the sky is one of the bodies of Nana, right?
As is the idol on top of the ziggurat in the temple.
And so these things are all connected.
I was about to go on an integration, but I won't.
About Enlil.
We'll do that another time.
So when Ura comes to prominence, so does Ura's moon.
God, right? Right. Over in terms of the other the other gods. It's not, we think of these
pantheons, right? Like we think of the Greek gods, the Greek pantheon, it's like the Justice League,
right? It's like the team up, like all the gods. Yeah. No. Right. It's more like a confederation of
local deities. Right. You know, local to particular places. Yeah. Okay. So here's the question.
and probably a lot of people might have.
I mean, when we encounter...
or in the Bible in Genesis, it's referred to as
Ur of the Caldys or Ur of the Caldians.
But actually that's no one at the time,
and Abraham's time would have called it that, right?
Right. He had no idea what a Caldian was.
Yeah. Or that he was one.
Right. If he was one.
Yeah, that term comes from a lot later, right?
Something like 14 or 1500 years after he was later.
Yeah, so the Caldeans prop
refers to the neo-Babalonian Empire, the new Babylonian Empire from the
six-century BC. Yeah, which at one point was headed up by our friend, Nebuchadnezzar,
whose real name was Naboo, correct me if I get this wrong, Naboo, Kuduri, Usur,
which means Naboo watch over my air. It was you know the name itself was a
prayer to their God.
And this is why sometimes in more recent English translations you'll see his name
Transliterated is never could dresser. It's ready to get that could could do a re part
But I love I love the anglicized Hellenized
Naboo Kodinousor
Right, and so so this is a sort of a wild anachronism, right?
but
There's
There's something theological going on here in Genesis,
which is the reason why the editor at this point
puts in this sort of reference of Colleague or of the Caldese.
Is that, right, Caldese were the neo-Babolonian empire.
And so this serves to connect the civilization
that Abraham came from to Babylon.
Yeah, even though they're not literally exactly in the same...
spot. Right. It's the same region. And 500 years off. Yeah. Right. Right. Yeah.
Right. Before the first Babylonian empire even, there were 500 years before that. So this,
but, theologically, right, we're connecting these not to connect it to homerabi, but to connect
it to Babel.
The Tower of Babel.
Babili.
the gate of heaven, the Tower of Bable.
Right, and this is reflected if you look at the actual biblical text by the way that the story gets told.
So in Genesis 10, you've got the Tower of Babel story.
11.
I'm sorry, you've got the Tower Babble story and then there's this genealogy, but the genealogy
actually makes...
it so that you've got what Noah's son,
Shem, and then boom, Abraham's father.
And it goes to Abraham's father, right?
So the genealogy doesn't start at the tower of Babel.
Yeah, it starts way earlier.
Right.
It doesn't go for the tower of Babel to Abraham.
It goes from the flood to Abraham's.
Yeah, there's this whole compression going on
without any indication that that's what's happening.
You know, but these things are being put together.
I mean, it's in some ways it's like when...
I mean, setting aside all of the theological importance of this, when they refer to Jesus as the son of David,
it doesn't mean his father's name was David, but it's connecting him directly to David.
Right? And that's a similar kind of narrative way of using this sort of language.
Right, and so this is way of connecting him directly.
We go straight from the Tower of Babel into Abraham's story, and that connects those two stories,
is theologically right rather than
going through a narrative of exactly how much time passed, which would serve to then disconnect them.
Right? There's sort of this immediate segue. And there are sort of Jewish legends.
And I call them that because these aren't really from Second Temple literature.
These are rabbinic stories that get written down. But the rabbinic stories when they get written down are
finally writing down
oral tradition that goes back before it
So, we're not sure exactly where they originate, but there's a number of them in a number of
variations, but they're canonical for no one.
Connects Abram directly to the Tower of Babel's story.
Yeah, so he's living next to the construction of the Great Zagrad of Ur, which is then sort
of conflated with the Tower of Babel, which is connected then also with the Babylonian
Empire.
All of those things are kind of piled up on top of each other.
Right, and so you get these stories of Nimrod being, you know,
angry at Abram because he won't worship the pagan gods and trying to throw him into the brick kiln.
I mean, there's a whole, there are all these elaborate stories.
But yeah, there's, and part of it is riffing off of a really obscure point
is that uh
or
Can actually mean in in
Old Canaanite and very early Hebrew or could actually mean fire
Oh, that's fun. So they decided to translate you know what God says to Abram
I saved you out of or of the Caldeans they translated that as the fire of the Caldeans
Oh, wow and then elaborated that into the whole brick kiln story and all of that like the three holy children
Yeah, yeah. You can see these different pieces of oral tradition about Abram's life that he was there when they're building the great Ziggurat,
and the Tower of Babel's story, and the story of the three youths in Babylon all kind of get mingled together in this oral mishmash, right?
That it's getting written down in the rabbinic period.
But there's also another connection here.
Okay, and that's that I mentioned that there were a couple of periods many centuries apart
where there were rebuilding efforts for the great cigarette in Ur, and the first
of those was actually by Nabonitis, who was the last neo-Babolonian emperor who
came and rebuilt it. So the great cigarette of Ur that was first constructed in
Abrams time was repaired and rebuilt by the Caldians in the neo-Babolonian
So they had another connection. Yeah, they themselves were actually connected.
themselves to this ancient civilization that they... I mean, there was a cultural connection
although with a lot of time passing, you know, maybe between the gap.
Subway's strained by that point, but yeah.
Right, exactly.
Alright, well, so having painted that picture of the civilization that Abraham grew up in,
we're going to go ahead and go to break and we'll be right back and we will take some
of your calls.
So let's go to break.
Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung
We'll be back in a moment to take your calls on the next part of the Lord of Spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF Radio.
With the Lord of Spirits, the Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen De Young.
If you have a question, call now at 855-237-23.
That's 855 AF radio.
Welcome back.
This is the second part of our show and it's where we begin to take some recalls.
Just like the voice of Steve just said, you can call us at 855 AF radio again 855-237-2346.
Before we do that, I actually realized that last time when we had our show two weeks ago,
I totally forgot to mention, and I don't know if this is evidence of my...
staggering humility or what? Creeping old age. Creeping that's quite likely.
Sinility. But I totally forgot to mention that actually just two days before
that show that I had a new book is out. So I've got a new book it's called
Arise O God, The Gospel of Christ's defeat of demons, sin and death and it's
published by Ancient Faith publishing you can get it at store. Ancient Faith.com
Um...
And the point of the book is it's a summary of the gospel from an Orthodox point of view.
And especially if you listen to this show, then you're going to see demons all over it because
actually the gospel has a whole lot to do with demons. So what I do in the book is at the beginning,
I actually talk about what is a gospel and how it's actually not what most people these days
in 21st century American Christianity.
Say that it is.
Then talk about what the Goths.
is from the actual biblical point of view.
And then I asked the question,
well, why is there a gospel at all?
Like, what's wrong?
Why does there need to be a gospel?
And then I just describe the actual contents of the gospel
and then get to the point where you actually ask,
well, okay, wait, what do I have to do to be saved?
Because, you know, spoiler alert, the gospel is not,
this is how you get saved.
The question, what do I do to be saved
is the response to the gospel.
And then I talk about what happens
when someone actually does respond to it and gets on board.
So
So, you know, I just wanted to mention it because I know that those of you who listen to this
show, that this will be right up your alley, it is a short book.
You can probably read the whole thing in the space of a couple of hours.
There's paperback version, there's ebooks.
You can get that from OrthodoxChristianEbooks.com.
It's also on Kindle.
And there's an audio book version as well which you can get through Audible and also Apple
books.
So I hope you'll check it out.
and something really well.
last couple of weeks. Thanks be to God for all of you who have gotten it so far. Thank you.
And we'd love to hear from you what you think about it. And please, you know, write a
review on Amazon or wherever else you want to write reviews. And that would be helpful
so that more people can get to it. And, you know, especially if you're clergy in listening,
I just want to suggest to you that this book will be really good for your evangelistic
work and also for your catacetical work, for people who are coming to your parish for
the first time and then also people that are being raised in your parish.
and need to be trained in this core question
of what exactly is the gospel.
So yeah, so yeah, I mean, it's a little bit of an advertisement.
But again, if you're listening to this show,
you're gonna be into this.
So do check it out.
I know a lot of you have so far.
Thanks a lot for doing that.
Okay, well, we do actually allow me to say.
Thank you.
Your new book is a little a puchin in size.
Yes, it's quite small.
probing negian in scope
Nice. Nice.
And I just wanted to promote it swiftly.
Because you came to me and told me you were writing it.
And I said, well, that sounds like a modest proposal.
And now I'm wondering how long you'll let me keep doing this.
No.
It was beautiful.
It was beautiful while.
OK.
Well, we actually do Jonathan Swift greater than sign
Jonathan Edwards.
Don't have me.
Amen.
All right, we do actually have a couple of calls coming in.
So one of them is Dolly calling from Atlanta.
So Dolly, are you there?
I am.
Hello, Father.
Welcome to the Lord of Spirits podcast.
We're glad to have you.
What's on your mind?
Well, I have a throwback to eating with the gods
and sacrifices of righteousness.
And so it really kind of turned my head upside down
when you redefine how I thought of worship.
as a meal with your God.
And it made me think about the function of the family table.
And it made me want to think about it sacramentally,
but then I didn't want to overstep my bounds
theologically speaking.
And so I was wondering about, you know,
in the kind of, if we're trying to unmodern ourselves
and live our lives more in touch with the unseen
as well as the scene, what are some ways that we can do that?
And, you know, the first thing I thought
about with the sound.
family table, but other sort of practical ways that we can live in a more
sacramental manner. Yeah. That's in the obvious. You know, reading your Bible
and praying and attending math and all that. Right. Yeah, I mean, that's an
excellent question. And I mean, I think that the family table is the place to
start because in a lot of ways in modern materialist America, it's kind of the
last sacrament that might exist for some people.
But even that's being torn apart.
You know, where many families, a lot of times,
family meal time is not family meal time.
It's just people showing up to the table every so often
with something they got out of the fridge.
But so, you know, I think the pattern that's going on
when people worship God by offering sacrifice,
especially the, you know, the Eucharist
within the Christian context, that same kind of thing,
although in a different way, it's not identical
when you sit.
town together with your family and have dinner, but there's something very similar happening
there, and I think that the way to the biggest way to underline that it is a, I'm trying
to think the best way to talk about it, it is an enchanted sacramental thing that we're
doing when we do that, is to begin obviously...
I kind of want to ask a Peugeot V& question, what is the symbolism of the...
Yeah.
Right, right. Well, I mean, it's about sharing life, right? And becoming like one another
and becoming part of one another. I mean, that's what's going on when you offer a sacrifice
to a God. He becomes part of your community. You become part of his. And so when people
eat together all the time, they become part of each other and they change one another,
right? And so part of the reason that we then pray before the meal and then also, you
in orthodox tradition after the meal as well.
is that it binds it all together with a blessing from God and reveals the meal to be what it truly is supposed to be,
which is actually a salvific experience for everybody involved.
But you can transfer that model to almost anything that you do, especially communally.
Right like if you're gonna take a trip together to pray beforehand and after and and you know try to sanctify it along the ways
as much as possible. I don't know if father's even as anything you wanted to add or expand on or um
actually. Well yeah I mean just building off of that right I mean the the families eating meals
together is one of many things but sometimes one of the first things we notice in terms of our
complete alienation from each other and the rest of creation right. We don't spend time with other
humans anymore. We sit...
next to them and look at our phones or we sit next to them and one person's reading
something and another person's watching television.
But we don't actually spend time together doing things.
So there are a lot of things that they almost seem quaint and overly wholesome and silly
to us now.
But you know, planting a garden and taking care of it together, taking care of animals
together creating things
and making things together.
This is what people used to do.
It would go, it makes something with wood, or makes something with fabric, or makes
it, and doing it together and spending that time together and reconnecting in any way
we can, and trying to reestablish a sense of community.
The best place, the only place to start now for that is our churches.
used to be.
you know, 70 years ago, there was the VFW Hall and the Union Hall and the Lions Club and
Rotary and Lodges and this and that, the other, where people would go out in public and spend
time with other humans in community. And there was a problem at the time because those kind
of pulled people away from the church community into these other sometimes secularized, sometimes
other kinds of communities, but now those are all gone.
don't have them at all.
There is no place now, especially after COVID,
where we go out and spend time in public with other people
in our community, except for our churches.
And so that's the only place to begin
to connect with people even beyond our immediate family
and try to extend those social bonds back out.
Because we weren't made to live as alienated, isolated
individuals, and we weren't even made to live as nuclear
families.
the nuclear families.
a weird thing that's come up since industrialization.
We're made to live at extended families and communities
and villages together and be part of each other's lives
and be connected to a hundred other people
and to plants and animals and crops
and the world around us.
So trying to rebuild that starting with small steps
is the way to go.
Yeah.
All right, well, I hope that's helpful to you, Dolly.
Thank you very much for calling in.
Mass quickly, what would a correct blessing look like?
A correct blessing look like?
Well, I mean, so...
I mean, so...
Yeah, well...
What would it need to include?
I mean, there's, you know, there's all kinds of Orthodox prayer books which have various meal blessings.
So there's a lot of versions of them.
Usually, almost always, they include some kind of things giving to God
and asking that he would bless not just the food.
but also the people that are there. But there's short ones, there's long ones, you know, they're all good.
So, all right. Thank you very much. Okay, we're going to take one more caller and then we're going to move on. So we've got
Salvatore calling from Houston. Salvatore, welcome to the Lord of Spears podcast.
Thank you, fathers. And I also kind of have a throwback to the eating with the God episode. My question is from the book of
Everything seems kind of walkie-jogs.
Sam Hill doesn't seem to be at priest, but he's offering sacrifice at high places.
The Ark of the Covenant is hanging out at someone's house for 25 years.
Other priests are sleeping with women at the tathenacle.
God seems to be okay with Samuel offering sacrifice, but not the stall.
What's happening?
I'm going to hand that right to you, Father Steven.
Right.
Well, so Samuel had two roles.
He's kind of unique, biblically, this regard, in that he was the prophet of God and he was the last judge of Israel.
The book of Judges ends and so sometimes we don't realize that but if you read the text of first Samuel or first came up carefully,
it refers to it's a, you know, Samuel judged Israel from this time to this time, right? Several times that's the verb that's used.
So he has this sort of unique role, but part of
what prophets do, and part of what they're called by God to do is to enact a judgment
against the corrupt Israelite institutions.
So like in our last episode, when we talked about St. Elias or the prophet Elijah, he was
enacting this kind of judgment of God against Ahab and Jezebel.
the king because the monarchy of the Northern Kingdom had become utterly corrupt.
And so this also happens with the temple or tabernacle and the priesthood that sometimes
when that has become corrupt and you point out to what example of how it became corrupt
during that period, but there are more.
Because the priesthood had become corrupt, right, God then uses his prophet to enact by
having him do the sacrifices and having him do them somewhere else and excluding the priest.
seductive judgment
against that priesthood. God is sort of taking that right and that privilege away from them
and giving it to someone else as a form of enacting judgment. And this dynamic sort of happens again
in the Book of Jeremiah that one of the themes in the Book of Jeremiah is that
everyone is sort of placing their confidence in the temple, that the place where God's presence is,
where his spirit is, where he's placed his name in the temple.
And it actually...
the temple was about to be destroyed, right?
Even though they believed, you know, well, God will never let his own temple get destroyed, right?
So, we'll have to be safe.
Right? But in actuality, the spirit, God's presence, God's, they've had been placed in Jeremiah himself.
Right? So, Jeremiah sort of becomes the temple, in a sense.
as a judgment against the corruption of the temple in the priesthood at the time.
So Samuel is sort of the one faithful prophet during a lot of that period.
Basically, until David shows up, he's about it.
Right? And so God's presence is with Samuel.
And so the true sacrifices are being offered by Samuel.
The true leader of Israel is Samuel, right?
Because of Saul's faithlessness and shenanigans. Right?
So yeah, so that's how that works.
All right.
Well, there you go, Savitory.
Thank you.
Thanks for calling in. All right, well rolling on. So Genesis 1 through 11. This is where all the bad things in the world come from, right?
Yes.
You know, death, sin, demons. Oh, buy my book, everybody.
Yeah.
Because that's really more about.
there was the we've talked about how there are these sort of three fall events.
Yes.
And so we're not going to go.
go through all that again right here.
But because as we just mentioned before the break,
Abram's story really is intended.
The way Genesis is constructed is
intended to follow directly on after the Tower of Babel.
We kind of want to focus on that.
Just a little bit in that remembering
that what's going on there is not just like, oh, hey,
now everybody talks different languages.
But that what's going on there is,
as we've talked about before.
God's presence was with humanity before the flood.
And humanity became so sinful that they experienced mass death by holiness, through God's own holiness,
sort of wiping them out.
And so after the flood, he sets his bow in the clouds and says, I'm no longer going to make war with man.
And so he's not going to destroy humanity again in that way.
And so then when we come up to, we see Nimrod, we see...
the giant thing happening again, when the tower of Babel happens, rather than God remaining
and destroying humanity, he departs.
This is the other option.
He can leave.
He can depart.
He hands over the rule of the nations to angels who then rule them by proxy.
And as we've seen before, of course, they fall because they accept worship, and that's
the origin of paganism according to the Bible.
Right.
And so this...
This third problem, this problem of the fallen power of principalities is set up by the tower of Bable,
and then we immediately go into Abraham.
Yeah, and it's funny because, like it's, so Genesis 12, it just says,
and God talked to Abraham.
Right.
He doesn't show up and say, oh, hey, hey, I'm, I'm, I'm, I'm, I am.
That's who you call me.
And, you know, like there's none of that.
I'm Yahweh, and I'm the most high God.
Right. Yeah, there's no introduction.
Yeah, which...
indicates that he always said to Abram, which indicates like he already knows him.
Right.
Abram already knows Yahweh.
That this is a relationship that already exists.
Right.
So this means that Abram is our first example, but not the last.
There's going to be another one within Abram's story that being Melchizedek, who we're going
to talk about in our next episode.
Yes.
There's Bill Kielsteadck also who are people who despise
what happened at the Tower of Babel and we talked about even you can see this in
anthropology and sociology texts that gradually the Most High God sort of
retreats into the background of pagan religion and the focus all falls to
the sort of lesser members of the pantheon, the local gods. That Abram and
Okzadek and there could be some others have remained faithful to the
worship of the most high god of one of the
The questions we sometimes get in regards to this problem with the fall after Babel is that
we'll get like, well, did no nation stay, you know, faithful to Yahweh and the answer to
that is no, no nation did, but some people did.
Some people did.
So the nations have fallen, but they're a handful of people who actually are still worshiping
the One True God.
And Abraham is one of them.
Right.
Abraham is me, if you'll.
So even though this story of Genesis 12 was kind of called the call of
Abraham right or the call of Abram and that might give us the idea that this is
something like the calls of the prophets that we're gonna see yeah it's not like
that he doesn't get like taken up to heaven or yeah yeah there's no big vision
yeah none of that right none of that and even the languages used later you know
he says to him walk before me and be righteous right and that walk language is
I just picked up from earlier in Genesis in the garden.
Right. So there is this ongoing life of faithfulness that Abraham is carrying out.
This is just an observation, say Paul Bess later, like, wow, that Abraham was a really faithful guy.
This is the crux of what's going on from his very introduction.
But as you just mentioned, these are isolated individuals.
So even Abrib's own father.
is set up in the text to not have been a worshipper of Yahweh.
Right.
The Messiah God.
Yeah, it mentions that he's a pagan actually in Joshua 242.
It says that he's, he doesn't worship.
Yes.
And it's remembered all those years later.
It's he's singled out.
Right?
Joshua is speaking and he says,
our ancestors lived beyond the rivers, right?
In Mesopotamia and worshipped other gods,
gods, including Tara, a-
of his father. Right, so he gets singled out for that. And we see this also in the narrative
itself in the end of Genesis 11 and Genesis 12. The end of Genesis 11, the end of the
genealogy is actually Terra. And what the, what it says at the end of Genesis 11 is that
Terra takes his family, which includes Abram and Nohor and Lot and Haran, and is going
you take them to canine
but he stops in Haran and stays there until Tara dies.
Then that story gets retold in Genesis 12 where Yahweh comes to Abraham and tells him to go to Canaan.
And Abraham stops and stays with his father, Tara, in Haran until he dies and then goes out and completes the journey.
And it's not a coincidence that Haram is another city, another Mesopotamian city where...
that the same moon god is being worshiped.
Yeah, so even though the scripture doesn't say this explicitly,
there's almost a suggestion that Tara got this call
to make the move, but failed to carry it out.
And Abram is the one who actually then does it, right?
And again, it's not explicit, but it's sort of suggested
because like why there is this move,
in that direction.
but he stops and doesn't go on.
He gets entangled up with the worship of that God
that they had been worshiping Pekin or as well.
So yeah.
Right.
And so because of this, because Abram is so different,
even then his own family.
And we're going to see, lot doesn't always do so great.
Right?
I did in the story of Abram and his life.
Because Abram is sort of different instead
part of this way.
This is known, this is built into the text, so in second-tempo literature and other stories
where you see the figure of Abram, there's always this incorporated, this kind of enmity
and alienation between him and the surrounding world, where this kind of evil paganism,
this idolatry, sexual immorality, these things are going on and he's sort of set apart from
that and that creates this enmity between him. There's a hostility of the world.
And this is, he sort of talks about this, right?
This quoted line where he talks about being a stranger
in a strange land, right?
That he's sort of alienated and St. Peter picks up on this,
saying that we should live that.
We should be like aliens and foreigners in the world
because we're of course all too comfortable
to Abraham in civilization.
But Abraham was sort of set apart because of that.
Yeah, yeah, so you let me know.
lives out as a nomad so he's not part of this civilization, the or civilization, which
I mean is also kind of an ascetical image as well, you know, that he's separate from all
of the benefits, you know, that are existing in civilization as well. And so then it's
in that context then that God gives to him these promises, right?
Right.
Yeah.
before we move on just to add this is this is a theme sort of throughout.
Abraham's story. The places where he or someone in his family get in trouble is
when they try to go back to civilization. The two times Abram visits Egypt.
He gets into trouble. When lot goes and moves down next to Sodom, he gets into
trouble. There's this sort of pull to come back into the world and back into the
world civilization and that's leading to destruction. Yeah, right. Yeah.
Okay, so then in Genesis 12.
when God speaks to Abram, he initially gives him the first version of the promises to him.
This is in verses 2 and 3. God says, I will make of you a great nation and I will bless you and
make your name great so that you will be a blessing. I will bless those who bless you and him who
dishonors you, I will curse, and in you all the families of the earth shall be blessed.
And it's particularly notable here that one of the things that's happening is that
God is the God of Abraham and not the God of a place.
He's the God of a person, not the God of a place.
We talked about this at some length in our Pentecost episode,
which was titled in a macular dwelling place.
So if you're interested in that question, go back and listen to that.
But then the promises get reiterated three times and kind of expanded out, right?
Right. They got flushed out.
Yeah, so I'm just going to read those real quick in succession.
Then we're going to talk about what they say.
So Genesis 155.
Then Yahweh brought Abraham outside, saying, look now toward the heavens and count the stars if you are able to number them.
Then he told him, so will your seed be.
Genesis 22, 17, I will surely bless you and greatly multiply your seed like the stars of heaven and like the sand which is on the shore of the sea.
and your seed will occupy the gate of their enemies
and then Genesis 264, but I will multiply your seed as the stars of the heavens
give to your seed all these lands and all the nations of the earth will be blessed in your seed.
Okay, so what's going on? What's going on within? There's like several different elements to this
promise that God is giving him, right? Right. And so and little pieces every time he reiterates those
promises, there are little nuances and pieces and angles, right, that that get added and fleshed out
there. So first and foremost, the probably the most obvious one.
Right is that there's a there's a sort of quantitative element to these promises. Yeah, Abram is 75 years old and has no children
And his name Abram means great father
And so most likely terror named him that referring to himself of course, but
He's got a great father, but it leaves it leaves this kind of bitter irony that he's childless, right?
Yeah.
And so there is this this quantitative element that he's not just going to have to say that it's what he's got this vast multitude
Right like the sands of the seashore and that nations plural are going to come from him that is part of the promise not just Israel but nations
Are going to come from him and all the nations of the world meaning the 70 nations, right are all going to be blessed through him
Right that it's through him that God is eventually going to call those nations back who are scattered at
at Bable. But then there's also an addition to that quantitative promise. There's also a qualitative
element. And so you see that in the first quote that you read from Genesis 15 verse 5, he says,
look at the heavens and tell the stars if you're able to number them. He says, so will your seed be?
He doesn't say so many will your seed be. So yeah, so right, your your your descendants will be
like the stars in this way.
Yeah, right.
And this is it.
just be trying to be tricking with the original language or something.
This is something that our earliest insurgent hearders saw.
So Exhibit A of this is Philo of Alexandria, who saw this very clearly.
And here's a couple of sight patients for you.
From Philo, he refers to this in his Trees, who is the heir of divine things in section
17.
He refers to this.
questions and answers in Genesis, book 4, section 181.
Where he directly talks about the fact that this is referring to Abrams' seed becoming
like the stars, not as many as the stars.
And this, of course, as we talked about earlier,
if you're part of the Sumerian retis on.
you understand that the sun moon stars in the sky are bodies of the gods, the lower gods,
the small G gods. The gods are now raiding over the cities who, who Abram doesn't worship,
by the way. He worships the most high god, right? Other beings, these beings who have provoked
this hostility between him and the world, they become like them. And that includes then a second
element that we see in
in the prophecy in Genesis 22 verse 17 that you read that is he would occupy the gates of their enemies
right so the city gate was you know we would think of this you know people get the key to the city
and it doesn't actually owe me that right but the gates of the city right you had the cities
in Asia well that these protected walls to protect from a packet and invasion and the gates therefore
you have to have that be the strongest part of your
defenses, but also the city gate is where the administration of the city took place.
The elders of the city would sit at the city gates.
That's where they would hear cases, and the court cases and side disputes.
That's where you'd go to ratify a contract or an agreement.
That's where marriages and divorces and these kind of things happened.
So all of these things take place at a
So the city gate is sort of the center of power of city, not the fringe of the city.
And so if you're camping in your enemy's city gates, that means you have taken control of their center of power.
You have taken control of their city.
It's of this at this element of displacement that they're going to come like them and replace them as they are punished.
Right, right, exactly.
So okay, well, we're getting unfortunately as you guys
Noah Hurricane hit Louisiana not that long ago and has kind of done some damage to the infrastructure,
the Internet infrastructure there. So we're going to get Father Steven hopefully switching over to
our backup system here. But yeah, so okay, so we're just talking about these promises to Abraham
and what the point of all the things going on there. What kind of summarizes some of this is again,
this Babel context, right? So again, remember the Abraham story follows immediately on the
the back.
story, right? And so the battle story establishes the idea that these hostile fallen
principalities are governing mankind now. And so the promises given to Abraham are
specifically about judging and displacing those hostile principalities. That's what's
going on there. So, so that's how these, that's one of the ways that these, these things
connected right so yeah okay
father you're there.
So these two obviously go together,
the judgment and replacement are certainly connected to each other.
And so the next little piece we have to talk about in these promises,
of course, is that there is this other element.
There's a material element to go with that spiritual element.
and sometimes
especially among some of our fellow Christians who aren't necessarily members of the Orthodox Church,
that material element tends to take the whole focus.
Yeah, yeah.
As I said, the spiritual element we were just talking about, in fact that spiritual element is almost gone.
That concept of basically fiosus that we're talking about is basically gone and replaced with
going to have this particular strip of land in Palestine and
Uh...
Oh.
All right, Father Stephen, do we lose you?
Well, it's live radio, everybody.
He was connected to mine, uh, Bobby. Sorry, we're...
Oh, there's father's team in the back.
Yeah.
Welcome back.
Okay.
Yeah.
So, I don't know where exactly I got cut, but so the spiritual element we were talking about,
which is basically talking about theosis, sort of drops out in a lot of contemporary
discussion of the promises to Abraham and is sort of completely displaced by the material
element of land, the physical land, and the quantitative element.
Right.
Of the
Lots of descendants.
A number of descendants.
Right.
And so to understand how those two things are related to each other, the material element
and the spiritual element of the promises, because it's not that the material element isn't
there, right?
It's just the spiritual element.
We have to kind of understand the connection between prophecy and signs as it exists in
Scripture.
And so, when they...
is given very often a company in sign is given. Right. Because a prophecy is going to have some kind
of fulfillment that is not immediately visible. Yeah, there's a kind of down payment so to speak.
Like, okay, something big is going to happen. I'm going to show you this to prove that it's going
to happen. Right. And a really obvious and well known one, thanks to Linus Van Telt is in Luke 2.
Thank you.
Yeah, he's a tough.
last name. Did you ever think about that? I never thought about that. One of the
peanuts was Dutch, but there we go. So it's Lucy. Yeah, right. Right. So in Luke 2, right,
after the stars have sung to the shepherds, the angel tells them to go and he says, this
will be assigned to you. He's just announced to them, the Messiah has been born. The savior
the world has been born. The Messiah is...
But they say, this will be a sign to you.
Go, you will find a baby wrapped in swaddling clothes,
lying in a major, lying in an animal food trough.
This is not something you normally see every day, right?
Right.
And so when they see this, this odd thing,
then they will know that it is true that this child
is the Messiah.
This sign will clue them in.
And this kind of goes the other way, too,
because
we find over and over again in the Gospels people coming to Jesus after he
preaches and after he teaches what he teaches and demanding a sign from him.
Yeah. Right. So show us some signs so that we may believe you. Right. I don't buy it. Right.
And Christ of course refuses. Yeah. The only sign I'm going to give you is the sign of Jonah.
right, which is of course his death and resurrection.
Right. And so built into that.
answers the fact that Christ's death and resurrection
improves that everything he taught and said was true.
So that said,
what we have here in terms of the material element
of these promises is that the material element
of these promises is the sign of the spiritual element.
So, the material element of Abram's descendant.
right, that the several nations descended from him, which biblically include not just Israel,
but also Adam and Moab. Right, them coming into at different times into the land that Abraham
has promised, and overthrowing the giants who are there, the spiritual powers of evil who the
the giants represent that.
on the visible level and the more immediate level,
it's still a few hundred years,
but on the more immediate level,
is the proof is the sign that the,
the, the, the,
defocation of Abrams descendants
is faithful descendants,
and their displacement of the powers and principalities
and the heavenly places is also a reality.
Right, right.
Yeah, so it's, I mean,
I just want to underline what you just said
because this is a super important point
in this whole story, right?
So number one.
Abraham has descendants other than Israel, right?
The Itamites, the Moebites and the Ammonites.
Like these are descendants of people like Esau,
and you know, right?
So it's not necessarily this line, you know,
the main air, but there are other descendants as well.
And they also have driven off
these demonized giant clans.
And this is the sort of immediate sign
that is the depiction of what's going to actually
old
happen. Like there is going to be, you know, Abraham, your seed is going to ultimately drive off all
these dark powers and to prove that to you in the meantime, a bunch of your descendants are actually
successfully do this kind of on a local level, right? Right? So that's part of what's going on in this
story. Right, and we read in Deuteronomy 2, and of course you can go back to the giant substore,
So we went through it in detail.
All the different giant clans, how the e to my.
drove giant clans out of what became
eaten, likewise with the moa bites,
likewise with the amonites,
likewise with the cough during the
Creotans and the Philistines, but you
can report about or listen to
more about that on our giant
episode. What the Greeks are doing
there.
But these, so the Abrahamites come in
and one of the things that sometimes
pointed out by our friends,
Who's
still want to focus on that material level of the promises and try to project that out into
the future. You know who you are. We're looking at you, just been
sationalists. So, tell us, it's not that far from me. Right. So, the, what they'll say
is, well, God actually promises to Abraham, this huge tract of land that Israel never
controlled all that way.
So eventually they, you know, they need to get it.
Right. And so, but if you actually read Deuteronomy, right, and you
include all the other Abrahamites, right, you include the Midianites, right, who are
Ishmaelites and Edomites. You include Edom, you include Moab, you're
Laman, we're descended from law, you include all of those groups, all the Abrahamite groups,
they did get that land.
Right. It's not just me saying so.
Yeah Joshua says it.
like twice yeah like yeah okay so especially once you get towards the end you
know towards the end of the book of Joshua in Joshua 2145 it says this right
explicitly it says not one word of all the good promises that the Lord had
made to the house of Israel had failed all came to pass and that was said right
after all the land had been claimed you know and not just by Israel but by
these other Abrahamite groups as well.
Right.
And you could promise fulfilled.
You could.
look at Joshua 11 21 through 23 and 21 versus 43 through 45. It directly refers to the giant
cleanse being driven out. It directly refers to taking the lens as all the land promises
made to Abraham were therefore fulfilled. They're done. At the end of the book of Joshua.
Yeah. Exactly. And so that then sets that part, the sign, therefore, is instantiated
is instantiated in the Scriptures, right? In the earliest lay.
of the Hebrew Scriptures. And so that is the guarantee for us that the larger promise is
going to come true. And so it's this, it's this greater promise of the theosis or the
divinization or the deification, however, whatever word we want to choose, of the faithful descendants
of Abraham who received this through their faithfulness in the way Abraham received the promises
through his faithfulness to God in the way he walked.
and lived his life. And remaining loyal and true to Yahweh, the God of Israel, and not
following after idols and these other gods. In the same way, this is what St. Paul goes
back to, what St. Paul talks about salvation. When he talks about salvation, when he sees
salvation in Christ, St. Paul's soteriology, right, his theology of salvation, is all based
around this is that now in crime
through the incarnation and death and resurrection and ascension of Christ, those promises have now been
completed. And that's why he goes back to Abraham and talks about his faithfulness. That's why he
talks about his inheritance. He talks about being sons of Abraham. He talks about being heirs of the
promises. Inheritance, all of that language that St. Paul uses to talk about salvation comes from the
now spirit.
element of those promises. Right. That salvation is bound up frankly in spiritual warfare and
not just warfare and defeating those dark powers but then the ascending of the descendants of Abraham.
Yeah yeah. Okay well we're gonna take a quick break and right we'll be right back in a second
and we're gonna talk about something that a lot of you have asked us about and that is Abraham
exactly what they were doing up on top of that mountain.
So let's take a break.
Father Andrew Stephen Daymak and Father Stephen DeYoung
will be back in a moment to take your calls
on the next part of the Lord of Spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF radio.
This is an ancient faith radio public service announcement.
the mental health.
task force of the Assembly of Canonical Orthodox Bishops has recently launched two mental health
initiatives, a national directory of Orthodox Mental Health professionals and an Orthodox
Mental Health Needs Assessment that are available at www.assemblyofbishops.org slash mental-health.
The directory of Orthodox Mental Health professionals features licensed Orthodox Christian clinicians
across the US who are available to serve as resources to those seeking mental health
care.
substance abuse care and or professional consultation.
While the orthodox mental health needs assessment is an anonymous survey for all orthodox jurisdictions,
clergy and laypeople across the US.
The aggregate data from this survey will help the task force better understand
and address the mental health needs of orthodox faithful through the development of ministry resources.
Once again, that web address is www.assemblyofbishops.org slash mental dash
health. This has been a public service announcement of Ancient Faith Radio.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits, the Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen
DeYoung. If you have a question, call now at 855-237-2346. That's 855-AF Radio.
Welcome back. It's the third part of Lord of Spirits. So we were
third half. The third half, excuse me, that is correct. It is the third half of Lord of
Spirits because this is a show and a half, everybody. So we just finished talking about the promises
made to Abraham and we wrapped it up with the conclusion about what St. Paul has to say about
about salvation and how that connects to all of that. So now we're going to be talking about
Abraham and his son Isaac. And of course, this is, this is
an issue that actually we've got a lot of questions about because when we started talking about
sacrifice really explicitly a few months ago many of you then thought, well wait, what about
Abraham and Isaac?
What's going on there?
So now we're going to go ahead and talk about Abraham and Isaac and we're going to begin
with St. Paul.
So Father, what does St. Paul have to say about this particular, you know, this scene, this
image of Abraham and Isaac?
Right.
There's this there's this one
element left over from those promises that we didn't really focus in on. And that's that over and over
again as you read those quotes from Genesis where God is reiterating the promises to Abram.
The word seed is used, right? The promises are directed toward his seed. And in Hebrew,
it's ambiguous whether C-
singular or plural because it's a collective noun, Zoraza collective noun. So it can be used
for singular or for plural. It's sort of like, you know, fish in English. You'd have one fish,
two fish, red fish, blue fish. And seed in English even functions that way. Like we use it both
as a collective noun and then also as a singular in our, in English. And it also can function as
a singular plural, but I was thinking of mousse actually.
Yeah, isn't it me's what it is not it is not in fact me's I know
It's all friend there
So there are places in the promises we read where it's very clearly taking a
plural
form because it will say for example
example, talk about his seed and they will camp in the gates of their enemies.
So this is third person plural, so we know that seed there is plural.
But there are other places where it's where ambiguous, and it could be plural or singular.
And there is a preexisting, this predates, St. Paul, a preexisting tradition of interpretation
that several of these are actually singular.
Then in addition to the sort of quantitative promise that we were talking about
about having
many descendants, that there's also one particular descendant in view through whom these promises
will come to fruition for the plural seed, for all of the descendants.
And so this tradition of interpretation is reflected in the Greek translation itself of
several of these promises because
In Greek, Sparema is not a collective noun.
You can decline it as singular or you can decline it as plural.
Yeah, Sparema and the Sparema, right?
Right.
And so they had a choice to make when they translated it.
And in several cases chose the singular and say,
Paul points to this singular.
Points to this, for example in Galatians 3-
16 as it is a sort of key part of his argument.
When he says that now the promises were made to Abraham and to his offspring, it does not
and this is of course seed Abraham and to his seed. It does not say into seeds referring
to many but referring to one and to your seed who is Christ.
Right. So Saint Paul is he's explicitly using both the singular and plural of the Greek
and making a point based on that.
Right, so he is treating the septuaget here as authoritative.
As an authoritative interpretation of the Hebrew.
Right, right.
He's saying, this is, and what I say, authoritative,
it's because he's just pointing to it.
And here in Galatians, he's arguing with fellow Judeans.
Yeah.
about the specific application of the Torah.
So he clearly expects this Greek translation choice
to carry a authoritative weight with them.
Otherwise, this is a pointless argument.
Yeah, right.
Because if his fellow Judean Pharisees
did not accept those decisions as authoritative,
they could just laugh this argument off
and say, well, that's not what the Hebrew says.
The Hebrew could be plural, right?
You know and and
a different interpretation. But so St. Paul obviously is applying this directly to Christ.
Right.
Saying that Christ is this singular seed. He is this singular sun through whom those
larger spiritual promises we talked about are now coming to fruition. But before that,
This was most directly applied to Isaac.
Isaac as the singular son.
of Abraham, even though Abraham had other children, right? So by applying it to Isaac, you
have both that element of yes, there are other children, but there is this singular
son. There is this singular seed, the singular descendant, who is the heir and through whom
the other children will receive the inheritance.
Right, so there's this emphasis then on.
on Isaac in particular, which then, I mean, this is going to sort of set us up then for
who is Isaac in terms of how he's understood in Second Temple Literature and, frankly, in
the New Testament and the whole Christian tradition.
Right.
And St. Paul explicitly uses this whole line of argumentation in Romans 9, right, where
he's talking about how the promises were not just even legionarically distributed to all
of the biological descendants of Abraham.
Right.
but that there was a single any points to Isaac,
any points to Jacob and not Esau, right?
Not that, as we were just talking about
in terms of the land,
not that Esau and Ishmael and there's inherited nothing,
right, but they received the promises through the air
through the singular sun.
Right, because of the way that inheritance works
in this time and place, which is the air
who is usually the first born son.
but as we saw with Jacob and he saw not always, right?
The heirs, the one who inherits everything from the father
and then distributes to his brethren and sister-in
of that promise that inheritance given to him.
Right, and so this first port is a status, right,
that you have and you don't have to have any other children
for the one child you have to have the first port status.
Yeah.
There are people out there who know why that's important.
But the
The
Ed in the case of like you put it out Jacob
It doesn't necessarily mean you're the chronologically first board. It means you have that status
Yeah, your first birthright as it's translated in the King James. Yeah, because first I mean first in Greek and we use this in
English in some ways too like first doesn't necessarily mean as you said chronologically first it just means
The you know the first among them the the one who is preeminent
You know, it's a place. It's not necessarily a time.
You know, I mean, there's a relationship between the two.
Like the church, the church, for instance,
the protos is the one who is actually celebrating
the church service and then everyone else is his
con celebrants and usually the protos is the one
who is the most senior, which is often related to time.
Right? Like if you've been a priest longer than another priest
who's of your same rank, then you are the senior
between the two.
to, but not necessarily like so someone could get elevated to rank higher than a priest
who has been senior to him in time.
And then he becomes, you know, he would be the appropriate protest to serve when they were
consulverating together.
Right.
And so this is the thrust of what St. Paul is doing in Romans 9 is that, you know, faced
with people who are saying, well, we're the children of Abraham.
saying yes but the
the sort of singular sun is Christ.
And so if you are not in this relationship of faithfulness
with Christ, you're not going to inherit
just by virtue of being a descendant.
But so what St. Paul is doing is he's taking
a whole set of imagery and understanding
and interpretations of Isaac and applying them to Christ.
and these Isaac-related traditions.
come out of the text of Genesis and then pre-exist, right?
And are developed and then St. Paul takes them to show how see
this is how you connect Christ to this narrative.
Yeah, so Isaac becomes then a pre-figuration of Christ
in this particular way in terms of being the heir,
the seed of the promise through whom the promises made
to Abraham are then going to be distributed to all the
brother in. Right. And in terms of that sign prophecy relationship we were
talking about. Right. Then Isaac the physical son of of Abram and Sarah Isaac as
a person becomes a sort of sign to Abraham of the eventual seed who is coming.
Right. Especially because we'll bring the fulfillment of those spiritual
promises. Especially because Isaac was not, you know, what to expect when
you're not expecting to expect.
You know, right?
Yeah.
Eyes in.
It was not 100 age 90.
Yes, right.
Right.
Yeah, he's definitely a sign.
And so, and this is the term that's
used that the King James translation in many places.
This is not 100%.
But the Greek word mononise is kind of ambiguous.
And it was a term.
interpreted in many places by the King James version,
somewhat incorrectly in that it was taken to be only begotten
pretty much every time it's used.
Yeah, well, I mean, so let's take the word apart for a second
and just sort of explain why that might be the case.
Because so you got mono right, which is solitary or only
or single.
And then Yenius, which can mean, it can mean your child,
but it can also mean like a kind, you know, like it's-
It can mean.
It can mean, you know, there are two possible roots for the Yenis part, right?
Monos is clear.
That's only your one, right?
But the Yenis can come from Yenos, which is like where we get genus.
Yeah, and genetics and that kind of thing.
Yeah, where we get genus.
So a kind of type, right, that becomes a species kind of idea, right?
if you-
come from the verb, you're not, oh, which is to be get.
Yeah.
Right.
And obviously those two words are related to each other.
You know, those, those words have a common root with each other.
And actually then are cognate.
And you know, this is where Richard Roland will write in if I'm getting this wrong.
I'm pretty sure are cognate with English words like kin and kind, actually.
These are all, these are all connected.
Yeah.
So when you put
together to Mano Yonis, depending on the conjugation or the declension and where it is in a sentence,
it could kind of be either in a lot of cases. So either only be gotten or one of a kind.
Right. You need. And so in many places, though, and so the King James, and so because of that,
a lot of people's brains, even people who aren't King James only, like that's an
the traditional thing if they're English speakers.
Right.
So any questioning of it is questioning tradition.
And that, and it's worth pointing out that the King James
translation, which I love, although again, I'm not a KJV,
only person, I love it for many reasons, not for every reason.
Because that's the way it's translated it there,
then a lot of other patristic texts that got translated
into English in, say, the 19th century, for instance,
which is where...
the big bunch that for first translate into English came from.
They then kind of imitate the King James language in many cases for translations of
patristic text as well, thus carrying forward this English translation.
Right. And so in many cases, but all you need really should be translated as unique.
John one is the case of this, the unique God who was in the bosom of the father.
there, for example. But one of the reasons why that unique sun would be used is not just
to differentiate Christ as the Son of God from other beings who are called sons of God.
Right.
That's one reason. But then also on the other side, to connect to this tradition of Isaac
as the unique son in terms of the relationship.
to Abraham. And so you can't, this is a general translation thing. And this is a problem
sometimes when people try to work with languages they don't know that well, like using a
concordance or that kind of thing.
Yeah, you can't just, I mean, you know, you can't just look a word up in your dictionary
and assume that the first thing that it says, or even maybe all 10 things that it might
say in an entry are the right.
thing for whatever it is that you're trying to read or
translate. Right. And then just go and plug it in everywhere.
Right. And it must be the same thing in all these places and
all these passages must be connected. That's that's not true.
Right. You have to go by what's being said in each case. So
sometimes and that's where it becomes clear how mononies is
being used. Sometimes it's very clear. It means that it's
only begotten. That's the idea. Sometimes it's very clear
that it's unique in the sense of differentiating Christ from the
angels and other sons of God. And sometimes it's pretty clear that it's connected to these
Isaac traditions. And those traditions were, this is a less common icon now for reasons we're
about to describe, but they were reflected in some of our iconography in the form of what was called
many centuries ago, the paternity icon.
Right, which is an icon, like there's two versions of this,
there's the sort of more ancient and dare I say authentic icon
where you've got Abraham as an old man and then in his lap
is Isaac as a young child.
Right, and it's sort of parallel to the icons
you would see of the Theotokos with Christ on her lap.
Yeah.
right, right exactly the same basic look. And then there are also then, I don't know enough about
iconography to say whether they are explicitly uncannonical, but certainly a kind of unconventional for sure,
icon, you know, a quote unquote holy trinity icon where you see the father depicted as an old man,
Christ depicted as a child, and then sometimes in his lap a bird for the Holy Spirit,
Certainly that
icon is controversial and from what I understand probably uncannotical but I am again not an iconographer
expert on iconography but doesn't add him. Yeah, don't add me. But the point being that there are
canonical versions of that that are expressing something that is uncontroversial. Abraham and I
And the controversial ones seem to be in a line of dissent from the uncontroversial ones.
Yeah.
That the A-brain-
Abraham and Isaac icons were intended to sort of the way that, say, Andre Rublo's Trinity
icon is meant to convey the Holy Trinity but not depict to the Holy Trinity.
Yeah, kind of an eye.
And I.
And I. In a sense an icon of an icon.
Right.
That Abraham and Isaac as persons are icons, you know, relating to the father and the son.
Um.
And then we make an icon of that of them being that.
Yeah. So it becomes very met.
Yeah. And in the same way that you will occasionally have people slip a little bit,
not quite understand and say that the that Christ and the two angels in the
root left Trinity icon are, you know, well, this is the Holy Spirit.
And this is the, well, we know that's not accurate.
Right.
that it's an icon situation.
The same thing happened centuries ago with the
eternity icons where the represent slipped out.
People just started saying,
oh, well, this is the father and Christ.
Yeah.
Yeah. Okay, so we've kind of established
what Isaac's place is, but within his story,
I mean, he shows up, he shows up like in Jacob's story,
but within his story in scripture,
what is he actually doing?
What is he accomplishing?
There's kind of two things, right?
So the one that everybody, I mean,
that he goes to thinks about first,
which is totally pro...
is the sacrifice of Isaac.
You know, the sort of attempted sacrifice of Isaac
by Abraham, right?
Yeah, we, I know it's funny, we call it the sacrifice
of Isaac.
I'm like, actually, he doesn't get sacrificed by the way.
But, and then also he gets,
he sort of does, he sort of does symbolically
when we talk about that.
Right, right, he's, yeah, exactly, exactly.
And then the other thing is that he gets married, right?
Which, you know, if you've ever been to an Orthodox
wedding service, you know that this gets invoked.
blessed them, O Lord, as that is blessed Isaac and Rebecca, among other, you know,
couples in the Scripture that are mentioned. So I mean, let's talk about that first,
because the sacrifice is the much bigger elephant in the room, I guess.
Yes, so what's going on with the wedding to Rebecca? What does that mean other than just,
oh, hey, Isaac needed to get married so that he could have kids so that this whole big
descendants thing could happen? Right. And they married a Mesopotamian rather than a
Okay, then.
Right.
They go back to his people.
Abraham going back to his own people actually, in this case means Isaac is married to
his first cousin.
But yeah, that's not the point.
It's not about cousin marriage.
It is interesting because of what it says.
And what it says is something that we gloss over very quickly as sort of modern Western
people.
Well, yeah.
deeply imbibed the idea of romantic love.
Yeah, it says, Isaac loved Rebecca, which that's, you know, that's kind of not even worth
mentioning these days.
Of course, a husband of wife got married.
Yeah, right.
Yeah, of course.
I mean, he must have loved her.
But like, that was not, that, that, what is unremarkable now was totally remarkable then.
The idea that a husband should love his wife was just not even on the radar.
Right.
Yeah, and it was an arranged marriage. I mean, that's the greater part of the story is that marriage being arranged
By Abraham through one of his servants. Yeah. Yeah, there's no point where Isaac says like his brother
There's no point where Isaac is like I hope I meet somebody
You know, maybe we'll
Yeah, they don't run into each other and fight out. They have a lot of the same hobbies
grew up watching the same TV shows. Yeah
so
Why is that a-
Well, it's not just that that's rare in the ancient world right at expression of love
But it's rare in the book of Genesis
Right, this is I mean you do have Adam and Eve in a monoclebus marriage sort of I mean marriage, right, but
It's kind of dysfunctional
Yeah
Yeah, we don't really see much about the marriage of Adam and Eve that looks that great. I mean, we don't see most of it
Yeah, but just kind of see
mostly the bad parts actually. Right, but you even look at Abraham and he's got
concubines right? He's got and Jacob has you know two wives and a couple of
concubines all that he has kids with. He saw as marrying pagans. It on and on. Right?
On and on. You have Ruben trying to sleep with one of his father's concubines. I
I mean, right?
So you do...
don't get a lot of solid monogamous marriages in Genesis, outside of Isaac and Rebecca.
Right. And so they serve as this sort of icon of, they're the ones in Genesis who do it the way God intended it.
Right. I say that's the way God intended it because Christ says that's how God intended it.
the hospitals, but that's the image of doing it right.
And so we have this, then there's a pattern that after the story we're about to talk about,
the sacrifice of Isaac, that you then have, then he then gets married.
These are the two, this is Isaac's life as his story is presented in an episode of
sacrifice and then his marriage.
Yeah, and it's important to note the sequence.
You know, he is offered up and then he gets married.
So just hold that in your mind.
And let's talk about the sacrifice now.
Right, by popular demand.
Yes, indeed.
So when we read it today, and this is partially
sorened Kierkegaard's fault, so something was rotten
in the state of Denmark.
And it ended up kind of fiddle-aig with how we read this story.
So we as as one of people.
we read the story of Abraham and the sacrifice of Isaac.
We approach it from Abraham's perspective.
Abraham is the character into which we insert ourselves.
Yeah, the big question being then is,
okay, if I'm Abraham and I hear a voice from God saying,
okay, go offer your son and kill him and sacrifice him to me.
And especially listeners to this podcast,
we'll then think the next thing.
And wait, am I supposed to eat him?
You know.
That's the big moral quandary, right?
Like to kill or not to kill.
What, you know, by the way, since he brought all the kindling,
this is the whole kindling issue, presumably it would have been a whole
whole burn offering, yeah, just to ease people's minds.
He was not thinking about eating guys.
Yeah.
That was not the plan.
Yeah, because there's, you know, as we've said,
there's multiple kinds of sacrifices and while some of them do involve eating on the part
of the people, not all of them do.
Right. So you can
the whole thing to God. Yeah, right, right, right. Yeah. But but then that's not actually the the
angle that second temporal literature again, this tradition that exists around the time of the
apostles. That's not the way that they tend to look at it. They don't tend to look at it as like,
oh, what should Abraham do? You know, how faithful is it a moral dilemma? Yeah, how faithful is he
is it going to be a problem?
It perhaps troll your problem.
Right.
Which I mean, like it's not that that's not an inch
. . .
interesting question, right? It is. Yeah, it's not like we shouldn't ever talk about that
or whatever, but that the main focus actually is on Isaac. What is Isaac doing as Isaac
as the main character in this scene? Right. Right. And that, that the idea was to view
the event from the perspective of Isaac. And when you do that, there are several things
that sort of emerge. And the first and foremost, the one that's the constant source of
meditations.
not only in sort of second-tepal literature proper,
but in prayers from that period that we have preserved,
this becomes a major, major emphasis
at a way of interpreting other parts of the Old Testament
that they focus on Isaac's silence.
Right.
That most of us, you know,
if someone was trying to tie us up and kill us,
would be kicking and screaming.
Right.
Even if it was our dad, right?
Yeah, reasonable, reasonable behavior.
But yeah, so he's quiet.
He asks, you know, he asks a question, but that's pretty much it.
Yeah, all the way, he asks, you know, hey, where are we going to get?
But then, yeah.
And so that silence, we talked about in the sacrifice episode that we just answered
a couple of colors about.
We talked about how there was we find this tradition and sacrifices where the animal sort of voluntarily offers itself
yeah, right and
That's how this silence the silence of Isaac was understood in this
In this context so that his silence becomes
emblematic of obedience and self offering and
and
That is so firmly embedded by the second temple period,
it's understanding of Isaac,
that the most common interpretation
of the suffering servant in Isaiah,
all of those passages,
as a sheep led to this slaughter,
as well as I would open it's not his mouth,
all of those texts, all the texts about the suffering servant
were interpreted as being initially about Isaac.
Hmm.
Right, sort of immediately as meditations on...
on Isaac, and there are prayers that we have reserved that I mentioned that are prayed
sort of from the perspective of Isaac from the second temple period.
And those prayers are interesting because they're hugely controversial because a whole
bunch of people want to insist that they have to be Christian.
But they're actually because before Christ.
Right, because the way they pertur-
Isaac is so close to early Christian so
voced meditation on the death of Christ
that that Isaiah imagery that they're
like there's no way but this was being
done with with with Isaac.
Yeah so where I mean what out of
curiosity what texts would you look
in to find those prayers?
Well you'd have to find a very obscure
book called prayers supposed to
be Jewish, published by the Society of Biblical Literature.
Wow.
What a title.
Yes.
We're supposed to be Jewish.
That sort of compiling the whole argument back and forth.
That's interesting.
About.
Yeah.
But yeah, so Isaac and yes, it is also true
that those text in Isaiah were understood
to be talking about the Messiah.
And this is true not only pre-Christian,
But even...
in rabbinic Judaism, you can go all the way to my monides in the medieval period was
still saying that that was about the Messiah.
People may be familiar with the more modern rabbinic Jewish interpretation that that's
talking about Israel, right?
Right.
Not talking about the Messiah because sort of all messianism has been purged from rabbinic
Judaism or close to it by this point.
reaction to Christianity, but even in the Middle Ages, that was all the Messiah.
But in all of those cases, they're still going through Isaac to get there.
Right? So understanding that is the Messiah, they were understanding that I,
this is talking about Isaac, but that Isaac is an image of the Messiah who is,
who is coming. And even with the people of Israel, they're, they're, they're really,
even in that modern interpretation, they're kind of going through Isaac as
representative of Israel, right, as the forefather, the patriarch of
of Israel being the singular person in that text, right?
So it's kind of unavoidable.
It's so embedded in Old Testament interpretation
and understanding.
So then the other big thing that gets talked about here
is certain folks, they know who they are,
get a little getty about this story.
because of the ram in the thicket.
Yeah, right.
Because they say, oh, this is where I can get my
substitutionary atonement back in here.
Yeah, and for those who don't,
who maybe not know what that means,
substitutionary atonement,
it's the idea that comes largely out of the reformation
that mankind because of his sins,
deserves punishment from God.
And so you're born with a sentence of punishment
And then
Jesus steps in and says, no, wait, I'll take that punishment.
Give it to me instead because God has to punish sin.
God has to be satisfied because of sin.
And so this is called substitutionary atonement.
And so then people look at the sacrifice of Isaac's scene,
and they see the ram that's in the thicket.
It's like, OK, that ram, that's Jesus, who's going to step in
and take this.
so that Isaac doesn't have to.
Although, I mean, there's all kinds of issues
other than just what we're about to talk about in terms of,
you know, like, just on its face, it's like, wait,
what did Isaac do that he has to be sacrificed as the response?
Like, what does it say that Isaac is a sin offering?
Right. Yeah.
Which goes completely against the whole system of the way.
I mean, you know, you don't have the whole Torah yet, right?
but yeah, yeah.
So yeah, just internally it has problems.
But actually, there's way more going on here, right?
Right, there is something positive going on with the RAM that you miss if you go and try
to go in that direction.
And just to save you some home actualies, right?
What you were describing coming out of the information is really penal substitution.
Penal, excuse me, yes, yes.
Which evolves out of satisfaction theory, which has some of those elements that's usually
associated with ANCELM five centuries earlier.
this Western development of the ID.
of substitutionary atonement over which penal substitution is a species.
Particular case.
Yeah, because, I mean, we don't have to go into it, but the idea that Christ is a substitute
is a thing in patristic commentary, but not in certain ways.
Yeah, it's certain ways.
In this way.
Yeah, right, exactly, exactly.
Right.
So, what's going on with the RAM?
And the problem is that the presupposition here is that you're coming to it with a presupposition
that something has to die.
That's the reason why the RAM is there.
Yeah, right Isaac has to die well if Isaac isn't going to die that there's some necessity here
And therefore if Isaac doesn't die something else has to die in his place, right? We must have blood for the blood god
Yes
That's right and and that presupposition is nowhere in Genesis up to this point. Yeah, just leave it at that right
There's nowhere where a reader of Genesis would get that without completely importing it
Um.
So where we get at the importance of what's going on here with the RAM
and why the RAM is being offered as a thank offering,
is the location where this takes place.
Right.
So the location where this takes place, the mountain to the top of which,
the high place to which Abraham takes Isaac to sacrifice him is Mount Moriah,
Right, Mount Moria.
And that...
name literally means the place where Yahweh appears.
Right, you've got that Yah there on the end.
Yeah.
The place where Yahweh appears.
So it is not coincidental that this mountain is the mountain where the temple is later built.
Because the temple is the place where Yahweh appears on the day of atonement.
Exactly.
Right.
We've talked about that at length.
what they had.
to offer the cloud of incense. And so this isn't just the place where Abraham offers this ram,
this one time. This is the place where all of the future rams, all of the future bowls, all of
the future that are legitimate offerings to Yahweh as he has said he desires to be worshiped. This
This is the place where all of those are going to be offered in the future.
Right, right. And so there is a kind of substitution here in the sense that all of these animal sacrifices
that are going to take place on this mountain are a substitute for the sacrifice of the unique sun.
Yeah, so that substitute actually goes the other way, then the penal substitution.
And so in a very clear sense then, the rams begin to be offered at this point until such time as the Monoyennis, the unique son, Isaac in his fulfillment who is Jesus Christ, will be offered.
Right? And so this is why very quickly, very quickly, almost immediately.
in the New Testament period, among the apostles,
they stop sacrificing animals.
That's how they understand that is being fulfilled.
The animal sacrifices there were,
the sin offerings there were a fill in,
a substitute for the real thing,
a shadow of the real thing,
an image of the real thing.
Right. And so when the real thing came
You don't need those pointers anymore, but the first pointer is Isaac himself
Right that it's going to be the unique son who's going to
To fulfill it
And there's one place in the New Testament where there is a sort of meditation on
the story of Isaac in general and
His relation to the promises and especially his this episode of the sacrifice of Isaac
directly, a direct, clear reference.
Yeah, and this basically summarizes together,
in one fairly short passage, everything we've just said
for this whole episode, right?
Yeah, so this is in Hebrews 11, verses 16 through 19.
This is what St. Paul writes there.
But as it is, they desire a better country,
that is a heavenly one.
Therefore, God is not ashamed to be called their God,
for he is prepared for them.
city. By faith Abraham when he was tested offered up Isaac, and he who had received the
promises was in the act of offering up his only son of whom it was said, through Isaac,
shall your seed be named. He considered that God was able even to raise him from the dead,
which figuratively speaking he did receive him back.
So what's going on?
on here. Right. So well, first at the beginning there in what's Hebrew's 1116, there's a pointer
to this idea we were talking about in the last act in a second half about the idea that
the the the the physical land was this sign of the fulfillment of the rest of the promises
to Abraham. But then it immediately
goes to the fact that those greater promises are going to be received through Isaac.
And specifically now it focuses on this offering of his only son through whom his seed would be named.
So this is the singular son.
This is who the promises are going to come through.
And Abraham's being told to now kill him.
Hmm, and so there's this obvious
immediate tension there, right? And so that tension is resolved here in, say,
Paul's epistle to the Hebrews by pointing out that Airem had it is head that God was able
to raise him from the dead, right? Which happens by way of a figure, by way of a symbol,
way of a sign. Yeah and it's worth pointing out here too by the way.
that the word monoyenis is used here to refer to Isaac in this passage, St. Paul uses that word,
but we couldn't understand it here. So this is an example of where we can't understand
monoyenis, meaning only begotten because Isaac is not Abraham's only begotten son. He's got,
in fact, an older brother, Ishmael. Yes, he's Sarah's only begotten, but not Abraham's.
Yeah, so the only way to read it in this passage is
as being the unique son, the one who is uniquely his son
in this particular way.
Right.
And so what here Abraham is said to understand
is that he is going to receive those promises
through the death and resurrection of the unique son.
And what happens on that mountain with Isaac
is the figure.
the symbol, the sign of
of that reality which then manifests itself in our human experience
in the person of Jesus Christ in his death
resurrection ascension, right, and of course his incarnation as a whole
That is the means by which those spiritual promises that and
And Hebrews is saying Abraham realized that.
Wow.
Abraham realized that through the sign.
Yeah, that's really cool.
Sorry, I just have to say that.
I mean, I've read this passage my whole life.
But, and, you know, the idea that this has something to do with Christ,
it's, you know, sure, okay, you know,
there's that, you know, God was able to raise him from the dead.
You know, he even says that.
But, but just to hear it all kind of brought together like that is,
is just really, really beautiful.
Yeah.
Yeah. And so that kind of manifests itself in various other ways at other parts of the
New Testament, right? So when when Christ is talking to the Sadducees about the resurrection,
right? And they of course do not believe in it. They do not believe the Anastasis is going
to happen. What does he say to prove it? He says God says he's the God of Abraham, Isaac
can check up he's not the
God of the dead but of the living.
Meaning he's saying Abraham, Isaac and Jacob
have already participated in the resurrection.
What St. John will call the first resurrection.
Meaning Abraham, Isaac and Jacob had received
those promises at the spiritual level.
They had received that theosis at deification right,
and we're now.
And this is why you usually,
This is why you see Abraham depicted in Paradise.
Yeah, right. In iconography. And then this is mostly a plug here, as we draw our third half
to a close, you should read for Ezra. Okay. Everyone, including Father Andrew. Yeah.
If you're a slav, it's in your Bible.
Yeah, this is one of the little...
differences of the Old Testament canon within the Orthodox Church.
It's, you know, the Russian canon has fourth Ezra, but the Greek canon does not.
Yeah.
And now someone will try to, I'm actually us by saying it's in a appendix and I will say,
okay, what's the canonical status of a appendix?
Right.
Exactly.
It's in there.
It's in the book.
That's all I'm saying.
And that means you should probably read it.
Right.
So why read fourth?
with regards to all of this.
In this context, one of the,
one of the, the book is a series of visions that Ezra has,
Ezra described, like the book of Ezra.
Or first and second Ezra,
depending on how you number those.
Anyway, that Ezra has, and one of them
is this vision of the bridegroom.
that's sort of a parable of the bridegroom.
And all of the bridegroom imagery that you see
in the New Testament is not taken from for Ezra
for Ezra was written too late from that.
But it's sort of drawing on the same wells.
It's drawing on the same traditions.
And so it gives us a glimpse of this.
And in it, the bridegroom comes to consummate his marriage.
and then
as he crosses the threshold to enter into the bridal chamber
and consummate his marriage, he dies.
And then there is this mourning that takes place
by the people for the bridegroom who died
before he could consummate his marriage.
And not only are a number of the parables
regarding bridegrooms and Christ portrayal
as a bridegroom in the New Testament
drawing on some of these same traditions,
but especially that
morning for the bridegroom. What's your familiar with it? A lot of what goes on in
bridegroom matins are the fact that it's called bridegroom matins at the
beginning of Holy Week. It starts to make a lot of sense because this is this is
that arc that we see in the story of Isaac as a person when he gets his own
story in Genesis. His death and resurrection and then his the consummation of his
marriage. The sort of idea.
realized a cut of graphic marriage, which of course everyone would say, oh well that marriage points to Christ of the Church.
Exactly.
So just a death at resurrection of Christ.
The resurrection of Christ and then the conservation of his marriage to the Church.
That's cool.
Yeah.
All right. Well, just to, you know, make some final comments.
One of the things that's most valuable to me about
everything that we just discussed is one of the
the kind of meta points of this podcast, which is to try as much as possible to give people
a framework within which to understand the whole scripture.
So, and then if you understand scripture, you understand Christianity truly, right?
If you understand scripture in the right way.
And there's multiple ways to do that.
So like one of the ways, the arc that we chose for this episode is the arc of the story
of Abraham. So you got, you know, Abraham being called out.
of this civilization that is dominated by demons
and that he has given promises by God
that his descendants would be as the stars
that they would also be numerous, right?
That they would receive this land
that they would displace the dark powers.
All of these promises given to Abraham and then
and then fulfilled through his seed, which in sort of
of the meantime is Isaac and then ultimately is Christ,
whom then we see fulfilling what Isaac did,
which is who symbolically dies and comes back to life,
and then is married, Christ truly dies,
comes back to life, and then his marriage to the church.
So I mean, this is one of the big arcs.
And you might ask the question,
well, what's the point in trying to understand the scripture
in this way?
Well, there's a couple of things that I want to say.
Number one, if you understand large-
arcs of scripture. Again, this is not the only one, right? There are multiple arcs that you can
use to understand the whole scriptures. But if you understand the large arcs, then actually then it
gives, it makes it easier to understand particular passages as you're reading it. Again, we're trying
to point people towards reading the scripture for themselves. And then it makes a lot more sense,
then, because it's easy going to get lost in the weeds in scripture. If you don't have the plot,
so to speak. Now there's several plots going on. So if you know...
particular ones, then you can see it more clearly.
But aside just from that sort of logistical advantage
to being able to read the Bible better,
understanding what Scripture says helps us to understand
who Christ is and what He accomplished,
right, and then also then what He expects from us.
And this is what the proclamation of the gospel actually is.
So we
Certainly we receive the gospel in an initial way and we believe it and we choose to become
faithful to God in response, but we need to be continuously re-evangelized.
I need to receive the gospel not just over and over but more and more deeply so that I
can be more faithful, so that I can know who Christ is, what he accomplished, what he
expects of me.
And I think that the story of Abraham
as continue then in Isaac and then fulfilled in Christ is really a powerful, powerful way
to receive the gospel.
And knowing this story, then, it's also a powerful way to preach the gospel to people.
The whole gospel message is contained within this arc that you see in Scripture.
This is all very practical.
Yes, you don't necessarily need to preach the gospel by telling people about the fact that
There's three
of or but really there's only two like that's not a critical critical
detail right
But but nonetheless having this sense of where Abraham comes from and then all the rest
That is a very powerful way of preaching the gospel so that's that's my primary takeaway father Stephen
so
We had a we had a color tonight asking about sacrament. Oh
living. And I think what I want to kind of focus on for a minute is this relationship
that we talked about between sign and prophecy, between sign and the thing signified between
the material and immediate sign and then the greater spiritual fulfillment, spiritual reality.
That's the core of what Sacramento or I guess
mysterious would be the or super orthodox version. What that is getting at, right?
That there is a complete union between the sign and the thing signified between the two. But
it's very uncommon for us as modern Western people to keep that union in our brain for very long
and there's lots of places where this can go sideways. So on one side, you have the more
material.
side where the focus shifts almost entirely to the material side, until sometimes that's
sort of functionally, even if you don't come out and say that you're denying the reality
of the spiritual functionally, you're only interacting on the material side.
This takes lots of forms.
We already took a mean-spirited shot at our poor dispensational friends earlier for focusing
on the sign part.
the physical land part of Abraham's promises rather than on the spiritual side.
But this is far more extensive than that in religious life in North America.
The idea that Christianity gets reduced to like a prosperity gospel, or even among people who
are more mainstream in terms of their theology.
on the conservative side, it's very easy for Christianity to get reduced to a kind of
private or personal morality.
I don't do certain things because I'm a Christian.
And I do a couple of things, but not many, like go to church.
But I don't do much of the, my personal morality, that's what I'm doing to be a Christian.
And then on the more liberal side, it gets reduced to a more corporate.
or community morality, or social justice kind of morality,
where we're doing good in the world
and that's what it means to be a Christian
is to go and do these good things in this world.
And that's it.
Or you can go in the other direction
where you begin to ignore the material.
And this may be a temptation
that maybe we experience more as Orthodox Christians
where we wanna talk about
theiosis all the time and prayer rules and contemplative prayer and hezekasm
and where we shift away that material, we shift away the sign completely, we ignore the
sign and we want to go just straight to the spiritual as if we can just sort of dive into
it and comprehend it without the material sign or participate in it without the material
sign and so then you know we sort of don't care about the fact
that we drove past five homeless people on the way to church because we're going to church
and we're going to celebrate the liturgy and have these great feelings of the presence
of Christ and the Holy Spirit.
And we're going to receive the sacraments.
Not that any of those things are bad.
It's just we're ignoring a whole other field.
And the truth of the reality of Christianity is found in, as we said, that sacramental
level of realizing that those are the same thing.
So when Christ went and fed people.
when Christ went and healed people of physical illnesses, right?
Those same people were going to die of something else later.
But when he healed the sick, he healed the paralyzed,
he healed the disabled, he fed people.
Those were signs of the coming of the kingdom.
Those were concrete actions and experiences that made the kingdom
and made the gospel and made who Christ was in His promises,
real to those people.
just as the gospel became real to Abraham as he actually stood on a mountain ready to kill his son,
but received him back alive.
And so this is the place where we need to go when we start to, as modern people, as we're prone to,
have doubts about the spiritual side.
Is this spiritual stuff really true?
The whole doctor of the Holy Trinity is fun to argue about online, but is it true?
is are these things real? You will find they're real when you start
participating in the signs of their reality. When you start giving a cup of
water to what of Christ little ones in his name. Not that that is an ended
itself, not that that is a good work that's going to earn you salvation or
something, but that is the place when you show love for someone. That's the
place where you will experience Christ's love.
And it will be
come real to you.
All of these things become real through those signs
and our behavior and actions in this world
toward other people at an individual level
and at a community level, at a social level
and privately by ourselves with our families,
with our communities, with our church, out in public.
This is where we have endless opportunities
to actively participate in and see the reality
the spiritual.
through the physical and the material and our own lives and the eyes, lives of other people.
All right, well, so this was our anniversary episode. It's been a whole year of Lord of Spirits.
We estimate that we actually now have about 12,000 regular listeners, which I mean, that's just
amazing. We're so grateful you're here. Occasionally we get asked if we're planning to wrap up the show
soon, but actually we've got a pretty endless list of ideas. So onward and upward,
Excel's year
I am Jack the King Kirby in this analogy, and so I accept it.
But I'm also here for, you know, you may be here for the 12,000 regular listeners.
I'm here for all the irregular ones.
That is our so for today.
Thank you very much everyone for listening.
If you didn't get a chance to call in during this live broadcast, we'd love to hear from
you either via email at LordOfSpiritsatheachintfaith.com or you can message us at our Lord of Spheres
podcast Facebook page.
We do read everything but we can't respond everything and we do save some of what you send for possible use in future episodes
And join us for our live broadcasts on the second and fourth Thursdays of the month at 7 p.m. Eastern 4 p.m.
Pacific and if you're on Facebook you can like our page and join our discussion group
Leave reviews and ratings everywhere but most importantly share this show with a friend whom you know is going to love it or
or hate listen to it regularly.
And finally, be sure to go to ancientfaith.com Stroke Submit.
and help make sure we and lots of other AFR podcasters stay on the air.
And by my new book, Horizon God, and also Father Stevens' book, Religion of the Apostles at
store.ancientfaith.com.
Thank you, good night, and God bless you.
You've been listening to the Lord of Spirits with Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew
Stephen Damick, and Father Stephen De Young, a listener-supported presentation of Ancient
Faith Radio.
I be held and I heard the voice of many angels round about the throne.
and the beasts and the elders, and the number of them was 10,000 times 10,000,
and thousands of thousands, saying with a loud voice, worthy as the land that was slain to receive power,
and riches, and wisdom, and strength, and honor, and glory, and blessing.
Revelation chapter 5 verses 11 through 12.