to a form of an idol.
So as we move through the rest of Great Lent, sharing this I'm going to try my best to
focus on just experiencing the fruits that taking care of my soul first will benefit and
give towards my body.
And how when I do do the right things for my body, my purpose should be with the
intention of allowing it to benefit my soul. So we see this beautiful relationship
between soul and body, but the center of it all is making sure that any
intention, anything that we are striving to do, we're seeking, yearning, trying
to love, deepen and understand Christ more.
And so as we have these beautiful seasons outlined for us throughout the church, let us allow
them to guide us to yet another joyous celebration of Paska, where we see Christ choosing to resurrect
us from the old to the new.
and fasting with Rita Madden. Rita Madden is a registered
dietician who finds inspiration.
in the great role that the Orthodox Christian faith plays in her modern day health care profession.
Please note that the information contained in this podcast is not intended as a substitute
for professional medical advice. Rather, it is provided for educational purposes only.
This has been a listener-supported presentation of Ancient Faith Radio.
He will be a staff for the righteous with which for them to stand and not to fall, and
he will be the light of the nations and the hope of those whose hearts are troubled.
All who dwell on the earth will fall down and worship him, and they will praise and bless
and celebrate with song the Lord of Spirits, 1st Inok, chapter 48, verses 4-5.
The modern world doesn't acknowledge but is nevertheless haunted by spirits, angels,
demons and saints.
In our time, many year into break free of the prison of a flat, secular materialism, to
see and to know reality as it truly is.
What is this spiritual reality like?
How do we engage with it well?
How do we permeate everyday life with spiritual presence?
Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen De Young
host this live Colin Cho focused on enchantment in creation, the union of the scene and unseen
As
made by God and experienced by mankind throughout history.
Welcome to the Lord of Spirits.
Welcome back everyone to the Lord of Spirits podcast.
Thank you, Voice of Steve.
I feel funny saying that because I literally just had dinner
with the Voice of Steve.
And he's headed back to New York now.
My co-host, Father Stephen D'Young,
is with me from Lafayette, Louisiana.
And I'm Father Andrew Stephen Damick
in a Mayus, Pennsylvania.
If you're listening to a sly, if you can call in it...
855 AF radio that's 8552372346 and Montesca Trudy will be taking your calls tonight.
Please be nice to her.
We'll get to your calls in the second part of today's show.
So Lord of Spirits is brought to you by our listeners with help from St. Athanasius Academy
of Orthodox Theology.
St. Athanasius is an online academy for kindergarten through 12th grade offering live classrooms
in core subjects for in languages.
various electives and orthodox studies.
To learn more about St. Athenius' Academy, please visit www.saot.edu.
So thanks, everybody. It's in Athenius for your help.
So how do we know what we know?
What in us is doing the knowing? Is it the mind?
Who is doing the knowing? Do we actually know what we think we know?
And do we know it in the way that we think we know it?
The modern world tends to collapse all of these questions.
into a few basic answers. We know their minds, our minds think thoughts, and we know things
because they can be proven. But the ancient world in which the scriptures were written, in
that world what it means to know and how things are known, and even what thoughts are,
form a much more complex picture that applies to human experience in a richer and more vibrant
manner. So tonight we mean to sort through these questions, especially focusing on what the
scriptures.
say about them. But first let's start with this modern concept. So father Stephen, I want
to start by asking, can we even know what we're knowing without ever knowing the way?
Well, anyone can see that the roads that they walk on are paved and gold. And it's always
summer and they'll never grow cold. Yeah. That's one of my favorite sort of semi-personal
apocalyptic songs. People just walk off into, you know, sleep it all behind. Yeah. When
When you walk off into the sunset though, eventually.
like you're just standing somewhere in the dark.
Yeah, and that's that awkward moment of
you've made your dramatic exit now what?
So yeah, we're gonna talk about
what it means to know things,
which people probably think they know
but maybe you don't know what it means to know things, right?
And mainly part of a big part of what we're going to be getting at tonight is that
it means different things to know different things.
Right.
And if we kind of boil that all down to one idea, which of course is what the modern world has done for us,
It's boiling all that down to one idea.
You're not going to have a good time.
Uh, because...
there are going to be things that you try to know in a certain way that you can't
know that way and just can't get at it. And things that then become completely
closed and unknowable to you. And that will make sense as we go on. That's not just us
playing with the word no. Yeah, this is not just a bunch of you know punny
double talk or whatever. Yeah so the place we're gonna start with
is the modern concept of knowing, right?
To me, the character, yeah exactly exactly, the ancient parallel.
Yeah, to me the characteristic phrase of the modern notion of knowing is, studies have
shown.
You know, when you hear that, it's like, oh, now we know that we know something because
studies have shown, whatever it might be.
So we tend to think of science.
Science is the way to know things in the modern world.
Yeah, and...
studies especially as we're going to see are sort of a democratization of knowledge, right?
So we sort of get to all of the vote. We did this study, X percent said this, therefore, why?
But we'll get there. So yeah, the word that's used for this kind of knowledge and that gets
translated into English and Greek is epistemi where we get epistemology, epistemic, and all those
related words and
Epistemia is sometimes even translated science
Depending on what you're reading translated from from Greek
And and this is the kind of knowledge we major in but in the ancient world it was distinguished
Epistemic knowledge was knowledge of very particular things specifically it was things that could be demonstrated and
Demonstrated had a particular meaning to it meant
Thank you.
I could show it to you.
I could prove it to you.
So if I come to you and say two plus two equals four
and you say, now man, I don't buy it.
Right?
What's all this about?
I can take two apples and put them on the table
and then take two more apples and put them on the table.
And I could show it to you.
I could prove it to you.
Right.
And so these are things that you can have a certain,
I was about to do a word play on the words.
certain, but you have a certain type of knowledge and that type of knowledge is certain.
You could be sure, right?
That's right.
Because if you ever have any doubt, it could just be demonstrated to you again, right?
Again, you can prove again.
Yeah.
And this is the basis for the scientific method.
And it's why, for instance, there's, you know, if you ever read stuff that's about the
way that science actually gets practiced, there's a number of interesting articles floating
around out there about what's called the replication crisis.
And the science is where a lot of studies that are done,
that no one can replicate them to get the same results
as this original study that was done that supposedly
everything, you know, some big policy decision was based
on or whatever, because scientific method requires
the ability to replicate that demonstration.
And if you can't get the same results over and over again
by doing exactly the same things,
then it's not really science, you know.
So it's not demands.
It's not appeased to me.
Right.
And so this is a very narrow type of knowledge in the ancient world.
Most of what we would say we know does not fall into that category.
So in the ancient world, history is not in that category.
Right.
Because I can't recreate and prove to you the date Napoleon was born.
Right? Or the political crisis of the 18th century in France,
like you can't run an experiment,
you know, where you recreate the French revolution.
Or do a mathematical proof, or, right?
So all of that was outside of that.
And so every other type of knowledge
that you couldn't demonstrate in that way
was some form of doxa.
and docks is a noun that
comes from the verb dokeo, which means to seem or to appear. And there was an ancient
heresy called dositism, which it was called dositism because it was the idea that Christ only
seemed to be human. Yes, yes, this was one. These were some of the enemies of our old
of the Palestinian Ignatius of Antioch.
Right. He looked like a man, but he was not actually a man.
Yeah, that was exactly.
So that was that's this idea of seeming.
And and so docks really conveyed that there was it was an appearance.
It was a viewpoint, right?
Right.
It was a perspective.
And so based on that, anything within that realm was going to be something
that you established sort of based on testimony.
you would collect the testimony of people
with various viewpoints on an event happening an idea, right?
And then you would sort of compile those, right?
To get a sense of it, but you could never demonstrate it.
You could never prove it.
Right.
And this, by the way, to annoy a bunch of people.
This could be one of those things that, see,
I'm not on Facebook anymore,
so I won't have to read all the people
I'm proud to challenge this.
they get upset. We'll father Andrew Will. It's true. The the docks in orthodoxy is this docks
uh yes it's the docks of opinion or of seamy or viewpoint or perspective the right viewpoint
the right perspective the right you know that the right opinion that's what orthodoxy means
the word for glory is related to this actually because glory
you can see how the idea of glory is related to the idea of appearance, right?
Yeah, or reputation. Right. And so you can see how those are connected, but even
that kind of glory isn't connected to worship. So folks stop saying that
orthodoxy means right worship. Right. Now we're not saying that orthodoxy
orthodox Christianity isn't right worship, but it's just not what the word
mean, not what the word means, yeah, etymologically.
Right. Yeah. So send your angry cards and letters to father Andrew Damick.
Yep. I'll take all of them. Yeah. Yeah.
Right. But yeah, books, this idea of a kind of knowledge that's about testimony and about
perspective. And we'll talk about why that's sort of a problem in the modern world.
And yet, it is capable, right?
So for instance, you know, like at a court case,
there's all kinds of things on which the basis
of judgments are made and verdicts handed down
that are simply based on someone's perspective.
Now they usually try to get multiple witnesses
to say, you know, to say essentially the same thing,
but it can't be demonstrated.
You know, you can't do a scientific experiment
to show someone killing someone else
or something like that.
right here.
evidence for it, but that's not the same thing, right? You know, it can't be replicated.
You know, all you have is these things that indicate that it did happen, but it's still
not a demonstration in the same way.
Yeah, and this, if you've ever watched a court show just about any court show, you've
seen this dynamic play out because they'll call some expert witness, right, who will give
the scientific testimony about the car accident. Like we can tell from the skid marks that the
car was going this fast, right? And this direction.
and here's how all the physics works, here's how all this stuff.
And the defense attorney will get up and say,
well, is it also possible that this other thing happened?
Right?
Is it possible that it actually went this other way?
Or are you saying that it's just completely mathematically
demonstrable that it happened this one way?
And the witness will admit, well, OK, no, it could have
happened this other way.
And then, oh, there goes the whole case.
Roll credits on the show.
Right?
Because...
because even if you're bringing scientific evidence
into something, it still has to be curated by people
who then delivery a thoxa about what it is that they saw.
Right, here's how the data seems to me.
It seems, yeah.
Right.
Yeah, that I'm looking over.
Here's how I interpret the data.
So, and we have a clear idea of this.
Like, I don't think anything we just said about data
having to be interpreted would be controversial.
But some of our friends 150 years ago
approached things a little differently, especially in Germany.
Is this 19th century German scholars again?
Yes, this is 19th century Germany.
And it bled out all over everywhere.
So there's a bingo sheet somewhere that just got crossed.
Yeah, it's all about the visten shopped.
Right, they, they want.
right? They were very keen on, you know, they still had that head rush from the
enlightenment going and they were very keen that all of human knowledge could
come to be sort of scientifically established. Right? So that means we can
make everything a science, right? So you get the idea of political science, right?
not politics the way Aristotle did it. Right. When Aristotle wrote...
his politics, he went and got the constitutions of Athens and a whole bunch of other cities
and compared them, right?
He evaluated them and interpreted that data.
He was not claiming to have some kind of mathematical science, but no, we're going to do political
science now.
And history, as we've talked about before, was seen in this positivist sense, you know,
as a science, just to take another shot at Hodge, an old print.
right? You read the preface to his systematic theology and he directly says, you know, you go to the Bible and you get the data.
You get these logical propositions, right? You get proposition A, proposition B, you use your logic, right? A, B, therefore C, you know, C, D, therefore E, you could
these logical chains. And so for Hodg, his 19th century
Presbyterian American Calvinism was as firmly established as the
laws of physics and justice demonstrable. Right? Right. And now we look at that kind of laugh,
or at least I do. But that was the idea. That was the idea. And those ideas still bleed through a lot.
There are still a lot of people among us with that enlightenment, head rush, still going on.
Right. You get these, you know, I'm an atheist. I only believe in science folks who want to come
and tell you that Jesus never ex-
because there's no evidence, because they're trying to do history by way of science.
Right. And the problem, of course, is that it's a reduction in terms of what human knowledge can be.
You know, if you say that something is an opinion, or it seems to me, right, in our modern parlance, that's immediately suspect.
Oh, well, that's just your opinion, right?
But the problem is is that...
We have ruled out that as being a valid way of knowing things without actually, ironically,
without actually demonstrating that it's always wrong.
And there's some kinds of things that you can't know through demonstrable, repeatable,
mathematical means.
And history is the classic example.
If we were going to try to use positivistic methods on history, we basically have to chuck
out pretty much all history that's ever been written.
because all history that's sort of been written requires
interpretation, it requires relying on testimonies,
all of these things that can't be shown in those ways.
So if we're gonna be truly consistent and say we only
believe in things that are truly demonstrable
in this kind of mathematical, scientific method kind of way,
then we have to throw out a whole lot of human knowledge,
culture, all kinds of things, you know.
And the problem of course is that it's not actually
can grind with human existence.
experience. Human experience knows that there's ways of knowing that are not about these
sort of scientific processes. We're not putting down science by any means. It is a valid
way of knowing the things that you can know by it, but it doesn't give you knowledge of
everything. It can't. So, you know, the difference, the shift that occurred is that this idea
of the locesa, the things that are based on perspective and testimony in the ancient
world where we regard
it is just as much knowledge. Now you treat them in a different way, you know, as then
you do demonstrable knowledge, but it is still a kind of knowledge that can only be gotten
in certain ways that can't be, you know, gotten through scientific or mathematical
kinds of means. So yeah, that's the problem is that we now have this idea that that's
not real knowledge except in certain limited kinds of frames. Like a courtroom is another
one. You know, it's a great example like we gave it for, you know, you
can't very well have a trial without testimony.
You know, if it's about anything really important.
So we accept that.
You know, but in our daily lives, we accept it.
Someone says something to you about something else.
You know, do you say, well, you have to show that to me.
You have to demonstrate it for me,
but there's some things that can't be demonstrated.
It just can't.
No one lives their life that way.
Yeah, there's no way.
Like you don't go and master mechanical engineering
before you get in your car and start it,
because you wanna make sure it's safe.
I have to have it all.
laid out to you like exactly the safety structures and the tensile strength of the
panel or do stress tests on the road that you're about to drive on every foot of it.
You know like it just it becomes and the problem is that we severely limit our
ability to know things because we in certain cases we'll cut off that kind of
knowing because it doesn't adhere to the criteria.
of the scientific method. That's the problem.
You know? Right. Right. So what you had in the ancient world
to borrow a turn of phrase from Plato that he used all the time is
based on testimony you could struct the likely story. Right. Right.
I mean, based on this is most likely, right in history.
This is most likely what happened. Right. Or this is most likely
likely how this works or
right? You you know have developed a certain amount of faith in your motor vehicle.
So you know when you go out to start it you think it is likely that it is going to start
and it is going to successfully get you to where you're going.
And so the idea is that rather than having an experiment where you
to repeat something and demonstrate it again.
You talk about
explanatory power, meaning I have this idea, I have this hypothesis, right, I have this
theory about life, I have this belief, and I evaluate it based on how well it explains
things, how well it explains the details, right? So I have a belief, right, that my wife loves me,
Right? If she did certain things...
Right? Like if she went and cheated on me, I would take it that data and say, well, my
belief can't accommodate that data. Right? Like, or at least it makes it difficult. At
least I have to adapt my belief to fit this new data. Right? That's how we actually all
operate most of the time in real life. Right? Because we have a belief that we adjust it.
Yeah, because like with the
example of, you know, if your wife loves you, the, you know, if you're going to take
this sort of purely materialist scientific method way of asking that question, the only
question it could answer is whether or not certain kinds of biochemical processes might
be observable under certain circumstances.
You know, does your brain do a certain thing when she thinks about you, you know, or sees
you in all of your glow.
when you wake up in the morning.
You know, no pun on glory there.
Actually, this is quite new.
I'll accept that pun.
But you know, it's a question that can't be answered.
And then the trap is to go full materialist and say,
it's not a question that's worth even asking.
You know, like there's no such thing as love.
Or you can never know.
Or you can never know because it's not something
not something that we can observe by demonstrable repeatable process.
processes. You know, and it creates, I mean, it creates all kinds of problems, you know,
like they can be interpersonal issues, like prove it to me, prove it to me, you know, or
even on a cultural level, right? It's interesting, for instance, right now, you know, within
the past, especially I would say 20 years, at least this is how I remember it, how much
kind of personal testimonies have become like really important in politics, you know,
that will bring up someone with a story.
and put it in front of everyone.
And then that's designed to elicit certain kinds of responses,
emotional responses typically, and then based on that
to make certain kinds of policy decisions and so forth.
And what's interesting is to watch the tension over that,
because on the one hand, people will say,
yes, this is what's really going on.
And so there's a sense of, okay, accept this idea of testimony.
But on the other hand, then you will get people who say,
well, that's just one person's story.
You know that?
one person doesn't establish a trend.
And in other words, trying to push it back
towards that kind of scientific approach.
And I would say that the solution to this
is not to push hard in one direction or the other,
but rather to recover a robust sense of, as you said,
the likely story as Aristotle puts it, right?
So it is true that one person's difficult story
is not something on which the basis of
you know, governmental policies should be made.
Because maybe that person's problem can be solved in some way that doesn't involve passing
a law that changes everybody's lives.
But seeing what a whole mass of people are doing for instance or whatever, you know,
yeah, it's interesting, you know, the kinds of pathologies that this puts into a society.
you know, where on the one hand, testimony is the
only thing that some people will believe.
And on the other hand, it's never believable because, well,
I don't appeals to emotion or whatever are irrelevant.
We shouldn't think about that.
And then of course, it can all be used very, very cynically
in a very manipulative way as well.
For any mode of knowing there are ways to turn it dark, for sure.
Well, and part of it is that what we call postmodernism,
like postmodernism.
structuralism emerges as the backlash against those 19th century Germans. Exactly. Right. So it's
we thought well we can know all these things scientifically and low and behold duh you can't know all these things scientifically
and so rather than going back to the pre-modern position
it's well know you can't know those things at all then. Right. The only things you can know are this small
scientific subset and everything else you can't know
at all. Everything else is just opinion. And therefore all opinions are equally valid, right?
On those all perspectives are equally valid. Right. Right. Right. So the the opposite extreme,
right? And so to make clear to people, because sometimes I know people worry that this is where we're
going. This is not where we're going. The rest of tonight is going to be about the ways that we know
and truly know, just as much as you know those scientific things, you could truly
know all those other things, you just know them a different way, right?
Right. Not in the same way. Yeah. So yeah. So, so you know, now nowadays we have
this notion of objective knowledge versus subjective knowledge. And objective is
this demonstrable stuff. And subjective is kind of everything else. And of course,
and then that means it can be dismissed. Well, that's just subjective. You know, but,
but in the ancient concept, and we're going to get to this after a break we're
taking a moment here.
There's actually multiple ways of coming
upon objective knowledge, but it's just received
in different ways.
It's known in different ways.
It's just a much more complex and rich picture, which
is great.
We don't have to live in a world where everything is either
fact, according to a certain sort of narrow requirements,
or that's just somebody's opinion.
Right.
And yeah, to go a little deeper to that.
Right. The way we use objective and subjective is completely wrong. Right.
You have never known anything objectively. Right. No, no human has. Right. Because the subject is
you and the object is the thing.
And I'm using thing here broadly to mean other person.
or object or animal or plant or the world or whatever or God right for you to know it
objectively would have to mean that there was no subject involved you cease to exist right you
know the object as the object knows itself right right that's not a thing that yeah that you know
the essence of the other person or the other thing or of God.
to happen, right? Right. So there is always a subject. There is always a viewpoint in all
knowledge that you will ever have because you are finite, right? So you are always there
as the subject. You are always approaching the object. Now there are different types of
objects. And this is a lot of what we're going to be talking about tonight. Right? So there
are different types of objects and objects present themselves and reveal themselves to you in
various ways.
So the things we're talking about here, so it is strictly objective versus
subjective. It's different types of objects. And the objects we're talking about
here in scientific knowledge are a certain type of object that very much reveals
itself to you. This is part of what I know certain listeners aren't big fans of
phenomenology, but sorry, here's some Heidegger. The brute
facticity of reality, right? These are things that impose themselves on you.
2 plus 2 equals 4.
You can't deny that that's true.
I mean, you could verbally do that,
but you can't really make your brain think
that 2 plus 2 equals 5.
You can't do it.
Right.
It impresses itself upon you.
Right?
And so those are the types of objects.
There are certain objects like that
that impress themselves upon you,
that reveal themselves to you all.
almost of their own volition, even though this is an ancient use of volition but not one
we're used to anymore because we think of that as making choices, but they impress themselves
upon you in that way and reveal themselves in that way.
And so we know those scientifically, that's why we can so easily demonstrate them is because
they sort of impose themselves upon us.
Other things we come to know differently because they're different objects and they do
do not reveal the
to us in the same way. My wife, right, to use her again, which I'm sure will make her
overjoyed when she hears this eventually. As another human, right, does not reveal herself
to be in this scientific way. When I encounter her and interact with her, I am not receiving
a bunch of data about her exact height and dimensions and, right, and the details of these
very excited to be like that's not how
mathematically that's not how she presents herself to me that's not how I
interact with her as an object in the world. That is how I interact with numbers.
Right. And shapes. That kind of thing.
Alright well that said we're gonna come right back in a few minutes and we're
gonna talk about the various ways and kinds of things that can be known and
we'll start to take your calls so we're gonna go ahead and go to break and be
We've wiped back in a second.
Father Andrew Stephen Damage.
and Father Stephen DeYoung will be back in a moment to take your calls on the next part
of the Lord of Spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF Radio.
No one of books these days offer us techniques for self-improvement.
But in the newest release from the ancient faith store, gratitude and life's trenches, Robin
Philips take
a different tack. He shows us that God meets us where we are in the pain and
heartache of the present moment. Instead of looking for a way to escape from
hardship we can cultivate an attitude of gratitude, peace, and self-acceptance
that will transform our experience of suffering. Drawing on his own
experiences and his work as a consultant in the behavioral health industry as
well as stories of saints and sufferers, teachings of the fathers and
and recent discoveries in neuroscience.
Phillips shows us that the journey to personal well-being is one we can all travel regardless
of the hardships we may face.
To find this book and others like it, you can go to store.angentfaith.com.
Again, that is store.angentfaith.com.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits, the Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father
Stephen DeYoung.
If you have a question call now at 855233
72346. That's 855 AF radio.
Thank you, voice of Steve. I feel like I just saw you. Welcome back everybody.
Before we start talking about the various ways of knowing things, we're going to take
one of your calls. So I believe we have James on the line. James, are you there?
I am. Thank you, Bobby.
Welcome James to the Lord of Spirits. What's on your mind?
I
James? Oh, I think we lost him. Wow, he was just there. He was just there. And you
had that mind pun. I know. I know. You lined up there and everything. James, are you back?
James, are you there now? Okay, well he looks like he's on the collar board, but I'm
I'm gonna try one more time. James, can you can you hear us?
All right, well
hopefully James can call back and we'll hear from him another time. This time we'll
boomer it up a little less on the technology. I know I I thought that what's on
your mind joke was a really good one. Okay all right okay I'm just being told to
try again James are you there yet? Oh man all right that's a live radio
everybody yes it is all right so okay well
There's lots of different ways of knowing.
So let's start rolling through our kind of catalog here.
The first one that we have is about moral reasoning.
I mean, is that really a way of knowing
or isn't that just a way of like arranging the facts
and figuring out the right thing to do?
So what's that all about?
Yeah, so yeah, moral reasoning or sometimes
if you're using old, this is the Greek term here
would be Fronisees.
which is sometimes in your old English translations, not old English, but old
or old English translations translated as prudence, dear prudence. And this is in
in the Old Testament in particular, this is the kind of knowledge we're talking
about when we talk about, for example, the knowledge of good and evil. Right,
knowing good and evil. So like in
Genesis chapter three, right?
Right.
And other places, notably a little bit of an expanded version shows up in Isaiah seven,
which is knowing to choose good and shun evil.
Right.
And that prophecy about the birth of Christ and other things.
Yes.
We won't go down to that particular rabbit hole.
We'll save.
that for a future Christmas episode. Indeed. Right. And I'll get to say Maharshalal
Hashbaz. Yeah. All right. Thank you. So I still prefer
Christian Rishatayam from Mahanaharayam. But that's just me. In terms of
the Old Testament names. But so when you take it in that context of knowing to
choose the good and
the evil that kind of puts it in perspective, because we tend to think of moral reasoning
as modern folks as I'm facing this ethical dilemma.
I have these options, which one is the good option?
Can there be more than one good option?
Are they all bad options?
If they're all bad options, which one do I choose?
Right?
and this is
not really the perspective of what we're talking about when we're talking about most of the
ancient world and in the Old Testament. Yeah, well, and even, you know, I'm a father of four children.
And, you know, part of parenting is a major part of parenting. Most of parenting maybe is teaching
children right and wrong. And as you watch children especially make the wrong choice.
but God willing, sometimes the right choice,
hopefully more often than not.
It's almost never, oh, I have this problem,
I need to figure out the right thing
and the wrong thing to do.
It's instantaneous, almost the time.
Right, there's just this movement
in a particular direction.
And human beings tends to move in the wrong direction
over and over again,
until gradually trained
to move in the right direction.
And then it becomes like a second nature, right?
It becomes the thing that you want to do.
That you don't have to sit down and, OK, now,
is this right thing or that the right thing?
Is this better than that?
It kind of caused benefit analysis.
I mean, we do make decisions like that sometimes,
but the vast majority of the decisions we make
are not made that way.
And we don't even have a conscious sense that we're making
decision.
Right, it's not like if one of my family members says something and I get angry
That I thought to myself okay, they just said this thing. What should I do now?
I think I'll get angry that seems like the right thing like that's not the way that it actually works
There's this sort of movement in that direction
Right so it so like you said it's it's about knowing how to to choose the good and to shun evil
But it's not it's almost never an actually a deliberative process
It's much more of what are you trained to do?
Yeah.
you know, what is it that you have been formed to do, right?
So yeah, it does have this connection very much to nature, but often it's skewed.
Right, and you're moving towards something in a way from something else.
Right, right. It's that kind of choice. You're moving towards something in a way from something else
by these choices. And yeah, this is the number one thing.
on those rare occasions when I'm asked to talk to teens, which really isn't a good idea,
because I'm like, hello fellow kids, but the one piece of hopefully good advice I try to give them
is that there's a person who God wants them to be and who they want to be when they're 40.
Right. And if they look at the decisions and things that they're called to make now,
now in terms of
of will this help me get there and become that person? Or will this make it more difficult
for me to get there and become that person? Right? When you think about it in that context,
a lot of those choices become clear. Right? That there are some of them that are not going
to help you get to that point and there are other things that are. Right? And so, this
points out that the kind of reasoning we're talking about here with moral reasoning is
not about
ends it's about means. Right? There's an end we're trying to get to and we're trying to figure out
the means what will get us there. And you see this sort of classically when the devil, right, the
serpent is talking to Eve and says, you know, no, if you eat the fruit, you'll become like God.
Right right knowing good and evil right so
wants to become like God, God has a way for her to become like him. It's not eating the tree.
Right. So it's it's her then taking this other means, her seizing this other means to try to
to get to that end. Right. Right. Yeah. I mean, in likewise to bring it back to the parenting
analogy or example really. I want my children for instance to be respectful to their mother.
Right, that's the appropriate thing for them to do. They're being disrespectful. I could
yell at them to be respectful to her. I could threaten them, right?
Those are means towards that end
or I could
train them by showing them what it's like to be respectful to her by
by helping them restrain themselves when they're being disrespectful.
The truth is, I want the same thing at the end, but there's one means that actually is
going to get me, you know, there might be more than one.
There are means that will help me get there.
And then there are means that feel right in the moment that are not going to help me get
there.
You know, what I would be teaching them by threatening them or yelling at them is you should be afraid
of your dad.
You know, that's the end that will come from those means.
Right.
And your kids do love their mother, right?
Like they actually do love her and want her to be
happy and want to honor and respect her, they just don't always know how to do that.
Right. Right. Right. They just don't always know how to get there.
And yeah, so this is then tied directly into for us human nature, right? The direct
in this of our being, the purpose for which humans were created, which is to become
like God, right? That's what you and He's created for, what we call.
theosis, right? And so when when we sin, pretty much all sin, and this is where the the orthodox
understanding of the sin of sin as the passions comes from, all of these sins are ways that
humans try to become like God or just become God, right? Or set themselves up as gods.
Apart from actually coming to know God, right?
There are these other other
attempts, right? Whether it's pride, just elevating your own ego to that point, whether it's
a massing wealth and power, whether it's becoming beloved by other people, whether it's
through pleasures of various pleasures of the body of various kinds, whether it's trying to
become immortal in some sense to stave off death.
But trying to do it under our own means.
Right?
It's power.
It's the exact who are reaching for the tree of the knowledge of good and evil once again.
We're grabbing for the fruit rather than doing what is needed to be ready for the fruit.
You know, like, you know, I've been having conversations with friends lately about,
especially people who are doing ministry in a way that puts them in the
the public eye, you know? And one of the observations that I think is really, really apt is that if
someone's sort of success outpaces their character, then they're probably doomed for some kind
of spectacular fall. And you know, it's exactly this kind of thing is that if someone's not ready
for, you know, for instance, being well known or whatever it might be, then it will destroy them.
You know they're reaching
for, as you said, for they're reaching towards Godhood, towards being like God, but they're
actually reaching in the wrong direction.
And so they end up becoming demonic instead.
You know, and as you mentioned, this is the basic for our medical theology about redirecting
the passions, right?
The desire, for instance, for immortality is a good desire.
The desire for love is a good desire.
I mean, these are good desires, but we try to sort circuit the way that God has given us
to arrive at those things, then it becomes very dark and can be very harmful to other people
and definitely harmful to ourselves. And it's interesting how much literature is based on this idea
that the quick path, the easy path, the path to instant power, celebrity, whatever is the destructive
one. But what's funny is that while these are the stories that we're telling each other,
the stories that we're selling each other, you know, get rich quick.
take this pill, it's going to change everything.
You know, solve this problem with one easy,
with this one weird trick.
You know, that's, it's funny.
We do both things at the same time.
And we wonder why we're so sort of kind of conflicted
and you know, function in this kind of,
like a multiple personality disorder sort of way.
We're very fragmented.
You know.
And I mean, I think that's why,
I think that's why good stories are so important is
because they help to form the taste of the person.
Like...
Like to me, one of the most important things that I know I keep coming back to parenting, but I think this is so when we're talking about moral reasoning, I think it's a great place of application.
You know, one of the things that's so important in my family is to give our children really good stories to read so that they have a sense of what it means to choose the good and what it means to shine the evil.
And what happens when you do those things so that when they then encounter a situation
that's analogous in some way...
that the narrative that they have in their mind is a good one and then they live into that narrative having already been formed by that
You know, so there's there's so many ways that this is applicable
and and I think the beauty of it is that
By seeing clearly what it is we're trying to attain to and knowing that there is a way given to us to attain it
then it becomes
I don't want to say easier but at least to be
It becomes clearer how he should live.
Because so many people, I tried this, I tried this, I tried this, but I'm still not happy.
I'm still not content.
I'm still not at peace.
Or whatever it might be.
I'm still not satisfied.
Well, of course not because those things can't do that.
You know?
Yeah, they can't actually make you like God.
Yeah.
And that end, that purpose, that tell us, is built into us.
It's built into every human.
You can't get rid of it.
it. Right? We can deliberate over the means, but the end is just there and just built
in. It's constitutive to us. Right? And so, yeah, that can go dark places. You can have a guy
like Lammock at the end of Cain's genealogy. Right? And, you know, what were what were human
beings built for? How do human beings become like God? Well, continuing God's active creation
of putting the world in order and filling it with life. Right? So what does Lammock do? Well,
He puts the world in order.
order all right by going out and murdering everybody who opposes him and becoming a tyrant
right and dominating everything.
And then he's fertile all right.
He's got multiple wives who he sings a song to about how great he is by means of seducing
them further.
That's how he's presented in the scriptures.
So these things can turn bad and in that boasting,
What does he say? He says, well, you know, God said he was going to avenge Cain, sevenfold.
You know, well, I avenge myself on my enemies seven times. Seven point. Right. So again,
setting himself up as, you know, not only like God but better. Right. Yeah. In that, in that sort
that sort of dark and twisted way.
Right, exactly.
Yeah, so, you know, the question with more...
reasoning is how do I become like God? There are the ways that he gives us to get
there and there's lots of bad ways to get there that don't actually get you
there. So all right well there's some more ways to know things. Before we move to
the next one God willing James has gotten back and touched with us. So James, are
you there? I am Father. Yes. Speak to us James. Speak to us.
And quickly.
Before I lose sight of you.
So I've been thinking about...
the news and our spiritual body in similar terms like the episode on Hades and
the mountain of God being richly present in liturgy or in tabernacle, not
side-eye, etc. And so thinking of it in context of what they talked about the
news or hearts being where sort of like where our physical heart is like when I
read some of the stuff on Hades of Casm, I go say like you want your awareness to
the out of your heart and but don't let it drift low.
because that's where the passions reside.
So I was wondering if there's a similar idea
where there's a ritual intersection
of our spiritual location of our passions
lower in our bowels and then our heart,
our news higher up closer above our heart.
And one of the things I was out of a month
right track of that and then also as a coach
I worked with personality a lot
and I was wondered where does personality fit
into all of this?
Hmm
So on that first question, it's interesting if you read pre-modern literature, there's
various ages where the concept of where the seat of emotion is, moves around in terms
of the way that it's conceived in the body.
So like in the modern world, we tend to think that emotions are in the hearts.
You feel things in your heart.
But there's a lot of medieval texts where you feel them in your kidneys.
That's where the feelings are.
And of course, as you move around to different parts of the anatomy,
there's all kinds of jokes you could make about where the real center of the human person is.
But yeah, I'm not an expert on this kind of ascetical literature about the mind descending into the heart.
And I think as this, but I do think as this episode proceeds and we actually, you know, this
is classic Lord of Spirits.
We don't ever start where we...
say what we're going to talk about, the news, you know, but I think that'll become clear
as we go. But I mean, we don't want to leave you totally hanging since you finally get
through. God bless you. But yeah, you know, it's, it's, I think part of the idea of the
mind and the heart is, it's really about focus for what it is you're taking into yourself,
right. And even though there's
I don't think, and I don't know, Father, you can correct me if I'm wrong with this.
I don't think that you can pinpoint parts of the material anatomy of the human person
as being sort of specifically linked to these spiritual realities that they're more, I
don't know, I would say that they're more metaphorical for a spiritual reality that is going
on, you know, like so if someone doesn't have their kidney anymore.
I was gonna say if someone doesn't have the kidney, is there more to-
that mean that they can't feel. I don't know.
Yes, save me, Father. But I mean, I get the basic sense from the
ascetical literature, but I'm not sure that I, you know, would
pair it up with particular organs, you know, like material
organs. So I'm actually me. Please, please.
Yes, I'm actually you a little bit. But I'm also going to be
it even worse, T's, because we're really going to get into this
in two weeks, our next episode of Lord of Spirits.
But, but, gotta keep it coming back for more James.
Right, so so
There is there is
materiality and spirituality to everything
Okay, because spirit and matter are not actually separate
Right, can we but can we peg these things to specific organs? That's that's kind of what I was sort of
sort of sort of right okay, so
Those chemicals in your brain when you see someone you love are not unrelated to love.
Love is not reducible to them, but they're not unrelated and separate either.
So there are, you know, yeah, you can't train, like, yeah, in Greek, the word for compassion
is built around the word for spleen.
So like when you read to the gospels that Christ had compassion for someone it
literally says in the Greek that he's sp leaned at them.
There's amazing.
Right, so you can't like, yeah, you can't like do it that directly, but there is a physiological
reality to all of these spiritual things, right?
And this is life is in the heart and also like the breath of life and yet all heart does
literally carry oxygen to our bodies.
I could have a physical corollary to that spirituality.
any kind of thing. Right, right. And we've all seen and known someone at some point in our life
where we've seen someone who has fallen deeply into sin and they look different. Yes, like
physically, physically they start to look different and we've known people who have repented
who have in the opposite directions started to look different.
That's that again, there is no separation between spirit.
and matter that these things are always connected and permeate each other and go both ways.
But we're going to talk about that a lot more in two weeks on the next alert of space.
Okay. Does that help lease a little bit there, James?
That does help a lot. Will the personality aspect possible because on the next episode
or that bit more of this one? Because I thought the personality is like a lens of perception.
So that kind of how we perceive the world through this lens,
As far as my identity I thought it was possible for me.
to say, and what is that fifth and this episode more
as far as I perceive, sure.
Yeah, we're not going to get into that next time, for sure.
Yeah, so the modern concept of personality
includes a lot of things.
Right.
And yeah, so it includes things like habits and patterns
behavior it includes
you know, learned responses, it includes all these, all of these kinds of things.
But then it also, like you mentioned, includes ideas of identity.
And that's kind of a rabbit hole.
We will get to this in a future episode.
But the way we think about identity in the modern, in our world today, it's a contemporary
world, I shouldn't say modern in this case.
in the contemporary world.
We think of identity as identity is what sets me apart from all the other people and makes me different.
And identity in the ancient world was the exact opposite.
Identity was like an onion or an ogre. It had layers.
And it was, it was these layers of belonging, right?
So it was your family and your trade.
and the city and place you are from.
And this is why we know all these people.
Like everybody refers to Thomas Aquinas as Aquinas.
That's not his name, that's the city he's from.
Yes, man.
You're calling him Ovakino.
But we read that as if it's the last name, right?
And many of the saints have the place where they're at,
because that's part of their identity,
the community they're part of and where they're from, right?
That's part of who they are.
Right, it's so...
So identity in the ancient world was composed of all of these things.
They were all the things that connected you to other people and places and realities and
things.
And so yeah, there's, we have kind of an inverted sense of identity and I think that affects
how we view personality too, where we tend to look at personality as personalities what
sets this person apart from other similar people.
Right.
rather than seeing it in that context.
So yeah, going further into that might be too much rabbit hole for this episode.
There's a wet map of type for future episodes.
There you go. There you go.
All right. Well, thank you very much for calling James. We're glad you finally got through.
Okay. So, well, we have another caller and we have a question from Troy.
So, Troy, what is on your mind?
Hello, fellas. Can you hear me?
Yep, we hear you.
Oh great, thank you for having me on.
My question is, so when you were talking earlier,
since we are subjects, we don't have access
to the objects of knowledge.
Does that mean there's a similar distinction
in how we know other people or angels
to the essence of energy distinction
with how we know God?
Yes.
Yeah.
Yeah, I recall, you know, when I was in,
and we don't just leave it at that,
although it's always great to get one of those monosolabic
yeses from Father Stephen, or the nose very good as well.
But I mean, I recall when I was in seminary and we were talking about this question of essence and energies
that Dr. Boussales who was the Patristics Professor at St. Tekon's at the time, great professor.
He, you know, someone said, wait, wait, because he was, we were talking about anthropology,
you know, about human beings. And someone said, wait, wait, so you're saying that God in his essence is
unknowable, but his noble and his energy is okay in human beings. It's the same essence, unknowable,
energy is noble.
And, and he gave just like Father Steve was like, yes.
And, and it's, but think about that, right?
You don't know, I mean, this takes us back in some ways.
You don't know what it's like to be a bat.
You don't know what it's like to be another person.
You can't know that person in their essence.
You can even know their experience of themselves, right?
All you know is your interactions with them, right?
Right, you know the way they look
know the way that they sound, you know what they have said to you and done to you, done
with you, you know what their reputation is.
You know, all of these things are part of that, right?
Now you wouldn't say because you don't know what it's like to be that other person that
you don't know them, you do know them, but it's the kind of knowing that you have.
It's the knowing that you participate in, right?
You can't know anything because you're, you know, only God knows things in their essences.
You can't even really know your own...
essence. You know what it's like to be you but you but but God knows you on a level that you don't even know yourself
Right. So yeah, it's true. You know that that
human beings likewise are
Participable in their energies, but their essence is off limits. You know, just not not accessible
Any um actually is there father Steven
No, that is yeah, yeah, you know what it's like to be a bat or a tree
or are we even or are we...
writing desk. Yes, thank you. Lewis Carroll. All right. Does that make sense, Troy? Yes, thank you.
That's very helpful. Thank you, Father. Great. Excellent. Yeah. You never know just how you look
through other people's eyes. Indeed. All right. So moving on, we've got another kind of knowledge.
And this is one that should be very, very familiar to modern people. And that's what in ancient
called technique, but we could translate it as...
know how, know how, you know, and it's the origin of our modern English word technique, right?
Right. And also technology, though, people jump to what we call technology a little too quickly.
A little too quickly, right? Right. It could be, it could be like, you know, I know how to work,
you know, I know how to drive my car. It doesn't mean I'm a, you know, computer scientist or an engineer
or whatever, you know, or I know how to brush my teeth.
I know it's this kind of.
I know how to whatever it might be.
It does connect with technology.
But it's about.
We use technology to refer to like digital technology.
Right.
And I'm sorry to any Amish people who might be
somehow listening to internet radio.
I guess I don't have to apologize.
But everything is technology.
Right.
The buggy was high technology at one point.
Yeah, human.
Right. The things that we made your coat were technology at one point, right? The coat slacks.
Right. Yes.
At one point, these were technological innovations. Yeah. Yeah. This has come up a lot for
Lord of Spirits listeners because of course we talk about the the the dark gift of of
technique to cane and other people throughout time that were given this knowledge by...
by demons. And so occasionally we get this question of like, okay, well which kinds of technology or demon technology?
You know, the idea that we shouldn't touch that because that came from demons.
You know, so it's very much an ongoing concern.
You know, and so this will be an opportunity to kind of talk about some of that a little bit more.
Right, right, because, and now this this care technique expands even beyond.
even those examples I just gave of technology, right?
Because we're also including with this, you know,
things like handicrafts and sculpting and art
and poetry, music, right?
And all of this sort of human creative activity,
taking the things that exist in the creation
and putting them in order.
Right.
and putting them to purpose.
Yeah, and so for all you Tolkien fans out there, his term for this is sub-creation because
human beings can't truly create, that is we cannot make something out of nothing.
All we can do is take what God has created and put it into a new order.
Right, so God made the things that we can make paints out of, we make paints out of them,
and then use those paints to paint icons.
Right so so yes icons are
man made, but it is they are sub created. They're not truly, truly created. But the reason
that we do that, I mean, this isn't inherently a good thing. We're made in the image of a
maker in whose likeness we are made. So, you know, we are made to be makers. We're made
to make stuff. So it's a good impulse that we have to want to do this. Now, the knowledge
itself right knowing how to make a chair.
is that good or evil, it's knowing how to make a chair.
What do you do with a chair?
Well, that might be good or evil.
But it's not inherently good or evil.
This is simply knowledge.
Now, what you do with it,
so for instance, when demons give technology
to mankind at various points,
they do it in such a way that they know
that will harm ourselves with it.
Like matches are a good thing.
they're useful item, but I'm not going to give them to my four-year-old.
It's not appropriate for him to have matches.
Now, my 14-year-old, if I give her matches and tell her to light a candle,
then she has done a good thing with the morally neutral knowledge that I gave her,
but she did a good thing by obeying her father by making light.
Right?
So that's what we're talking about.
And this is in a classical world, the ancient world.
This is a kind of...
of knowing how to do things. This is knowledge.
Right. And it's, as you said, it's, it's morally ambivalent, right?
Ambivalent meaning ambivalent, right? It can go either way. Right.
You can take any of these arts or any of these crafts and use them to, to, to,
to do good or use them to do evil, right? You can make a side to help you harvest crops.
You can turn that into a sword and use it to kill people.
You can...
you can make the first two Pearl Jam albums,
you can make Nickelback albums or record
as your alter ego, Chris Gaines,
and create abominations, right?
Any of these things can be taken in either direction,
right?
Like at any point.
I'll just say I wondered if you were gonna work
in the Nickelback reference, that's good.
Yes, I was.
And people get mad when I take cheap shots at Garth Brooks.
Sorry.
through that into.
Well, this is how you remind us who we really are.
Yes.
So I know that one of bunch of Canadian awards,
but that's low hanging fruit.
Come on, don't come at me with that.
Don't, don't, don't add me for what he just said, everybody.
What, what are the Canadians gonna do?
They're gonna be friendly about it.
They're gonna be kind about it.
They're good people.
Indeed.
We love you Canadians.
You have many great qualities.
So, right, so this could go either way.
And that's why there is that danger of giving it to someone who is not prepared to execute
that moral reasoning.
Right, right, exactly.
And that's what's going on with the fallen angelic beings in Cain's line.
Right?
They're giving the metallurgy not so they could make tools to help them, you know, produce
more crops to feed more.
people had prosper on the earth, they're giving it to them so they can make weapons and
kill each other. Right. Right. Or like music. Like music can be used to make something
beautiful that lifts the person towards God. Or it can be used for seduction. Or not
so much these days, but in certain times music was used to to rile people up to do to make
war. You know, I mean, I recall in some of the wars between the English and the Scots,
English actually.
actually declared the Great Highland War pipes to be weapons, which, you know, as a lover
of bagpipes, you know, I'm both sort of delighted by that and also slightly appalled. So I do
sometimes feel victimized by bagpipes music. Oh, I must say. So there's something to that.
Right. But so this is a type of, but this is a legitimate type of knowledge. Yeah, right.
This is a legitimate type of...
Jonathan Peugeot knows things about working with wood.
Then I do not know that craft is something which he possesses.
It's a kind of knowledge and a relationship with those objects in the world
that he has where those objects in the world reveal themselves to him in a different way than they do to me.
to me. Right. Right. This is arts and crafts, also artisans and craftsmen. Right. This is
making things.
You know, and there are people, you know, I'm sure some of you listeners are really great at making things.
And some of you are not so great at making things.
I'm only not so great at making things line at least in terms of what people might normally think of as art.
I would say you could make a lovely kind of macaroni picture like for a father's day thing or a mother's day thing.
That seems up your alley to me.
I'll have to try that.
Okay.
At the made recent I mentioned Pasho there was again I'm trying to get back in with the Canadians after yes, it's true
Yeah, I mean I mean after William Shadner
He is the world's greatest Canadian possibly yes. Yes. Yes. There we go. Yeah. Yeah, yeah definitely
Definitely the greatest Jewish Canadian number two Leonard Cohen
Just for the record
So this brings us to our penultimate way of knowing
which is wisdom. Yeah, and it's great that we just mentioned Jonathan Peugeot because this will be,
this will really, really appeal to the Peugeot Vians out there, this section of the podcast.
It's almost like it's almost like I plan to segue. It might well have been.
And this is in Greek, this is Sophia in Hebrew, this is a whole bunch of words.
Yeah, which was news to me.
Yeah, I mean.
Do they have shades of meaning that are different from each other?
Yes, but there are shades.
This is, I think this is sort of the,
Indigenous people in Alaska and Canada have, you know,
what, seven or nine words for snow, kind of thing, like
Yeah, although some of these are legends.
Some of that's about legends.
Early, early, Semitic languages have like all these
different words for variations of wisdom.
My favorite, which is
calm. But sometimes I think Hebrew should be flemish really based on they have six
consonants that make roughly the sound. So yes. Yeah. So wisdom is and here's here's where
all the peasantians will love this wisdom is the patterns built into creation. Well, yeah,
wisdom is knowing them, discerning them knowing them. Yes, perceiving. Yeah, right. There
within the created order.
And as we talk...
about God creates by setting things in order. Right. Right. That's what the creation story
in Genesis 1 is. So since he creates by setting things in order, that ordering is perceptible
to us, right, in varying degrees. Right. But that way of knowing, that way of perceiving
it. That's what we're talking about when we're talking about wisdom.
And that order built into creation is also connected to the idea of justice, which is why wisdom and justice are always kind of aligned in the Old Testament.
Now, I mean, now would this be the kind of thing, like, for instance, astronomical observations or ecological, I mean, like, is it even on that level?
Right. All of that. That's why in Proverbs you get the go to the end to that sluggard.
Right.
which famously inspired Henry Pim to become Ant-Man.
But the...
So you look at ants and you perceive something, or when Christ,
Boyzis, has considered the lilies of the field,
consider the birds of the air.
It's pointing to these patterns in the created order.
And then revealing them about the way in which,
if the whole creation is ordered in this way,
also applies to
humans and human life and the human soul and the order that should be reflected there as well.
It goes downwards and that way and then it also goes upwards, back toward God who put the order there.
Right. And understanding in this way is much deeper than the proof that sometimes given for the fact that God exists.
Oh look at the creation, look how beautiful it is that much.
must have been made by somebody.
Like, that's true, right?
That's true.
Of course, it's true.
But there's something much deeper there
that's related to real attention being paid
to what's going on in creation.
You know, a much deeper sense of that
than just simply a kind of aesthetic appreciation
for what you see in here and smell and so forth.
You know, so the wisdom, the logic of creation itself
is
something that's knowable and worth knowing and does lead you to God. I mean this is this is the idea right that you know that the stars preach the gospel right.
Right. Right. You see this in both Romans one right when Romans one where St. Paul is talking to the Gentiles about how they had knowledge of God before the gospel came to them.
when he talks about how the invisible attributes it's usually trans...
in English of God were made plain in the created order, right, in the creation, right, that they
could have looked with wisdom and discerned, right, those patterns and come to understand, understand
who God was. And then also in Romans 10, where he's talking about, again, how they could have known
the gospel before the gospel came to them by saying that as we talked about back in our
Christmas astrology.
episode that was written in the stars of the heavens that these patterns were there for
wisdom to discern. And yeah, when in those passages and proverbs and elsewhere in the wisdom
literature, the Old Testament where Christ is identified as wisdom, it's always in tandem
with his involvement in creation.
Right, so the second person...
Yahweh the God of Israel is involved in creation and is serving this function of wisdom and
This then gets developed through you know St. John's use of logos in the prologue of his gospel into what we see later in
Petristic theology
St. Maximus the confessor being exhibit a of the idea of Christ as logos and then the logia of creation
Right? The sort of the sort of the structures, the patterns, the order in the
creation that leads back to the logos.
Yeah, you know, and I've read some of those passages
on from St. Maximus and I see people talk about them
a lot on the internet and a lot of it's kind of bewildering.
You know, like I've seen a lot of weird things
that are said about them.
So I don't know, I mean, could you give a brief summary
of exactly what he's, I mean, really, right?
Just to lay this out because it's one of these things
gets taught to
about all the time, or at least in the stuff that I read.
But could be, I don't know,
can seem very esoteric, right?
Like each thing has a logos in it.
Like what is that?
Is it some sort of mystical diamond that I
rise carrying around?
It's not the essence.
Yeah.
So you start with Christ, right?
Christ is the logos that are right.
Yeah, the word is the logos of God, right? He's the logos of God. So that setting up a a paradigm of the
relationship, right? So he is how God reveals himself to creation, right? We don't come to know
God, the Father directly. We come to know Christ. We come to know the logos and through him, we come to
to know the father, right?
So the the the the logi or the logi in in all created things are
that capacity in which it's it's coming at I was using the the
phenomenological language of the way objects in the world present themselves
to us this is coming at it the other way this is the element of the objects in
world that is accessible to our knowledge.
Right, so it's coming at the same kind of idea from the other direction.
I see. So this is what we can sort of perceive of them. Right. Right.
Right. The order, the structure, right, what makes them them?
So it's closely related to nature. It's closely right.
Right. It's not the particular essence, right, because we don't come to know God in his essence. Right.
Right? Maybe don't come to know Christ in his essence, right?
We come to know his person as the logos of God.
So it's not the individual essence, but it is the pattern,
the form, the structure, right?
And that is what is accessible to us as subject when we look at,
when we perceive and come to know object.
Gotcha.
Well that makes sense.
But so and that's how they can lead us back right because if we start to understand these structures and these patterns
and we understand them through wisdom at a larger and larger level they lead us back to the logos the
the logos proper which then leads us to come to know God. Exactly. Exactly. All right well having
set all of that we're gonna go ahead and take our second break.
and we'll be right back. Give us a call.
Father Andrew Stephen Daymick and Father Stephen DeYoung
will be back in a moment to take your calls on the next part
of the Lord of Spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF radio.
Bigin Heaven, a collection of short stories
available now on the Ancient Faith Bookstore.
Sometimes poignant, sometimes funny, sometimes heartbreaking, sometimes convicting.
These stories of life in an inner city immigrant Orthodox parish are guaranteed to shake your assumptions
and make you see your life and face in a new way.
They are not for the faint of heart, but they are very much for all who want to embrace the truth more fully.
And you didn't have to ask Russ go over for help cleaning polishing
carrying in or out any work in the church the woman was
a stalled a tallade you could count on no one knew her suffering
they never bothered to look into her eyes it surprised me that most of the
church folks at St. Alexander the Rolling Dirt Parish didn't even know her name
it wasn't anything they thought about to find this book and others like it you
You can go to store.AncientFate.com.
Again, that...
a store.angentfaith.com.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits,
the Father Andrew Stephen Damick,
and Father Stephen DeYoung.
If you have a question, call now at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF Radio.
All right, welcome back everybody.
Welcome to the third half of the show.
We'd love to hear from you.
So we've been talking about various modes, ways of knowing,
kinds of knowledge that come by means of those ways of knowing.
This is the news episode, so we're now finally going to talk about the news.
And I recall when I was in seminary, I don't know,
maybe my first or second semester, we were in a class and the professor was asking
provocative questions. I can't remember and, you know, throwing out stuff.
and one of my clients.
classmates raised in hand and said, is it the news?
And the professor says, don't worry about that.
You're going to hang yourself with it.
So I always think of that now, whenever I start contemplating
the news, obviously the Greek word,
news and the modern English word, news are not the same word.
Although now I have to go look at the etymology
just so I can see what the origin of the English word is news.
So what is the news father Steven?
Yes.
So this isn't a pretty news.
This isn't.
fake news. I get all my news from Gary Goodnew by the way. Oh man! I got it! Yes!
Oh boy that thing really does take me back. So the modern English word
news as in the thing you hang yourself was comes from the Latin no-duce which
refers to a knot. So that's that's where the concept is. They're not related.
So now that I've done digging in the reference crates. Thank you. Thank you for
throwing me
few bones, I really do appreciate it. So yeah, this is news usually translated into English's
NOUS. Right. And often translated as mind, but a whole bunch of other things we've been talking
about are also translated as mind. And a lot of your English Bible translations. So, but
But to get into this, we have to get into then sort of the concept of the mind.
And we have to start getting into that by sort of breaking down our common contemporary
notion of the mind, which is really the brain.
Yeah, right.
Okay, so before we jump into that, we actually do have a caller.
So we have Scott.
So Scott, are you there?
I am father.
Can you hear me?
Yes, we can hear you, Scott.
Well, it comes to Lord of Spirits podcast.
What is on your mind?
Thank you.
Yeah, I had a...
This is thought as you were describing wisdom in the previous hash that the wise men of the East seem to be like, what is their characteristic that calls them wise?
They seem to be Gentile or pagan people who understand the patterns of the world.
And is this their wisdom that you talked about in the previous app?
The understanding the patterns of...
of what goes on?
Yes.
Yeah, I mean, you know,
think of, they're described often as essentially
having knowledge of the stars, right?
So they're astronomers at the very least.
And if you look at, I mean, this is, right,
the word philosophy comes from philosophy, right?
The love of, so fear, the love of wisdom.
And when you look at the first philosophers,
you look at the priests of critics,
what are they trying to do?
They're trying to understand.
you know the structures of the principles that underlie the world around them right everything is water
everything is flux everything is earth everything is right everything is white and then you look at
you look at socrates and he's trying to understand like what is justice not you know what are some
examples of justice and injustice but what is justice what is the pattern or the structure
that exists, and of course, played over by extension, that...
that we're pointing at when we say this is just or this is unjust, right?
They're looking for those patterns and to understand those things.
The same thing with Aristotle.
That's really what Sophia Wisdom means in the context of philosophy, at least originally,
is understanding these patterns.
Right.
Does that look like a concrete example of, yeah, it feels like a concrete example of what Paul was talking about in Romans.
like there is a wisdom that the Gentiles can...
and see having not seen Christ directly,
these guys were coming to worship him.
They've done nothing but based on nature.
So, it's right.
And if they follow it out, it will lead them to Christ.
It's not a separate other way to get to God,
but it will lead them to Christ who is the logos.
Yeah.
There you go.
All right, well, thank you very much for calling Scott.
Thank you.
All right, we have Aaron on the line.
So Aaron, what are you thinking about?
Hey, can you guys hear me?
Yes, we hear you.
Yes, sir.
Alright, so what's the deal with the soul?
What is the deal with the soul?
I feel like that's a question, like that's a sign felt.
What's the deal, too?
I spent a long time thinking that the voice in my head was myself and that that was the soul.
That I sat in my mind and I judged thoughts.
thoughts and now I'm starting to form the idea that that not the soul of an
aspect of my thoughts and that the soul is kind of this thing that I have to train for
right conduct and not so much for like, you know, pursuing my passions and ultimately
shape my soul to the Zembo Christ and to, you know, get to know him.
But also I'm kind of curious because the Orthodox Church is always referring to the soul in
like female pronouns her and she and it's like
the bride of Christ, like the church, we are all members of this body and Christ in the
bride room and we collectively, maybe collectively our souls are the bride of Christ that's being
shaped and acting in the world. And so my general question is, yeah, what's the deal? What's the
what is the soul? What is the soul? Well, you know, with regards to thoughts, this is literally
the next thing that we're going to be talking about.
So just hang in there.
Yeah, so father, how does that relate exactly to the soul?
I mean, your thoughts are not your soul.
We'll at least start with that.
Right, right.
And your soul is also not your identity,
which is another way we tend to think about it,
or your ego, right?
The eye is not your soul.
The eye would refer to you as a person,
which includes your body.
So your soul is a few things,
in terms of what it's doing.
So the first thing it's doing is it's giving shape and form
to the big pile of matter that is you.
That is you at any given point in time.
because the batter in your pot.
body changes out about every seven years.
So what makes you you is not the particular matter that makes you up at any given point
in time.
Something like between 30 and 40 percent of the cells in your body are actually cells and
organisms other than you strictly speaking.
Yes.
Lots of bugs.
There's like bacteria colonies living in your digestive tract that communicate chemically
with other bacteria colonies out in the world.
I've creeped everyone out completely.
But so your soul is giving form to all of that matter
and all of those sub-organisms all the time
and is what's persisting in your person
and making whatever matter
composes you at any given time you.
It is also what is animating pardon the pun
because Anima is the language for soul.
Right? Is animating that manner, that matter, right?
as a human person.
So when you're, this is how Neffeschen Hebrew is used
throughout the Old Testament. And this is why in the ancient world, including in the Old Testament
and the New Testament, animals and plants also have souls because they're alive.
But they have a different type of soul.
Not all souls are the same type of soul, but everything alive has a soul, that's what makes it alive.
And so when
something dies, right? That means that that life, right? The soul of the life has left it, right?
And so since it has left it and the life is no longer there, that life no longer gives
form to that matter, the matter decomposes. Right? The matter falls apart and decomposes.
And so when St. Paul, for example, talks about what happens when we die, we tend to kind of
RAFI are sold
into a thing, right? We're kind of closet originists and think there's like this sort of sphere
that's our soul that flies up into the sky somewhere, right? Like ghosts too, dwell somewhere.
Or we think of our ghost, right? Sort of an ethereal version of us that's up in heaven somewhere.
But what St. Paul says is, our life is hidden in Christ, right? That life doesn't just vanish
when it leaves us.
our body, but that life is hidden in Christ.
Meaning he's got it, he's cherishing it, he holds it, he possesses it.
And that is then returned to our bodies at the resurrection.
The question of, well, what's that like?
The answer is, oh, so the only person I could think of who we could ask is maybe Lazarus,
But St. Lazarus has it appeared to be to let me-
ask of that question. So because he's done it twice. But yeah, so we don't we don't
know what that's going to be like to experience anything without our body. But but that's
really what the soul is. And that's why sometimes in scripture and people get all worked
stop trying to get this all nailed down in their spreadsheet.
This is why sometimes soul and spirit are spoken of differently.
When sometimes soul and spirit are spoken over the scriptures, like they're the same thing,
and sometimes they're spoken of as if they're two separate things.
When they're spoken of as two separate things, it's because the soul is being used in this strict sense that I was just mentioning,
of sort of the life of the body.
Right, and then other things related to us as person are ascribed.
to spirit and then sometimes those things are put together in one category.
So don't sit around getting an argument. It's about whether humanity is
bipartite or tripartite. It's more a good passe. Yeah and you I mean you can see
church fathers will some of them will say body and soul some say body and soul
and spirit. They don't fundamentally disagree with each other.
Okay so what is it? What is the difference between a soul and the spirit?
Well, I'm not gonna like do a hollow question.
but yeah, it depends if they're being separated out, right?
Then soul is being used strictly to refer to the life of the body, right?
Whereas spirit would then be what they're talking about would be with Christ, right?
And spirit is something within immaterial body.
Uh
by the definition of body we used in our body episode,
which is like an angel is a spirit, right?
It has a body, right?
It has a nexus of powers and potentialities,
but it's not a material body.
So I understand that the soul is kind of like a nexus
of potentialities, and that the news is one of those
potentialities that our human souls have,
that the tree doesn't have.
It's the place where we meet God.
Well,
The news has both a spiritual and material reality.
Yeah, which we're about to talk about that in some detail.
So just hold on.
And then I get a little comment.
I know I'm long a little comment on why I was referred to female.
Yeah, I mean, that's mostly grammatical.
Yeah, because the words have grammatical gender that's female.
And you know, in modern and the late modern.
that we speak almost no word has grammatical gender anymore although we have
kept it around for a few things like ships ships or she's wire ships she's
because they were in old English pretty much actually Richard Rowland right now is
writing it down I'm gonna call him it's not in old English but yeah it's
about grammatical gender is really all it is all right thank you fathers okay
Okay, so all right
Okay, so yeah, the modern concept of the mind tends to be this notion that we're sort of that it's equal to the brain
Which is like a meat computer that you know comes up with thoughts
Right, it's in your brain. It's in your the box of your skull. Yeah
It's sort of churns and processes information that comes in through your eyes and ears and nose and mouth and
nerve endings. Yeah
That's that's yeah, that's that's the mind in the modern because and I mean we can you know
we can we can
blame day card or whoever, but but but that's the way that we that's the way we can see of it now.
You know we don't and this and I hope that everyone will listen to this part especially closely
if you haven't if you haven't really been close to this thing yet but really listen to this part
closely because you're going to see how this actually really gets down to the individual spiritual life
and you know pastoral work and all this kind of thing because the question and we'll get to
Yeah, the question is...
Where do thoughts come from?
And it's really vital that we correct our way of conceiving this because if we have this modern idea that thoughts are something that are generated by your head, right, that you come up with them like a computer.
And then let's say you keep having a bad thought over and over and you can't get rid of it. Maybe it's a horrible, horrible thought.
then
And it would be potentially reasonable for you to conclude, I am a bad person.
And I am flawed.
And there is something wrong with me.
And I can't get rid of this.
This is just who I am.
Right?
I was born this way.
That is not congruent with the ancient conception of what the mind is.
the nuces and where thoughts actually come from. Thoughts are not something that you come up with.
In the ancient conception, the mind is actually essentially an organ of perception. Like your eye or
your ears. That it receives thoughts. That thoughts come from the outside. So if you keep having
the same thought over and over again, that means you keep receiving it over and over again.
Now...
It's your choice as to what you and we'll get into this.
This choice is to what to do with the thought.
It's your choice to pay attention to that thought, but the thought is not being generated
by you.
So I turn my head left and right and different kinds of light come into my eyes and then
I perceive that light.
I see different things in the room that I'm in right now and I focus on them and I see
See that image right?
I'm not creating those images. Now you could talk about the way the mind deals with that stuff,
but fundamentally I'm not inventing the way that, for instance, the room looks. I'm perceiving.
I'm receiving. That's the way thoughts are in this ancient conception. As you listen to what
we're about to talk about, it's going to become clear, I hope, that this is actually a much
more workable way of understanding spiritual life, of living the spiritual life, it's doable.
It becomes doable.
If we make it a purely psychological thing where like, wow, I just keep having terrible
thoughts.
I can't give rid of them.
Then it might be a trap.
Whereas if we understand thoughts in this way, then there is something you can do about it.
There's something you can do about it.
So the news is a perceptive organ.
it sees the spiritual world, it receives thoughts, and ultimately it's designed to see God.
That's why God gave us the news, to see Him. That's what He wants us to see Him.
Right. And this corresponds to our experienced reality. I've never met anyone who's actually
experienced creating a thought. Yeah. Yeah. Thoughts appear in our heads. And we may wrestle with
thoughts we may struggle to understand and interpret.
thoughts, but there's no experience of generating a thought, right? Like I can, I can experience writing a sentence,
right? Like I write a letter and then another letter and I write a word and then another word. And I might
be kind of composing and coming up with the sentence as I'm typing, right? Or writing on a piece of paper.
I have had that experience, but I've never had that experience in my mental world of composing a thought.
Hmm, right.
And in fact, what...
I'm doing while I'm trying to write the sentence is thinking thoughts is dealing with thoughts
as to what I should put next, right?
But those thoughts are just appearing before my mind.
So this is this is the way of seeing it is based on how we actually experience it.
And so this is how when you get in any ancient source, it was...
start with a couple of Greek philosophers.
But when you go into any ancient source,
this is how they view the news as sort of the highest
of all these ways of knowing, the news
is sort of at the top of the heap.
And all of the others participate in the news to one degree
or another.
This is the highest way of knowing.
And all the other ways of knowing are related to it.
but so, put it for...
Plato, the news is how you discern the eternal forms,
like the unchanging eternal reality
beyond the world of becoming and change
and chaos and transition, right?
You come to see them for Plato with the news.
You perceive them.
And Aristotle, when you get into metaphysics, Lambda,
and he's talking about the being that later becomes known
the prime mover.
who's more the unmoved mover.
He describes it as the Noesios,
which is something that people struggle to translate that.
It's based on the word news.
It's sort of the news that's noosing.
So it's sometimes translated as something
like thought thinking itself, right?
sort of pure thought in action with itself.
But how did Aristotle come to
Come to perceive that well he came to perceive that
Knowedically through like a meditative process
Right for him in the metaphysics you arrive at this is kind of meditation by which you ascend above
the being of beings to being
being.
Right, capital B.
To the contemplation which and contemplation means C.
looking upon this, this, right, thought, thought thinking itself, however you want to want to
consume. And I've never met anyone who's read metaphysics, it's specifically metaphysics,
Lambda, in Greek, and hasn't gotten a headache because I'm trying to, you know, deal with this.
But you also find this, here's to be the totally non-controversial part of this episode.
We'll also find this in great detail in Eastern religions.
Yeah, it wouldn't be Lord of Spirits,
we didn't do at least one segment
that's about something deeply weird.
Yeah, yeah, so get ready, buckle up.
Yeah, there's this notion of, here we go.
The third eye, right?
And it's just usually depicted or painted
or indicated at the center of the forehead, right?
Associated with the mind.
Up top, yeah.
and you're trying to open it up is
is the idea so it can see.
You know, there's the notion of,
okay, I mean, you're gonna just need to help
everyone with this, the pineal gland.
Right, so that is associated with the pineal gland,
which is sort of at the center of the brain.
And the pineal gland is triggered by a bunch of things.
Both meditative spiritual practices
and
second out drugs. We'll put it that way.
So yeah, that that that trigger it. And this is again, what we were talking about
that we would be talking about more in two weeks that there are these physical structures
associated with these spiritual realities, this material structures. And so then
what you find in for example ancient Greece, particularly in the mystery cults,
you find all this imagery of the
stock and this is corn in the ancient broader sense. So don't send your cards and letters. We're not talking about maze
Yeah, yeah, it's it's right. It's corn as in Commonwealth English meaning grain
But so a stock of grain with the head of grain at the top or it works with a corn
Cobb if you want to think of it that way it works with any kind of grit that kind of imagery right where you have this at the top and
This is related to
edit
in these mystery cults and in Easter religion,
where some form of energy was seen to travel up the spine
to the pineal gland in order to activate this.
And so in certain forms of yogic practice,
this is what's referred to as the Kundalini serpent,
which is you've got to think of like a cobra that's standing up,
right, with like its head up, and the idea is that
that this is sort of this energy pattern or being that's coiled up in your
bowel region, which sort of extends itself up your spine and then bites into your brain,
sort of into your padeal gland and injects it.
And this is supposed to be a good thing.
Yes, thereby opening your third eye and giving you access to the spiritual world, right?
And then as we mentioned, like psychedelic drugs, the same kind of idea, whether it's in
some kind of native shamanistic practice like Ayahuasca or what have you or more modern,
you extract DM.
And so all of these things represent by technique or by chemical means a way of sort of spiritual bootstrapping, right?
Yes.
Short cutting using the news to access the spiritual world.
And I mean, this is in some ways this is basically taking technique and trying to, you know,
Wedged in to
this, right? Like yes, yes, I could go through all kinds of purification and, you know,
asceticism and repentance, or I could just do drugs, you know, or whatever, one of these
other techniques and the idea is to kind of force it to make it happen, right?
But inducing that experience in yourself, inducing access to the spiritual world does not mean
Does not entail that you're going to have the means by which to interpret understand
Prosper right operate within the spiritual world in a way that is healthy and not harmful to you
Because the way this is supposed to happen right is is through the Holy Spirit
That's the Holy Spirit purifies the news the Holy Spirit purifies the eyes of the heart
right and it opens them and
And in the light of the Holy Spirit, there's this participation in the divine light that
then allows Christ to be revealed to us, right?
And then the news finds its proper object, which is seeing Christ.
So any kind of bootstrapping by nature does not involve the Holy Spirit.
It involves other spirits.
Yeah, there are other spirits who are perfectly happy to help you open that third eye, or
whatever conception.
you want to use, you know, to open it up and give you access, but it gives them access
to you. It's a mutual, it's a mutuality, you know, like we said, the news receives thoughts.
So if you're opening yourself up to other kinds of spirits, you're going to be receiving
something from them. So all right, we're going to talk a little bit more about that.
We'll head out to one of my favorite places and that's out into the woods.
One of my favorite musicals is into the woods by the way, great show.
Very related to all of these things actually.
Yeah, yeah, spirit's out in the woods.
You know, almost every, almost every pagan culture has this idea that their
spirits that live it out in the woods.
And even, you know, this is non-pagan culture.
Yes, that's, yeah, that's what I was about to say is, you know, Israel has this idea
that out in the wall.
There are spirits out there, right? Like this is a thing. Again, you know, so many of the sort of facts on the ground are agreed upon by both Israel and pagans.
The question is interpretation of them and what exactly you do in relation to those beings.
Yeah, so if you go out into the woods and you feel some, you know, something deeply that then makes you act in some way that you don't normally act, it was understood to be that you were under the influence of spirits.
You know
if you are overcome with rage, you are filled with a spirit of rage. If you're overcome with
lust, you're filled with a spirit of lust. I mean, everybody agreed on these ideas.
And this is this is this idea that thoughts happen to you. And and there's even and this was
something that I didn't I hadn't thought about, but it should be pretty obvious to me. The the
the Greek word of the ammonia or eutomoenia.
you want to sort of angusize it, which means, you know, kind of blissful happiness in our
modern sense of that. I mean, right there in the word, it means you have a good demon.
You have kind of good spirits. A good spirits are there, you know. And so, so, you know, again,
the idea of the human person as being this kind of impermeable, closed off fortress is just
not a thing in ancient conception.
And so it's not a thing in Christian theology.
The human person is very permeable.
Right?
So a lot of what spiritual life is
is about guarding that permeability
and using it appropriately.
Right.
And thoughts come into the news
from noetic beings.
Right.
From spiritual beings.
Right?
Who bring them put them there?
And that means
Your inner mon...
is not you. It's not you narrating your life. As much as we've been conditioned by television
shows and the original kind of blade runner to think so. It is it is not you. The voice of
Morgan Freeman in my head. No, that would be nice. Or just pay someone to follow you around
to describe what you're doing.
So this is one of the big shifts we have to take.
That's not you.
So then what do you have then?
What you have is a point of focus or a point of attention.
You have the point of focus or point of attention
before which those thoughts enter.
and then
through which those thoughts enter.
That's what you have to do.
That's what consciousness is, right?
That's what you're human consciousness is.
And that's what's you.
And so, therefore, as you were giving the example
with vision and turning your head, right?
We are not required to focus that point of focus
on every thought that enters our head, right?
that is not a
facto given. Right? And so this is the whole idea of guarding your thoughts. Right. Right.
And asking God to guard our thoughts. Right. Placing a guard, not letting everything in. And then
thoughts are sort of like seeds, right? Even once they come in, you don't have to let them take
root. And even if they have taken root, you don't have to let them keep growing. You could rip them
them up by the root and throw them out.
This is what Paul is talking about in Second Corinthians 10,
5, when he talks about taking every thought captive
and making it obedient to Christ, sort of capturing it.
But so doing that is a discipline that has to be developed.
And we, because as modern Western people,
we're the only people in the history of the world who
don't believe in the news.
That's everyone else always has understood that it's there.
Since we don't think it's there,
since we don't believe it's there,
and that's not how we understand things,
we don't exercise it at all.
We don't attempt to use it at all.
And if we have, it's probably
because we've dabbled or gotten involved
in some kind of new age practice or Eastern practice
or the Opeg in practice, right?
And that's been how we've approached it,
So we have an approach that from this.
Christian perspective. And so getting from the point where we have this constant
right the stream of thoughts is not again my internal monologue or narration it
is this stream of thoughts flowing through my head right just like the cascade
of images you see when you you know watch TikTok clips that go past it hello
fellow kids that go past super fast, right? You have these thoughts.
This constant stream running through your mind, right, all the time, right?
And this has been the great boon to the demonic powers of archetypillary era
is that were constantly bombarded by all of these thoughts.
This is why when you go and try to pray, there are all of these thoughts, right?
Right.
Because they show up and start putting them in your head and giving you all of these things to think about.
And so when you look at the
disciplines of the Orthodox Church, they're aimed at helping you exercise this flabby muscle.
They're aimed at working at this. So you have the prayer of a single thought.
Right. The Jesus prayer. Yeah, monologues, those F-he, which is the Greek phrase for that.
And you start there by training that point of focus that you have to focus on just that one thought
and get rid of all the other ones.
Right, right. Run off all the other ones and train yourself to focus more and more on just that one.
And the goal is eventually to get to the point where even that one goes away.
Yeah. That's when you have contemplative prayer. This is Hezekhasm. This is the silence of Hezekhasm.
Right. Of those thoughts being gone and being able to purely with the news come to see Christ.
Yeah, and you know in terms of one's experience of
the Christian life. I've been sometimes asked, why is it that Orthodox prayers, for instance,
are so overflowing and poetic and long, with all of these endless periodic sentences.
Oh God, who? Kamakama, Kamakama, Colin, please now do, they go on like this. And often people give
of explanations like, well, you know these...
from the ancient world where people are just much more poetic and that's the way they talk
and that kind of thing. I think there's actually something much deeper going on, which is that
in the way that this pattern presents itself, it's actually designed to be like a shepherd for
your thoughts. Right? If you're prayer functions in a purely utilitarian fashion, if that's all you've
God, then...
There's a lot more space for your thoughts to get distracted by it, you know, for you to receive
distracting thoughts. And so, you know, if you look, if you just walk into an Orthodox church,
the way that the prayer works, the way the music works, the way that what you see works,
the way all of it works together is multi-vectored and designed to bring you all to Christ,
like it's designed to, you know...
give you many good thoughts all at once, right? And you can kind of follow any of them and get to Christ.
And it's, you know, it's, it's why like, you know, think about, so the opposite, what is the opposite of an Orthodox Church? Well, it's time square.
Right? That's the opposite. It's, you know, it's being bombarded by advertisements and all kinds of other, you know, thoughts that are trying to extract something from you.
Um.
But the way that Orthodox life actually functions in terms of its prayer and so forth is is not designed like you know
You're gonna have a thought when you attempt to pray that says just get this over with
Right, but why would you want to get it over with? Well, so you can move on to other ridiculous distracting thoughts
That's why you know, so so
The the struggle is to focus the struggle is to bring ourselves back to that single thought who is Christ and
and to receive help.
You know, and it's I found, you know, in pastoral experience, especially when talking to people in confession, that explaining this and beginning to teach, I mean, I'm no expert at this. I just passed on the wisdom that I've been given. But, but in, you know, explaining this beginning to teach that this is the way thoughts work and how you can actually be working on them is very liberating for people.
And then there's a final goal, right?
Washington say final, but there's a goal to this.
You know, why do you want to receive the thoughts that are from God and turn away from evil thoughts?
Because it actually does do something, right?
So, what is that father?
Right.
So, the news is also, you know, transformational.
So to quote the quote Aristotle again.
as we've done a few times this evening, right?
The mind in some sense becomes all things, right?
Is shaped and formed by all things.
And so whenever we direct that point of attention at,
that point of focus at, we are going to start
to become like it.
It is going to shape and transform us.
Yeah.
And so you're going to become what you focus on.
And so this is intimately connected
to the idea of theosis on the...
positive side that we've talked about before and also on the negative side
demonization that we've talked about before on the podcast that what you're
what you're focusing your gaze on what you're seeing is going to be what you're
going to become in the way in which you begin to change and shift and you
referenced when we were talking about this before in Matthew 6 something that
crisis on this account. Yeah Matt you see
verses 22 and 23, the eye is the lamp of the body. So if your eye is healthy, your whole
body will be full of light, but if your eye is bad, your whole body will be full of darkness,
if then the light in you as darkness, how great is the darkness. So you get this idea of, you know,
like shining a light into something and it lights up the whole thing, you know, it begins to glow
sort of from within. It transforms that thing. And that's the way that the news works is if the
light of God shines in.
you through the news, then you're lit up. You change. You become like him. You shine with his
light. But if you receive instead the dark light of the demons, then you become like them.
It actually does change you. You know, there's there's sometimes, you know, people will say
about various kinds of sins. Well, you can look so long as you don't touch. I'm sorry, but looking
is touching because looking is transformational.
You know, I mean, there are circumstances in which you might say that and not mean quite the same thing.
But if you look with lust, if you look with envy, or if you look with anger, I mean,
if you're looking as to bring that thought into you and to turn it around within yourself,
you are being changed by that look. You know, you're receiving something by that look. So that's
the lesson is that you are receiving something. It's not just what you touched. Looking is touching.
you know.
on a certain level.
So yeah, it's a great, I mean,
you know, I remember reading that passage
from Matthew 6 and always kind of wondering,
like what exactly is meant here?
And then as I learned about what the new say is
and how it functions and so forth,
then it punfully intended lit up,
it lit up for me exactly the way that it works.
Right, and this is why when we've talked,
when we talked before about man being in the image of God,
we talked about how that's kind of a verbal.
idea of imaging God. And some people have asked us questions about how you find in some
of the fathers, they'll say that the news, right? Sometimes translated as reason, right?
Or the mind is the image of God, or they'll talk about the angels also being in the image
of God in a sense. And this is what connects those concepts, right? Because the news, the
mine is the capacity that we have that we share with other
poetic beings like angels through which that imaging happens. This transformation we're
talking about is that imaging, right? So this ability to image God is through the news
and that's so those are connected. But then of course on the flip side as we said, you
can also use the news to image the demons and do you want giants? Because that's how you
good giants. That's exactly yeah yeah there isn't
an opposite to theosis, an opposite direction.
So yeah, well, this is another mind-bender, again,
punfully intended.
But I think that even though these are difficult concepts
and maybe new concepts for some folks,
I think they're really, really important to wrestle with.
And I believe that the reason why they're really important
to wrestle with and to gain some...
master of these concepts is so that we can actually exercise who it is that we, you know,
what it is that we have in a much better way, much deeper, richer way, right? We went
through the various kinds of knowledge, according to the ancient world. And, you know, if you
understand that all of those kinds of knowledge truly are knowledge and are worth pursuing,
know in the good ways, right?
then it opens up so much, right?
And it helps us actually to be more compassionate
to other people, right?
So for instance, let's say someone pursues knowledge
that is within that category of Voxa, you know,
and they're really pursuing that.
We should see that as being a good thing
and not just say, well,
you're just living in a world of subjective opinion.
You know, that's stuff you can't really count on that.
Now it's true knowledge.
but I sp-
Especially with regards to where we just finished.
I already said this before a little bit, but I feel that it genuinely bears repeating,
which is if we understand that the thoughts that we have are being received and
not internally generated, then that actually puts us not in the position of the tortured
prisoner down somewhere in the dungeons of the castle who can't get away from himself.
the worst thing ever. But rather it puts us on the walls of the castle and we are there
to guard the entrances and you know when enemies come to the gates that we turn them away.
If enemies come through for some reason then we defeat them and send them on their way.
And then when the king comes to the door you open the doors to him.
That's what the spiritual life consists of in a certain sense.
And so all of the things that we do, whether it's our training in prayer, whether our training in asceticism,
our training in corporate prayer especially, participating in the sacrifices of the church,
going on pilgrimages, almsgiving, I mean all of these things that are evangelism, all of these things that are the good things that we are to do as Christians.
All of these are designed to purify our news and to train us to focus on
the thoughts being given to us from God and from, you know, sometimes through his
angels and saints, but ultimately from him and turning away from thoughts that
come from the dark sources. And the more that we do that, then the more we become
like him. And we don't have to feel trapped by our thoughts. We don't have to feel
like there's some kind of fatal flaw that that can never be overcome. You know,
I'm just broken. I'm just no good. I'm just born
that way. We have the ability to refocus ourselves and it takes practice, it takes a lot of practice
doing it over and over again. We get comfortable receiving certain kinds of thoughts. We might like it.
But then we get addicted and then we get destroyed. So it's really a beautiful teaching and
and a liberating teaching and shows us the love of God for us that...
You know, one of the most beautiful things that I ever heard
was that every good thought that you receive
is from the Lord.
So think about that for a second.
Think on that. Focus on that for a second.
Every thought that you have that is about
God's love for you, every thought that you have that is about doing something
caring for another person, every thought that you have that's about making
beauty that has been sent to you from God.
And so receive that thought, you know, nurture that thought, integrate that thought into who you are, and you will become more like him.
Father?
Yeah, we live today, probably anybody who's going to hear this podcast at least, in the
society of the spectacle where we are
and surrounded continuously by this spectacle that's made up of propaganda and advertising
and images and thoughts and ideas that are being continually projected at us.
And it's not reality. We know it's not reality. That's often what makes it very attractive to us
us because we for various reasons it various times.
times don't want to deal with reality.
And so the circus, the spectacle seems very attractive.
And it's coming to us through TV and streaming services
and the internet and social media and podcasts,
other than the ones that Father Andrew and I do.
And a thousand other sources continuously.
And the producers of the spectacle
know full well that it's shaping us.
That as we take it in it is shaping us and it is changing us.
And they're deliberate about it.
It's changing us into something that is not as good as being human.
It's changing us into consumers.
People who want to not only consume goods and services and commodities and things out in the world,
but who
to consume each other for our own gratification of our egos or our desires. It's making us into
something worse. They don't understand the producers of it that it's making us into something more
like the demons because they don't believe in demons. But they think it's making us into consumers
and customers that it's making us into something that's more useful to them.
And so if we...
We want to escape that.
If we continue to just passively receive
and absorb all this stuff, as we've been trained to do,
to just sit and passively let things stream into us
and over us, if we want that not to happen to us,
we have to be very deliberate.
We have to make a conscious decision
about disciplining our minds, and about disciplining our thoughts.
thoughts and about
spending our time and our energy and our focus on things devoted to Christ and
to God and to each other rather than taking in the spectacle because it's
focusing on those things. It's our relationship to Christ mediated through
prayer mediated through each other mediated through our church community
media
through the holy icons, mediated through the scriptures, mediated through all of
these connections. These are the things that are going to transform us in a
different direction and make us human. Make us human again. There's a lot of
things that we talk about on this podcast that we've lost from the ancient
world. And one of the struggles I know people have because they ask us about it
all the time is, well, how can we go back and look at the world?
that way. How can we go back and think of the world in that way? And yes, you
can't flip a switch and just see the world the way an ancient person saw it. But
you can by drawing near to Christ become human in the sense that they were human
again and become a real person again in the sense that they were real persons
and have real relationships with your fellow human beings the way they did. And
and draw close to Christ not only yourself but together with your family.
and your community and have a real sense of community and that you're not alone.
And a sense of community that's not just based on you consuming the same things,
but based on what you're becoming, more like Christ together.
But we've got to get serious about it and we've got to actually do it and not just talk about it.
And that means we've got to give up some things that come quick and easy
that make us feel better when we don't want to
deal with some of the rougher stuff and the tougher stuff in life, we've got to stop
taking the easy way out because it's not just alcohol and drugs that are easy ways out.
It's the spectacle that surrounds us all the time.
So that's my thought for tonight is that once we understand that what we allow into our
mind and what we entertain there changes us. Then we should realize the
danger that we're in, living in modern Western culture.
Thank you.
Well, that is our show for tonight.
Thank you everyone for listening.
If you did not get a chance to call in during the live broadcast, we'd love to hear from
you, either via email at LordofspiritsatAncientsFaith.com or you can message us at our Lordofspirits
podcast, Facebook page.
We do read everything but we can't respond to everything and we do save what you send
for possible use in future episodes.
These are the month at 7pm Eastern 4pm Pacific.
If you're on Facebook, you can like our page and join our discussion group.
You can leave reviews and ratings everywhere, but most importantly, share this show with a
friend whom you know is going to love it.
And finally, be sure to go to ancientfaith.com, stroke support and help make sure we and lots
of other AFR podcasters stay on the air.
Thank you very much and may God bless you always.
You've been listening to the Lord of Spirits with Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew
Stephen Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung, a listener-supported presentation of Ancient Faith Radio.
I be held, and I heard the voice of many angels round about the throne, and the beasts,
and the elders, and the number of them was ten thousand times ten thousand than thousands
of thousands, saying with a loud voice, worthy is the land that was slain to receive power,
and riches, and wisdom, and strength, and honor, and glory, and blessing.
Revelation chapter 5 verses 11 through 12.
In 1892, a young man left his home in the coastal foothills of Lebanon and searched for a better life.
Coming to America with his newlywed wife, he found work as a traveling peddler before settling on a small farm in Central Nebraska.
Years later, personal tragedy and an unexpected...