He will be a staff for the righteous with which for them to stand and not to fall, and
he will be the light of the nations and the hope of those whose hearts are troubled.
All who dwell on the earth will fall down and worship him, and they will praise and bless
and celebrate with song the Lord of Spirits.
1st denoc.
Chapter 48 verses 4-5.
The modern world doesn't acknowledge but is nevertheless haunted by spirits, angels,
demons, and saints.
In our time, many year into break free of the prison of a flat, secular materialism,
to see and to know reality as it truly is. What is this spiritual reality like? How do we engage
with it well? How do we permeate everyday life with spiritual presence? Orthodox Christian priests,
Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen De Young, host this live Colin show,
focused on enchantment in creation the union of the scene and unseen as made by
by God and experienced by mankind throughout history.
Welcome to the Lord of Spirits.
Welcome to the Lord of Spirits Podcast.
I am Father Andrew Stephen Damick.
And if you're listening to us live,
you can call in at 855-AF radio,
which is 855-237-2346.
and we are gonna get to your calls.
in roughly the second half of today's show.
So this is our very, very first episode.
So today we're gonna be discussing angels and demons
as a way to introduce the program to you
and lay some foundations and let you know what it's all about.
So some of you are probably familiar with the work
that I've done with Ancient Faith Radio.
And I'm sure that many of you are familiar
with my co-host Father Stephen D. Young's podcast
and blog which are both titled
the whole council of God.
But especially for those of you who are totally new,
I thought we'd begin by each telling a little bit
about ourselves and especially why we're doing
this new show.
So, Father Steven, why don't you introduce yourself
to our listeners and tell them what you hope
to accomplish with this program.
Sure, my name, as you said, is Father Steven D. Young
and I'm the pastor at Archangel Gabriel Orthodox Church
in Lafayette, Louisiana.
Beyond that, my origins are mostly shrouded in mystery.
I
I think the main thing I want to do here is disambiguate the two of us.
Right.
Father Andrew Stephen Damick is one human person.
And Father Stephen D. Young is a different human person.
Although my first name is his middle name, and we both have a last name starting with a capital D, we are different humans.
Alright, so your thing, my name is not Duh.
No, it's even young.
No, it's actually James.
But I don't use it because apparently that confuses people,
as you've just got it.
So it turns to what we're here to accomplish.
If anyone knows anything about me, you know, I'm my Bible guy
and I do Bible stuff.
And I think what I really want to do
is do a little part of the work of helping
English-speaking American Orthodox Christians kind of appropriate more of the
fullness of the Orthodox faith particularly as it pertains to our spiritual
sensibility, our sense of the spiritual world and the way that can and should
infuse our whole lives.
Yeah, yeah.
Well, and as I said earlier, I'm Father Andrew Stephen Damick and I work full
time for ancient faith ministries as their chief content officer.
A position that I started just five, six weeks ago actually.
I did serve in Paris Ministry for 13 years, including 11 as a pastor.
And one of the kind of fun things that Father Steven and I share is that we actually have both had the same job.
Although I had it for just two years and he had it for eight.
But we are both the former assistant pastor of St. George Orthodox Cathedral in Charleston, West Virginia.
Hello to any of you Charleston people out there who are currently listening to two of your former assistant pastors.
But I'm super interested in this show because I think that there's so much about spiritual
life that it's easy for us not just to miss but to have endless struggles with that we
don't necessarily have to have, right?
And we're going to talk about this a lot as we go and of course not just in this episode,
it's going to be perennial issue.
The sense that we have that the 3D
world that we experience is kind of all we feel like we can access most of the time, right?
But as Christians, we want to access something beyond this and it's very frustrating when
you maybe reach out for God or the saints and you're like, well, where are you?
You know, what's going on, right?
And serving as a pastor for 11 years, this is a perennial issue.
And I think any pastors that are out there, you've had the same experience, but even just
Christians, you know, that...
that we all have this difficulty
because we're modern people living
in a way of thinking and looking at the world
that makes it difficult to access spirituality.
And so my interest is pastoral.
I mean, it's also just like I like to geek out
about this kind of stuff.
But I think one of the important kind of disambiguation
to use your term father's even to make here at the beginning
is that just to def-
find that one of the differences between the two of us is that you are an actual biblical
scholar, right? And maybe make you list off the languages that you read at some point.
But and I'm not. So I'm not like it's not like, you know, and now we have a panel of two
experts in biblical scholarship ready to answer your question. That's not what this show
is, right? So if you, you know, if you've read Father Stevens' blog, the whole Council
God you listen to his podcast you know that he's studied this stuff very very closely and has a lot
a lot of really in-depth knowledge.
He actually has a doctorate.
Is it biblical studies or New Testament?
I'm trying to remember which...
Biblical studies.
Biblical studies, okay.
This one actually, yeah.
Yeah, he actually has a PhD in this stuff.
I super don't, right?
But, you know, when we were first talking about this show,
I said, I said to Father, Steve, I said,
so like how are we gonna make sure
that this show isn't just you telling about the things
you know and me seeing there saying,
that's awesome, do your awesome.
And your response was something like,
Voila!
way more practical than I am, right?
You know?
So yeah, yeah.
Well, my original pitch was that you would read newspaper headlines and then I would explain
how that relates to end times, prophecy.
But you knits that.
And then yeah, you were more practical and also much more of a professional broadcaster.
So without you, this would just be the semi-unending ramblings of a...
great.
Right.
So, I think one of the things you're going to hear as we go on this show is I want to be
learning.
I've learned a lot from my friendship with Father Steven.
And I'm trying to learn from a lot of other sources as well.
I mean Father Steven sends me stuff all the time.
is what we want to accomplish with this is that we're going to...
be in a blurring process together, and that being an orthodox
Christian isn't about mastering a specific set of data,
and now you've got it down and you're cataclyzed
and you're good to go when you get to the gates of heaven,
they're gonna check and make sure that you can answer
the catacetical questions.
Like that's not the way that being a Christian actually works.
And in the past few years, a lot of things have really
kind of opened my eyes to whole parts of orthodox tradition
that are there in an office.
staring us in the face, but that we're often not paying attention to.
I'll just give one example.
OK.
So you're probably going to hear us talk a lot about what we're going to call spiritual
geography, right?
So where is paradise?
Where is the underworld?
You know, the mountain of God, Hades, like all this kind of stuff.
OK.
And one of the things that one of the teachings that's actually preserved in the
Orthodox Church and has been handed down for many, many centuries, but that I
Bye.
I've been an Orthodox Christian for over 20 years now that I never actually paid attention to.
So if you had come up to me and said does the church teach this, I would be like,
I've never heard that. And and one of those things is this teaching that
Saint John the forerunner, John the Baptist,
went to Hades to preach the coming of Christ. Now you're not going to see that in the Bible,
but it is a belief that is actually in Orthodox tradition. And so I actually noticed this for the first time just a few years ago,
and the 40
thing is, it's actually kind of staring you in the face. It's referenced in lots of places,
especially in our liturgical traditions. So for instance, a couple weeks ago, on the new calendar,
we just celebrated the beheading of John the Baptist, that feast. And I had noticed that in the
Apolitikian, which is kind of one of the main hymns for the feast, that it actually mentions that he
goes to Hades to preach there. And I'd sung it for years, but I'd never just taken notice of that
that particular phrase.
It's in the Apolitikian, and so I started looking at other
texts and you know what? It's in the Kentucky and two, the other main him for the day. And I started looking at more and more especially throughout the
manane, which is a main set of festival texts for the feast. And it's everywhere. It's mentioned over and over that he goes to the underworld to
preach to those in Hades. And so that's just one example of something that's right there in our tradition and kind of staring you in the
phase but unless you're oriented towards paying attention to it, you're probably
just gonna kind of skip over it. Not really even know that it's there.
And so if someone was saying to me, you know, we could say in a nutshell, what is this show about?
It's about talking especially about those things that are right there and in the Bible right there in the church services right there in the church fathers
but that
maybe we've never noticed or we didn't know what to do with it
So we just kind of skipped over it or maybe it was hidden behind a translation issue and we just didn't know because we don't read the original languages
which is, and sometimes these are really...
kind of important issues, right?
It's not just obscure little things like,
oh, that's neat.
You know, it's really important issues for your spiritual life.
So I know that's a much longer way of saying
what my motivation is for doing this.
So, but I think it's important for us
to lay the stuff out at the beginning.
So the people get the idea, you know,
this is not a couple of professors teaching the class
in demonology or angelology or any of that kind of stuff.
Like that's not what's going on.
but obviously we're gonna be touching.
on a lot of those kinds of topics, right?
So is there anything else that Father, you wanted to add in terms of, you know, laying
out what it is we're trying to accomplish with this particular show?
Well, just going along with what you were just saying, that, and one of the questions
that we will probably end up getting asked relatively frequently is sort of why people
haven't heard this stuff before, right?
you know I get
that at least when I go dredging up some eukaryotic legend or something and saying,
oh see, this explains this icon.
You know?
And by the way, eukaryotic is one of the obscure languages that Father Stevens knows how
to read.
It's super helpful if we ever get a time machine and I can go back to like 1,500 BC.
But, you know, it's important to recognize that the, one of the things, as you just
mentioned once.
So you read something or someone tips you off to these things.
And you start seeing them in iconography.
You start hearing them in the hymns of the church,
like they're everywhere.
It's just we haven't been taught to sort of think
in that way and think in that direction.
So our Orthodox tradition has sort of preserved all
of these data points, has preserved all of this information
and all of this context for us.
It's just we have it necessarily as English.
speaking Orthodox Christians in the West sort of fully appropriated how to connect those dots
and how it all fits together and what the connective tissue is between these different things,
between this biblical passage and this icon and this hymn.
Yeah, and I think that, you know, as people living in the West, we tend to value education a great deal.
And so this is one of the places where a, you know, a godly education, right,
And appropriately spiritually
formed education can really be helpful to us, right?
So we're not talking about academia in all the negative ways
that people tend to use that term, right?
You know, we're not, it's not about ripping apart
the tradition or destroying what people believe
or anything like that, but actually using all kinds
of great tools of study that show us, as you said,
the connective tissue between things that are right there
in our tradition.
So the question is, not, you know, should this be
in our tradition, but why is it there and how does it connect
with all this other stuff?
you know so i i think people
going to be delighted and really excited and interested and a lot of the stuff that we're
going to be talking about. And in many ways, you're never going to be able to see the Bible
in the same way again. Like I remember the time you told me that the book of Joshua was about
giants. I was like, wait, what? What? What? What? I was just really excited to hear that. And
that's one of the books that a lot of people never want. Don't want to read because they feel like
like it's a book about genocide.
And we're not going to talk this.
is not the giants episode, but there is going to be a giant
stuff episode.
So yeah, giants and dragons and all these things are in the
scripture and in our tradition.
And so the question is, what do we do with that?
And how do we understand what it means?
And then how do we best live in that reality?
Right? You don't want to open up boxes that you shouldn't open.
but there's also just a reality of spiritual reality
that's there. So anyway, so you know, we want to start our discussion today. As I said, this is a
this is a an episode about laying the foundations for the rest of what this show is going to be. And we're going to, by the
way, we're going to be on twice a month. So the second and fourth Thursday of the month, it's not exactly fortnightly because
occasionally there's going to be five Thursdays in a month, right? So, but it's going to be the second and fourth Thursdays in the month. And,
And you know, that's where you can be able to tune in live and it will
will be available as a podcast for those of you who can't tune in live for whatever reason,
you're a time zone that's halfway across the world or you have something going on, right?
But we wanted to start with this discussion of the question of materialism, okay?
And I think in Christian circles, we tend to use the materialism as a kind of synonym for
greed, right?
That person's very materialistic.
They want to buy a lot of stuff, they're obsessed with their stuff.
But that's not what we mean by materialism and what we're talking about.
So.
So if you had to give a nutshell definition of materialism father, what would you say?
It's basically the belief that matter and energy and their co-relationships and interactions
are all that exists. So there's no demons out there. No fairies. No demons, no gods, no
no no miracles just you don't have a soul mathematics and science
and explain everything.
And yeah, yeah.
So.
It's just atoms bouncing off each other
and that's all there is, right?
So it's sort of the ultimate, in some ways
it's kind of the ultimate deterministic universe
where everything that you think and feel and do
and say was actually determined
from the moment of say a big bang
which got all the atoms bouncing off of each other
and now they've bounced and they made you
for this one little blip in time.
And if that sounds ultimately kind of meaningless,
that's because it is.
But we don't believe that.
We're not materialists.
We believe that there's an immaterial character to reality.
But here's the thing, right?
Modern Christians, I think, are materialists.
And here's why I would say that.
It's not because most Christians don't believe
that there's an immaterial element of Rhea.
that they don't believe they have a soul,
that they don't believe there's angels,
that they don't believe that God is real.
Right?
Christians will say, I mean, I've never met a Christian
that doesn't, you know, that doesn't believe
in an immaterial reality.
Maybe they're out there, I don't know.
It doesn't look like Christianity to me.
But I would say that modern Christians are materialists,
not on purpose, but by habit, right?
That on a day-to-day basis, the way we mostly live
Our lives is...
As though the 3D world of the senses is all that there is.
Right?
The example I often give is, you know, one time I ate a lot of pizza and some spicy hot wings.
And, you know, I'm getting to be middle aged. In fact, Father Stephen and I are almost the same age.
He is a little older, but just a few months, forever, correctly.
Yeah.
you know, get middle-aged, you eat hot wings and pizza and stuff and your innerd are gonna...
Let you know later in the day, maybe immediately that that was not the best thing to do, right?
So what do we do when we have, you know,
Asin and digestion, you take antacids, chew up those little pills.
I like the mint flavored ones.
And you feel better.
And that's all there is to it.
You had a problem, so you took a medicine and boom, you're better, right?
There's nothing wrong with that.
But like what point along that continuum of...
experience and response, did I include anything having to do with God or the saints?
I mean, if the idea of having ascent and digestion sounds like it's too trivial to involve God
in, then that means that you are a materialist by habit, right?
And I am, right?
I think everybody listening this probably is.
Now it's possible that there's some very spiritual people listening to this who aren't.
And, you know, if you are...
Please pray for us, right?
But I think most of us are materialists by habit.
The other example I give is like,
if someone, I experience this many times as a pastor,
someone gets sick, they go to the hospital,
after they're at the hospital, they call the priest.
It's interesting the order, right?
First let's go get the medicine,
and then after that we will add some prayer, right?
There's nothing wrong with the medicine,
there's nothing wrong with going to the hospitals,
nothing wrong with the doctor.
I mean, those are all things God provides,
but we tend to think of prayer
is kind of a...
Fr-
frosting on the cake, you know, or like, we'll make sure you pray.
You know, that's the way that we function.
We're sort of materialists by habit, by habit.
And so this presents a problem to us,
especially when we're actually then experienced something in life
where we realize that our material habits actually don't address our problem,
that don't address my, and it's not just the problems of like
everyday aches and pains or things to solve in your life,
but the problem of being a sinful person in-
this world and trying to be faithful to Christ. That's the problem, right? And if you're
a materialist by habit, then that makes that problem a lot harder. A lot harder, because
you feel like you don't really have access to God very much. You're like, oh yeah, I pray
all the time. And somebody will say, oh, I feel that God is with me. But like, do you know,
I mean, do you have a sense he's actually fair, right? And one of the things you probably
notice if you read the Bible enough, or if you read other kinds of ancient sources,
a lot of people.
people in those texts are not like that.
They have a sense that God is with them
and that spirits are there.
Right?
So there is a difference between us and them
and I think it's mainly a difference of habit, right?
And we're gonna get into that
as to what can you do about that.
But that's one of the things that we want
to try to address with this show is how to,
and this is what kind of the more
some of the practice.
physical side of this comes in.
It's like how to alter your habits so that you are more human actually, and more in tune
with all of reality and not just the 3D world of the senses.
Right?
You have anything you wanted to add to that, Father?
Yeah.
I think the way it pragmatically works out for most Christians in America and in the West
is you have essentially two incompatible ideas.
you have been...
Basically, an atheist worldview and a Christian worldview,
that you're kind of switching back and forth between.
Right, atheist most of the time.
And that works.
The analogy I use, I guess it's an analogy,
is that we sort of have this set of brackets,
where we sort of bracket off certain things.
So like the miraculous stuff that happened in the scriptures,
okay, well, I've got to believe that that's real,
that I believe in.
So we put the brackets around God and the miracles in Scripture.
And then depending on what sort of Christian group you're in,
those brackets may be very wide or very narrow.
But they're always sort of there.
There's always a point where you go outside those brackets
and where we start becoming sort of naturalists again.
So if someone, you know, if a Buddhist comes to you and claims
there was a miracle, the first thought of most American Christians
is
not, well this is demonic activity. The first thought of most American Christians is
bull, right? You're making that out. That never happened. Right. Or your elderly aunt
comes to you and says, you know, your grandmother talked to me last night. You know, your
dead grandmother. She came to me. Like, is that, well, I'm going to, you know, that's nice.
Like we tend to function that way.
We don't give credence to it.
Now, the problem is I think that we have this fear
that if you start to give credence to it,
then you become gullible.
Right?
Which we don't want to be.
Right, you don't want to be superstitious.
That's not the same.
Like we're not teaching people
how to be superstitious as well.
That's not what we're doing.
You know?
But atheists will make hay of that.
You're right.
Right.
They say, hey, I'm just saying the same thing
about your miracles that you say about everybody else's.
Right.
I'm just saying the same thing about your God
that you say about everybody else.
Yeah, I just believe in one fewer God than you do.
Right.
So I've heard that a bunch of times.
Yeah, and it's, and they kind of have a point in that all too often we are basically looking
at most of the world the same way they do.
Right.
And then being inconsistent in these areas, you know, that we've got bracketed off.
And you can't just like flip a switch and decide, okay, I'm going to be, I'm not going to be
a materialist anymore.
Today
even spirits. I'm going to be I'm going to court a low grade controversy by saying the
rubber met the road with this recently with a lot of people even in our orthodox circles
where when the pandemic started and people were saying okay we need to take reasonable
precautions we need to be you know obedience to our bishops and the civil government but
we also need prayer incense you know in orthodox countries people are going out with holy
water in the street.
right and a lot of our of our Christian brothers and sisters in the United States
were like okay guys this is serious this is a disease this is real right in response
you know like yeah all that stuff's fun on Sunday morning but this is a serious
situation people are dying yeah yeah yeah don't don't call a priest for this we
We need epidemiologists.
It's not that we're saying...
your local Orthodox priest is a witch doctor and don't take medicine, right? That's the other opposite extreme
that the world is composed of both the physical world that's described by science and the spiritual world
that we come to experience through Christ and those two have to be kept together. And the problem is where at one extreme
the answer is not to go to the opposite extreme.
Yeah, I mean, that's one of the reasons that why, in the description for the show,
I wanted to especially use that phrase, the union of the scene and the unseen.
Right?
You know, we're not just talking about, like this is not a show about ghosts, right?
It's not, it's not like, you know, here's how you do with your haunted house.
Although I'm sure, I hope we do it get at least one caller that calls in and says that their house is haunted.
And what do you do about that?
Because there is something to do, actually.
Yes, and I have done it.
i have done an excerpt it
i have done an excerpt
is amount of house to tease everyone.
Yeah, there you go.
All right, everybody.
Yeah, so that's the problem of materialism, right?
And so in a few minutes, we're going to go for our first break.
But before we get to that, let's just talk for just a very few minutes about the title of this podcast,
which we talked, you and I talked about this.
We went back and forth for weeks to try to figure out exactly the right thing.
and I'm not going to, I, I, I, fortunately I have for
most of the bad suggestions that we had.
But we finally settled on Lord of Spirits, Lord of Spirits,
which one person with ancient faith radio kept calling Lord
of the Spirit.
And I was like, oh, maybe we'll get a few Lord of the Rings fans.
That wouldn't make me unhappy at all.
But no, it's Lord of the Spirit.
Although you could say Lord of the Spirit,
that works too.
Lord of Spirit, so it's not a phrase you see.
I don't think it's in the Bible, is it?
Is it in the Bible?
Well, it depends on your Bible.
Are you...
Ethiopian. Oh, there you go. Yeah. Okay. So yes, open that up for us a little bit. Where does the
sprays Lord of Spirits come from and and why did we pick it? So Lord of Spirits is one of several
titles that's ascribed to God in the inocic literature, which is the various books of Enoch as
well as other books like the apocalypse of Abraham and the book of Jubilee's and a few other
in the Dead Sea Scrolls.
Lower spirits is mostly used in the second portion of First Enic or the Book of Enic,
which is called the Book of Parables.
And the reason it's used there is that it's a title for God that describes his relationship
with the other spiritual beings whom he created.
So it's a way of referring to God in relationship to...
the Heavenly Host, the Divine Council, some of these other concepts that we're going to be talking about a lot, not only in this episode, but in a bunch of episodes.
And I'm sure in people's questions, the parallel title that you find more commonly in the Hebrew Bible is Yahweh, Saba-Oat, which is usually translated Lord Saba-Oat.
Um.
And a lot of people in the liturgy we transliterate rather than translate
Savo Ode. Right. And so because of the way it looks in English, the way it's
spelled in English, people think it refers to the Sabbath. Sabbath, right? And when I
say people I have a recording of Bart Irman saying that. Oh boy. So his Hebrew is
really up to stuff. Yes. I mean I don't read Hebrew but I know that that's not
Yeah
But the Old Endig is a feminine plural ending in Hebrew,
Sava means to be many, to theme to be many.
And so that in a nominal form in the plural means like big groups or hosts.
Lord of hosts is how the King James Old Testament.
So we sink right in the anaphora of the divine liturgy.
We sing what in Latin is called the Sanktus, holy, holy, holy Lord of Sabaoth, heaven and earth are full of that glory.
So this is one of those things, like, so we're talking about here now. This is one of those things that's right there core piece of our liturgical tradition.
I mean, it is right there at the heart of the divine liturgy. We call God the Lord Sabaoth, the Lord of hosts.
Right and so it's there and you it doesn't just
mean that he's got a lot of angels available to him. We're going to be talking about all of
that but but you know he is Lord of hosts and it's interesting and then and it also comes in
you've ever gone to great compline which we especially served during at least in our tradition
during great length but it shows up of course at other times of the liturgical year. There is a
there is a hymn in there called Lord of hosts, O Lord of hosts be with us where we have no
know whether it helped but in times of sorrow but the
right, which is in the Byzantine tradition is just a wonderful big throaty, it could have
manly hymn. But what's interesting is that in Greek it's Kediye Vename on Lord of
Powers, but it means the same thing, right? I mean that's just simply the, isn't that
just the Septuagin translation of Lord Saboth, right?
Yeah, it gets complicated because the Septuagin is in different ways, but yeah, it's the
same kind of idea, God of the powers.
The hymn, the the the the the the holy holy holy Lord Savahot is
speaking sung by the angels and it's a way of the angels expressing and
worshipping him as their God. That's a way we don't always think about it and
that's why there's a similar phrase also in our memorial prayers which is
actually taken directly from the book of Jubilee's a different piece of
an occupier literature, where the prayer begins, oh God.
of spirits that evolve flesh. Right, another piece that probably just rattles by most of us.
Like I pray for years as a priest, oh God, of spirits evolve flesh. You know,
but I never paused and thought, wait, wait, who are the spirits that we're saying he's the God of?
Exactly. Well, this is what we're talking about, right? That's what this is. So, all right, well,
we're gonna take a break now, and but when we come back from the break, we're gonna start talking
about the many different ways that the word God's.
is used in the Bible.
So, you know, we want you to call in.
We're gonna take calls in the second half of the show.
You can call at 855-8F radio.
That is 855-237-2346.
And I have to admit, I'm always tempted to say 855-a radio.
But then I think people might put the letter I in there,
somewhere where I shouldn't be.
Anyways, all right, well, let's take a break
and we will be right back in just a few minutes.
Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung
and the young will be back.
in a moment to take your calls on the second half of the Lord of Spirits. Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF radio.
Hi, this is Father Evan Armitas, priest at St. Spirit on Greek Orthodox Church in Luland,
Colorado and the host of the ancient faith radio Sunday night call and show orthodoxy.
I am pleased to announce today the release of my first book for ancient faith publishing title toolkit for spiritual growth a
Pactual guide to prayer fasting and arms giving
It seeks to provide a guide to the three basic and primary disciplines of orthodox spirituality
Through these disciplines Christ opened for us a path that frees us from the disordered way of life
Has become normal for many even though their hearts and minds tell them otherwise
Please join me in exploring the Three-Legged Stool of Orthodox Spiritism.
practice, prayer, fasting, nomsgiving, books now available at store.ancientfaith.com
And the title once again is Toolkit for Spiritual Growth.
I look forward to sharing it with you.
God bless.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits, the Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father
Stephen DeYoung.
If you have a question, call now at 855-237-2346.
Let's eat 5, 5, A-F radio.
All right, well, we are back.
And before we get to our discussion about the way the word God's is used in the Bible,
I just wanted to thank the man whose voice you just heard.
And that is our good friend, Stephen Christophero, who has provided the voice over work for this
podcast. I think he just nailed it. So if you know Steve tell him that he-
did a fine job. Thank you Steve, I hope that you're listening. So yeah, let's talk about the word
gods as it's used in the Bible because that I think is going to be the one of the ways that
people are going to hear stuff that we're going to say on this show and it's going to sound
weird to them and they're going to wonder if we're actually Christians because we're saying,
well I believe in lots of gods actually, you know, but so let's talk about why as a Christian you can
and should believe in many gods.
If that doesn't weird you out too much.
So let's begin by talking about how the word God's is actually used in the Bible.
And this is one of the ways that sometimes translation is hiding something from us, right?
So we have an English translation that might use other kinds of words,
but lurking underneath is a Hebrew word or a Greek word that actually is saying God's.
And that's, but it doesn't get translated as God's in English.
So what are some examples of that, Father?
Yeah.
Before we freak everybody out, let me give one more profile. So in terms of why we're freaking everybody out. Yeah
You one might wonder why you would do this to people
The the reality is that that
There are certain things that are just in the scriptures
whether we as sort of modern
Christians with the materialist bent kind of are comfortable with that or not and
and they have a way of speaking and
from the Victorian era through until
Probably the 1950s or so in America
There was sort of a gentleman's agreement that we would all sort of paper over these things in our English translations and
Not push on them to push on them too hard
And so that we could all be comfortable
and
the the problem is that
If we want to continue to do that as
as Orthodox Christians were setting ourselves up.
for a problem with future generations.
Because while I may not want to get into, say, a passage
in the Old Testament that talks about human sacrifice,
the atheist roommate of my son or daughter,
the atheist professor of my son or daughter
is going to have no such qualms about bringing up all
of these things.
Yes, uncomfortable stuff in the Bible.
and when that happens
If we have tried to paper over it and not talked about it and not explained it to our people,
not only are they going to fall for whatever narrative they're told, but we're not going
to have any credibility to come back with a response, because we've already proven that
we're trying to keep things from them.
Yeah.
I'm embarrassed by our own central text.
So, uh...
That's why we're going to talk about these kind of things.
It's not because we're trying to shake anybody up
or be firebrands or cause controversy or you know.
No, I mean you and I, you and I are both dedicated
to being solid, normal, mainstream Orthodox Christians,
that hopefully the only thing extreme about us
is our repentance and I'm just learning that.
You know, you know, these are not like this is not about pitching crap
part theories, folks, it's not. It's about looking very closely at our Bible, at our church
fathers, at our church services, and saying, what do they really say? And what are they
taking seriously that maybe we're not, right? So, you know, one of the examples, and
you know, Father Stephen is very hopefully provided a lot of the research for this. One of
the examples that we have in our notes that I thought is a great place to start, and it's
kind of a shocking passage just to be just simply read it.
and actually pay a little bit of attention to it, is from the very beginning of Psalm 82, so
get out your Bibles, ladies and gentlemen. Psalm 82, if you're looking at like a King James Bible
or another Bible that's using the Hebrew numbering of the Psalms, but it's Psalm 81, if you're looking
at the Greeks of 2-digit numbering, and I just wanted to read the first verse actually, and
And just to show that what we're talking about is not something...
that we're making up, right? So here's Psalm 81 or 82 depending on which version you're reading,
verse 1. And I'm reading it out of the Orthodox study Bible. God stood in the assembly of gods.
He judges in the midst of gods, saying, and then it goes on to say what he says. God stands in
the assembly of gods. I can't doesn't say God stood in the assembly of so-called gods, right?
It doesn't say, it just simply says gods in the assembly of gods. And if you read, you keep reading
the summit never says it.
anywhere in it, those beings that he's standing in the midst of are not gods. Right? So,
what's going on there? Like, what's the deal? I thought we believed in only one god.
So do you want some more examples first or do you want to do that? Yeah, right. Yeah, sure.
Let's roll on with some more. Yeah, let's just leave that question hanging.
Let's pile them up. Yeah, let's pile it up. Yeah, right. Because it's everywhere.
Right, okay, yeah, yeah, give us another one, Father Steve.
Right, so, so
1889, 88 in the Greek numbering and beginning around verse 5, let the heavens praise your
wonders, oh Yahweh, your faithfulness and assembly of the holy ones, for who in the skies
can be compared to Yahweh? Who among the sons of God is like Yahweh? A God greatly
to be feared in the council of the holy ones, and awesome above all who are around him.
So this is talking about the relationship between God and heavenly sons of God.
It says who in the skies, so that's kind of hard to make be humans of any kind.
It's not about people, right?
You can't just read this as being about sort of theoses because it's in the heavens.
Yeah.
And I'll just keep rolling.
Yes.
And let me just say actually, I just noticed the very next verse, right?
what you read, verse 9, I'm looking at the Orthodox study Bible.
O Lord God of hosts who is like you.
So the next line is describing this relationship that we're discussing.
Okay, go on.
What's the next end?
Well, and it even added that it goes on in verse 10 to talk about God crushing a sea monster
and throwing its carcass to the earth.
Yeah.
We have to do a whole episode on monsters.
on specific monsters like we could do on liveirth and
one on behemoth.
Yes, you myth.
Yeah.
Oh yeah.
But so then Exodus 1511, you know, who is like you, O Yahweh, among the gods, who is like
you majestic in holiness, awesome and glorious deeds, doing wonders?
This isn't comparing God, the God of Israel, to imaginary characters, right?
That wouldn't be a big praise.
Like who in the Marvel Cinematic Universe is like God?
Right.
Right, right.
I mean, no.
Okay, but what does that prove?
Right?
Actually, it was 1811, three chapters later.
Now I know that Yahweh is greater than all gods because of this affair they dealt
arrogantly with the people.
The they is the gods.
The Egyptian gods in this case, right?
Right.
Yeah.
And the Magiara characters can't deal arrogantly with people.
Right.
later in excess where God says that he's judged the gods of Egypt.
It's earlier that's what he's doing on Passover night, right?
He's judging the God's judgment right so like is God rendering judgment to
Made up characters that the Egyptian pagans are worshiping like it doesn't the text doesn't say that it doesn't say
Their fake it doesn't say that they don't exist
Right and and you know, I mean we could we will get into it in the new Testament later
I mean most of the stuff we're reading from the old, but we're showing
If you look at the scriptures closely, you'll see that the scriptures are taking these things very seriously and not saying this is some kind of metaphor or again made up stories.
One of the problems with the way that the modern world tends to look at ancient religion
is they'll say, oh, well, they noticed that there's lightning in the sky or they notice
that there's earthquakes or they notice that the Nile floods and so they came up with
some kind of exposure.
for it and eventually that explanation evolved into believing in some kind of God of lightning or what no that's that's not the way that the Bible depicts this stuff
And it's not the way that the people on the ground understood what they were doing
Right that that's not that they they attested the fact that they had encounters
with these spiritual beings and the Bible takes them very very seriously
Again God standing in the mix the gods God judging gods
you know it's lots of
Okay, I know we got some more. Okay, let's talk a couple more here. Yeah, yeah, because we do want to take some calls
Yeah, due to the enemy 1017
For you know, your God is God of God's and Lord of Lords
The great the mighty and the awesome God who is not partial and takes no bribe
Yeah, there and some 95 three is similar. It's for for you always a great God and a great king above all gods
So when we see this language God of God's it's not just a superlative
It's saying that the other
gods have the God of Israel as their God. Right. I mean you could say like you
could read Lord of Lords and say okay that means that God is above all the
kings and the presidents or whatever the earth but but God of God is harder to
explain away. Right and especially when it's disambiguated as the great king
above all gods. Right. Right. That it's not that they don't exist it's that he's
he's their king and so what's going on here is
a couple of things. The first is that the word God is just being used to refer to spiritual
beings. It's like there are effects in English. We usually do that by using a capital letter
for God and then a lowercase God or God's for these other beings. But the reason for
that, and the father is actually when they talk about the word, the Greek word the
O's and what it means.
They really get into the idea that it's kind of a verbal idea even though it's a noun.
Okay. What do you know that the word is something that God does.
He is God. It has to do with his like godding.
It's it has to do with his dominion and his rule and his power.
And some examples of this that might help with that
in the New Testament. For example, St. Paul refers to the devil as the God of this present age.
Right. He's not saying that he rivals the God of Israel in power, right?
Prestigia is a second God. He's certainly functioning he has.
And or certainly he's not saying that he should be worshipped.
Right. And what can I tell you? I know over and over and over about that issue.
Yeah, but say Paul is saying that
He is worshiped in this present age.
Right.
Yeah.
And so these spiritual beings can be called gods.
In English, we do it with a small G, but they aren't
using capitals in Greek.
Can be talked about that way because either on the one side,
God has chosen to share his rule and his dominion with them.
and so with
with angelic beings, they are sharing in and raining with God and God is exercising his
rule and his dominion and his power and his authority through them, graciously sharing
it with them. Or on the other side, on the more demonic side, because humans in their
rebellion and sin have elevated these spiritual beings and chosen to worship and serve them
and become enslaved to them.
And so they are functioning as gods.
in that sense. They become their God. And I know I think it may be even our next show in
a fortnight we're going to go deeper into this but this is a big part of what's going on when
the fathers talk about fiosus and talk about us becoming gods that's directly connected to the
idea in the New Testament of Christ exercising his rule and authority through the saints in glory
that they rule and reign with him and share in his
So...
it is dominion, but we'll get into that.
Yeah, yeah. So I just wanted to make another, because we're going to be talking, I know,
because we're both nerds in different ways on different levels, for sure. But we're going to be
talking a lot about words and what they mean and how they're used and how they're used in lots of
different ways. And someone might counter and say, well, it doesn't the word Elohim, which,
you know, doesn't that mean God's in Hebrew? Doesn't Elohim just mean the Father's Son and Holy Spirit?
Doesn't that just mean Yahweh, right?
Is that the case? Is Elohim only used in the Hebrew Bible for Yahweh?
No, in fact it's even more flexible than Thelus.
Oh wow, right.
Right, Elohim is used to refer to any spiritual being.
So it's used to refer to God, the true God.
It's used to refer to the gods, the same word, Elohim.
and
really freak people out. No, yeah. I have a couple of examples where it's even used for deceased
humans. The first one and the one that might freak people out less,
in 1 Samuel 28 verse 13, and this is first kingdoms if you're looking at a
a 2-idgin Bible.
If you're in your Orthodox study Bible.
Right.
This is when Saul, near the end of his reign as King, and his disobedience goes to consult
with the witch or the medium at Endor, not the one with the Ewoks.
Oh man!
The city, it's Valentine.
And asked her to sum it up the spirit of Samuel.
And there's this moment in verse 13 where she's kind of seemingly maybe a
little surprised at how well it worked. And because she starts freaking out. And
verse 13 says, the king said to her, do not be afraid. What do you see? And the woman said to
Saul, I see a God coming up out of the earth. So and then that turns out to be Samuel's spirit
and he speaks. Right. So he's called a God in the Bible. Right. So he's the term Elohim
is used to apply to him.
And the biblical author is not saying that the prophet Samuel was another person of the
Trinity or that he was a polytheist and the prophet Samuel now lived on Mount Olympus or
something.
That's not what he's going for.
The word is just flexible to include that.
And now the one that would be most controversial that I kind of warned you about, but we're going
go there.
And this is in Exodus 21, verses 1 through 6, which is in the context of laws governing slavery.
So not controversial at all this passage in the Torah.
And so this particular rule that's being made in the first six verses of Exodus is for a situation where
Someone has been in a period of indentured service.
So they've been working for and part of a household for some period of time to pay off a debt.
And they come to the end of their term of service, but they like the household and the family and they want to stay on.
There were strict rules about how long you could keep someone in slavery and all of these things that are outlined in the rest of the chapter.
the rest of the chapter. But so if a person voluntarily says, you know, I rather like being
the tutor or nanny for your children.
and I want to stay, you know, I feel like I'm part of the family.
There was a provision to do that.
And so there is a ritual described here for what you do
with that person who has decided they want to stay permanently
as part of the household.
And so I'll read Exodus 21 verses 5 and 6.
But if the slave plainly says,
I love my master, my wife and my children,
I will not go out free.
that his master shall bring him to the gods.
And he shall bring him to the door or the doorpost,
and his master shall bore his ear through with an all,
and he shall be his slave forever.
There's not a way to get around the fact
that it says that he will bring him to the gods.
Yeah.
In the Hebrew, there's a definite article.
So the word the.
So you can't say bring him to God.
Yeah.
Yes, the God.
and Saint Jerome translated this just
woodly literally. It's if you look
in in the Volga, he has a deus.
It's just the plural of God. Bring
him to the gods. He just translated
it directly from the from the Hebrew.
The Greek is interesting because the
The Greek says, uh...
that you should bring him before the court of God.
Right, yeah, like the Orthodox city Bible has the judgment seat of God.
Right. And it's not the word judgment seat.
It's the word, it's where we get the word criterion actually.
It's criteria owned.
Yeah.
And it means a law court.
It means like the actual court.
Yeah, so there's other people there.
Right. Yeah, so it's talking about like the council of God basically.
Yeah, yeah.
Yeah.
So, are people in council?
Well, so okay, so I want to move on here so we can start taking a couple of calls because
Bobby is telling me that we have a lot of people who have called in.
So, thank you everybody.
Let me have one little talk before we do that.
Do you want to leave people hanging with?
Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
That's the first thing.
That who that's referring to are the Department of Family members.
Oh yeah.
right? Right? Right? There.
Cause there's still around your
home. Some sense. Right.
God is the God of Abraham, Isaac
and Jacob. He's the God, not the
God of the dead, but of the
living. Yeah. And so the idea
here is that it's not that you
like sum it up the spirits of
your dead ancestors or worship
them or sacrifice it. There's
none of that here. Right. But
you take them to the door post,
which is sort of representative
of the household in the family.
That's why that's what was
marked with blood on the pass
over.
You take them there and you do this to do this ritual because you're making them a part of the family.
And so it's talking about those ancestors as witnesses.
It's more closely related to the great cloud of witnesses in Hebrews 11 than to some kind of ancestor worship or something.
Yeah, but I wanted to get that in so people walk away with a with a weird idea.
So just to summarize real quick then so when we're talking about spirits or gods
Setting aside those terms to use refer
to Yahweh, Father, Son, Holy Spirit, there's kind of three kinds of beings that are described
as gods in the Bible. And we're just talking about the Bible here. We're not even getting
into some of the more interesting, I want to say more interesting. Some of the literature
you probably haven't read too much of, folks, you know, like Enoch or Jubilee's, whatever.
And there's three kinds of beings. There's angels, there's demons which really are just
angels that are rebelling against God. And there's dead people, you know, those who have
the past on.
those are all referred to as gods in the scripture. So yeah, so I want to start
taking calls but before we take the first call actually, I wanted to answer a
question that came in over email and this comes from Brian who's actually
relatively local to me and he sent me an email earlier today because he heard
we were going to be talking about angels and demons and so forth and he sent
this question. He said, my grandson.
John Cassian, what a great name for a kid, who is six years old.
Is going to be listening to your podcast in Angels tonight from Scottsdale, Arizona.
He is very interested in Angels right now, wants to ask if good angels are able to be killed
by bad angels.
He's curious about whether they can die or not.
And I just want to take this one and the reason he is why.
Because this might be the only question that I can answer from the other one.
We'll see if I can do that.
I'm actually you.
Yeah, maybe, maybe.
I like that tension out there.
Right, exactly.
That's one of the things that's going to be going on.
I'm ready to be corrected.
I'm ready to learn.
But I'm going to say that good angels cannot be killed by bad angels because they don't
have mortal bodies.
Am I correct in that?
We do have an episode we're going to be talking about spiritual bodies in the future.
But this is not it.
Yeah.
Without going into the whole body's question because, yes, that's a big topic.
Yes, right. So it is true that you are correct. Obviously that that evil angels cannot kill good angels. Right. However, however, evil angels can die.
Yeah. Yeah.
Red from Psalm 82. Yes. Yes.
You read the verse, but verses six and seven.
I have said your gods, but you shall die like men.
Right, you will die like men.
And...
So the thing we have to keep in mind is that when the fathers talk about death, they
say, John Damascus clearly disambiguates this.
There's physical death and there's spiritual death.
And so physical death is something that happens to humans where our soul is separated from
our body.
Yeah.
And so as you said, angels don't have mortal bodies, so they can't die physically in that
sense.
Right.
spiritual death which is the separation of the
the soul or spirit from God.
Yeah.
And that is the fate that awaits the demonic spirits
at the final judgment.
Which, if I'm correct, doesn't mean nonexistence.
It's kind of an eternal dying or eternal death.
Right, because death doesn't mean
not existence for us either.
Right, right, right.
Okay, all right, we're gonna go to break and then as.
.
Hey there, this is Bobby Maddox Station Manager of Ancient Faith Radio and it appears like
we perhaps lost Father Andrew.
I'm here.
Oh, you are here.
Yeah.
Okay.
Well, you just got quiet and we did not know what was happening.
So oh, I'm sorry.
Yeah.
Yeah, can we go to break?
Yeah, let's go to break.
That's good to break.
Father Andrew, Stephen Damick and Father Stephen De Young will be back in a moment to take
your calls.
on the second half of the Lord of Spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF radio.
Now available on Ancient Faith Publishing,
the shield of Salt McPrayer,
reflections on translating, interpreting,
and praying the Psalter.
In this posthumous collection of poet and teacher
Ronald Cheyenne's reflections on Psalms and Salt McPrayer.
Called from his journals and teaching notes,
you will find two quite different kinds
of writing working in tandem.
Poetic and personal journaling by a man of faith,
a scholar, a linguist, and in the deepest sense, a teacher.
Alongside scholarly linguistic and poetic analysis,
by a man steeped in poetry who thought like a poet.
Here's what bothers Steven Freeman has to say on the phone.
In the spiritual life, two things are essential, what we do and how we do it.
In this wonderful collection of the late Donald Sheen's thoughts on the Psalms, we see both.
He takes us into what the Psalms are in depth, that is the Word of God,
but he also demonstrates time and again how those deaths shape his life in the world in which he lives.
Thus we are GIF
and two things, the Word of God and the life in which the Word has given shape. It's a path
we all should walk.
237 2346. That's 855 AF radio.
All right, we are back and we are now ready to take your calls. And the first call that
we want to take is from Aiden in Illinois who has a question about the Divine Council.
So Aiden are you there?
Okay, all right. Well, we're going to try to get some of our other calls first then. Sorry
about that, Aiden. We have is Daniel there who has a comment or a suspicion. That's
why I'm reading in my notes here about the gods of Egypt. Daniel, are you there on the
line? Oh okay I'm getting voices on my ear this is how you can tell it's long
live radio folks telling me that some of these folks are way
way done on the queue.
Actually, you know what?
There's somebody who contacted me beforehand who I know
had a really interesting question.
And that is Stasia in Georgia.
So can we get Stasia on the line?
Hi, father.
Can you hear me?
I can hear you.
It's working.
What are you talking about?
You look at it.
Hi.
So wonderful.
The life will be on the show glad to hear from you.
I'm going to question about the first occurrence and the 11th.
I've been covering my hair daily for most of the year.
I probably started last November.
I cover my hair about 90% of the time.
And I don't really know why.
I see it in Icon.
That's the only reason I have right now.
But I'm looking at first Corinthians 1110.
And my cap of version here says, therefore,
we have to have a sign of authority on our head
because of the angel.
Because of the angel.
Can you tell me what was that?
Yeah, so this is one of these things.
things that there is a very long explanation for this.
But I know that Father Stephen has covered this in some detail.
So I'm going to punt this to him and say, give us the short version, Father Stephen, as
to what it is, why does a saying, Corinthians 1110, that a woman should have her head covered
because of the angels?
Yeah.
So this is good that we have a first question like this, because I want to let people know
That was...
Some of the questions that I've even seen in advance
from people who have emailed or sent them in other ways
are very good questions and very big questions.
And so some of these are going to end up being
an episode under themselves at some point in the future
because we want you justice to it.
But so when we get a question like this,
this is an example of one of those really good questions.
I'll try to give you at least a summary answer
and then we will probably come back to this at some point and expand more.
in full. And also because that will give me time to prepare this answer because,
though I won't go into it right now, the Greek in that passage is very sexually graphic.
And look that way in English. But what it is basically referring to is St. Paul,
But one of the major problems he's addressing throughout his first epistle to the Corinthians
is...
helping the former pagan now Christians in the Christian community in Corinth to sort
of fully separate from their pagan way of life, including pagan modes of worship, which
included a lot of ritual sexuality in their worship.
And so St. Paul is in that over-artured passage from which you
the verse is reiterating that there is no place for sort of sexual expression or sexual immorality
within the worship of the Christian Church. That seems obvious to us, but it wasn't obvious
to a pagan in Corinth in the first century. And so the reason he specifically refers to angels there
is that for St. Paul and just about any other first century Jewish person,
sort of the two parades...
cinematic sins were idolatry and sexual immorality.
And so the worst thing you could do would be to mix those two things together.
And the ultimate example of that in the Hebrew Bible in the Old Testament
is actually what happens at the beginning of Genesis 6.
And the first four verses of Genesis 6 that talks about the origin and the giants,
that talks about some kind of sexual
congress between
rebellious angelic beings and human beings,
and it was sort of ritual sexual immorality
that produced sort of these horrors on the earth.
And so St. Paul sort of alluding back to that
and saying that a woman needs to be not only
not making a sexual display in the Christian church,
but practicing sexual modesty
not only because of the other humans there,
we sometimes hear about modesty in that sense,
we don't want to tempt the men in the congregation
and then that gets into all kinds of sexual politics and things.
But St. Paul is even throwing it open to,
because sexual immorality in any kind of ritual sense
opens the door to all manner of sort of horrible evils.
So that's what St. Paul's alluding to there.
Uh, uh,
is that idea.
And so that modesty is important.
Support we go in the exact opposite direction
of any kind of sexuality involved
in our worship, our worship needs to be chased
and pure, our worship of the true God.
Yeah, and I know we're gonna get into it
like in a future discussion,
but at least part of why,
if I remember correctly,
part of why this is important in this case
is that in that time and place, a woman displaying
her glorious hair openly was regarded as essentially a thing to do to attract men.
And so doubly and appropriate for church, but as to why that is considered attractive to men
in that time and place, we're going to have to save that for future episode. It's going to blow
your mind when you hear it though folks. So our next call comes from Gareth.
who is in Louisiana. So he's
somewhere near you, Father
Stephen. He has a very
there me. Oh, so you know
him. So yeah, Garrett,
who's in Louisiana has a
question about about Mount
Hermann. How's it going?
No, but can you guys hear
me? I read? Yes. Yes,
it. All right. So, yeah,
a little bit of context for
my question. So Father Stephen
the block post he did.
a while back about Mount Sabre and Mount Hermann.
This is a common traditional site
for the Transfiguration of Christ.
It's called Mount Saphon and the Bell Cycle
and this is after Bell defeats Yam,
who's the Canaanite God of the Sea,
the PSNs to become more of Mount Saphon or Mount Hermann.
This is also in the in the Aynothic literature,
the site of the
and the fallen angels descend upon earth.
Second Enoch 19 says they broke their promise on the shoulder of Mount Hermann to defile themselves with human women.
So this question is kind of, I guess, refers to any sort of physical geography and the correlation it has to heavenly events in places.
But what is it about Mount Hermann that makes it a recurring physical place for events of such cosmic significance?
So do you want me to go straight for that one?
Yeah, right.
Sure.
So yeah, Mount Hermann.
I mean, Mount Hermann, we've been talking about the,
we're going to talk about the divine council over and over
and over and over and over again on the show.
So what does Mount Hermann have to do with all of that
then in a nutshell?
I know.
Yeah, again, this is another one that's
going to be probably a future episode at some point.
Yeah.
But Mount Hermann is not only a mountain,
And of course the...
throughout the ancient world, gods live in gardens on top of mountains. It's just a common place.
And so that imagery isn't just used in scripture for the Garden of Eden or for Mount Sinai and Mount Zion,
but it's used, obviously the one most people will be familiar with would be Mount Olympus.
But in the case of Bale and the Divine Council of L, that was mountains of fun.
the word for, Semitic word for North, so it's the mountain of the North.
And that corresponds to Mount Hermann, which right now is kind of on the border of the
goal and height, so it's not a place I would recommend visiting currently.
But in addition to being this mountain, which was seen by people from at least
at least the late Neolithic period as being a home of the gods.
One of the
things that further that is there's also a natural spring in a cave at the base of mountain
hermene. And natural geographic features were the first shrines for pagans, mostly springs,
groves of trees that they could fence in, those were sort of the first temples. And so that
cave in that spring.
were considered sacred to bail again going back into the
likely vanilla-liffic period.
It sort of got rebranded.
Later it became a shrine to pan the Greek god,
and the name was changed to panias.
And then today it's called Banius.
It's gotten switched from a P sound to a B sound.
And if you were to go, which again I don't recommend
at the present time, to Mount Herman,
It is dotted with...
hundreds of pagan shrines from all of those periods, going back to the Neelith period all the way up through the Roman period,
all over its face, at its peak, altars, and the cave with the spring at the bottom was considered to be an entryway to the underworld.
So any kind of, of, of, of,
ronic God, any kind of God associated with the underworld,
which includes Bale, that would be a place where people would
go in order to interface with those spirits.
And so yes, a lot of,
there are things with the transfiguration associated with it
and with Christ and Moses and Elijah being a topet
instead of sort of Bales council.
That is also the place.
It was near Bannyus where...
Christ told St. Peter that the gates of hell would not prevail against the church
and there were literal gates to Hades that you could point at at the time
that Christ said that because it was right after they left Cessaria
Philippi which is right there. So this is a theme we're going to come back to a
a lot is yeah all of these sites in the underworld and in the
that are talked about in scripture and in other cultures
all also correspond to actual physical places.
Yeah.
And they're seeing that the spiritual world,
we tend to think of like, well, heavens up at the sky somewhere
and the underworld is down below us.
But in actuality, they saw the spiritual world is sort of overlapping
with the physical world.
Yeah.
All right. Well, thank you very much for that call, Gareth.
I'm curious.
Next we have Michael who is in Arkansas and Michael has a question or a comment about polytheism versus monotheism.
So Michael are you there?
Yes I am. How are you father?
Good. How are you?
Good. Thank God. I have a question for father Stephen DeYoung.
You know, I was told once that there may have been a change at some point in just a way we're educated about religion.
And I remember being taught about
monotheism and polytheism and I wonder if in the ancient world it was taught the same way and how could this maybe contribute to our perceptions when we read God's in the Bible?
Yeah, that's that's a good question. I know you asked have to father Stephen, but can I just begin to take a shot at this if you don't mind?
Sure, please do because yeah, yeah, because I mean he's the expert, but I do have a couple things I want to throw in here if only so we can hear him correct me.
So.
Um, actually, um, actually.
Exactly. Everyone get out. You're you're animated gifs for that. Yeah, so you know we today like
Christians today we tend we are monotheists. That's why we talk about it and we're not polytheists.
So there's this idea that that we we worship the one true God and those pagans they worship many gods.
Right. But that as you know if you listen to the beginning of what we were talking about tonight,
You know that that's not the image that the Bible depicts.
It uses the word God's to refer.
to all kinds of beings and doesn't see a problem with using that same word to refer to the father's
son and Holy Spirit, the one true God, you know, the one true God that phrase that we use doesn't mean
that that's the only being that we use the word God to refer to because the Bible doesn't do that,
right? So this idea of polytheism versus monotheism is actually a relatively later kind of notion in
in Western intellectuals.
history. And the reason why the idea of monotheism was kind of come up with is to try to group
sets of religions together. So we're monotheists and Jews are monotheists and Muslims are monotheists.
And over here you have polytheists, you know, these other kinds of religions. But I don't think
anyone in the ancient world would have looked at it that way. I mean, that's not the way that religion
kind of works and the way people understood it. And the question is really not, is there only one
God which is what monotheism means that there's only
God, we see the Bible doesn't teach only one God, the
difference is that there's only one God that you worship.
And the other significant difference is that the God whom we
worship, the Father, Son, and Holy Spirit, is a very different
kind of divine being from all these other divine beings,
right? So we, you know, like we were talking about atheists
earlier who say, well, I just believe in one less God
than you do. And it's like, well, no, the God that I believe
and worship is a-
God who is outside of time and space is the God who created all things, right?
Is, you know, that is a different kind of being if we can even speak in those terms
from what how pagans understood what their gods were.
And, you know, a pagan god is really a much kind of smaller kind of being.
And the reason why is it because of pagan god, we're going to talk about this a lot.
I know a pagan god is a fallen angel, right?
So it is a God in the sense of being a divine spiritual being but
It's not a God worthy of worship.
Now people do worship them and have worship to them.
So that is what I would say is kind of the big difference
between this idea that we have monotheism
and polytheism, really what the picture
that the Bible presents is actually not monotheism,
but rather monolotry, meaning there's only one whom we worship.
You know, we recognize there are many gods.
Now they're not equal.
They're not equal.
They're not.
you know, the father's son in holy spirit is not the same kind of thing that, you know,
Zeus or Hera, right, not at all.
But the main question is how we behave towards them and we're to worship only father's son
in holy spirit.
So father's, Stephen, do you have any way you wanted to correct that or add that or magnify
that or what?
Not really, not really correct it.
I'll fill in blanks.
I don't have to come.
Great.
Actually, yeah.
Yeah, it wasn't the term monofias.
was created at the end of the 16th and beginning of the 17th century.
Which in Orthodox time is like last week.
Yes, it doesn't even count for Orthodox people.
And it's not that it couldn't.
I mean, Monos and Theos are both Greek words.
Yeah.
Right.
And you do find Poli Theos in used as a term by the fathers to refer to pagans.
But not monothos.
When they talk about the fact that we have one God who we worship,
like in the discussions about the Trinity, and saying that they weren't trifiest,
the term they used was monarchia.
There's one archie, one first principle.
This is how they chose to express themselves.
So monotheism gets invented.
And basically this whole taxonomy was invented so that we could have this
this evolutionary
review of religion. And it was created mostly by 19th century liberal German scholars who
not coincidentally at the end of their taxonomy discovered that 19th century German liberal
Protestantism was the pinnacle of all human religion. Right? Like it evolved to them, right?
And so they paused it well, see polyphys was this sort of primitive thing and then you
I could aggro that to monotheism.
And they did this whole haggle thesis antithesis thing where you have, well you have monotheism and polytheism
and then the synthesis of that is the trinity or something.
And as silly as that sounds or as silly as I'm making it sound,
if you or one of your children goes and takes an Old Testament course
just about anywhere at a secular university or even most big Christian universities,
They will be taught that
Israel started out polytheists and evolved into monotheists.
Right.
And they will quote some of the passages we just quoted and say,
obviously these are leftovers from back when they were polytheists.
And try to set up this sort of tax out where it just sort of evolved,
religion just evolved. And that, of course, takes the idea that God
himself to humans out of the picture, which is why...
which is why we would want to have that theory if we're atheists.
And so it's important that we not only say, well look these categories aren't ancient and aren't original,
but that we say that taxonomy doesn't work.
And a couple of things real quick that refute it are, number one, it depends on the people who put together the Hebrew Bible,
being both incredibly sophisticated editors and writers.
of deep theological truths and being complete imbisels because while they were doing all the editing
and while they were changing all this stuff to make it look like they were always monotheists
they just missed all these passages.
Oops, whoops, yeah right exactly.
We have some left all this polytheistic stuff in there, our bad.
So that's a problem and then the other to me that really blows it out of the wall.
is that the plural form of gods, talking about gods in the plural, is actually more common
in the Dead Sea Scrolls than it is in the Old Testament. And the Dead Sea Scrolls are written
right before and during the time of Christ. So they clearly had evolved in their language.
They were still talking about a plural of God's. And what last note on this question, hopefully
that.
but one last note of this question,
because I think this is important,
is what we mean when we say that there's one true God.
What it means to be a true God,
because I think what we hear as modern American Christians,
what you hear true God is,
oh, well, he's the one that exists,
the other ones are fake.
Yeah, right, exactly.
The other ones are made up, right?
But remember what we were saying earlier in our discussion,
the idea of being God is...
the idea of exercising authority and dominion and reign.
And so God is the one true God.
He is the one who truly holds all authority and power
and dominion over the entire creation.
Anyone else who has any authority or power or dominion
has received it from above, has received it from him
or they don't have it.
It's derivative.
It's yeah.
Right.
That's why we reiterate that in the creed.
that Christ is true God, right?
It's not just that he's God that he's divine, right?
But that he is true God.
He exercises the same authority.
All right.
So Michael, does that answer your question?
Yeah, that was excellent.
I feel a bit misled by our education systems.
So I appreciate you both clearing that up.
Yes.
Well, we're probably going to do a whole lot of debunking.
So all right, well, thank you for that, Michael, and we've got another good angelic name next, Rafael,
who has a question about, or comment about guardian angels. So Rafael, are you there on the line?
God, I hope so. All right, welcome, Rafael.
Right on. Thank you, fathers. First of all, congratulations on the episode. I am blown away,
So far. Yes. And we're just sort of stumbling through this.
Who like you?
Yeah.
I'm learning how to do this.
So thank you for bearing with us.
Oh, absolutely.
No, this is fantastic.
I actually have tons of notes already
on questions I could ask, but what I was really curious about
since we're talking about Angel's demons
is how can I deepen my relationship
with my guardian angel?
Oh, yeah.
It's something that struggled with the past, you know,
seven, eight years.
Yeah.
and
So that is a good and a very, that's a great question.
And I think really important because, you know, if you look at the baptismal service,
we ask God in the course of that baptismal service to assign a guardian angel to that person.
So we, you know, and we don't say that because we just want to say it, we believe that that happens.
We don't ask God for things that we don't think are going to happen.
especially in services like baptism.
so that angels are assigned to us, to guard us, to help us.
So how do you interact more with your angel?
Well, number one, a lot of prayer books, for instance,
will have a prayer in there called
the prayer to your guardian angel.
If you don't have it in your prayer book,
then you could probably find an orthodox prayer
to the angel online somewhere.
I'm sure that you can find something.
And that's something that I would incorporate
into your prayer every day.
But you know, one of the things that actually I-
I don't know why I started doing this. Not that long ago I'm kind of ashamed to admit.
Within just the past couple of years, as I'm going to sleep, first of course, we pray to our
Lord Jesus Christ to preserve us and to save us, of course, because we could die in our sleep.
But also, the next thing that I do then is I specifically say, oh guardian of my soul and body,
protect from me from all assaults of the evil one this night. And then I also add,
because I'm a
husband and a father protect my wife and my children and I name them in that prayer as
I'm going to sleep because you know you go to sleep that's kind of a vulnerable position
to be in and you want you want you know the guards up and doing their task in the night
while you're asleep and and that's what you know that is one of the things that we know
that the angels do that's not all that they're about for sure we're going to be talking
a lot more on the show.
about what angels are about and what they do but but but
One of the things that they do of course is to guard us
You know that they they they keep us from harm not just physical harm
But also spiritual harm like there is a war going on
There is a war going on it is a spiritual reality and we're participating in it
We're either participating in the works of God and becoming more like him or we're participating in the works of the devil and becoming more like
Kim. Like I wonder the one of the the biggest aha moments in my conversations with
Father Steven was when he said, you know that there's there's basically a thing
that's the opposite of theoses. You know that there's a I said, what is a demonosis?
He's like, well, I don't know there's a word for it specifically, but but there
is like you participate in what God is doing and you become like him.
But if you participate in what the dark powers are doing, you become like that.
Right. So it's you're always headed in one direction or the other. You don't get
to stand still.
So.
So how do we participate in the reality of our angels?
I mean, prayer is the biggest thing,
but also just have that sense.
I think especially when you're going to sleep
is a good one, but also when you wake up in the morning
to say, help me today, be with me.
We're not talking about some kind of flim flammy.
I hope angels are watching over you.
Like that's okay to say that, right?
But that's kind of not all that they're really about.
These are God's armies, his created-
his government in a very real sense, right?
And part of our task is to become like them.
You know, the Lord said that the sons of the resurrection,
this is in Luke's gospel, sons of the resurrection become like sons of God
and equal to the angels.
So we, we, we take on their roles, we do the things that they do.
So, so yeah, you know, you're, you're guardian angel,
you're patron saint, like the one you're named after,
after the one...
who's assigned to your parish, the siege who's assigned to your parish, is very concerned with
the place that your church is in. Right? So I think if we just beginning, it's just to acknowledge
that. Like, my church is just named after, like here in Emmaus, our church is named for the
Apostle Paul. It's not just named after the Apostle Paul. He's here and this place is important to him
because we asked God to assign him here and so we believe that that happened. Right? So like Mike.
my studio, my studio I assigns to St. Raphael of Brooklyn.
I don't know if you're named after him.
Yeah, very good.
So right, so he's, he's here with me right now
and he's here with you.
You know, he's doing that.
So I think those are the key things is, you know,
add that to your regular prayer and understand
that they are part of your life, you know.
They're not, they're not just there as a kind of like
spiritual technology, like, oh, hey, I need some protection.
So I hope the angel shows up, right?
But, but that there's the...
there, you know, they're assigned to you, to your place, whatever.
So, no, Father Stevens, do you have anything to add to that?
Just a couple quick nuances there.
One that you brought out there at the end that it's not just the Frank Peretti version of Guardian Angels fighting off.
Right, anybody out there re-Frank Peretti? There was a novel series called...
I'll man on piercing the dark.
Yeah, this present darkness and piercing.
that darkness. I read those when I was a kid and it scared me to death. Like there was
an angel and there was a demon under my bed or whatever. You know that kind of thing.
Oh man. This the word I bet you were going to get a lot of Frank Peretti calls over the
over the course of the show. Anyway sorry father. Go ahead. But this role is as angels proper
as messengers that they bring our prayers before God and and and are a part of that communication.
Beyond, as
spiritual warfare factor is important, but that yes, that they're bringing our prayers
to God. And potentially, although this isn't something we initiate, they can bring messages
from God to us. That doesn't mean you summon them up or ask them.
Yes, don't do that.
them or any of that sort of new age angel channeling stuff.
Yeah, so I'm in the rest of what what Father Andrew said.
Yeah, thank you.
Well, thank you very much for that call, Rafael.
Thank you.
It's good to have you on.
And thank you to everybody who called and to all of those
who joined us in the chat room today
to those who emailed us.
And even God bless you, spammers, who showed up
in our Facebook event and posted all those ridiculous links.
I had nothing to do with our show.
Thank you, everyone, for participating.
And thank you for bearing with-
us on this inaugural episode of the Lord of Spirits podcast. And you know, God willing, we're
going to have a lot more episodes after that after this. So that's our show for today. Thank
you for listening. If you didn't get a chance to call in during the live broadcast, we'd
love to hear from you either via email at Lordofspiritsatentfaith.com or you can message us at our
Lord of Spirits podcast Facebook page and join us for our live
broadcast on the second and fourth Thursdays of the month at seven Eastern 4 p.m. Pacific.
And don't forget to like our Lord of Spirits podcast, Facebook page while you're at it.
Leave a recommendation and invite your friends.
And if you leave a review on Apple podcasts, Facebook, or wherever you get your podcasts,
then that raises the visibility of this show and gets more people connected.
And finally, finally, be sure to go to www.extinfaith.com slash support and help make sure
Sure we and lots of other AFR podcasts stay on the air.
Thank you and God bless you.