He will be a staff for the righteous, with which for them to stand and not to fall.
And he will be the light of the nations and the hope of those whose hearts are troubled.
All who dwell on the earth will fall down and worship him, and they will praise and bless,
and celebrate with song the Lord of Spirits, 1st denoc, chapter 48, verses 4-5.
The modern world doesn't acknowledge but is nevertheless haunted by spirits, angels, demons, and saints.
In our time.
many year into break free of the prison of a flat, secular materialism, to see and to know reality
as it truly is. What is this spiritual reality like? How do we engage with it well? How do we permeate
everyday life with spiritual presence? Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew Stephen
Damick and Father Stephen De Young host this live Colin show focused on enchantment in creation,
The union of the scene and unseen as made by God.
and experienced by mankind throughout history.
Welcome to the Lord of Spirits.
Welcome back, everyone, to the Lord of Spirits' podcasts
where we're going to be taking a voyage
into the unseen world.
I'm Father Andrew Stephen Damick in Emeas, Pennsylvania,
and joining me tonight is my co-host, Father Stephen DeYoung
from Lafayette, Louisiana.
And if you're listening to us live,
you can call in at 855-8F-Rideo.
Let's 855-237-2346.
and we're going to get to your calls in the second part of today's show.
So William Shatner, who just turned 90, three days ago,
is having video recordings of himself made so that when he eventually dies in a century or so,
an AI-driven interactive computer program will allow people to have conversations with him.
The question then is raised, would that be the real William Shatner?
But if everyone treated him as William Shatner,
Would William Shatner be a human being?
anymore, where and what would William Shatner even be? And while you ponder that question,
we're going to start talking about what it means to be. You probably heard that therapeutic
saying, you're not a human doing, you're a human being. Well, actually you are a human
doing. But that's because it's the same thing as being a human being. Are you a human doing
or a human being? Yes, you are. But isn't this episode supposed to be about sacred
geography. Well, Father Steven.
Explain all that for the people in the back.
Or we could just keep talking about William Shatter.
There we go.
Perfectly happy to do that too.
It's right. His birthday is March 22nd, major holiday.
Yes. At least his date of Canadian.
I know that it is.
And in William Shatter, by the way, he is a Jew, but he is a Lithuanian Jew.
Yes.
I just wanted to put that out there.
It's very true.
So, but the Greek William Shatter aside.
Yes, we're going to
be talking about a bunch of mind bending things. I would go by Dr. Mindbender, but I don't have
the mustache for it. I don't even own a monocle. So, um, wait, so just, that's just a, hey,
buckle up guys, uh, warning. Yeah. Yeah. I'll tell everybody it's going to start out harder
and then and I hope anyways get easier as we go
and and I
I think I'm not sure. We'll have to ask our audience whether we think by the end of this
that this is going to be more or less mind bending than our episodes on bodies. So stay tuned.
Yeah, so but you already started it with the to do is to be to be is to do yes or as the
great Frank Sinatra saying do be do be do be do and also I did it my way. Yes. So all that aside,
80% of kidding aside.
But we're sort of starting out with, as you said, what it means to be.
And this may seem like a weird question, because, you know, aside from certain former presidents
who asked what the definition of is, is that's not a definition we think about a lot at a
day-to-day basis, right?
Something either exists or it doesn't.
Yeah, it's, this is a thing, or it's not a thing.
and time.
We at least think we're pretty clear on that, but
That's because we've been inculturated in an uncertain idea of what it means to be
Right
What it means to exist
And this this is really critical to look at because
You know one of our core missions on this show is combating materialism and this kind of cuts
rights, right to the heart of at least one of the issues pertaining to...
materialism. Right, right. And before we could get to talking about how a place is a place, we have to define what that is means.
Right. What does it mean for something to be something. And so our idea of being, being is sort of opposed to nothingness.
Yeah, but even as we say that
The English language has this tendency to reify things. Latin does the same thing.
So, nothingness or just nothing is a noun.
Yeah.
It's a thing.
There's a thing.
So we think of it like it's a thing. Right? Like there is nothing. We think of it as
if there's something and that something is nothing, right? Which is self-contradictory.
Right.
Right. Exactly. And I think, like when we think of this doctrine of creation, exneelo,
out of nothing, like the idea that we have behind that is, well, at first there was something called nothing,
but then there was something called something. Yeah, but there were things. But instead of that nothing,
there were things. Nothing is not a thing. Like literally, it's not a thing. It's just a non-thing.
It's not even it. You can't even give it a pronoun. Right. And so we think of what it means to exist
for us because again we're coming from this materialist viewpoint is something
exists if it has material reality in particular.
Yeah, there's so-
There's so-
Edums you can spot molecules.
Right.
Horses exist because there are horses made of matter that I can go and see.
Right?
There's one just down the block for me because I'm in Louisiana.
But unicorns do not exist because there are not material unicorns that I can go and see
in touch.
right in the world. And so a horse is a unicorn isn't right is how we look at it. And so then as
you mentioned with creation xd hello, if God made a unicorn, that would mean that he took this thing
from nonexistent and then made a material one.
Yeah.
That would be sort of how we read that.
Yeah, and then and then there's this fun
Messed up place that people go is they're like well it existed in the mind of God
And you know like like woo woo
Whatever you know what's yeah, right? How do you know? It's in the mind of God?
I mean you know setting aside all that wonderful theology from St. Maxime's to confess her about the logi or whatever whatever
Right that's not what people generally mean when they when they talk about it right
Yeah right so I mean the loading
or anything, anyway, we don't want to go down that rabbit trail. But yeah, that's not what
safe acts of us was talking about. Right, right. God has a brain, like God has a giant brain
and there are all these ideas floating around in it. Here's an idea that occurred to him at some point.
Yeah. He made up. Right. So, so the key then is to get to, because we're Christians, the biblical
doctrine of if it can be said a biblical doctrine of non-existence.
or what, or really, yeah, right?
I mean, here we go.
Like, we can't even not talk about it, right?
Yeah.
You know, so I guess the big question
that is what happens at the creation?
Right.
So in the ancient world, generally,
and in the Old Testament in particular,
and this is true of the New Testament also,
but being is not opposed to nothingness or non-being,
right?
Which again, our English language wants to turn into a thing.
Existing is an-
opposed to being imaginary, right, or an idea for any ancient thinker. So being is
opposed to chaos. And this takes various forms. So in Genesis 1, and we've talked about Genesis
1 a little bit on previous episodes that we're going to refer back to that a little bit here,
not going through it all again. But you start out with primordial chaos. That's what the waters
represent that are sort of there at the beginning of Genesis 1.
that the Holy Spirit is hovering over, sort of brooding over the way a hand brood over her chicks,
or over eggs. You have this primordial chaos at the beginning, right? And then creation is then
setting things in order, right? So to be means to be ordered as opposed to chaos. Now,
Now when we've talked about this before
We've gotten the emails.
Well, who created the chaos?
Yeah.
Right?
Who created the chaos?
Where did the chaos come from?
Right?
Because when we're talking about these waters,
we're not talking about H2O.
H2O is an ordered thing.
That's an ordered molecule.
Right?
This is water as it symbolizes and represents chaos,
just utter chaos.
Yeah.
But the question who created chaos for an ancient person
would be the same as the question,
Well who created
created the nothing that was there before God created.
Yeah, and or like it's inherently contradictory
in the ancient conception.
It's like saying who ordered the chaos?
Well, once you ordered it's not chaos anymore.
Right.
If you created it, that it wouldn't be chaos,
it would be put in order,
because the act of creation would be put in order.
Yeah, and I think it's important to distinguish this.
I mean, I don't know how many people we've got
in our audience who know a lot about Mormon theology,
That's it.
I'm just gonna put this out here because it's actually a really important element of Mormon theology.
Joseph Smith taught that all matter is uncreated, right?
And so everything is just rearrangements of pre-existing matter.
And that's why he can say, for instance, that human beings are, you know, what human beings
are now, you know, God was just like, although he didn't put it in those terms, but that God
was what we are and we can become exactly what God is.
Because it's just pre-existing matter that gets your three arranged and some of it gets
elevated to be a god.
What we're talking about is different from that because that theology is predicated upon
materialism.
It's predicated upon the idea that there's just a bunch of building blocks out there
in a big pile and then God started putting blocks together and making stuff out of those
blocks.
Right important, but, but but a lot of creation x nilo is
not the idea of void as the pre-existing addition. The important part of creation
X and Elo, what the fathers are aiming at with creation X and Elo is to say that there is no
thing which is co-eternal with God. Exactly. Matter or anything else. Matter energy, time space.
The created and the uncreated. There's a radical disjunction between them forever and always,
You know like yeah always always right
But again, when we say nothing is co-aturnal with God,
we don't mean that there is a thing called nothing that is co-aturnal with God.
Right. I'm having flashbacks. Every time you say the...
Every time you say you use the phrase of the nothing,
I start thinking about the never-ending story.
Which, I mean, I watched that again recently. I'm like...
Reliving the childhood trauma of the horse going into the...
It didn't... I mean, forgive me if there's fans out there. I felt like it didn't hold up.
Oh, sorry, I look
when I was a kid, the old man. Well, there's also the void for
century fans, but that's a deep cut. So we probably, it's not one I know.
But okay. So what it means to be created, and therefore what it means to
exist, because everything that exists has been created by God. Right? Right.
We wouldn't say as orthodox Christians at least, we wouldn't say that God
exists. If by exists, you mean the same thing as
the chair I'm sitting in exists.
Yes. And even just linguistically it doesn't work because the word, I mean not the
etymology is everything but this gives us a clue. The word exists literally means to
have your being out of something. X, you stay right? So, you know, God doesn't have his
being out of something. He is being.
Right. So everything we talk about existing, we're talking about created things. Right.
And so we can't even predicate that verb of
God in the exact same sense as we do of the things he created.
But so what it means to exist then is that God has created it.
And that means he has set it in order and he has placed it within a web of relationships.
Right.
So to exist means to be not only set in order internally, right, as a thing, but to also
be connected by this web of relationship to other things.
to the rest of the things in the world.
And so, we have an example, or at least I have a favorite example to use,
which is that of a tower. So if you have a tower, someone builds a tower,
this tower serves as a tower. The matter that makes up the tower is being a tower.
right centuries past the tower crumbles
the tower no longer exists. There is no longer a tower. There is a pile of rubble.
And that pile of rubble contains most of the matter that was part of the tower.
But it's no longer a tower. Now it's being a pile of rubble.
So being is a verb.
Yes, right, which is which is why I thought that whole human being human doing thing it's a being it
The matter is the same as now being a pile of rubble and someone can come and take
stones and wood from that pile of rubble and go and turn it into something else.
Place it in a new order and set it up in a new set of relationships and it can become
a table or a wall or right or something else right and then that matter, say matter, will be being that
right? Who will be being able for a while? Right?
That's what it will be doing. It will be being a whatever it is, right?
Yeah, and I just have to throw a bone out there for those who think that this podcast has
something to do with JR Tolkien. You know who you are up there in Minnesota.
Yeah, so actually it's interesting like you mentioned the image of the tower and the pile of stones.
Tolkien actually uses exactly that image in his essay called Beowulf the Monsters and the Critics.
in which he's complaining about the way critics look at Beowulf, this epic poem in Old English,
and they just want to look at sort of the parts and the influences and all that sort of thing.
And for them, that's what Beowulf is. And he's like, no, no, no, no. Beowulf is this poem.
As it is, you know, that the bones that you put into the soup are maybe interesting,
but the point is the soup, right? And he talks specifically about a tower and how people came
and knocked down the tower because they wanted to-
analyze which stones came from an old house nearby and which, you know, which those
quarried from here or there. But he said, but he could see the the ocean from the tower.
You know, that and so he's making the point he's talking about storytelling and literature,
but he's making the point in another way that the way that this story functions by being
Baywolf, that's what it is. Certainly we can look at all the influences that went into
and so forth and that can, you know, maybe...
deep in our understanding. But if that's all we think it is, then we're missing, we're
missing the thing that it actually is. Like, like, I remember, for instance, there's a great
episode of Star Trek next generation where Picard and gang run into some aliens and they
refer, and they, they, they have to run them through some kind of translation matrix,
and the aliens refer to them as ugly bags of mostly water, which is exactly a way of expressing
this thing. It's like, well, human beings are not bags of water, ugly or not, we're human
beings, right?
And so it's, it's a, you know, the aliens were essentially analyzing humans according to their constituent pieces.
Like that's what they are is mostly water. Well, that's true. I do comprise mostly water, but that's not what, that's not what I am.
You know, so I think, you know, it's a problem that we run into, right? We do think about it.
And we run into it in literature and some of this other stuff. But it's, it's, I think that the difficulty is that,
The difficulty is that...
Like, you can hear it expressed, for instance, and we're going to get into this, but just
to kind of tip the hand a little bit, people will say things like, well, the church of
the Holy Sepulchre there in Jerusalem, is that really the place where Jesus rose from
the dead?
Is that really the spot?
And that is a materialist reading of this issue.
you're looking for I guess a piece of dirt or whatever.
You know, I mean, you could even, you could even, if you really want to analyze it out and be really super materialist about it, you could just say, well, the truth is that the planet Earth is not even the same position it was when I began the sentence.
So no place is the same place, you know, it's just it's just not even or or the fact that, you know, molecules trade out in everything.
is it the same thing? It actually is the same thing.
though the material is not exactly the same material. So yeah, like you said,
I've this web of relationships, you know, and it's fascinating to think about what that means
in terms of creation. What creation is, it's really, you know, it's really vibrant,
understood that way, really powerful. It's not the sort of static set of stuff,
you know, we're not, we're not animists, but you can kind of see where animism gets its sense,
There's this sort of life in everything as a result.
It's not easy to think about, but I think it's important that we at least spend some time
trying to tease some of this stuff out anyway.
I like that you phrased it as Picard in the gang, sort of TNG by way of Scooby-Doo.
I mean, so kind of wacky antics. Wesley is definitely a hitscubi.
do of the thing. So he's more scrappy, I think. He thinks he's scrappy, yes. So we've talked
before about sort of the four main means we have of interacting with reality as humans.
being language, art, music, and ritual.
And we've kind of...
find what those are before, but I want to hone in now based on what we're talking about
on what that interact really means. What these four things are is they're four creative
actions, right? They're ways by which we as humans place reality in order, place it in
order and then and then put together these
connections, this web of relationships between things and other things. Put them in order,
put them in their place and establish their relationships with one another. We do that
through language. We talked before about the naming of the animals and that being this
putting in order and the hit-type iconography of kings naming animals to show this kind
of ruler, dominion and justice and establishing order.
We do this.
this with art, we use to express the relationships between things and the web in which they sit,
the same with music, and the same with ritual.
Ritual is making a time and a place that we're going to go deeper into this as we go tonight,
but it's making a time and a place be a particular time and place.
Yeah
when we celebrate rituals.
You know, and this is also probably the good moment
where we can give a shout out to all of our friends
who have joined us via Jonathan Pajot,
who talks about symbolism being inevitable, right?
And that's just another way of talking about what we're saying
here is that recognizing patterns in the world
is not just this sort of human act that's sort of arbitrary,
but it is inevitable.
and it is what makes things what they are,
which might sound a little,
that might be a little controversial to say,
but how can we conceive of a thing without conceiving of it?
Right?
Or just the fact that even,
like even, I don't know if it's,
it's, you know, physicists now even say that,
that material particles behave differently
when they're observed versus when they're not observed.
So even on the purely materialist...
observable level like that.
There's something going on there that has to do with human consciousness
and the way that human beings organize their understanding of what's going on.
We're not just observers in a detached,
and the detached observation is not even a possibility.
You know?
Right.
Yeah.
And I, of course, I'm going to double down even further.
call the
world is the product of human consciousness. It doesn't exist outside of human
consciousness. Which is not solipsism, but why? Why is it not solipsism? Well, first
of all, how we've just defined existence, right? Right. As being in order and
being within this web of relationships, right? That that requires human
consciousness. But let's give some examples.
So when I say the word bat, there's something it's like to be a bat, but you can't even know what it's like to be a bat.
So we have no access to what it's like to be a bat or what a bat or bat-ness means from a bat perspective.
I say bat and you think of a scary thing or a cute little baby thing you saw in a video from the dodo or you think of
you know, getting vengeance for your parents' death against crime on the streets.
On Guam, they would eat them.
They would eat them.
You think food, right?
Yeah, exactly.
You say, good.
Not recommended, actually, you can get some diseases.
Right.
But none of those things we just listed exist without human consciousness.
It's not scary unless it's scary to a human.
It's not cute unless it's cute to a human. It's not food unless it's food for a human.
human. Right? And if Bobcane and Bill Finger had never written a set of stories, or you weren't
aware of them, you would have no idea what I was talking about about fighting crime. Right?
In Gotham City. Right? So when Bobcane and Bill Finger wrote those stories and put those
stories together, they created something. Yeah, that is now part of what a bat is.
for me and for everyone else who's heard those stories.
Right.
And you can't unhear those stories.
Yeah.
One could also say obviously Santa Claus exists.
If one were so inclined.
Indeed.
And unicorns.
Right.
So to give a counter example.
Before about 2,500 years ago,
the color blue did not exist.
Yes.
Right.
This is something that people will say, well wait, the things that are blue now were blue
then, right?
Like, like Lapis Luzulet was blue.
Well yeah, they were, but no one perceived the color blue.
Yeah.
When you read ancient accounts, Homer talks about the wine dark sea.
He looked at the Mediterranean and thought it was burgundy.
Yeah.
That's what he saw.
And the sky, right?
Is white.
Yeah, it's done. It's
at dawn and sunset it's red and during the day it's white and there are still
you can go on YouTube and look this up there are still tribes in Africa who
don't have the color blue they still say the sky is white and researchers
anthropologists will show them like color swatches and there will be like three
three red and one blue square and they won't be able to tell them the
different.
They honestly will not see any difference.
But then if you keep watching the videos,
they can be taught to see the color blue.
And then once they've been taught to see the color blue,
the color blue is immediately obvious to them.
They can identify the blue square instantly
and they can't unsee the color blue.
Now blue things look blue to them.
Yeah, I recently had a conversation with somebody
in which, so I have, if you ever meet me in real life,
what you have. And maybe...
some of your listeners have.
I have an annoying habit, which I constantly have to restrain myself from engaging in,
which is, let's put it this way, enhancing other people's pronunciation of English.
And the person I was having conversation with said a word, and I was like, no, no,
the word is pronounced this way.
And then I suddenly realized what I had done.
And it was simply, it was a matter of stress.
So I don't even remember what the word was.
So.
I can't even think what the word was.
So the person said it would say,
stressing the first syllable and then
unstressing the second, whereas it should
have been the other way around.
So for instance, the word, I don't know why this popped in my head,
but dismay, they would have said dismay.
I was dismayed.
And I said, no, it's dismay.
And this other person said, that's the same.
I was like, you don't hear a difference between
dismay and dismay." And they said, you just said the same word exactly the same way two times.
And I was just baffled at that for whatever reason. They just didn't perceive that. They just
did not perceive the stress in that word. And you know, as you said, you can be taught to
perceive things like that. And I think it's one of the reasons why it can be difficult, especially
as an adult, to learn another language. Because you just don't perceive what sounds important and
different
to speakers of that language.
Or there sometimes our perception is submerged.
So for instance, a classic example in English is the word
key and cool.
Well, if you feel what your tongue does at the beginning of each of those words,
you can tell it's in a different place.
But English speakers perceive those as starting with the same sound,
whereas there are other languages which those are distinctly different consonants.
Right?
So as another example, you know, not visual, but in this case
oral, right? Yeah, Father. It's great, Lent.
And it's time for us all to take an honest inventory of ourselves.
I feel like you need to not make excuses and just embrace the fact that you've been a grammar Nazi
for a good portion of your life.
Well, it's not all about grammar, you know, there's uh, oh yeah, I'm sure there's
Depths to plumb there, but I'm not your spiritual father so you could address that with him. Yeah, yeah, so
And so this
One place where this becomes really important, right? I already brought up the bat
So we also don't know what it's like to be an angelic being and
And how then angels perceive the creation is entirely different
than how we do.
But this is important and I know we have some of our listeners aren't listening live right
now because they're at their annunciation services tonight.
We had them this morning, you and I.
But this is all over the place in the liturgics of the annunciation.
What we find with spiritual events and spiritual realities in the scriptures is that they are
revealed.
The language is of revelation.
not of them becoming real or happening.
Yeah. Right. So that's really important.
One of the big examples, of course, is how the scriptures can talk about the
Lamb's slain before the foundation of the world.
And yet we still have time-space coordinates where Jesus Christ died on the cross
us outside Jerusalem, right? At an actual time.
Yeah, right. Well, how does that work? Right. Yeah. Right. Right. I mean, like one of the liturgical texts and this is actually just being asked about in our Facebook group.
You know, from an initiation from Vespers last night said something about the Archangel Gabriel revealing the pre-eternal counsel of God to the Virgin Mary. Right. And the question was like, well, how can something be before eternity?
You know right
Right, right. And this is the feast in Greek is actually the evangelism of the Theotokos.
Yeah, she's been just faithful.
How can she hear about a victory of God that from her perspective hasn't happened yet?
Yeah.
Right? Because we look at it as the past no longer exists and the future does not yet exist.
Right? Because we're thinking of existence in terms of this quote unquote coming into being.
Right, it's not.
materially real yet, and so that means it doesn't, it doesn't exist yet.
But the language over and over again in the scriptures is that these events, these things,
these truths are revealed.
They enter into the realm of human consciousness at a particular time and in a particular place.
Yeah, they sort of intrude right they intrude into the
the world of human experience, the world of human consciousness that we've been talking about.
Right. Which then, you know, makes you question, for instance, we, as a sort of shorthand, we talk about
the pre-incarnate Christ, you know, like, for instance, visions of the sun and word of God in the old testament.
But what does it mean to be pre-incarnate in these terms, right?
Right.
You know, right.
that God is going to be out on a parallel track.
Yeah, right.
And then like it jumps the track down to our track
and then jumps back to his track.
Right.
Right, which is why then we can say
that he's incarnate without change.
That's not a slight of hand.
We're not saying, well, there was really a change,
but there's also part of him that didn't check.
Like that's not right.
We'll talk about Christ entering into the
the realm of human experience and consciousness at a particular period of time.
And we're going to go into some things related to this a little later on in the second half.
But to tease that a little here, even though there's one sort of archetype,
one archetypal point at which these events and these truths come into the world of human consciousness,
they can also do so again both before and after.
So you might almost put it in this way that,
for instance, that the incarnation of the Son of God
affects both what happens from our point of view after
and before, which is among other,
you know, to put it in sociological terms,
is why Old Testament saints can be saved.
Right, friends, Ed's
Yeah, like I said, we'll get into that more in just a little bit.
We got a little bit of groundwork to lay.
Yeah, before we get there.
Yeah, okay.
Well, let's back it out a little bit then and throw in a little bit of Greek philosophy
since we like to do that once in a while.
Why not?
Yeah, why not?
And just for all those people like, oh no, they're, you're, you're, you're, you're
like, no, no, no, no, no.
This is just to help us understand the terms.
have you know many of our Orthodox brethren promote the spirit of Hellenism. So we're just doing our
little bit here. Right. I mean today is the Greeks March 25th 2021 so there you are. 200 years
ago something happened. So that is now we're we talked about what it means to be what it means to
exist. To be in order to be within this series of relationships and then that is something that is
Done within the realm of human consciousness.
as it is relevant to humans, right?
And so now we're moving to the slightly too,
what does it mean for something to be what it is?
Right.
Because it doesn't just exist, it exists as something.
Right. It is something.
Right.
Which is a basic sort of obsession with ancient philosophy.
Right. This is the big question of classical Greek philosophy.
philosophy.
is what makes a thing what it is.
Right.
And this is you go back to the presacratics, right?
Heraclitus famously, you'd ever
step at the same river twice, right?
So we say that's the same river.
But if we're talking from a material perspective,
the water keeps moving.
Right.
So the Mississippi River I can drive over
and see right now, isn't the same material river
that was there if I went and looked yesterday,
or that we'll be there if I go and look tomorrow.
Right. So Heraclitus's perspective is that everything is flux, so everything is really still chaos.
Yeah.
We just are sort of conventionally in order to operate and function, sort of putting,
you know, making assumptions and putting categories.
David Hume takes this to kind of a ridiculous extreme when he says, you know, you walk out of a room
and walk back in and you just assume that the furniture is all the same furniture.
You can't actually prove that.
I'm trying to write through now the money Python philosophers song in my head to sort out all these various philosophers.
But it's not coming. Yeah, David Hume could out consume and drink you under the table.
Yes. But right. Okay. So yeah, everything is fundamental chaos. I recall, you know, one of the pre-secretics Thales said that everything is water,
but now knowing what we know about water, that doesn't mean everything is liquid. Right. No, it means everything is in change in a state of change. Yeah.
Parmenides then it's sort of the up
positive that who's sort of it is what it is right like just things are right right so this is
you know if we want to go to a more modern person like Heidegger talking about the brute
facticity of reality right you're suddenly aware that you exist and there's this other stuff
and there's nothing you can do about it right it just is what it is right yes yes and if you you know
if you if you if you can't handle that then you go in the zonpal star direction
The fact that there's other things
I think that, you know.
Yeah, especially other people.
Yeah.
Yes.
So one of the sort of thought experiments
that's used by many Greek philosophers
to address this, to think about this,
is that was mentioned on WandaVision,
if people have watched it.
Don't worry, we're not spoiling.
We're not spoiling anything in WandaVision
if you haven't seen it yet.
But it is reference there.
And so.
I said, hey, let's come at it from this perspective because people have heard of this now.
Right.
It's now a thing.
They've heard the stories, so now they can't unhear it.
They can't unhear it.
So it's the ship of Thesias.
Right.
And Thesias, of course, great Greek hero.
They have his ship on which he took his famous voyages on display.
Well, as anything made out of wood does...
it starts to rot. And as the planks of wood start to rot, they replace them with new planks.
Eventually you reach a point where none of the original wood is there.
Is it still the ship of theses? Yeah, because he never stood on any of those actual planks.
Right. Materially it is a different object. Yeah. Right. So does it still have that identity
as the ship of Thesis.
And this works even on the very human bodily level too, right?
Where every single atom in your body gets traded out.
I don't remember how often it is.
It's every few years.
Yeah, literally you are not the like I am literally not what I was when I was a kid.
Right.
None of the matter that was Chris made it is still in you.
Yeah, because that was, you know, 23 plus years ago now.
Right, so I identity in that sense
can't be a material thing.
It can be based on a material definition.
Now nobody noticed it, which kind of saddened me.
But when we titled the episode, I said,
boat of theseus.
Yes.
And what I was doing, see, I changed one element
of the name.
Is it still the same?
It's a little too subtle, maybe.
God experiment.
See what I did there.
It's like an inception.
No one's done what I did there.
Okay.
But so then how do we say, do we just say no it isn't the ship of theses anymore, the ship of theses is gone.
The ship of theses has ceased to exist and now you have a replica, right? That's one possible. That's the materialist answer.
Right. Right. This is a replica of the real ship of theses has rotted away and disappeared.
That is going to cause a lot of problems when we come to the human body's matter all being replaced. Right.
years right because then that means you're not you you're a replica.
Right.
That's all right.
Yeah.
And here's the thing, like, this is not only a problem in terms of questions of consciousness
and so forth.
But like, for instance, think about the legal ramifications, right?
Like let's say someone assaults me in an alley and the police only figure out the identity
of the person who does it 10 years later.
It
Is it right to try that person for assaulting a material being that no longer exists?
Right, right so so even our whole everything we do is is is predicated upon
Different notions of identity than the one that tends to function in our head, you know, it's predicated upon non-materialist notions
You know like there's something called Pennsylvania. Yeah, I mean, what is that? Yeah, right?
Right, right.
So the answer to this, right,
from the biblical perspective,
and from the perspective of Orthodox theology,
and influenced by in a lot of ways Aristotle,
and I won't go down a rabbit trail about Aristotle
in St. Maximus or St. John of Damascus,
but is that, yes, that is still the ship of theses.
Right. Even when all the matter has been replaced, even if it's all been replaced two or three times, that's still the ship of theses.
Why? Well, because to exist and to exist as a thing means to be placed in order and placed in that web of relationships.
So the ship of theses, that matter, it's a different set of matter, but that matter is at that time being the ship of theses.
The people who come and see it see
it as the ship of theses. They experience it as the ship of theses. It's playing the role culturally,
societally, the role in human conscious experience of the ship of theses. So it is the ship of theses.
And this is primarily a question then of what's called teleology, of purpose, of functions.
Right. Right. So it makes it what it is is this idea of purpose and function and aim and
right as a particular sense of that web of relationships.
Yeah, and what human beings do with or how they understand a thing
is what makes that thing, or I should say,
is a significant element of that, right?
For so, for instance, you know, the coffee mug that is currently in my hand.
I did in fact drink coffee out of it.
You could say it's a cup, you could say it's ceramic,
ceramic, you can see it's a paint.
piece of ceramic, but what makes a coffee mug is that's what I use it for. And, you know,
I could smash in a million pieces and make a piece of art out of it. And it's not a coffee mug
anymore. It's art, probably terrible art, because I'm not an artist. But coffee mugness is not a
thing, like an independent existing thing. It's just, as you said, it's teleological.
Right. It's the purpose and the use and the way it is situated in that web of relationships.
If I take my old iPhone and drop it on an isolated island,
and people who have never heard of an iPhone find it,
it will not be an iPhone.
It might end up being a mirror.
It might end up being a curiosity.
It might end up being so much garbage.
But it won't be an iPhone.
Because it will not be functioning as an iPhone.
in any real sense.
Yeah, so to kind of summarize some of this,
being nature, these are dynamic.
Nature is in the nature of a thing,
not nature like nature outdoors.
Like nature of a thing.
Yes, nature capital.
Yeah, like these are verbs,
being the being, no.
You are a human doing this.
Yeah.
Right.
That.
Yeah.
And so we've already we touched on this a little when we were talking about bodies that
we were talking about Christ, divine and human natures.
Yes.
Right.
That these are powers that have had these are dynamic ideas.
Not if you if you reify them, if you turn them into things, right.
His divine nature is one thing and his human nature is this other thing and they're related
in some way.
Congratulations.
you're an historian. Yes, right. Right. And then also, and then also, you know, another thing
we've talked about is what it means to be in the image of God. And it's better, maybe, to say that
we are imagers of God because talking about the image of God, people tend to think like, okay,
what parts of what human parts, what human aspects are like something that God has. But the point
is is to do the works of God. Yes, we're to we are created to function as the image of God. Yeah. Yeah.
So to image.
We are the image of God and we are made to be imaging God at the same time.
And you know right before we go to break this actually has just to try to bring it down.
Okay, so we've talked about kind of very rarefied metaphysical terms here, okay?
But just to bring it down to maybe a
satirological level
even though this show isn't about apologetics, we occasionally do make some comparisons with other kinds of theology.
So here's the question. What does it mean to be a saint?
right?
What
doesn't mean to be again be a saint. So and I'm going to super simplify here. So I'm
sorry. And for those of you who haven't read, I actually have a 400 plus page book where
I do a lot less simplifying about these kinds of things. But anyway, it's a super simplified
log plug plug. Yeah, I think yes. I didn't name the book. But available at store.
www.dintro.nch.com.
So, what does it mean to be a state?
Well, you know...
most kinds of Protestantism, if you are a Christian truly, you are a saint, period, end of story.
You don't need to do anything to become more of one or whatever, like that's just what you are. You're that thing.
Whereas the way that Roman Catholicism tends to function, so this is the debate between, one of the debates between them,
It tends to be that you aren't to see it until you reach to a certain point, which is why
then there's this whole theology of satisfaction and merit and all that stuff, right?
Whereas orthodox theology, having this understanding of being that it is a verbal thing, right?
And by that, I don't mean just words.
I mean, it's action.
It is teleological.
You are a saint and you need to become a saint in maturity, perfection needed to become
what you are.
This is what Steve Paul says as well.
Now, I know full well that many Protestants, many Catholics would agree with what I just said about Orthodox Christianity.
And if so, great.
But nonetheless, there is this sense of both a reality and an urgency at the same time,
an actualization of those, that's right, probably not the right word.
And a still becoming at the same time, that is really core.
orthodox, satiriology, you know what it means to be saved.
So before we go to break, is there anything you wanted to add to that?
Or, yeah, let me just a little to minorly flesh that out.
I won't take too long.
Right, so this is if you've heard this talked about outside of it,
maybe even within some orthodox circles, especially when it comes to
the Bible and biblical studies, they'll talk about what's called the
eschatological tension between the already and the not yet.
Yeah, right. Eschatology being the
study of the last things. So there's this idea that because you know we're all
reading the Bible and we're smart people right so people can see that yes
Saint Paul will sometimes refer to people as saints and then other times
refer to those same people as those called to be saints right so that's what
this tension is like in some sense they already are in some sense they're not
yet but they're called to be that and that tension then gets resolved in certain
issues on certain ways.
So I think-
what Father Andrew was referred to here is, particularly if you take the example of
Saint Justification, right? In the traditional classical like Protestant
Reformation understanding, right? You're declared righteous, right? You're declared
safe. You're declared a saint. And so you are a saint. Whether or not you actually
become a saint in your life, right? Whether there's any visible change in your way of life,
even if you remain a sinner, Luther referred to this as being similarly,
you said Picotto, at the same time you're just and a sinner.
So he resolved that tension to the one side, to the already.
Yeah. Classical Tridentine Roman Catholic theology,
then resolved it in the other direction, in the direction of the not yet.
That you are in the process of becoming that, but you only
are a saint once that process is completed.
Right so you're your cold
to be resolving it in that direction.
Whereas I think the Orthodox solution to that
and what I think Saint Paul is really getting at
is that your identity is your tellos,
your end, your purpose, your goal.
And so you are a saint because you're called to be a saint.
The fact that that is your end in goal is why you are that,
already, because that's how identity is formed.
and then...
So both of those can coexist at the same time.
This is why St. Paul is always talking about growing to maturity, all this language of
tell us, maturity, perfection, completion as this goal.
It's not you become something different.
It's what you are comes to its fullness and completion.
Exactly.
So before we go to break, which we're going to do in just a second, I just want to add this
little kind of caveat off to the side, which is I know that a lot of these concepts are difficult,
they're difficult for me. Like I've conceptualized a lot of them now, but that doesn't mean that I
have the habits of thought that are not materialists, right? And we just still have those habits of
thought. And you can't just flip a switch and decide, I'm not going to think this way anymore.
It doesn't work that way, but nonetheless these habits of thought, they can introduce a lot of
of distortions that are understanding of what Christianity is.
And even though we can't necessarily just sort of radically change them,
we can at least kind of enter into criticism of them and correct ourselves and return back as much as we're able.
So that's a lot of what we were just now doing.
And frankly, it's what a lot of this show is about.
So, all right, well, let's go ahead and go to a break and we'll be right back after this.
Father Andrew Stephen Daymek and Father Stephen DeYoung will be back in a moment to take your calls on the next part of the Lord of Spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF Radio.
Are you struggling in your walk with Christ?
Do you want to rediscover your reason for living?
The person you were created to be.
Renewing you, a priest, a psychologist, and a plan
gives you the keys to unlock areas of your life
that hold you back from fully experiencing
experiencing the renewal and transfer made.
God has in mind for you.
Co-author by a priest and a psychologist,
Father Nicholas and Dr. Roxanne Lowe,
renewing you combines principles of spiritual growth
with psychological tools to help you become your best self,
fully connected with God's purpose for you.
To purchase this book, please go to store.AncientFaith.com
That's store.AncientFaith.com
We're back now with the Lord.
spirits. The father Andrew Stephen Damick and father Stephen DeYoung. If you have a question, call now
at 855-237-2346. That's 855-AF radio. Thank you so much, Voice of Steve. Always happy to have you with us.
All right, this is the second part of the show. We do want to hear from you 855-AF radio. All right, so
So we took a trip into my
metaphysics and definitely bent my brain a little bit.
The metaphysics of identity yet.
Yeah, right.
Exactly.
Right.
Okay, so let's start easing into place.
Man, there's so many good puns possible with this.
Yeah, okay.
Good pun is an oxymoron for the wreck.
It's what some of the notes of our hemnography is based on.
It's punning.
Just putting that in the instruments.
Yes.
Not every wordplay is a pun.
But anyway, we're drag-gracing radically at this point.
All right.
Well, let's talk about plays.
Because we've talked about what it means to be,
what is being humans or human doings.
But does that have to, I mean, is it just humans?
Or I mean, obviously we're seeing that everything
has its own sort of teleology, right?
So OK.
So how does this work in terms of?
place. Yes. So yeah, the first half of the show was not just me getting excited because
they mentioned something about philosophy on one division going off on a digression, I promise.
It was like the graph for this. Now we're going to talk about place and sort of the place where
where this rubber meets the road is the idea of God being in a place. I don't know if this
This has ever jumped out at anyone, but this is something that's going on.
all through the Old Testament, for example, where we say, well, yeah, God's everywhere, right?
I mean, there's not a place where he isn't. But then he's like really in the tabernacle.
Yeah. Or he's really in the temple. Like he's there a lot or something.
Yes. I mean, you know, or like wasn't it wasn't it was a Jacob who built an altar and called it
Bethel because those were at last night. In this place, right? Yeah.
Bait L, the house or temple of
God. After he saw, oh, here we go again, ruining your Sunday school. It's not a ladder. It's a
ziggurat. Yes. With a ziggurat. But anyway, that's another digression. So, right, so there are
these places, right, where God like extra is or something, right? And so this is what we're going
to talk about now. What does it mean that God is somewhere in particular in addition to being
everywhere.
in general. Right? That's yeah. And you can't really separate space and time in this regard.
And here's what I mean. Any time that the Old Testament, for example, we talk about this in the
New Testament too, but we'll use the Old Testament, says that God is in a particular place in this
special way. He's in that particular place at a special
way for a particular period of time. Yeah. Right. So like it wasn't that he just
happened to live on Mount Zion and David found him there when he captured Jerusalem. Right.
Oh look honey. God came to dwell there. Right. He came to dwell there on Mount Zion. Right.
and then Ezekiel sees him at the time of the exile, leave.
So his presence was no longer there.
So it wasn't just sort of a set of spatial coordinates,
but it was also, there's like spatial temporal coordinates
for all the fans of Wibblywobbly, Time U Imi stuff.
Right.
And just to give an example, a much smaller example of this,
I've lived in 23 different homes,
And so my family has long had the weird little habit of
whenever we happen to be visiting one of the towns we used to live in, we might go and
drive by the old homestead.
And but it's interesting, you know, and with only one exception, I've never like gone
up to the door and knocked on the door and said, hi, I used to live here.
Would you let me inside?
Although there, so the one exception is I actually drove up and I was sitting out on the curb
In front of the house just sort of looking at this house that I lived in.
when I was a kid.
And then the owners came out,
who is this guy looking at our house.
And I told them and they invited me in,
which was really great,
but the point being that,
like so when I went in there, it wasn't my house.
I mean, it was the house, but it wasn't my house.
It was no longer my home, it was no longer being my home.
And there's a distance,
when it's no longer functioning in that way.
My presence is no longer there,
it doesn't belong there anymore, right?
Yeah, so obviously we're not just saying that when it involves God it's much bigger, but
at least it's a way that we can understand what we're talking about some small way.
And when we're within the divine liturgy and we say Christ is in our midst, we don't
mean that when liturgy is over he departs from us and is gone somewhere and then when
And we come back for Liturgy, he shows up again.
Right?
This is not...
as opposed to absence, right? This is a contemporary example in our ritual life of that presence at a
particular place for a particular time. And this is where we're going to go deeper into what we
started to get into a little in the first half in terms of this idea of spiritual realities,
or heavenly realities or eternal realities, however we want to, whatever language
I'm sure he's just...
them intruding into the realm of human conscious experience and becoming part of that web of
relationships at particular points in time as we mentioned we were going to go deeper into.
And so again that example of Christ being the Lamb slain before the foundation of the world is
Jesus Christ who died on a hill an actual hill
outside the actual city of Jerusalem, right? As we argued in the Christmas
episode 30 AD, and so that's the point at which that event didn't become true
or become real but was revealed and entered into the realm of human conscious
experience. And the
That event, as I mentioned, can then become present again.
Right. Right. Right. So another day in another place can become that time and place.
And that happens through ritual. Yeah.
Yeah. Right. Ritual makes the current time and place that time and place.
And in terms of the cross, we're going to do this on Holy Thursday.
Yeah, yeah, that's why I win.
would we sing, we sing today, not back then, today because we've made that day
ritually the original day.
Yeah.
And like, I mean, as an example, you know, we made the mention about Hellenism earlier,
you know, today is the 200th anniversary of the Greek war of independence.
But actually it's kind of not because they were on the old calendar.
Right.
So, but I mention that because...
It still is, right?
Because the Greek people are celebrating it.
So it is the anniversary of their war for independence.
It doesn't matter that the clock hasn't turned a certain number of times or whatever.
It is because this is them doing it.
You know, even on a much more mundane example, right?
Like my birthday is always a fast day, no exceptions.
It's a single fast.
day. And so ever since it become orthodox largely speaking, if my birthday gets celebrated,
it gets celebrated on some other day because I mean, it's kind of a drag to celebrate
your birthday on a fasting day. Does that mean that the celebration is false? It doesn't
mean that my birthday becomes that moment even though the date on the calendar, we didn't,
This part of the celebration is okay today now is that deep.
We don't do that, but that's why for instance, you know, you know within the Orthodox Church,
we've got a multiplicity of calendars in function.
It can be theophany on the new calendar, and if you're 13 days later, you're in an old calendar church.
It is again theophany. It's not not really theophany, or the early one wasn't really theophany. It is.
You know, it is because you're, as you say, you're richly participating in it. You're actually doing the thing.
So yeah, you have
There is for any of these things, any of these mysteries, a paradigmatic date on which it was revealed an archetypal point.
So for the crucifixion, we talked about that.
But let me give another example because this really cuts to the core of how
ritual worship is understood in the scriptures.
So we'll take the feast of feast, Passover.
So, there's an event where the Israelites are set free from Egypt.
Right and as we've talked about there's that free from bondage to the gods of Egypt
That's an event that happens as we've talked about before the ritual celebration of that is actually described before it happens
Yeah, and when that ritual celebration happens later they don't say
When asked by their son how is this night different than all of their nights? They don't say well
X number of hundred years ago on this date
We are ancestors were set free from Egypt.
Yeah.
They say tonight is the night that we are set free from Egypt.
Right.
Us sitting here, wherever in Babylon, in Rome, in Munich, in Toronto.
Brooklyn, right?
Yeah.
Right.
We tonight are set free from Egypt because, richually, that original archetypal day has been made that
been made that.
day. Right? Part of what happens in the separation between Judaism and rabbinic Judaism and Christianity,
is a debate over which event is the archetypal pasca? Is the archetypal pasca event
the Exodus from Egypt to which it refers back to, which would make Christ last supper
just
instance, the mystical supper, an instance of that event, projected forward. Or is
the archetypal event, the death and resurrection of Christ, of which freedom from Egyptian
bondage was a retrojection into the past, was an intrusion into the past, the Christ
event intruded into the past and into all those subsequent past-overs and now into the future.
And.
When I say there was a dispute, this dispute is enacted
in the liturgics of rabbinic Judaism.
Wow. A lot of our non orthodox Christian friends,
like to at some point go and experience or see or watch or reenact
a Passover Sater. Right? Yeah. And
I am family members who do that. Yeah. And they generally react to it.
Like oh wow there's a-
symbolism about Christ there. Right? And this is an unfortunate historical misinterpretation
because the way a Passover Savior celebrated today is a product of rabbinic Judaism,
later rabbinic Judaism. Yeah. And there are things that are deliberately borrowed from Christian
liturgics. Right? This is the bread of our suffering. Right? Says the father when he holds up the
the bread.
Okay, that was not in the mystical supper.
That was not in Passover before him on the third century AD.
That was taken from this is my body.
It went the other way.
Wow.
So the Passover Seder was restructured in rabbinic Jewish liturgics
to explicitly make the claim that the Exodus Passover,
The first pass over is the archetypal and paradigmatic pass.
of which the mystical supper is an instance,
not the other way around.
Wow.
Wow. Okay, so before we get deeper into that,
we actually do have someone calling.
So Austin is calling.
And Austin, are you there?
Yeah, I'm here. Can you hear me?
We can hear you. So Austin, welcome to the Lord of Spirits podcast.
What is your question, your comment for us tonight?
Alright, um...
So it's not really related to today's episode, but it was regarding sort of the life after,
I guess the world to come I would say. And it's like, is it like a, or do we have a teaching? Is it
the black and white to where everybody experiences, you know, the eternal condemnation the same and everyone experiences.
the eternal life the same or is there an idea of some sort of gradient differences?
So it's actually deeply related to what we're talking about.
Does that make you happy to know that?
That does actually, yeah.
Yeah.
No, so here's how I would say it's related.
So you're, you know, let me make sure I'm getting your question right.
essentially asking if...
people who are among the saved? Are they all having the same experience or some people
having a sort of better experience than others? And then those who are among the damned are
some of them having a worse experience than others. Is that what your question is?
Yeah, that's pretty much exactly it.
Right, so here's how it's related in my understanding.
We started out by saying that the world, as we know it, is essentially a product of human
can't
So that means that the orientation that you have towards God and towards participating in his works or towards participating in the works of the demons.
the orientation that you have is going to be the key thing in terms of what your
experience
of that participation is, right?
So why is it even in this present life
that there are saints who experience the presence
and the power and the love of God in a way
that is way more intense than anything
I've ever had in my life?
You know, if you believe what they say,
they're clearly experiencing something that I'm not.
And certainly there are people
have had much more demonic experience.
is in life that I have had. And it's the same really in the life of the age to come. It's because of the way that we orient ourselves towards it.
You know, why is it that saints have these kinds of experiences? It's, you know, look at their biography and you're going to see a lengthy usually and definitely intense dedication to prayer and to selflessness and to arms giving. And you know, all of this kind of stuff, right. They have oriented themselves to do the works of God.
God and so they
God in a much more intense way than I do.
And the life of the age to come is simply the fullness of all of that.
Father Stephen, am I getting that right?
Yeah, well, and we'll eventually, we're going to do an episode on the news and the news
as a means of perception and experience and experience.
We loop back around to everything.
Yeah, we'll get into that more deeply.
But yeah, there's also firmly within the...
the Orthodox Christian conception, the idea that the saints in glory, which hopefully
will include us, will continue to progress into eternity, right?
Van Glory to glory.
Right.
That it's not just sort of this static state where you go to heaven and you're sitting on
a cloud or everything's made of milkshakes or all you can eat frozen yogurt or whatever.
Yeah.
Oh my God.
That we're continually, we have a continually deepening experience of God.
There is not necessarily a corresponding teaching that all of those under condemnation things
will just get worse and worse, infinitely worse and worse.
At least I don't see that anywhere.
In fact, there are a lot of clues and we'll talk about a big one of those clues in our
very next episode about the underworld that there, in terms of the experience of those who face
eternal condemnation, that there is some differentiation there. And that differentiation
there is not that, oh, your sins were worse, so you're going to get punished harder. It's
more of a distinction of mercy and grace being shown.
but we'll get into that more fully in the very next episode.
So does that help you out there, Austin?
Yeah, that's a great answer and I can't wait for the next episode.
Oh, boy, it's going to be so fun.
So all right, well, thank you very much for calling in tonight.
All right. Thank you for taking my call.
Absolutely.
All right.
So yeah, I saw on the call board what his question was and I was like, oh, this is cool.
So yeah, it's just another like it's another
But the facet for looking at these things, right?
Again, this teleological understanding of what reality itself is.
Right.
And the, you know, continuing what we've been talking about, that this is what the scripture
see as the primary work of the Holy Spirit.
The Holy Spirit creates, right?
As we said, the Holy Spirit is hovering over the waters, hovering over the chaos, brooding
over it. It's bird language.
in Genesis 1 and is involved in creation and then in recreation in the way that the New Testament
authors speak of the Holy Spirit but also the promise of the Holy Spirit in the Prophet Joel
and in Jeremiah and Ezekiel is of recreation being put back in order and having the correct
web of relationships restored right and
Both of those pieces are equally important and then also metamorphosis and transformation.
Not coincidentally this is how we understand what happens in the Eucharist in the Orthodox
Church, that it's the Holy Spirit who makes the bread and wine to be the body and blood
of Christ.
Right.
Yeah.
So we actually have...
We got a...
a message with a related question, this is a written question.
And I just thought this is a good one to put in here because I think it's a good
transition to the next thing we're going to talk about. So Laura asks this,
she emailed this to us if I remember correctly. She says, how does the
Celtic concept of thin places fit into these ideas of sacred geography?
They're described as spiritually porous places with a barrier between the
seen and unseen grows thin.
of these sites sinister and others good. In Scotland and Ireland some of these were pre-Christian
pagan sites that later became sites of Christian churches or saints shrines. And I think that this
feeds really, so thank you for that, Laura. I think there's very much feeds in what we're talking
about, especially when you, you mentioned the idea that God is sort of really present in some places
at certain times. But then there's also this, there's this other side, which is like, okay, if you go
to this particular place, you're more likely to have some kind of experience.
of the other world, of God himself, of the saints,
is there something that sort of stuck there
about the materiality of that place
that it's become spiritualized,
or is it the fact that people go there
or kind of, you know, Porque no los dos,
as the, you know, why not both, right?
You know, like what's going on there with thin places?
It's a cool concept.
Yeah, yeah, and we got it.
this a little bit in our first episode on Sacrifice, right?
That the earliest ritual sites are places where there were encounters with spiritual
beings, right?
Unfortunately, some of these are, you know, negative spiritual beings, right?
It's not just encounters with God, like in the Old Testament, but also encounters with
the demonic and other spiritual realities.
And so these places were marked and became ritual sites precisely because as we were saying,
of the function of ritual is to
make a previous day today to make a previous event recurred to participate in that event,
right, to realize it again, to represent it, not represent in some kind of disconnected
way, but represent it. And so you see this a lot with some biblical examples, right, you
You see this a lot with Stan.
stone monuments. This isn't just something the Israelites did. This is something all their
neighbors did. You would put a standard Joshua when they crossed the Jordan puts this standing stone
there with an inscription on it saying this is what happened here. These other places the same way.
These places, and so a stone would be put there. And ritually, we have a lot of rituals
who got it did this a lot right so there were these place
where that was the place where something happened to the story of bail, right?
Where one of these events in, in, in, Bales, that was, you know, associated with this place,
and there would be a standing stone there with an inscription, and they would go and
anoint the stone as part of the ritual of making that event present again, right?
And then reenacting the story, sometimes grotesque stories, but reenacting those stories
ritually.
to make that event present again to participate in it.
Yeah, and it's interesting that even here, like here in the US,
we have historical markers.
But like why put those up to begin with,
if it's not in some way even very reduced,
to try to reachfully participate in the thing that happened there.
Right, you know.
And then some people take it further,
they don't just go and read the plaque at Gettysburg,
they get dressed up and go and re-enact the battle.
Right.
Exactly.
Disappear in it themselves right and connect right and try to represid it again in in
In this kind of ritual way and this so this is why these sites then become Christian sites because
This is again a recreative act
Yeah, this place has been the place where bail did xyz
Now this is going to be the place of this martyr
Yeah, right. This is the place where god put the smackdown on this particular demon right
be put in a different order now and a different set of relationships.
And so this place is now going to be a different place than this place was previously.
Yeah.
Cool.
All right.
So I know that the next thing that we're going to discuss is about the compass directions.
Yeah.
We're getting close to our actual topic.
We're closing in.
Our actual topic of the podcast.
That's right.
Take good care.
A lot of groundwork is always has to be laid before we get there.
Yeah.
Okay, so cardinal directions.
What's that all about?
Right.
Yeah, and that's not the guy who tells you where things are at the Vatican gift shop.
Cardinal business.
Oh man, this is like Basil Exposition.
These are the four main compass directions.
Yeah.
And these have clear associations.
And when I say that the compass directions have associations,
this means they're not identified
with a particular place.
Right.
No matter where you are, east is east and west is west.
Right. Right.
At North and South is south.
Unless you're at the North or South Pole,
which exit Israelites weren't,
so they didn't have to worry about it.
Yeah.
Yeah, what do you do?
It's all south from here.
If you're a...
North Pole, I don't know. Yeah, let's go down. So, probably the most familiar one of these
is we'll kind of go from most to least familiar probably. That's through these. Probably the
most familiar is East, the association of East. Right. That's where all the good stuff is. Right.
Right, Christian churches are supposed to face east.
But as we've been discussing...
No matter what direction your church points at points east. Yeah, Kristen Graves
face east face east
We have that the him talking about the east of the highest that we talked about in our our Christmas episode
Yes, and that is because
We're told in Genesis 2 that when God plants the Garden of Eden when he plants paradise
He does it in the east
East.
and he doesn't say east of what?
Yeah, he doesn't say east of blank. He he planted a garden at just as he plants it in the east and you may say well that that means east of Jerusalem
Right. Well, here's the problem
Later on as we're going to talk about the third half
Jerusalem comes to be identified as the place where paradise was right?
So can't be east of itself. Yeah, right?
So yeah, it's just the East.
The East is the place where paradise is.
The East is the place where God dwells.
So if you're going to face toward God, you face East.
Because that's where paradise is and where He dwells.
Yeah, and interestingly again,
this points to a teleological reality.
So facing East is a matter of facing East.
It's relational.
It's volitional.
It's orientation.
You're boring, I tell you.
literally orienting yes, yeah, yeah, or the orient yeah, so
probably the next more familiar is north
which may not be immediately familiar to anyone but north which we think of north is up
right when we draw maps north is pointing up at the top of the map right that wasn't the case
in ancient Near Eastern maps.
Ancient Near Eastern maps.
up was what we would call West, up was the Mediterranean.
Okay.
Which means that North was to the left.
So that already gives you a clue that there's something sinister about it.
Yes, literally.
For those of you know, a little Latin.
It is the left-hand side.
And so the North is throughout the Scriptures the abode of evil.
Yes, right.
So, Baal and his Council of Gods met on Mount Zafon.
Zafon is Hebrew for North, the mountain of the North.
One of his titles was Baal Zafon, Baal of the North.
And it wasn't just that there were a lot of Baal worshipers in Lebanon, though there were.
Yeah, right.
It's not about Lebanon as the abode of evil.
Right.
That's right, no.
But this is a place in North. So when we read the resurrection gospel in
Mattins, we read it to the North. So we proclaim the gospel of Christ's
resurrection, the news of the defeat of the powers of evil, we proclaim it to them.
Right? By facing toward them. And my understanding is that in Western
traditional Latin liturgics, they read the gospel all the time toward the north.
Yes, right not not now but but traditionally
That's the way it's done. Yeah, right that they would always read the gospel for the same reason right you're telling them about Christ's resurrection to proclaim their doom
Right the gospel isn't good news for everybody
So then that's North West as we mentioned would be the Mediterranean Sea and the sea as we've already talked about the waters of the sea is chaos
right chaos or destruction and then south then south is kind of interesting in
that the south when you talk about things in the south the south is sort of
always sort of the predecessor or precursor civilization not in the bio-ware RPG
but in the in the
uh...
So the Greeks believed their civilization came from Egypt.
The Acadians, Akkad believed their civilization came from Sumer.
And then importantly, in the Old Testament, there are all these texts
that refer to as the Yahweh from the South passages, where Yahweh, the God of Israel,
comes up into, comes to dwell amounts, I am, but he comes from like Edom and Midian.
into comes to dwell amounts I am but he comes from like
Adam and Median.
And that's related to the fact that Moses learns about Yahweh from
Jethro, the priest of Godboastai, his father-in-law, who's a Midianite.
The Idomites and Midianites had continued to worship Abraham's God.
And Israel receives that worship back from them.
Yeah, there's a sense that the South is kind of the ancient, the old school,
the past, right? You know where I live obviously that would be Lancaster.
County where all the all the Amish people live right and the men and
nights and stuff. So yeah, see it works here in Pennsylvania too. Yeah. And this
is, you know, the Queen of Shiba who comes to visit Solomon is the Queen of
the South. Right. Right. Right. Not just because the the the
now to the kingdom. Oh, the Sabine Kingdom. The Sabine Kingdom is,
you know, in Ethiopia and Yemen. But then it's this ancient right this
ancient civilization comes to see Solomon for his
wisdom, right? It's sort of a flip of the natural thing, right? You'd expect Solomon as the king
of this sort of newer dynasty to go and inquire of the ancients, but it's the sort of this reverse of
that, right? Where the ancients come to inquire of him, because he is, he knows Yahweh, and so he has the
true, the true sort of wisdom. Yeah, yeah. I should add here, by the way, that some of my Baltic ancestors,
there was a legend among them that that civil
came to them from Rome, that ancient Lithuanians were in fact Romans who made their way north at some point.
So, but I mean the same thing, like even the same thing holds within Norse mythology, right?
Like if you read the Edda's at the beginning of the prosetta, which I mean the prosetta is actually
written by a Christian, so it's interesting that he puts it this way, St. Louis Sturelson.
He says that what the Norse worshiped as gods were actually heroes who had escaped from Troy.
way.
Right. So there's again this sense that, you know, what's way down south somewhere, that's
the source of our civilization and order and all that kind of stuff. So yeah, it's interesting
how that theme, you know, gets reused over and over and over again that south is where all
the civilization comes from. So Father Steve, you still there?
Yes sir.
Okay, just I started some crackling, I'm like oh no.
No, are we having those?
Yeah, no, I was just trying to prevent the Mexican radio station from.
Oh, oh good.
I know.
Right to blog.
That civilization from the South breaking through it on you right now.
Yes.
There's a lot of good food from down there.
So although you're in Louisiana, you have a lot of good food there as well.
Yes.
We have the easiest lens ever with all the seafood.
Yeah.
There you go.
Okay.
the way that this, you know, plays out is like for instance
we have the tradition of praying towards the east, but it's towards the east, not towards
for instance Jerusalem, in which you would have to adjust which direction, which I mean by contrast
with Muslims who always pray towards Mecca, they try to figure out where Mecca is and pray in that
direction. It's a kind of a materializing of the place of the direction of prayer, there's a spot.
But ancient Israel and of course the church as Israel prays toward the east.
from wherever you are it's always, always east.
So yeah it's not towards a particular spot.
It's relational, it's relational.
So yeah, yeah.
All right, well, the second half was actually relatively
briefer because we didn't have to do as much
metaphysics this time.
So we're gonna go ahead and go to break
and we'll be back with the third half of the Lord of Spirits.
So let's go to break.
Father Andrew Stephen.
and Father Stephen DeYoung will be back in a moment to take your calls on the next part of the Lord of Spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237-2346. That's 855-AF radio.
Hi, this is Father Evan Armitas, priest at St. Spirit on Greek Orthodox Church in Lolland, Colorado.
and the host of the ancient faith radio Sunday night calling
show Orthodoxy Live. I am pleased to announce today the release of my first book for ancient
faith publishing.
Title, Toolkit for Spiritual Growth, a practical guide to prayer fasting in almsgiving.
It seeks to provide a guide to the three basic and primary disciplines of Orthodox spirituality.
Through these disciplines, Christ opened for us a path that frees us from the disordered
way of life has become normal for many, even though their hearts and minds tell them otherwise.
Please join me in exploring the three-legged story.
of Orthodox spiritual practice, prayer, fasting, and non-sgiving.
Books now available at store.ancientfaith.com.
And the title once again is Toolkit for Spiritual Growth.
I look forward to sharing it with you.
God bless.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits, the Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father
Stephen DeYoung.
If you have a question, call now at 855-237-233
That's 855 AF radio.
Welcome to the third half of the Lord of Spirits podcast.
Before we get into talking about the mountain of God, finally now here's the topic, right?
One of the main topics of tonight's show.
I just want to actually lay out for you, I put this in our Facebook group, but I just
want to lay out for everybody kind of roadmap for the next few episodes.
So today we're in.
introducing the idea of spiritual geography of secret geography, and now we're going to be talking about the mountain of God next time two weeks from today
we're going to be talking about the underworld and
then
two weeks from then
Well my unofficial I will have to see if this passes muster with the with the brass my unofficial title for that one is the Lord of Spirits goes to hell but
We're going to help you have the most metal Paska ever
That's right.
Absolutely.
And then post PASCA, not immediately right after,
but the week, I think it's the week after that.
So remember we're on the second and fourth Thursdays of the month.
So the second Thursday of May,
we're gonna be doing a Q&A episode,
and it's gonna be just Q&A.
So we actually had a couple of calls tonight
that were not super connected
what we're talking about.
So we told them, you know, please call back later.
So we will be doing a Q&A episode.
So that's gonna be a lot of fun.
And the other thing I want to kind of let everyone...
everybody know about is that because we get questions about this, it seems like every
other hour in our email or in the Facebook group in particular is that he doesn't like
to chew his own horn, but Father Stephen has a book coming out and God willing, it's
going to be coming out right after Paska. I mean, these timelines are always a little
flexible because of the printing and all that kind of stuff. But it's called the religion
of the apostles and it's going to be covering a lot of the themes that we talk about in Lord
spirits and and this is
main reason I mentioned this, one of the questions we constantly get is can you give us some suggested reading
for some of these topics and you know what, there's going to be a bibliography. There's going to be
a bibliography and a big index in the back. So I've seen the manuscript, you guys are going to love it.
So it's just a tool again to kind of help us to talk about and to understand some of these same
Topics better it's called the religion of the apostles. So that's coming out God won't
shortly after Pascar. So all right the mountain of God here we are now finally
coming down the mountain and everyone has their own opinion that's a
reference you didn't get but anyway I don't know it sounds biblical so I'm
gonna laugh so it wasn't at all but anyway what I'd be opposite almost so we're
We're talking about, not just any mountain,
but the mountain of God.
The mountain of God.
Right, and there is a mountain of God, but several mountains have been being the mountain of God at different points in time.
Wow.
Have been being...
Gotcha.
Pass, per... wait.
The double, the double, perfect patto.
Sorry.
Yeah.
This is part of your penance as a grammar Nazi.
Yeah, start doing things like that.
To be good.
Yes.
So when we're talking about the mountain of God, we're talking about first of all the place
where God dwells, but another biblical name for it is the mountain of assembly which in Hebrew
is Harmoid.
Har is mountain and Moid is assembly.
That's the same word for assembly that gets translated in the Greek Old Testament as...
Ecclesia, which of course gets translated as church in the New Testament.
And so sometimes our English translations obscure that. The idea that the church is the same assembly as the assembly we're talking about, which is God's divine counsel, which meets a top of the mountain.
So, and so this isn't, I mean you're probably immediately aware that the idea that God lives on a mountain and even that
divine council meets on a mountain. We've already mentioned mountains of
phone in bail worship but probably Mount Olympus brings to mind for a lot of
people. Lots of gods meet on mountains. The Egyptian creation story it starts on
a mound. So this is kind of a universal thing that that there was an
understanding by everyone in the ancient world a preserved memory that God
lives on top of a mountain.
So why in the Psalms it says, I will look up into the hills from whence come with my help.
Is that what it is?
That's actually different than how we usually read it.
Okay.
All right.
That's actually just done that.
Yeah.
I lift up my eyes to the hills.
I'll go ahead and talk about this.
That's what the songs of Ascent when people are on their way to Jerusalem.
And that reference to looking up to the hills, that's a reference to the high places of
the pagan gods.
Oh.
Okay.
That you have to go past on your way.
That's why the next thing is I left a-
my eyes to the hills from whence come with my help. Oh, I gave you an old KJV there. Yeah, I am.
With my help. My help comes from the Lord. Yeah, not from it. Right. Yeah. Not exactly. It's a
conscious. Okay. All right. Not those hills, but the hills. Right. Yeah. But the mountain. Right.
Right. Don't settle for lesser hills people. Yes. And so or mounds or just humps. Yeah. Barrows. Yeah.
So, and this, this of course is why we have cigarettes,
step pyramids.
Right.
pyramids.
These are our
hanging gardens of Babylon,
which all civilization players know about.
Right.
These are all our civilization.
Recreating the mountain of God, right?
These are human recreations of the mountain of God
as temple so that they can ascend it.
Richly, tower of Bable, right?
That's what's going on.
in the Tower of Babel.
The Ziggurat of Babel.
And then hanging gardens of Babylon being a really good example,
there seemed to be a garden on top of the mountain,
in which the most high god and the divine council dwell,
and they dwell in particular intense on top of the mountain.
And so this is going on in, for example, in Hebrews,
when it talks about how.
how Moses came into the sanctuary on top of Mount Sinai,
and created the tabernacle as a sort of recreation and icon of
the place that he experienced there and the heavily sanctuered top of the mountain.
That's literally the tent, the tabernacle, where God was dwelling
and where the assembly was meeting on top of Mount Sinai because Mount Sinai was
at that time. The Mountain of God.
So when they when they moved around with the tabernacle would they then try to erect it up on top of something or
Does it if they if they could it was yeah the center it was at the center of the camp there
We actually get in the book of numbers, which I know is everyone's favorite and actually describes it detail
where each tribe camped
Like the exact layout of how the camp would be and how they would file in and how they would file out when they broke camp
So yeah, was it the
center so that even if it was on a flat you still have this idea of this is the peak right it's the center okay okay it's the it's the
focus and
So I have a tab around this is also related to why on the mount of transfiguration
when
St. Peter sees
Christ meeting with the divide council of the persons of
The prophet Elijah and and Moses he says let's build three tents
There you go. Right. One for you and one for Moses and one for Elijah because he sees, oh Mount
Tabour here has become the mountain of God. Hmm. Right. This is this is the place for us to dwell.
And so the first sort of instantiation we see in the Bible of the mountain of God is Eden itself.
Yes. Right. Where you've got, uh, and if I recall correctly, it doesn't explicitly say that in
in the Genesis text that it is
mountain, but it does say that there's four rivers flowing out from it in all
in different directions, and they're all obviously flowing out from it, so
that means they have to be going downhill. Right, right? So logically, we are at an
elevated spot. And those rivers are presented as the the Nile, the Tegris, the
Euphrates, and the Danube, which don't flow for many actual spots.
actual geographical point right.
But the idea is that the whole world is being watered, being nourished by this water that's coming out from the presence of God for the place where God dwells
there in Paradise and while the four rivers just sort of suggest that if you read Ezekiel 28 verses 13 through 16 which is part of Ezekiel's prophetic recounting
of the fall of the devil he refers to there to Eden as a mountain.
Yeah, uh, directly.
So this is the mountain of God presented sort of as itself and not directly associated with any particular
physical location as much as history channel documentaries
Would want you to believe otherwise right like the archaeological search for Eden right yeah, right
So yes, but but
going forward.
mountains that are in the world and that you could go visit become the mountain of
God for certain periods of time, right, temporal, cordonets, as we said.
One of whom we already mentioned Mount Sinai, right, comes the mountain of God
and Moses ascends, he enters into the council, he enters into the sanctuary,
the tabernacle there as Hebrews talks about St. Stephen in his...
is a sermon in Acts also references this.
I'm sure at some point we'll end up
doing an episode where we talk about
the law being given by angels,
which is referred to several times in the New Testament
and is nowhere the Old Testament.
Right.
Yeah.
So, right.
So that's our first one.
Our second one then is Mount Zion,
Right, where the temple
is ultimately built. And as we mentioned, David didn't come into the city and find God there and say,
oh, hey, I found the mountain of God. Right? We got it at dress. We tracked them down.
Hey, you guys, God lives here. Right. But Zion, when it becomes the place where God dwells,
becomes the mountain of God, becomes paradise. And so when the temple is built,
all of the iconography of Eden, right?
The pomegranates, the tru-
all of the decorations and iconography of the temple are built as a garden.
Right. It's now a garden on top of a mountain. Right. Because this is the place where God is going to dwell and tell us we mentioned Ezekiel sees.
Right. It leaving. But the temple, the idea of a temple in the scriptures maintains this connection to paradise.
Right so when Ezekiel prophesies a future temple
He describes it as having waters flowing from it,
that water the whole earth, which is a clear reference back to Eden in the Four Rivers.
Yeah.
Then when we move into the New Testament and some of our listeners are probably
hearing this right now instead of us if they're injured,
or they recently heard it or they heard it this morning and last night.
Bye.
the theotokos coming to be described as paradise. Right right exactly there's
there's you know not only is there the image of course of the theotokos as
the eastern gate through which the Lord enters but then but then you know
there's like there's the the the hymn of the cut of his he is the cross where
we sing thou art the mystical paradise right where she's described as a
miscarriage and doubt with speech in some cases.
Why? Because she's the place where God dwells.
Right?
And if she's the place where God dwells,
then that makes her into paradise.
Right?
She is paradise while God is dwelling within her.
Yes.
Yeah.
Yeah, that's what paradise is.
It's the place where God dwells.
Right.
And the reason why we talk about,
and last night at Vespers, we read that section
of Ezekiel's temple prophecy about the case in East.
This isn't just a wild allegorical thing.
Right? Right, allegorical detail. Right? It's because of the understanding pretty much unanimously
the Church fathers because they're getting it from the New Testament that Christ is Ezekiel's temple.
We especially see this in the Johanian literature. Yes. Right. Right. Right.
Right.
And St. John in his gospel makes this about his point,
his about as bluntly as you can.
because he presents the episode where Christ says,
destroy this temple and I will rebuild it in three days.
Yeah.
Say John adds the editorial note.
He was speaking of the temple which is his body,
right?
Just in case you did this that together.
Right, right.
And it's interesting.
Like, you know, it's funny.
You could still read that as saying,
and people do like,
oh, he just, he just means temple is a kind of metaphor for his body.
But like, well, why would he pick the temple?
but why not to see it?
a house or, you know, like it's a particular, it's about temple, it's about paradise.
He is the, you know, where he is, is the mountain of God.
You know, that even our churches, right, become the mountain of God.
Right.
Why is it that ideally, altars, you know, within the sanctuary of the Orthodox church are
placed higher than even if it's like, like our parish here in Emmaus, it's just one step
up up.
But there's others where there's a few steps up, you know, why is it always higher? It's not so everyone can see
Right, and it's why like
I'm not a doctor, but there's a tabernacle. Yeah, literally is a tabernacle
Like it's not in it right right right and and it's and so I also like for instance
I mean, I've seen this in some churches where churches that the seating is like an Estadium or like in a
You know a theater where the
old
is down at the bottom and I'm like, no, this is exactly the opposite of the way that
it should be. Don't have a raked. If it's going to be raked, it should be raked the
other way. But anyway, and when Christ says that, he's saying that at Herod's temple.
Right. So he's deliberately making the point, right? There's this prophecy that the temple
would be rebuilt that there would be a new temple in Ezekiel. This thing Herod put up
it. Right. And it also means I'm it. Christ is it. Yeah. And it's also why there's like
there's certain Christians dispensationalists. I'll just put it out there who believe that there's
going to be some prophetic moment where a temple gets built in Jerusalem on the temple mount.
You know, and that's the Zechial temple. Yeah. Yeah. Right. That is the temple. Material building. Yeah.
No, it's Christ, it's already...
HAPPY!
Christ is the new temple. Right. And the proof of that, the proof of that is that
Ezekiel says that is the temple where God will dwell forever forever forever.
When you get to again the Johanian literature you get to Revelation chapter 21
in the new heavens and the new earth there is no temple, say John says. Yeah. And he
says the reason there's no temple is because God and the Lamb dwell with them. Right.
Because
Christ is there, you don't need a building, right? So if Ezekiel is talking about a physical material
building, that building will have to get destroyed after it's built, which means God won't be dwelling
there forever, which means it's not what Ezekiel is talking about, right? So that that just doesn't work
as an interpretation of Ezekiel. But if we accept that what Ezekiel is talking about is Christ,
then this gate facing East thing makes perfect sense. East that
That's where God dwells.
So if God is going to come to dwell in a human body, right, body understood in the ancient
way, right, if he's going to take a human body, a human nature, right, he's going to come
from the east where he dwells, right?
So the gate that faces east is the gate through which he will come.
And it's a Zechial who adds the details that only the prince will come through that gate
and no one else and the gate will remain shut.
Yeah, yeah, and and it's also then why we get all this cool imagery in scripture of water flowing out
From Christ
Because in the joy and literature especially yes, right not you know, so you got the woman at the well
Right, you've got her you know
But but even like when he stands up in the the synagogue and reads you know
If anyone is thirsty, let him come to me and drink on the last day of the feast. Yeah
Yeah, I will give the water and and
and water will...
or forth from his belly.
Right, right.
So believers become the mountain of God.
Believers become, you know,
don't you know that the kingdom of God is within you.
The paradise is within you, you know.
Right, yeah.
Because the Holy Spirit comes to dwell within you
and your body becomes the temple of the Holy Spirit.
Right, right.
And also just to mention, you know,
this awesome image from the prophecy.
Daniel, the stone from the uncut mountain that smashes all of the idols and all the kingdoms
of this world and then grows to fill the whole earth.
Grows into a mountain.
Yeah, it grows into a mountain, right?
Grows into a mountain that fills the whole earth, right?
And the God comes to fill, the paradise comes to fill the whole earth.
Yeah.
Yep.
So the last sort of element of this is that we get from scripture is that the
holy mountain at certain points comes under siege. So one of these we've already talked about back in the
Giants episode so everybody get excited. The Amalakites, right when they come to Mount Sinai, the Israelites
come to Mount Sinai, Mount Sinai is being the mountain of God at that point, right? And so the Amalakites
come and lay siege to them and to the mountain, right?
And there's that passage where it says the amulacites have dared to lay a hand upon the throne of Yahweh because it's become the mountain of God. That's where his throne is
While he's there meeting with Moses. That's where his throne his dwelling enters into the realm of human conscious experience in that place at that time. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. And that's why they siege to him. Yeah. And then that's why then Israel is sent
to go and to
Take God's revenge against...
the Giants against the Malachites, because they attacked the throne of God
effectively. And this then happens again in Revelation again, this is Armageddon,
right? A lot of people, again, I'm sorry, history channel documentaries, they
really want this to be Maguino. Are you really sorry to the history channel
documentary sorry not sorry not sorry documentary no aliens evolved and
This isn't this isn't Megido. This is Armageddon is a Greek transliteration of
of Harmoade. It's an it's an Ion is the A in Moade the A sound and in its ancient
pronunciation that was pronounced like yeah very close to a hard G sound so for
For example, Sodom and Gomorrah, the Gha in Gomorrah is actually...
It's actually an iron. It's actually this letter.
Yeah, which if you speak Arabic, you know how to say the iron.
Yeah. So it's not like, you know, this is Harbaway. This is the mountain of assembly.
All of the enemies of God led by the dragon and the beast gather out like the amulakites to lay siege to the mountain of assembly
and then are defeated and destroyed in the middle of Revelation.
But what this means is what this means
that wherever God's paradise is, wherever the dwelling place of God is,
that place is going to be under siege by the enemies of God, by the spiritual enemies of God.
That includes within us, right? This is part of the basis of our understanding of spiritual warfare.
If the Holy Spirit is dwelling within us and we're the temple of God and we're the dwelling place of God,
and we become paradise within and the mountain of God.
within, then that means there's going to be a siege. We're going to be under attack by God's
enemies. And so this form's important basis is deeply connected to our understanding of spiritual
warfare. So yeah, the mountain of God is not only some physical mountains, but it's inside you.
It's part of your internal geography.
Yeah.
Okay, well, to wrap up this first of our two episodes, or is it three about spiritual
geography, sacred geography?
You know, I'm especially on that last note, which I think, I mean, it's all fascinating,
but I think that this last note in particular is one of the places, it's not the only place,
but it's one of the places where the rubber meets the road, right?
The paradise is within you, the mountain of God is within you, and you're going to be
under siege by the enemies of God.
not just because people get excited when we talk about amalachites.
I remember, and we just actually marked the commemoration of his passing just a few days ago,
a priest that I knew, Father Alexander Addy, was he the Dean while you were at St. T. Conzer?
Was that as your master? A little after, yeah.
I met him a few times though.
So Father Alexander Addy who you know passed away untimely from our point of view of cancer.
Just a few days actually after Metropolitan Phil of the Antioch and Archdiocese, so it was 2014
And it was you know early later in March, so just a few days ago
I remember one of the things that he said to me one time and this was in the context of giving advice
You know, he was a very experienced pastor. He was a pastor for decades at St. Michael's church in Louisville, Kentucky
He said
Make the place you're in.
into paradise. Right? And the specific context of the time was, you know, the parish where
God has put you as a pastor, make it as parodysaic, all as possible. Right? But that's not the
only application of that. Okay? So if the kingdom of God is within you, and again, this
emphasizes this sort of, as it's called, it's called eschatological tension of both now
and not yet. So so
If you are a baptized Christian, then you are the place of paradise because you've put on Christ.
Right? As many have been baptized in Christ, put on Christ. And if Christ is the temple of God,
if he is paradise, then it's within you. So if you've done that and you are the paradise of God,
but you also are not yet because we're
were still on the journey, right? It's both now and not yet become the thing that you are.
That means that spiritual life is about making yourself paradesical. This is one of the ways
of talking about it. It's not the only way. And so, so how do you do that, right? Well, what is
appropriate for a temple. What is appropriate for paradise? What does that look like?
What do you do?
there. You know, number one, you are there to be with God. You are there to
commune with God. You are there to worship God. That's what a temple is. That's
what Paradise is. It's the place where Adam meets God and where he is one with
God and he is in communion with God. And so that means that prayer and worship
are utterly core to our to who we are. It's not just sort of something that
helps with spiritual
or something, I make sure I try to do that every so often. It doesn't help. It is who we are.
Right? But also, you know, think about all these things we've talked about in terms of sacrifice in previous episodes
and about purification of the temple of God. And all of that,
that also applies to you, to who you are.
All of these things that are what the way that a temple functions and is treated and people go
there and do those things, all of that is who you are. And even like this image of pilgrimage,
right? We started with that when we started talking about sacrifice. There is an internal
pilgrimage that you make within which we participate in by making external pilgrimage. And by that,
I can mean you can mean going on a long journey. But it also means simply the pilgrims you take
when you get up on a sunny morning and go to your church, even if you live right next to order it.
but also is the pilgrimage that you take when you wake up and you walk
and stand in front of your icons.
You know, in the morning and at night
you're making that pilgrimage to this holy place
because you are paradise and you are making yourself
parodysaicled by then going to, you know,
another paradise, so to speak, within your home,
within your community.
You know, all of these things, you know, it's,
it's sort of stacks, you know.
There's, paradise is upon paradise, right?
Right, and why do we go to the saints?
because the saints have become paradise.
We go there because we meet with God there
and we connect with God there and commune with God there.
So all of this reverberates just beautifully,
beautifully, right?
And if we, even with these sort of difficult
metaphysical concepts that we began with
about being a human doing,
that being is a verb, right?
That
That figures into this very, very deeply.
And if you understand this the right way and you're oriented the right way, then you'll
know that it's not a matter of like, am I good enough?
Have I done enough?
Did I go to church enough?
Did I love my neighbor enough or whatever?
Because again, that's a very sort of quantitative approach to these things.
The question is, how am I being?
How am I being?
am I fundamentally oriented towards God?
and going to that mountain of assembly to meet with him.
That's, I sometimes tell people,
it's not a matter of progress or distance or arrival,
it's sort of vector, so to speak,
to use a mathematical term.
What direction are you moving in?
And that's spiritual life from this particular angle.
So I love this conversation on sacred geography.
The first place I go is this question that Laura talked about.
you know when I learned about the idea of thin places where I was like whoa there's places you can go
where you can meet God and the answer of course is yes but also thinking about that beautiful
advice given to me by Father Alexander Addy that the place I'm in can become paradise that
this studio that I'm talking to you from right now it is paradise because here I meet with God
And that's the purpose of this
place. So my prayer is that all of this will help to contribute to your paradise, which is
not a separate one from the paradise. It's simply participation in Christ himself, who is
the paradise, where we worship the One True God. Father Stephen?
Yeah, and this is kind of a obligatory but I mean as you said you can find
Paradise setting
anywhere. You can find it in Paradise City. You can find Paradise by the dashboard light.
Anyway, we're going to be low hanging fruit. You know, I know we have a fair number of
listeners who aren't necessarily Americans, but I think this may apply beyond America.
But I could say for us, Merkins, our heroes are individuals, right? Our heroes are
lone wolves, the tough cop who plays by his own set of rules.
You know, you don't see a lot of TV shows and movies about people who do things by the
book.
You know, it's sort of do a solid job.
It's, we all want to be individuals and achieve like individual excellence.
That's what we're oriented toward.
But what are the consequences of everything we've been talking about tonight?
But especially in terms of identity and the time we spent talking about identity and what makes something what it is,
including what makes you and I who you and I are, is that it's not just about us being put in order.
It's not just about us, right? It's not just an internal thing of being justified and set in order and properly arranged.
Though this tends to be the focus of a lot of
our Christian life and thought is I need to get my stuff together right I need to get myself
straightened out I need to repent of my sins and get myself okay so that I go to heaven when
I die and I need to find salvation for myself and that could even just be I need to become
a saint. I need to achieve some kind of spiritual excellence, some kind of spiritual level.
But just being set in order, just being a certain thing isn't your identity.
Your identity includes and is dependent on that web of relationships we were talking about.
The way we fit into the rest of creation, including our fellow humans, but going beyond our fellow humans to all of the rest of creation,
having that set of relationships, those connections being right.
being set right, being put in order and in their proper order. Without that, we can't be internally
set right. This is why all through the scriptures, famously in 1 John, but all through the scriptures,
you can't love God and hate your neighbor. You can't have things right with God, you can't be
justified and have things be out of whack at the same time.
pick on him too much but I'm sorry Martin Luther, you can't be just in a center at the
same time. You just can't. So we have to always remember and especially now during Great
Lent, when we're really focused on this, we focus on repentance, that this is not just
a move inward. Everything that we said about paradise being within you and the king to be
within you is absolutely true.
But that doesn't mean that you fold in on yourself and become a solopsist and become entirely
self-focused.
Because finding yourself and finding what is within you is only going to happen through
correcting that web of relationships.
You're going to find yourself in other people.
You're going to find God in other people.
when we're loving our neighbor and we're setting things right and we're making a
as part of our repentance and we're putting everything around us back into order.
That's what's going to cause all those things within us that are out of joint and out of place to slide back into place.
That's where things are going to come together and we're going to find out who we really are and what it really means to be a human.
And thereby by discovering what it means to really be human, to discover what it is to be like Christ and to become like God.
which is
what we call theosis and what salvation is really all about is about becoming a son of God as we've
said before, becoming like him, becoming like Christ, that doesn't happen for us all alone on our own.
That happens for us as part of the church, as part of a community of the faithful, both those who
who are alive with us in this world now and those who have gone before.
find salvation and restoration and paradise together.
Oh man. Well next time we're going to be following Orpheus and taking a trip into the other
underworld. But that is our show for tonight. Thank you very much everyone for listening.
If you didn't get a chance to call in during the live broadcast, we would love to hear from you
either via email at LordofspiritsatAncientFate.com or you can message us at our Lord of Spirits podcast
Facebook page we read every
but can't respond to everything, and we do say what you send for possible use in future episodes.
Join us for our live broadcasts on the second and fourth Thursdays of the month at 7pm Eastern 4pm Pacific.
And if you are on Facebook, unlike Father Steven,
like our page and join our discussion group,
leave reviews and ratings everywhere,
but most importantly, share the show with a friend whom you know is going to love it.
I was bad, so I don't get to talk about Facebook anymore.
And finally be sure to go to ancientfaith.com
Stroke Support and help make sure
We and lots of other AFR podcasters stay on the air.
Thank you very much and God bless you
and may he give you a beautiful, beautiful land.
You've been listening to the Lord of Spirits with Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew
Stephen Damick and Father Steve.
to young, a listener-supported presentation of ancient faith radio.
And I beheld, and I heard the voice of many angels round about the throne and the beasts
and the elders, and the number of them was 10,000 times 10,000 than thousands of thousands,
saying with a loud voice, worthy as the land that was slain to receive power and riches
and wisdom and strength and honor and glory and blessing.
Revelation chapter 5 verses 11.
be individuals and achieve like individual excellence. That's what we're
oriented toward. But one of the consequences of everything we've been talking
about tonight, but especially in terms of identity and the time we spent talking
about identity and what makes something what it is, including what makes you and
who you and I are is that it's not just about us being put in order.
It's not just about us, right?
It's not just an internal thing of being justified and set in order and properly arranged.
Though this tends to be the focus of a lot of our Christian life and thought, is I need to get my stuff together, right?
I need to get myself straightened out.
I need to repent of my sins and get myself okay so that I go to heaven.
die and I need to find salvation for myself. And that could even just be, I need to become
a saint. I need to achieve some kind of spiritual excellence, some kind of spiritual level.
But just being said in order, just being a certain thing isn't your identity. Your identity
and is dependent on that web of relationships we were talking about.
way we fit into the rest of creation, including our fellow humans, but going beyond our fellow
humans to all of the rest of creation, having that set of relationships, those connections,
being right, being set right, being put in order and in their proper order, without that,
we can't be internally set right.
This is why all through the Scriptures, famously in 1 John, but all...
through the Scriptures. You can't love God and hate your neighbor. You can't have
things right with God. You can't be justified and have things be out of whack at the same
time. I don't want to pick on them too much but I'm sorry Martin Luther. You can't be
just in a sinner at the same time. You just can't.
So we have to always remember.
and especially now during Great Land,
when we're really focused on this.
We focus on repentance,
that this is not just a move inward.
Everything that we said about paradise being within you
and the kingdom being within you is absolutely true.
But that doesn't mean that you fold in on yourself
and become a solipsist and become entirely self-focused.
Because finding yourself and finding what is within you
is only going to happen through
correcting that web of relationships. You're going to find yourself in other
people. You're going to find God in other people. And when we're loving our
neighbor and we're setting things right and we're making amends as part of our
repentance and we're putting everything around us back into order, that's what's
going to cause all those things within us that are out of joint and out of
place to slide back into place. That's where things are going to come together
other.
and we're going to find out who we really are
and what it really means to be a human.
And thereby, by discovering what it means to really be human,
to discover what it is to be like Christ
and to become like God.
Which is what we call theosis
and what salvation is really all about.
It's about becoming a son of God, as we've said before,
becoming like him, becoming like Christ.
that doesn't.
happen for us all alone on our own. That happens for us as part of the church, as part of a community
of the faithful, both those who are alive with us in this world now and those who have gone before.
We all find salvation and restoration and paradise together.
Oh, man. Well, next time we're going to be following Orpheus and taking a trip into the other
underworld. But that is our show for
Thank you very much everyone for listening. If you didn't get a chance to call
and during the live broadcast we would love to hear from you either via email at
Lordofspiritsatainchentfaith.com or you can message us at our Lord of Spirits
podcast Facebook page. We read everything but can't respond to everything and we
do say what you send for possible use in future episodes. Join us for our live
broadcasts on the second and fourth Thursdays of the month at 7 p.m. Eastern 4 p.m.
Pacific. And if you are on Facebook, unlike Father Steven,
like our page and join our discussion group,
leave reviews and ratings everywhere,
but most importantly, share this show with a friend
whom you know is going to love it.
I was bad, so I don't get to talk about Facebook anymore.
And finally, be sure to go to achiefaith.com,
stroke support, and help make sure we and lots of other AFR
podcasters stay on the air.
Thank you very much, and God bless you,
and may He give you a beautiful, beautiful length.
You've been listening to the Lord of Spirits with Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew
Stephen Damick and Father Stephen De Young, a listener-supported presentation of Ancient Faith
Radio.
And I beheld and I heard the voice of many angels round about the throne and the beasts
and the elders, and the number of them was 10,000 times 10,000,
and thousands of
f-
seeing with a loud voice worthy as the land that was slain to receive power and riches and wisdom and strength and honor and glory and blessing.
Revelation chapter 5 verses 11-12.