He will be a staff for the righteous, with which for them to stand and not to fall.
And he will be the light of the nations and the hope of those whose hearts are troubled.
All who dwell on the earth will fall down and worship him, and they will praise and bless,
and celebrate with song the Lord of Spirits.
1st denoc, chapter 48, verses 4-5.
The modern world doesn't acknowledge, but is nevertheless haunted by spirits, angels, demons, and saints.
In our time, many year into break free of the prison of a flat, secular materialism,
to see and to know reality as it truly is.
What is this spiritual reality like?
How do we engage with it well?
How do we permeate everyday life with spiritual presence?
Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen De Young
host this live Colin show, focused on enchantment in creation.
the union of the scene and unseen as made by
God and experienced by mankind throughout history. Welcome to the Lord of
Spirits. Welcome back to the Lord of Spirits podcast where it's the weirdest
Bible study ever. I am Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Emmaus Pennsylvania and my
co-host Father Stephen DeYoung is with me from Lafayette, Louisiana. If you're
listening to us live, you can call in at 855 AF radio. That's 855-237-2346 as
as you just heard the voice of Steve tell you,
Mathew's good,
Trudy will be taking your calls tonight and we're going to get to those in the second half of today's show.
The appearances of the resurrected Christ are emphasized so repeatedly in Orthodox tradition that there's a cycle of 11
Resurrection appearances by Christ that are repeated at the Sunday or Throne's
Gospels throughout the year and they're announced by the priest while he is facing the North.
North and if you listen to our episodes on sacred geography you know that
That is the direction of God's enemies.
These are the gospel readings used as the announcement of victory against those who
oppose the Lord.
That's how important they are.
Yet the resurrection appearances of Jesus Christ are often thought of as a kind of day
new month in the gospels and epilogue after the main action of Holy Week.
Or sometimes they're understood as the evangelist presenting evidence to prove that Jesus rose
from the dead.
But is that what's really going on?
What is no one see?
to recognize Jesus even when they see him. So in typical Lord of spirits fashion before we answer
those questions, we need to set the stage. So let's begin with what exactly it means when we say
that Jesus resurrected. Father Stephen, doesn't that just mean that it was like when you see the doctors
shock a dead patient in the operating room and he jumps up gasping and is just like he was before?
No. I will never get tired of doing that.
Yeah, so this is...
This is not flat liners, either the good one or the horrible remake.
This is a completely different sort of thing.
This is also not the terminator ending of Passion of the Christ or any of several other
popular presentations.
But that's sort of how, you know, as you mentioned, and we're going to be trying to push back
against this whole episode.
The the resurrection appearances of Christ have so been treated as an epilogue
Right right that that I don't think in like the atrical presentations and stuff
I don't even think that much thought is put into them
It's trying to figure out what's going on or it's just sort of like
Yeah, Jesus is alive and some people saw him
Right, right that that's about it right if that if it doesn't get left out of the movie entirely
We are done.
I think of course our dramatic crescendo is the crucifixion really.
Right.
And then the resurrection even gets treated sometimes as sort of an afterthought, let alone
the resurrection appearances.
Yeah, especially if someone's theology kind of focuses on the cross as being the end
all be all of what Jesus came to do.
Right.
And we have to back up a little.
only a little this time. We're not going back to the Chalcolithic period or anything.
Yes, right.
Yes.
As this our long long ago before the fossil record began.
Yeah.
So yeah, we don't have to deal with any any thousands of years BC dating issues. We have to
have a fact we're only going back from liturgy to madness.
There you go.
It's madness. That service that takes place.
when no one's in the church sadly,
in many cases, or, you know, which,
so like in our tradition, we're Antioch in Priests,
it's done on Sunday morning right before the divine liturgy.
And if you go to a Greek Orthodox church,
you would see the same thing.
And in Russian Orthodox parishes,
it is sometimes done on Saturday night,
combined with great vespers,
but there's a lot of variation on all these points.
But yeah, it's this service that happens
every single weekend in most
churches and you know the point of this episode is not to complain to people like why aren't
you at that service but I do hope that by the time someone gets the end of this they will be
more interested in going if they haven't been going you know just because of this particular
piece that's embedded in that you know these resurrectional appearances of Christ are one of the key
moments in Sunday mountains so. Also stay off our lawn and the basketball is mine now.
Okay.
So in terms of elderly person rent, why did it go to Matt?
It's right.
Oh well, he told me.
He yells at clouds.
So that may be our first Simpson's reference actually on the show.
I don't know.
Maybe anyway.
Yeah, anyway.
Yeah.
So yeah, the resurrection.
What's the difference between.
So, yeah, so it starts with really.
We don't even have to go back to Matt and it's quite yet.
because we're starting with...
what we say when we say Christ is risen.
At least what we say in Greek, and also at least Arabic.
Unfortunately, this is not necessarily clear in the Dutch version, for example.
As much as it means me to say, almost physically.
So when we say that Christ is risen in Greek, we say,
Crystal Sunesty, right?
And the fact that we use the verb
a nesty is important.
Right, because there are other options.
Right.
And the clear other option, the other biblical option,
the other biblical verb that's used to refer to Christ
rising is a E. R.O.
So we could say a E. R. A. Christos a E. R. A.
which would be something like Christ has,
Well, literally Christ has got...
up, but something like Christ rose like he got up again.
Yeah, because that's the verb that you would use like if I was, you know, sleeping and
then I got up.
Right.
And that's even that verb is even used of Christ in the New Testament, right, to talk
about his act of physically rising.
Right.
But what we profess when we're professing that Christ is risen is more than that.
Not less than that. It includes that but it's
much more than that.
Yeah, he's not just waking up off an operating table.
Right.
Like he flatlined and then now he's back.
Which I think, I think that's, we're going to unpack what that means.
But I think this is a really, really important point to pause at for a second because I think
that's what a lot of people imagine when they think of the resurrection.
In fact, you know, well, and they think for instance...
the stone gets rolled away, well, of course the stone has to get rolled away so he can
get out, you know, which is the way I've seen even depicted sometimes, right, in, you
know, various dramatic presentations as the stone has to get rolled away so that he can
get out because otherwise he's trapped in there, you know, which if it's, if it's, he's
just sort of resuscitated, then that's, yes, obviously, that would be sort of necessary.
But actually, the stone gets rolled away so other people can go in and have a look.
and see that he's not there.
Yeah.
Right, right. So he's not just getting resuscitated. There's something else going on here. Right. It's it's so what what's happening when
In Christ's resurrection is different than what's happening when
Lazarus is restored to life right or the widow of name son is restored to life or the widow of Zarafath's son is restored to life by
The prophet Elijah right. It's not the same thing though. I think a lot of people may think about it that way
Yeah.
Christ just sort of comes back to life and then 40 days later flies up into the sky.
I mean, it's not that those other raisings are unrelated, right?
And we're going to talk about especially Lazarus later, but they're not the same event.
It's not the same phenomena.
Right.
And so we don't, and this is why we don't go around festively proclaiming Lazarus is risen.
because the consequences are not-
the same. So that particular word, right, anastasis that we use to refer to Christ's resurrection,
right, the icon of the, it's actually the icon of the hairling of hell is usually labeled
in Greek, Eonastasis.
Amazis, right. That's what it's a depiction of. And so then that's against the, the aero
verb right that I was saying earlier.
And so that the verb form on East Amy, which is related
to Anastasis is actually a very important one
in the Old Testament.
Yes.
Yeah.
Sorry.
You guys thought you were going to escape the Old Testament
for a second there?
Yeah.
No.
That's not a thing on this podcast.
So we have to go back when we're talking about Christ
or want to understand that we have to understand how that verb is used in the Old Testament,
and it's used particularly in relationship to the day of Yahweh or the day of the Lord
as it's usually translated in English.
So which produces the interesting thing in most English Bibles that it's day of the Lord
in all caps in the Old Testament and day of the Lord without the caps in the New Testament.
Yeah.
as if it's two different days,
but we'll come back to that too.
So that day is a day that's described
prophetically in the Old Testament
when several things are going to happen.
And they all come under the context of,
this is the day when Yahweh is going to visit his people.
The God of Israel is going to come
and visit his people, visit his creation.
Right, right in.
And this is a really important word.
And it does not mean like, oh, my cousin visited last week
and we had a good time together.
It's not that.
It's the visited, and judgment was visited upon them.
That's the visitation they were talking about.
We don't usually use it that way.
That's more of a, I think we probably associate that
mainly with the Bible.
But we still do have that usage in English that there's this visitation of the Lord, you know, God showing up in person
Or you know as every mother has said at some point wait until your father gets home like that's what's being kind of
Talked about like there's a it's a warning
You know, there's something really big that's that's happening so you know you better get it together
Right it's the it's the archetypal instance of this is in Genesis 3
when Adam and Eve have broken the one commandment, they had one job, right?
Yeah, you had a good job.
And they've broken it, and then God comes walking in the garden.
In... it's usually translated in the heat of the day.
It's actually literally in the Hebrew in the spirit of the day, in the Ruach.
That's interesting.
and it's the heat or the spirit of the day.
right? So it's oh, interest is already an early like illusion to this day of the Lord
idea, right? And so that's why I had to be kind of scatter and hide, right? Because he's
now come to visit and so some things are going to happen based on him now. Stuff has been
present. Yeah. So the kids go and hide behind the furniture, right? Right? Right. Right.
Yeah, you know, it's funny. You know, you mentioned that, but we were just doing, so I'm taking
Old English among other things, and we were just doing a translation of Genesis chapter
three from Old English into modern English. And what was interesting was to look at the
way that that translation worded things. So for instance, you know, in most English
Bible's where God shows up in the garden. You know, he says, why are you hiding to Adam?
you know, where are you? And Adam says, well, I hid because I was naked, right? And
in most Bibles, you see him saying, you know, who told you that you were naked? Did you
eat of the tree? But in the, and the old English, it says, how did you know that you were
naked if you didn't eat of the tree? Like it's this sort of accusatory, you know, like
he's not even giving Adam a chance at that point in the old English, which is kind of fun.
Okay.
I think follows the Latin that the Old English is from.
This is not a huge digression.
It's actually kind of a fun point about this,
because it's this idea of, you know,
Dad is showing up.
Things are out of place and he's come to put bring justice.
Right, and that's, I'm pretty sure we've talked about this
in a past episode that justice,
biblically is not criminal justice.
Right, it's not punishment.
People have broken the law, so now here come the cops
to punish everybody.
right for the bad things they did.
It's justice is a state of being where, you know, the web of relationships we've talked about,
it sort of constitutes what a thing is, those are all correct and all in the right place,
and everything is in proper order, and everything is functioning together properly.
That's justice.
Right.
And so injustice is when someone does something that throws that out of whack.
And then to judge is to come and put that back into whack
Right? It's a bit back into the correct order. And so when God comes to visit, that's going to happen.
Right. And so that's going to be good news for some people and not good news for some other people.
Right. Right. And so this is one of the major things that's going that when the day of the Lord comes,
Yahweh the God of Israel is going to come into His creation and He's going to set things right.
right this is what the profits are saying
and again and again.
And do you want to read an example?
One of many that we've read.
Yeah, right.
I mean, there's piles of them.
Yeah, it's fun.
If you go to biblegateway.com and just search for instances
of day and Lord in the same verse,
you'll just see boom, boom, boom, boom, boom, boom,
all these references to the day of the Lord.
And here's one example.
So this is Isaiah chapter 24, verses 21 and 22.
On that day, the Lord will punish.
the heavenly forces in the heavens and the earthly kings on the earth. They will be imprisoned in a
pit locked up in a prison and after staying there for a long time they will be punished. That is the
useful net Bible which is not particularly poetically phrased but what kind of gives you the
sense of what's going on with the underlying language. Yeah, the day of the Lord, he's going to punish
the heavenly forces and the heavens and the earthly kings on the earth.
So there's that that that's
sense of the judgment of both the, you know, the divine council and human beings at the
same time.
Right.
And an important thing to note here is that you notice that they're imprisoned on the
the day of the Lord. Right. And then punished after this, after many days. Yes. Yes.
Yeah, as the net Bible puts it,
they'll be imprisoning a pit,
locked in a prison,
and after staying there for a long time,
they will be punished.
So there's clearly a span of time
that happens between the student events.
Right, and so this has something to say
about how we interpret Revelation 20
in light of the Old Testament, right?
That when St. John talks about demonic forces
being imprisoned or bound for a period of time,
after which comes their judgment.
That's not some new
Revelation part of the pun that he's having right about
About pure future of it. He's he's
speaking out of
this prophetic
idea so the day of the Lord here for Isaiah is not
the last day
Like the end of the world day. No, right right last day
No, it's the coming of the Lord to set things right
Yeah, it is.
It is sort of a quintessential day.
It is a day where certain divine realities are going
to break into the world of human experience.
Right.
In a powerful way.
It is frankly a doomsday because to lay down.
To some doom.
Yeah.
Well, but to lay down doom is to lay down judgment.
Right.
So like the English word, I deem, right?
A deem is to is about perceiving the way things are
and laying down a judgment of what the way they're going to be.
So it is a doomsday, you know?
So I had to throw in a little bit more old English there.
So I'm just...
This is your one.
Right, right.
Thank you.
I can't make all of the pop culture references that you make, so I'm going to import a bunch of old English.
Yes, yes.
Different kinds of nerds.
Yes.
Those are free of C.A.
It's okay.
Our repertoire.
Exactly.
So there are also a number of passages within the prophets.
of profits.
that talk about the signs of this day, right?
When this day arrives, here's how you'll know
it's that day.
Yeah, right.
And we've got, honestly, again,
for any of these things we're talking about,
their countless examples.
I, we mostly talk about it, we picked shorter ones
so that we wouldn't be reading all night.
once you once you know the pattern you start to see
everywhere. But so we've got one of those from Isaiah 2. Isaiah as well. Yeah,
another yeah. Isaiah chapter 13 verses 9 and 11 again this is from the Net Bible. Look the Lord's
day of judgment is coming. It is a day of cruelty and savage raging anger, destroying the earth
and annihilating its sinners. Indeed the stars in the sky and their constellations no longer
give out their light. The sun is dark and as soon as it rises in the moon does not shine.
It's interesting how again you've got this theme of justice being given in both heaven and earth
At the same time
Yeah, yeah, there is never a point where the Hebrew prophets are
materialists
Yeah, where they're where they're just purely talking about like social justice
Yeah, they do talk about social justice, but they talk about social justice as it flows from
Right.
the rebellious spiritual powers,
the way in which sin infects humans,
and then the way in which they then tyrannize
and victimize the poor in the week in the...
Cosmic Juz of powerless.
Right.
And so when God casts His judgment,
He starts with, you know, it goes from the head down, right?
So it starts with the actual progenitors
and the actual problem.
But as Father Ed was reading that,
you might have noticed that
the description there of the day of the Lord and you'll find this if you if you
do the searching and all these passages a lot of that imagery shows up in the
gospels yep in a particular play and that surrounding the crucifixion yeah and
is depicted in our crucifixion icons of Christ the sun and the moon hiding
their faces it's in our himnography right and we've talked about how the
in the moon.
There.
having faces is not quaint or artistic, right, or a subreference to Mac tonight. But is
you see these are the spirits associated with them, right? These are the heavenly hosts that the
heavenly powers, right, who are being sort of blotted out. So this is here's one association
where we see that the gospel writers are telling us that this day of the Lord that was
prophesied comes about at Christ's crucifixion. And so then there are other things within
the prophets that are going to happen when the day of the Lord comes. And one of those
is the rising of the saints, of the righteous ones, of the holy ones. This is the resurrection
as, for example, the fairest.
would have understood it. Right. Right. Which is comes out of you especially find this theology laid out really well in second macabees where within the experience of martyrdom that the faithful Judeans had under the Greeks, under the cell you could empire, where they refused to disobey God and were tortured and killed for it for keeping the Torah.
Uh...
The promise to them is that not just that, oh well, you'll have some kind of bodyless
eternal heavenly well-being, you know, or you're going to have some kind of paradise, but no,
you know, the limbs that are now being tortured and severed will be restored.
Right. Right. That there will be part of that justice being established is that these people who
have been wrongfully slain will live again.
Yeah, there's the
for all of you Pejo fans out there, a flip that occurs.
Right? Those who have been being oppressed by these evil powers,
and by those who are in co-huts with them, those who are being oppressed are going to be lifted up on high,
not to become new oppressors, but rather to take the place of these rulers who have abused their rule,
harmful to others, you know.
that the fallen are going to be lifted up, right,
that they're going to be vindicated,
and not just vindicated, like given,
like some kind of restitution or whatever,
but actually brought up to the very top.
I mean, it's a pattern you see over and over again
in Scripture, right?
I mean, think about Joseph, for instance,
who's given in slavery into Egypt,
and then, you know, by the end of the story,
he's in charge of Egypt, essentially.
You know, and he, of course, is regarded as a type of Christ.
Yeah, so I mean it's a cool
It's a cool pattern and it's again, it's a really interesting because it's not one you see in paganism.
Right? And paganism, the, you know, this sort of great chain of being where the important people
are on the top and the the the the the the the the lolier on the bottom, like that's the way it's supposed to be
and it never changes. You know, peasants and slaves don't become rulers within a pagan model, but
But this is exactly what happens on the day of the Lord, is that people who are
slaves become like stars. Yeah small G gods. Yeah. Yeah. In the romances of its
Caesar who who becomes a god. Right. And the slaves, you know, become dirt. Right.
Which is really slightly above in in the first place. Right. And so and this is
what Christ is saying over and over and over again. He says the last shall be
first and the first should be last.
Right?
And he has been faithful to the little little bit.
given much. You know, it's been right. We'll have it taken away from him again and again
again. So in particular, Saint Matthew and his gospel highlights this happening at Christ's
death. And that's in that kind of cryptic and somewhat weird passage in Matthew 27
versus 52 and 53.
Yeah.
Where many of the saints of old name, though.
holy ones of all these righteous ones.
And it's interesting how, if you read it in detail,
how Saint Matthew describes it, right?
Everyone reads over it very quickly,
it just says, oh, so people came to life
and they were seen around Jerusalem.
Yeah.
What it actually says is, they rise, they come back to life,
right? They're resuscitated in their tombs,
but they don't come out of their tombs
until Christ comes out of his.
Yeah
a lot of very literal reading. It's like St. Matthew is saying they sort of sat
around for 36 hours or so in their tunes. On Friday night, Saturday, in the
tombs because they didn't want to jump the gun and then when Christ rose, they
came out. Now that's I don't think that's what he's trying to say. Yeah. Like I said,
it's a very literalistic reading. I think what he's doing is he's tying
their rising to Christ.
death through the day of the Lord. This is one more piece that this is the day of the Lord,
but he's saying that they aren't seen in Jerusalem until after Christ's resurrection in the
harem of Hades. And just as a kind of sidebar on this, because like some of the questions that we
get sometimes are about questions about literal versus metaphor and all that kind of thing.
And this is important because often modern thinkers we
We tend to, we put things in either one of two categories.
This literally happened or it metaphorically happened which means it didn't happen but
it teaches us something useful, you know, whatever.
And this particular example, when we say that this is the way that St. Matthew depicts
it, that's the important very first step, right?
We're not going to say, do we need to say that these people were hanging around for 36
hours in their in their tombs waiting for Jesus to rise and then
they could come on out like we're not saying that but we should ask well why does Matthew
depicted in this way even while we don't know what actually is going on inside those tombs, right?
And you know the answer to that question in this case is because Matthew's connecting it
to the day of the Lord it's saying these are the things that happen when the day of the Lord comes
right and so these are signs by which we know that the day of the Lord has happened.
And so, you know, that one can look at something and
say, well, that's not just a metaphor or it's not just a symbol. And yet not take it literally
in a materialist sense. Like materialism is not the only way to take things literally. If
that makes, if that makes any sense. Like when we say that the sun and the moon and the stars are
angels, if you take that literally as material, in a materialist sense, then you're saying,
we say your saying they're not big balls of gas. Is that what you're trying to say? You know,
but, but again, taking it in the sense literally, in other words, taking it by what is written,
that's well.
literally actually means that assuming materialism as the only frame within which to take
things literally is where you get into big trouble with all of this.
So I know that's a bit of a digression, but I think it's a useful hermeneutic point
to make as we kind of move forward through some of this stuff.
Right.
It's you determine what St. Matthew is saying, and that is Orthodox Christians were committed
to the fact that what
you as saying is true, right? But he's not saying everything. He's not saying every possible
way you could read it. He's not a 21st century person. Right. So he's not making any, they
might be giant subreferences, right? Even if you think you see one, you're wrong. He's not making one.
Right.
Now you might be the way around.
Yeah, I might be the other way around.
they might be giants might be referencing Saint Matthew. But
right, so you know, that's the key to key is what is he, what is he saying?
Yes, right? So what can I read into that? Right. So the righteous
live again as part of the day of the Lord. And it's fun
actually like there's an again, this is this is not a piece of
dogma, okay? But a couple of episodes back, you heard me finish
without the episode by reading from the
gospel of Nicodemus talking about the harrowing of hell.
The interesting frame that I didn't read as part of that is that sometime after the
resurrection, there's this conversation going on and I think they actually have an
NIS and Caiaphas become believers, I think within this text, if I remember correctly.
That's not the important point though.
The important point is there was a discussion about the harrowing of hell and I think it's
Demis says to these other Jewish leaders.
Well, if you want to know what happened down there,
do you remember when these people rose from the dead?
When Jesus died?
Well, two of them were the sons of Simeon who received Jesus into his arms when Jesus was a baby.
And these two sons of Simeon are living in this town nearby and they're just praying night and day.
Maybe we can get them to come here and tell us what it is that they saw down there in Hades.
when they were there.
and everything went down.
So that this bit from Matthew is used as a sort of a framing
device for that passage, which is so powerful.
And I mean, I'm not saying that I believe
that that is literally what happened
and that whoever wrote that text is saying
that that's literally what happened,
but as a way to introduce, you know,
transmitting that tradition to us,
that's the frame that's used within the scope of that text.
And I don't...
need to accept that as being a historical document in the sense that we think about those things now like it's a newspaper article, you know,
but rather the point is it's expressing this is what happens when Christ Harrow's hell.
And I've never seen it written in any better way actually, frankly.
Yeah, and so
All of this is gonna happen on on the day of the Lord and so because of that what we find in the Psalms
particularly other places as well but particularly the solbs because this is
hemnography right are these calls for God to come and to come out of his
holiness and come to visit right to come from his throne right where he's
seated and in throne to come and judge the earth right to come and do this to
come and have this visit have this day bring about justice restore restore them
And so the way those calls are phrased is forgot to arise.
Meaning from his start to arise.
And in Greek it is honesty at various forms of the verb that are used in these Psalms to describe this.
You know the one that should jump to mind if you've been listening to our past episodes is probably Psalm 82, 81 in the Greek.
Right.
Verse 6, right, arise, O God, and judge the earth.
Not so.
O Theos, right.
You shall inherit from all the nations, right?
But there's a ton of them, and I'm going to rattle these off.
They'll be in the transcript at some point.
And you'll cause.
There you go.
Pause the recording of this later.
We're not going to read them all, but these are just a sample from the Psalms.
7.7.6.9.19.10.12.12.5.17.13.
1868 verse 1, 74 verse 22, 102 verse 13, and then I threw in Isaiah 33 verse 10.
That's the other one from Isaiah, where it's calling on God to using that verb, arrive.
Right.
And many of those, if you, when you could posit or transcript it or what have you, if you
look those up, you'll see that several of those are actually used as the prochemanon,
they're so
right before we read the resurrection appearance gospels in
Mattins in Orthoros. So they're done immediately as
a leading. Right. And they're calling on this. And so this
means that the day of the Lord also becomes known as the day
when God will arise to come to judge. It becomes
the day of Anastasis. Right? And so when in our Pascahemnography, on Pascah and we're still doing it
now for the whole Pascah season, when we sing, for example, this is the day of resurrection. This is the
day of Anastasis. Yeah. And also, this is the day that the Lord has made. Yes. That doesn't just mean,
Hey, God's giving us another day.
Yeah, no.
trees and flowers and butterflies. No, this is the day that the Lord has appointed.
This is the day he set aside. This is the day that he made for all of this to go down.
Right. Which is how it fits. Right. We have this sequence when we're singing the
Possible verses, you know, of God arising and his enemies being scattered, and smoke vanishing,
and wax melting. And then it's like, this is the day the Lord has made. Let's rejoice and be glad.
Yeah, yeah, it's not like a non-sign.
right? Yeah, it's this is the day. That's why we're rejoicing and that's why we're glad.
Because God has come to visit His people and establish justice and that's what we're celebrating on POSCO.
We're celebrating the Anastasis. And the New Testament, particularly St. John's Gospel,
really establish this point that Christ is.
the Anastasis. Yeah. And Christ is Yahweh the God of Israel visiting his people. Right. Right. And I think sometimes when
when people celebrate POSCO or Easter, they have the sense of again, this takes us back to that resuscitation
versus resurrection thing. You know, like, oh, he, like he made it. Like that's, that's the way I think some people
feel about it. I'm like, like he did, but he made it.
you know, they brought him back.
That's the way it's taken sometimes.
And obviously it's super charged with the sense of he did it
for himself or the God, the Father raised him
or the Spirit raised him, right?
I mean, these are all, this is all biblical language.
But still, I think it's the sense of like everything was risked
and it looked like he died, but he made it.
But actually what's going on here is this is him.
I mean, we talked about the hearing of hell,
a couple of episodes ago.
But this is in a sense, this is now what's going on everywhere else all at the same time, right?
You know, like there's this great hymn that we say, it's said by the priest during the divine liturgy.
It's also done at the end of the the
proskemiy service, and I think there's a couple of other places to where we say,
in the grave with the body, but in Hades with the soul as God,
God and in paradise with the thief and on the throne with the
father in the spirit of his style, Christ, filling all things
I self unsurcrubscribed. In other words, he was doing, he was
harrowing hell, his body was in the crave, he was, you know,
meeting the thief in paradise, and he was on his throne, you
know, raining with God, the father and the spirit all at the
same time. This is all this is so in some sense, this, this
episode is continuing to talk about everything that happens
in the resurrection, you know, that it's that it is, as you
said, it's just arising, he's standing up now to offer
Judgment on the world.
Which as you said is bad news for some beings and good news for others based on where they are are they unjust then they're going to be you know
Put in their place if they're just then they'll be justified, you know, they're they're they're vindicated
They're put back, you know where they should be
in a good way yeah and
And one of the ways St. John really brings this out in Christ's identity.
Right? And this is another one of those pieces of the Gospel writers do full well that they
were saying Jesus is God. They were saying he's Yahweh the God of Israel, right? Who? Because
this arising is arising from his throne in the heavens and coming to earth to visit his
people, right? And so when St. John says, that's what Christ is doing, right? The Christ is
the anestheties, that's what he means.
But in John...
on 11 verses 23 through 25. There's kind of a subtle wordplay going on in the Greek that
doesn't necessarily come out in English. And this gets a little thorny. So I'm going
to go through it slowly. Yeah. So this is the raising of Lazarus. And it's the little
dialogue that Jesus has with St. Martha right before he calls Lazarus forth from the grave.
Right, she has sort of gone out to meet Christ as he's arriving from her perspective.
arriving too late. Right? Because she's said, she's already said that, you know, if you
had been here Lazarus wouldn't have died. Right? So in verse 23, Jesus says to her, your
brother will rise again. Right? Literally your brother will rise. Your brother will,
and it's honesty. It's that verb. Right? Your brother will rise. Right? And so St. Martha,
Here's the...
interprets it as Christ saying that St. Lazarus was a righteous man. He's one of the
righteous. And so can he be part of that resurrection? Right. When the day comes he
will be one of those who is restored who shines like the stars. He will be one
of those. Yeah. And so we know that that's how she heard it because in verse 24
Martha says, I know that he will rise again. I know that he will honesty and in
English it's in the resurrection right I know that he will
honesty in Eonastasis, right?
He will rise when that day comes,
when the inastasis happens, right?
When God visits his people, yes, I know.
He was a righteous man.
He will rise.
You'll be one of those who rises when that day comes.
And then she says, at the last day, right?
So she's referring specifically to that event.
When the day of the Lord comes
and the anastasis happens, then he will rise.
Verse 25, Jesus responds to her and says, I am a go-a-me. He spells it out, which you don't have to in Greek. That's why it's so important. You don't need to put the a-o there.
Yeah, yeah, you can he can just said me right yeah, yeah, he me covers it right
He says but he says I am invoking obviously
all of that for the Old Testament, the resurrection, the
inostasis and the life, right? So he is, he says, I, I am the
inostasis. So he identifies himself, Christ, I
did it by himself in that verse as Yahweh, the God of
Israel, who has come to visit his people, meaning Lazarus
doesn't have to wait. Yeah, right. Lazarus doesn't have to
this is happening now.
The day of the Lord has come.
And now would it be correct to say it's in progress,
even now, 2,000 years later.
Well, no.
But we'll get to that.
All right.
I'll get to the third half.
Yeah.
But so if you understand that, if you understand that exchange
and that Greek wordplay of what Christ is saying there,
then all of a sudden the troparian that we sing,
Alright, the raises.
go of Lazarus, the apolitikian of Lazarus Saturday makes a lot more sense.
Yeah, and then we sing on Lazarus Saturday and then the next day in Palm Sunday and it
brings all this together. So this is what it is in the version that we use.
O Christ God, when thou disraised Lazarus from the dead before thy passion,
thou disconfirm the universal resurrection, wherefore we like babes carry the insignia of triumph
and victory and cry to the old vanquisher of death.
Huzan in the high end.
blessed is he that cometh in the name of the Lord. So you've got all this imagery there of not just
raising Lazarus from the dead, but then it's connected to that to the resurrection, right? But then
also triumph and victory, destroying death and blessed is he that cometh in the name of the Lord,
cometh to do what? He's bringing the day of the Lord. That's why he's arrived. All of that is coming
there. Yeah, you know, it's interesting to me.
A lot of times you hear sermons on Palm Sunday where, and this is not wrong, right?
They'll kind of put out the irony.
Like, well, today they're saying, you know, blesses he that come with the name of the
Lord, but then, but, you know, in a few days they're going to be saying, Crucifan, Crucifan,
which is accurate, of course.
But the himnography, actually, for Palm Sunday is nowhere ironic like that.
Because I think it's underlining like, no, they're right when they say that this is the
day of the Lord.
When they're saying, blesses he who comes in the name of the Lord.
correct. Now.
they don't really understand the full import of what they're saying, but, but that's correct.
And so we're going to say that with them. This is the day.
Right. Right. And universal resurrection is not my favorite translation in that because
it, we think of universal meaning, oh, well, just, you know, what do you raise Lazarus?
That showed that everybody's got to rise from the dead, right? No, right.
And it's actually like some translations have this, the resurrection of the universe.
That's right. The cosmic resurrection.
Right. So Lazarus, rising is the sign. Right.
It's the sign that's given at the time that to show, to St. Martha and everyone else,
that what Christ just said about the day of the Lord having come is true. Is the fact that
Lazarus isn't waiting around. He's already risen. And that confirms that the whole cosmos,
the Anastasis of the Cosmos.
Now is...
is coming. Right? And so that's why throughout the New Testament, the New Testament authors,
the apostles will refer to the time we're living in, that they were living in the beginning
of and we're living in the second millennium of, or the, sorry, the third millennium of,
is the last days, the latter days, the last days. Because we're in that window that we
for exact others.
plenty of other prophets who talk about it, but that we saw the prophet Isaiah talking about
between the day of the Lord and the final judgment.
Yeah, so there were in the period where he rules in the midst of his enemies.
Right.
So the day about more about that in our next episode.
Yeah, yeah, right.
We're going to a future episode.
People play in Bingo out there.
That's right.
Our second episode in two weeks, right?
Lord of the Spirit's Bingo.
Yeah, in two weeks it's gonna be essential.
and then a couple weeks after that, we're going to talk about
Pentecost, so it's going to be fun. Yeah, so the day the Lord has come, we are now in the last days
and then there's this final wrap-up that's going to occur.
And we'll be doing Lord of Spirits episodes until then. God will it.
I don't want to live that long. So yeah, who knows how long that's going to happen.
If I make it to 90 I'm gonna wake up every morning and just look around and be like
like really? Seriously? Yeah, I mean, yeah, you know, three score years and ten, four score
years, more than those, the 200. Yeah. Yeah. So all right, well, that wraps up the first
half of our show. So we're going to go ahead and go to break and we'll be back and we'll
be taking your calls. Father Andrew Stephen, Daymak and Father Stephen
DeYoung will be back in a moment to take your calls on the next part of the Lord of
spirits. Give them a call at 855
5, 2, 3, 7, 2, 3, 4, 6.
That's 855 AF Radio.
Big in Heaven,
a collection of short stories available now
on the Ancient Faith Book Store.
Sometimes poignant, sometimes funny,
sometimes heartbreaking, sometimes convicting.
These stories of life in an inner city immigrant Orthodox
or guarantee to SH-
shake your assumptions and make you see your life and faith in a new way.
They are not for the faint of heart, but they are very much for all who want to embrace
the truth more fully.
And you didn't have to ask Rusk over for help, cleaning, polishing, carrying, inter-out.
Any work in the church, the woman was a stalled, a talladeesh you could count on.
No one knew her suffering.
never bother to look at her.
eyes. It surprised me the most of the church folks at St. Alexander the
Rolling Dervish parish didn't even know her name. It wasn't anything they'd
thought about. To find this book and others like it you can go to store.AncientFaith.com.
Again that is store.AncientFaith.com.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits, the Father Andrew Stephen Damick and
and father Steven to young. If you have a question, call...
Now at 855-237-2346, that's 855-AF radio.
Welcome back.
We are now at the second half of the show, and this is where we begin to take your calls.
And like you just heard, the voice of Steve said, it's 855-AF radio.
That's how you connect with us.
And we actually do have a caller waiting, but I'm not exactly sure who this is.
So, uh, Collar, can you hear me?
he will be a staff for the righteous
wait for them to stand and not to fall
Jury did you play the recording again there?
what's going on?
I hope of those who should I keep going?
I should keep going.
Also, I have to say, when you do that live read every single episode
you nail it at the beginning.
Ladies and gentlemen, the voice of Steve.
Yeah, Calculon is a one-take robot.
I mean, I get it every time.
Bobby, that's pretty good. I mean...
I like, are you almost made me believe that that that
that Judy was playing playing the recording? So nice.
Yeah. Yeah. Long time vote. So over contributor.
First time caller. Thanks for taking my question.
So, so, so, so before we get too deep into the gagels,
which I know we can do, I, you know, because you guys are
talking about post resurrection appearances of Christ.
And I guess the question that I want to toss out to you is
something that father Steve alluded to earlier when he
mentioned Genesis.
chapter three, which includes a pre-
manifestation of the Lord, right?
The walking in the garden, the hearing of the feet,
the footsteps.
But the question that I have is, in the hymn of Cassia Nii,
which we sing on the matins of Holy Wednesday,
she draws a connection between the feet of Christ,
the feet that the sinful woman washed with her hair
and the feet that were in the garden.
and into this question of like post.
versus pre. What does that mean for a lord that in this resurrected body walks around
with a wound in his side and enters this room where the doors were locked? I'm not trying
to ask a time travel question. I don't know if I'm asking a time travel question.
These are the questions that my wife hates. She actually fast-forward through a lot of
calls. No offense callers, but what could it say? But yeah, T.C., whatever you watch Star Trek,
is like it's a time travel episode I'm leaving.
Like a-
They're hard to write. They're
hardly they're hard to write.
So so okay, so your question basically is
is the the God who walks in the garden
is that the resurrected Christ?
Is it the same body? You know, like
maybe that's a way to phrase it.
Is it the same body?
Is it the same feet that are that
the sinful woman is wiping?
That that that that Adam and Eve
here in the garden?
Maybe that's the way to ask you.
Although even then, like...
She's doing that before he's crucified before, you know, like obviously there's lots of
time he whimmy wibbly wobbly.
I'm not actually a doctor who fan, but I know that phrase.
Yeah, you said it backwards.
Well, that proves I'm not actually a houvian.
I tried and they became too creepy for me.
What can I say?
Sorry, houvians.
And that's for what it's been.
There's only sad years of catch-up to do.
Right?
That's from Blink, which is one of the best episodes.
Is it?
from season.
three of the new series.
I think it's episode 10.
Anyway, of course you can just rattle that off.
Congratulations.
Thank you.
You're welcome.
So right, OK, so what is the relationship between?
Because I mean, I think I have some idea of this,
but I mean, I don't know, lay some of it out.
And part of the answer to this question actually
is so just to pull the veil off a little bit
for everybody, part of the answer to this question
is, you know, see the second half of this episode, right?
But but but but but
can take it head on initially. So help us out here, Father Stephen.
So the question is, are they the same feet is the same body?
The answer is yes. There you go.
Thanks. Thanks for thanks. I appreciate it.
Right.
To say a couple of other things, and let the reader understand, or the
here understand I guess.
in this case that someone keeps moving my chair.
Oh, see, I got that one.
I caught that reference.
So Captain America, I caught that right.
You catching that reference was a reference to the exception
sound.
That's right.
That guy out there who hates the giggles on this show right now
is out of his mind.
He's going out of his mind.
Yes.
But the say somewhere is part of-
I think what's getting asked in this question aside from the wibbly wobbly time you want me to bits is
I think partly it appears question because sometimes it's depicted that way at orthodox iconography like you can find icons of the creation of man
Where it's Christ right the way he looks in the incarnation in the icons of Christ right like forming Adam out of mud
Yeah, I have one of those right here in my studio.
have him creating the sun and the moon.
Yeah.
And so in so far as it's a question of like when Moses was sitting there talking to Christ,
was he seeing the form that the disciples saw?
the visual thing that gets complicated, that's part of
what we're going to be talking about in this half.
And so, because there's this degree to which,
after the resurrection, Jesus didn't look like Jesus.
Yeah.
And even more so in the book of Revelation,
St. John sees Christ, right?
It's the same person who he was like leaning on
at the mystical supper, right?
And he's like bronze and has...
Uh...
white, woolly hair, but he still knows exactly who it is.
So the yes is to identity.
The yes is not necessarily to the way in which it was visually
is he was experienced by human eyes.
Right. Yeah, I mean when Moses sees the aims of the Lord in the burning bush
That is our Lord Jesus
But he's not seeing him the way that
You know Thomas saw him when he said my Lord and my God
Well, he's his act of seeing is the same
Yeah, there you go, right, but right he describes that experience is different. Yeah, it's different
Right, but there's
there's still an identity there.
Right.
We are at a very visual age where for us,
I dended one of the big factors that I did it, right?
Your ID card has a photo.
Yeah, right.
Right.
That's how you prove you are, who you say you are,
is a photo ID, right?
Here's a picture.
Here's me.
They look the same.
Take your mask off, right?
But that's not when you have a society
They can't even think of a camera.
right? That's not how you identify people. Right? That's that's not your sense of
identity isn't what you look like. Right? When you've seen you know a not very
good quality reflection of yourself on occasion. You know? Yeah. Right. Your
image is not who you are. Right? I would say now today and I think social media
has really brought this home that the image we put out there is not who we are.
And we probably know it.
But it sort of it sort of never was.
So that that gets into another aspect of what we're about to talk about in this half.
And so if you want to just hang around Steve for the next 45 minutes, I mean.
We could spend an entire time. I'm sure you just answering questions from Steve.
Yeah, well, I mean, I've got to talk you guys into the next commercial break.
Yeah. Yeah.
So all right. Well, all right. Well, I'm just going to leave you unmuted.
If you
If you have something really important that you want to ask about, but remember this
is not your show, okay, Steve.
So I know boundaries, I appreciate boundaries.
I don't want people to think that we're suddenly having quote unquote guests on the show.
So it's just a collar.
But anyway, yeah.
A persistent collar is overstated.
Exactly.
Well, there you go.
Yeah, so voice of Steve, everybody.
That's great.
Round of applause.
Thank you.
All right.
Okay, so all right father
Christ's resurrection appearances, we mentioned these are in the the they're what are called the aothenon gospels
that are in
The there's 11 of them in in mans on Sundays
um and
We hear him over and over again. I mean just we do all 11 and then we do all 11 again. We just keep doing it until
until the
You know till lint starts right
Actually, it even continues into Lent, if I remember correctly.
So like, you know, this year's lens is actually affected by last year's PASCA.
You know, these, these, these same, the same cycle continues on and on.
And then it finally resets then when you get to Palm Sunday is actually when it finally
resets.
So okay, Christ appears.
So let's actually talk about some of those, what's going on there when Christ appears.
Right.
the Prochimena.
Right, right, right, setting the stage for what was going to happen and recovered a bit of what happened.
And so now this is the next thing, right, this is the next thing that happens, right.
But these are resurrection appearances, right.
These are resurrection gospels, right.
So what's going on in these series of stories in the final chapters of the gospels
And in these appearances is...
heart and parcel of what a Nostasis is. It's part of that reality. So we have, actually,
before any of the Gospels were written, St. Paul was already writing his epistles.
Yeah, they're older.
In his first canonical epistle to the Corinthians, which wasn't the first one he wrote,
he refers to a previous one. In chapter 15 this is sort of well known.
I think by people as sort of the resurrection chapter, right?
This is the Anastasis chapter.
This is a chapter where St. Paul is talking about Christ resurrection and our resurrection
and sort of laying all that out.
And so he begins that discussion in verses three through eight by laying out sort of what
a lot of people think is an early credal statement.
sort of a really statement of an early account.
of the gospel. Yeah. Okay. I'm going to read this to everybody so you can get
over talking about this. This is 1 Corinthians chapter 15 verses 3 through 8.
For I delivered to you first of all that which I also received that Christ died
for our sins according to the Scriptures and that he was buried and that he
rose again the third day according to the Scriptures and that he was seen by
by Seifus, then by the Twelve. After that he was seen by over 500 brethren at once.
of whom the greater part remained to the present but some have fallen asleep. After that he was seen
by James then by all the apostles, then last of all he was seen by me also as one born out of due time.
And it's interesting like he says, now I'm going to deliver to you this gospel that I received
and he lists off, you know, four things. He died, he was buried, he rose again, and he was seen,
and he was seen and he was seen and he was seen and he was seen
Like for Paul, this is part of what the gospel is as he was seeing him.
Right. And actually most of the text, right, for
about that, right?
Here's our words is about these resurrection appearances.
Right. Right. He covers Christ, crucifixion, burial, and
rising in, you know, two verses and then
spends three on listing these, sorry, spends four or five,
listing these appearances. Right. Yeah.
Um
And so clearly these appearances are of greater import to St. Paul in terms of his argument
about the salvation of humanity.
St. Paul sees the resurrection in appearances as playing this important role which would
explain why we read them over and over again in our Sunday mat and services.
This is the church in her liturgical work.
The partnership has carried on this sense of importance that St. Paul already saw in the 50s AD.
So nonetheless, the way this is read, this list is read by most modern people, regardless of their sort of background or theological commitments or otherwise,
is this is read as St. Paul is presenting about
of evidence. Yeah, right. So St. Paul, you know, says this that Christ was crucified and
that he was buried, he doesn't think he has to prove that, right? That's a matter of
Roman record, right? Nobody's, nobody's disputing that. But then he says Christ rose from the
dead. And so he's expecting that there are going to be some people who dispute that. And
so he's like, well, I'm going to give evidence. I'm going to name all these witnesses,
right to to to to prove my case
that Christ rose from the dead.
And there are examples of this sort of across
the ideological spectrum when it comes from the Bible.
One on the, what we would call the more liberal side.
Now Rudolph Boltman is not a 19th century German liberal.
But he's not as well-be sorry.
It's a mid 20th century German neo-liberal.
Yeah.
That's it.
He said about this passage.
And his comments on this passage was that he found it very strange and surprising that
St. Paul thought that giving evidence for Christ's resurrection would help prove his case.
Yeah, right.
Like he thought that was weird.
This comes from something we talked about.
or whoever's last time of the time before,
I bash 19th century German liberals so much,
it's hard to keep track.
It's like this.
It's sort of,
positivist, this 19th century,
positivist view of history, right?
Where we can have this scientific understanding
of exactly what happened, right?
And you apply this methodology and we determine what happened.
And so, you can look at that and say, well, look,
You know, we've read David Hume.
testimony can ever prove that a miracle happened because a miracle is so far
outside the bounds of nature that the amount of evidence you would need to
believe it can never be supplied by fallible humans. Therefore we can't believe it.
So Boltman looks at it and says, well, listing a bunch of people who claimed
they saw Jesus doesn't, doesn't prove anything. Yeah. This can't be a historical
event because people don't rise from the dead.
right so this has to be a spiritual some kind of spiritual event or metaphor or
Something in the immaterial realm that he that that St Paul is talking about and so why is why is he talking about evidence
And so then we also talked about how the response to that from most conservative
Protestant and Roman Catholic
Scholars Bible scholars has been rather than
and staking out at other positions has been to take
that same definition of history and then just to insist that no, what the Bible gives
us is exactly that kind of objective, prospective-less, mathematical, scientific kind of history.
Yes.
So, trying to satisfy the historical, you know, the historical, critical method.
Right.
And so, Josh McDowell and son, I'm not meaning to pick on them, they're just, they're
the highest
profile people who have done this, who have taken this evidential approach to
Christ's resurrection appearances very publicly and are famous for it.
Say, okay, well no, St. Paul is giving evidence and this is good evidence.
Right? And this testimony is good.
And this proves Jesus rose from the dead.
Right?
Right.
And that's not a solution to the problem either.
As St Paul was
not a 19th century German and didn't understand history that way. And isn't trying to, isn't
here trying to give evidence, right? That's not why he lists this. As we're all, we were
already talking about it and as we're about to talk about further, there are other reasons
why Saint Paul sees these appearances as crucially important to the Christian Church.
part of the gospel. Yeah, right. Yeah, right. Right. Yeah. And I think a lot of this thing.
is we can kind of wipe away that whole question of evidence by asking this question.
Why does almost no one seem to recognize Jesus after he rises from the dead?
Right.
Is the reason why?
Yeah, exactly.
As a way to describe this, because if this is supposed to be quote unquote evidence for
the resurrection of Jesus, then why include the detail that they didn't recognize them?
undercuts that argument.
Right, you know, well, they saw somebody who knows who that was, you know, if you were manufacturing
manufacturing stories, right, if you were manufacturing
evident testimony, right?
There are all kinds of things in these stories that you would definitely not include and
this element of
people not recognizing Jesus after the resurrection, like, I mean, this is basic, right?
your whole idea of testable
would be if you're gonna have someone testify to the fact that Jesus rose from the dead, it would be,
yeah, I saw Jesus die and then later I saw him alive, right?
I just same guy. Yeah, basic and it's the same guy. Yeah, I can't find put him in a lineup and identify him.
Yeah, but that's not what's going on over and over again. You get this detail that
some people like who is this or that they have no idea who he is even though they totally knew him before
You know, right over and over. You have you know
in Matthew 28 verse 17, all of these people are gathered on this mountain in Galilee,
where Christ is. They all see Him there and it tells us in Matthew 20 verse 17 they worshiped
Him but some doubted. Yeah, right. That's another one of those phrases you're like, I don't know what
that means. We're just going to keep reading. Right. Some doubted that He's standing right there.
right? Like, what? Why?
Why would anyone doubt if he's standing right there, right? Yeah, there's something about him that is not the same
Right and the memory that they had
Right and you and you see
Now we have to we have to do a brief. I'm not going all the way down the rabbit trail. I promise
but
St. Mark's gospel is
is the gospel that if you go with what's called the shorter ending of Mark.
where it ends in Mark 16, verse 8,
there are no resurrection appearances
in the St. Mark's Gospel, properly speaking.
Right?
The second eothenean is from St. Mark's Gospel,
but it's the women, the Holy Marbeurs,
coming to the tomb and seeing that Jesus isn't there,
and then that's it.
There are another 12 verses that are,
that are referred to.
was the longer there's some other stuff too. But anyway,
it refers to as the longer ending of Mark. This could get really
granular. I'm fighting my urge to get into it because I'm a
nerd. This is hard. But there are these other versions.
There were first was the longer ending of Mark, these other 12
verses. And those other 12 verses, when you read them are sort of
summary of I was out like clear narration
of resurrection appearances. It's sort of a summary of a bunch of resurrection appearances,
some of which are in other gospels. Like it refers to Christ appearing to two of them while
they were walking on the road, which seems to be a reference to the road to Emmaus in St. Luke's
gospel. Right. And that kind of thing. And so there's all this back and forth in scholarship about
whether that's part of St. Mark's gospel or not. But there's like a really simple solution to it
if you're familiar with the ortho-
selectionary because those extra 12 verses are the 30 Athenian gospel. So they
come after Mark 16 1 through 8 is the second Eaphvenin and before the beginning
of the ones from Saint Luke's gospel. So there are actually several little pieces
of scripture like this. The woman taking adultery is one of them. There are little
parcels versus where in our
New Testament manuscripts, they show up in different places.
Sometimes they're admitted, sometimes they're in a different gospel, sometimes they're in a different place in the same gospel.
And so your typical practitioner of biblical scholarship amongst our Protestant friends will say based on that well,
It's not quote-unquote original, just ignore it, get rid of it, don't worry about it, not in the Bible.
Because there's this concept that the Bible consists of a series of continuous texts known as the Gospel according to St. Matthew or the Gospel, you know, whatever, rather than the way that these texts actually were used initially, which is as lectionary readings.
Right. And just shy of half, a little over 40% of the New Testament manuscripts we have today are lectionary manuscripts.
If you buy a
a critical addition of the Greek New Testament,
there are precisely two of them
that were incorporated into it.
Not 2%, two, like one, two.
All right, so there are literally thousands
like 2,400 or so, little more than that.
Of New Testament manuscripts
whose readings you do not find
in critical Greek New Testament.
the patriarchal Greek tech.
that the patriarch of Constantinople put out in 1904 and it was revised in 1912, used 250 of those
lecturearies to put together its text. But so even with that there's thousands of lectureary
texts not taken into account. If you're copying from a lectureary into a continuous text,
So someone wants a copy of the Bible for themselves for their own study.
We're going to be giving a copy of the Scriptures to someone.
A bishop comes to visit the monastery, and so we're going to have one of our copyists
make him a beautiful text of the Scriptures to give to him as a gift to take back to his
cathedral.
The texts you have to copy from, in a lot of cases, are your lexionary texts.
You've got the gospel book, the epistle book.
So when you take a copy from those, you run into things like the
D. Athena. Yeah. Well, where does that go? Well, we can't shove it into the middle of Luke to put it before
E. Athena and for Luke's gospel. That wouldn't make any sense in the reading. But if we put it at the
end of St. Mark's gospel, it kind of makes sense because he doesn't have any resurrection appearances.
Yeah. Right. And so if, for example, at different monasteries or different churches,
the gospel reading about the woman taking it adultery was
read on different days, it would fall in different places in the
lectionary. And so when a copy of the Gospel of St. John was made
from those lectionaries, it would occur in different places when
you copied it. So there's really a simple explanation for that.
All that is to say, there is a Mark 16 verse 14, right? So if we
take this longer ending, right?
Or if you'd rather...
If you want to be super dogmatic about it, in verse 6 of the 30th Evening, Christ basically
upgrades his disciples for not believing that he was risen from the dead.
Yeah, which is an interesting point because it says, you know, in that verse, he rebukes
them because they did not believe those who had seen him after he had risen.
So what you're getting then is...
You know, this bit that's stuck at the end of Mark where it's referring to things that
didn't happen anywhere else in Mark's Gospel.
Yeah.
But so even in St. Mark's Gospel, if we take that longer reading, here again we have this
weird thing where people who, people have seen him and they don't believe it.
Right.
St. Luke's Gospel, right, the road to Emmaus is probably a famous one of these where Christ
is walking on the road with two people.
those two people are talking to Christ about Christ.
Right. They're talking to Jesus of Nazareth about Jesus of Nazareth
and don't recognize that they're talking to Jesus of Nazareth.
Yes, this is the one that I refer to as the feast day that comes to our church here in Emmaus once every 11 weeks.
Yeah. And actually, we have... So folks, if you ever come to St. Paul's here in Emmaus, Pennsylvania,
You will see on the outside of the church great big icon of Christ sitting down at the table and
eating with St. Luke and Cleopas, breaking bread with them there. And that's the moment that they recognize him.
After having this whole conversation with him on the road, I always get these jokes.
Like, so do you live on the road to a man? I'm like, no, I live in a man's. I live on the roads in a man's.
Not to road to a man's. That's known as Alan Town. That's the road to a man's.
But yeah, that they have this whole chat with him and then it's only at the end that they finally
they recognize him for who he is.
So again, after he's explained the whole Bible to them.
Yeah, right, right.
And not just explained the Bible, but explain how the Bible applies to him, you know.
Yes, yeah.
All the things in the scriptures concerning himself.
Right, right.
Yeah.
And so you see this in, you see this again in another well known one, John 20,
verses 14 through 16, right?
We're St. Mary Magdalene, turns around and is looking right at Jesus.
Thinks he's the Gardener?
Right. And asks him where he put Jesus. Right. So asks Christ where Christ is while she's looking right at him.
And it's only when he then says her name all of a sudden he recognizes him. Yeah. And then you have it in the next chapter in this is what are the weirdest ones in terms of how it's phrased.
in John 20
or sorry John 21 verse 4 right Christ is walking on the shore they're fishing they see him
they don't know that it's Jesus then in verse 12 once they've come ashore they're getting ready
to eat with him there's this phrase that St John uses no one asked him who he was because they knew
it was the Lord yeah which suggests that on the one hand they are not sure who this is
That's why no one dared ask him.
You know, like it's on their minds,
like, should we say, who are you?
You know, and yet they somehow they know
that it's the Lord.
Right. Like no one says on Sunday, right,
after liturgy at my parish,
they wouldn't say, well, none of us asked who the priest was
because we knew it was Father Stephen.
Right. Right.
And it was not saying to say, yeah.
Right. It would just be, yeah,
our priest is Father Stephen, right.
So even though they now know it's him,
You
not because they recognize him and it's not until verse 20 in the same chapter, it says
then the disciples were glad when they saw the Lord. So they know it's him but they haven't
seen it's him yet. Right. Verse six verses. So yes, this is this pattern that we see in
the resurrection appearances of Christ through all the gospels.
that is weird and especially makes no sense if these are supposed to be evidence
that he rose from the dead. Yeah right because if you were to present this as
evidence any cross examining attorney worth their salt would look at this and
say they weren't sure it was him. Yeah right this is bad evidence. Right this is
not a good ID this is not a good witness ID right. If you told them that yeah we
That'll work.
up and at first they didn't recognize them, but then all of a sudden they did and now they're totally
sure that would not go over in court. And the amazement is the worst because they literally spend
all this time having a conversation with them. And they're like so wait, so you're saying, you know,
counselor that your witness here had this whole conversation, then only later said, oh yeah,
Yeah, that was Jesus.
Yeah, it's terrible evidence.
Right.
So.
Why are the gospel writers presenting us this shift
between seeing Jesus and seeing the Lord, right?
Seeing this person standing in front of them
and seeing the Lord, right?
And where do we have a parallel for that in the gospels?
And that's one place that's the mount of transfiguration.
Right.
Where they go up on the mountain,
Peter James and John go up on the mountain,
they know they're there with Jesus.
They've been...
with him, they went up there with him and then he's transfigured in front of them and they see him
for who he is. They actually see the Lord of glory in his glory.
Right and so that is what is being described in these resurrection appearances.
Right. They're glad when they see Lord because Christ reveals his glory to them. This is talking
talking about his divine identity.
Yeah, it does not necessarily mean you here.
It doesn't necessarily mean that they saw some kind of blinding light.
Right. Right. Like it's not it doesn't say that.
But he reveals himself in glory to them, because his glory is, as he said, it's who he is.
It's his identity. Yeah. Right. Right. So this isn't ID card identity. Right.
This isn't a picture. This isn't what the person in front of me looks like.
They're identical. The shape of their nose and the shape of their eyes. Right. Right.
like, like, like, like, like, like, like?
These resurrectional appearances are,
and we've hammered this 20 times now,
they're not evidence that he rose from the dead,
they are revelations of who he is.
They're, it is a revelation of Christ.
And this is one of the reasons,
I mean you could say that he spends 40 days with them.
You know, he appears to them,
clearly he appears to them many, many times
that aren't mentioned in the scriptures.
You know, he appears, he's with them for 40 days
and appears to them many times.
And then...
ascends into heaven. So there's revelation that's going on here. Right, and this is, yeah,
this is this is a Christ presenting his divine identity to them. So it's after on the
road to Emmaus, they understand the scriptures and what the scriptures say concerning Christ
after the breaking of the bread, which is pretty obviously to everybody, you know,
Right, this is when they see
that Christ is Yahweh the God of Israel, which means God has come to visit his people,
which means the day of the Lord has come.
Yeah, yeah.
You know, I wanted to give a fun detail that, so there was a senior Ukrainian priest who
lived here in our area for a while named Father Basil Zaviruka.
It took me years to learn to pronounce his last name and then God blessed him.
He died.
I loved that man.
And one of the things that he told me about, which I had no idea, when I first met him,
So you're the...
in the man's and I said yeah. He said, did you know that a lot of the Byzantine churches in
southern Italy during that period that the icon that was in the apps of the church? So in other
words, if you don't know where the apps is everybody, that's the usually curved wall that is right behind
the altar. So if the priest is standing at the altar and he's offering the divine liturgy, he's
looking across the altar and the apps is what's sort of
in front of him, that the icon that was placed in the apps rather than being as you see in many churches,
you know, the community apostles or sometimes the crucifixion of the resurrection, various things
like that, that often it was the supper of the mass. And so you think about that as being not just
a eucharistic image, but this is a revelation of Christ in his glory that's right there in front
of the altar. It's pretty cool. So I just wanted to share that image and his memory. So yeah, okay,
so it's in.
You can't present evidence that Jesus of Nazareth is Yahweh the God who created the universe.
Yeah, like what evidence?
Like on the what basis would you say that this is the right evidence to show that?
Right.
But he saw that he was.
They saw that he was, but like if you're a forensic investigator, whatever,
it's not like you can pull out your book and say, okay, so this is what we're looking for.
If we're going to expect to see Yahweh the God of Israel.
You know that Jesus is him like there's no there's no book for that right you know, but so when you have what you have
State Paul doing instead as he says Christ is crucified and dies according to the scriptures
He's buried it rises again
According to the scriptures he repeats that phrase yeah, and then he appears he appears he appears so when he says according to the scriptures
What's he saying he's saying that
Christ is back there he's talking about the Old Testament New Testament had been written yet
Christ is back there in the Scriptures, right?
And the testimony to the fact that Christ
is the God who revealed Himself to the fathers of old,
in the Old Testament, is that He was seen to be that,
that the day of the Lord has come, that the fulfillment of those
Scriptures has come specifically in Christ.
And the places where the sort of
places where people see the Lord have this experience of seeing the Lord in the Old Testament
or when prophets are called as prophets.
Yes.
And that vision is stuff, like the way it's actually described in the scriptures are scenes
where it's unmistakable what they're seeing.
For instance, Isaiah sees God enthroned in glory.
So it's clear that he's seeing God or Moses, for instance, sees him up on top of the mountain
and he understands that's where you meet God.
You know, like this is, or, or, you know,
the vision of Ezekiel God in his chariot throne, right?
It's, they're seeing God and thrown.
They're seeing God acting as God.
You know, it's unmistakable who they're seeing.
This is the prophetic experience
that is what makes them prophets.
And the vision is then accompanied by them being
sent. And that verb in the Greek of these of these prophetic commissions is
Apostello. That's where we get the word Apostle. That's where we get the
noun Apostle. That's what makes someone an Apostle. They're sent on a mission.
And this idea is preserved really well in the Arabic language at which I am at
best a dabbler but this bit I know.
And that's that there there are actually two words in Arabic I mean there's probably more but there are two main words that are used for a prophet.
And those words are na'b which is from the Semitic root in Hebrew it's na'b if you've studied other languages beyond English you know that the bus sounded the bus sound tend to be the same consonant in most languages.
Yeah.
Right. So it's Navi, the implural to the Navi-eam, the prophets that are part of the Hebrew Bible, but it's Navi in
Arabic, but then there's also the word Rasul. Rasul, right? And that word is also used for the Apostles. Right. It's used for both the prophets and the Apostles. You could say,
Ilyas Arosul, alaistah prophet, or bulus Arosul, Paul the
apostle but it's literally the same word in both cases in Arabic.
And the way this has been distinguished in Arabic is that a Nabi is someone who
brings a message right he comes and he he brings a message whereas a Rasul is
someone who receives a message from God himself right who has this direct
contact with God Himself.
and then conveys it. So all of the
resoules, every resoules is a
is a is a no-b, but not every no-b is a
resoule. Right. Right. And so by using
that word for the apostles, that
word contains the idea that the
apostles saw the Lord and received
the message and the commission
directly from the Lord and then
went and brought it that it was.
was at second hand. And so that they're able to convey through that terminology a lot of what's going on with St. Paul when he's defending his claim to be in apostle that he didn't get at second hand, that he received it directly from the Lord, but also what he's doing again in in 1 Corinthians 15, that the apostles are those who had this prophetic experience, this apostolic experience of seeing the Lord face to face, and that that happened in these resurrection.
directions, appearances.
Awesome.
All right, well that wraps up the second half,
and we will be back in just a moment
with the third half of the Lord of Spirits.
We'll be back.
Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Steven DeYoung
will be back in a moment to take your calls
on the next part of the Lord of Spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF radio.
Saint Ignatius, 1st century bishop of Antioch, called the Godbearer, is one of the earliest
witnesses to the truth of Christ and the nature of the Christian life.
Tradition tells us that as a small child, Ignatius was singled out by Jesus Himself as
an example of the child-like faith all Christians must possess.
Inbearing God, Father Andrew Damick recounts the life of this great pastor, martyr, and
safe.
And interprets for the modern reader five major themes in the past store letters he wrote.
martyrdom salvation and Christ the bishop the unity of the church and the eucharist.
For Ignatius martyrdom is really the fullness of christ the might in a sense which that can be challenging for us because
number one he doesn't seem to have any reticence at all about going to martyrdom like there's no sense of well this will have to do
have to do, you know, I wish I didn't have to, but this was God for me. He is going to it.
to find this book and others like it.
You can go to store.enginefaith.com.
Again, that is store.enginefaith.com.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits,
the Father Andrew Stephen Damick
and Father Stephen DeYoung.
If you have a question, call now at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF Radio.
you know
now I'm not sure whether that Steve or whether it's Steve, you know, is it life or is mysterious?
Indeed. Okay, well we actually do have another caller. So Alex is calling in and he has a question
about life after death. So Alex, can you hear us? Alex, are you there?
I think we might have lost Alex.
I'll say Alex kid and he got lost.
lost in miracle world. See, that's a reference I didn't get. But I giggled anyway just, you know,
yeah. It's okay. Yeah. Right. All right. Well, Oh, Alex, are you there? I am. Hello. Yes. We,
he made it. All right. Yeah. Thank you. Welcome, Alex to the Lord of Spirits. What is your
question, comment and situation accusation? That's. Yes. My question is about our
Rxp
experience of afterlife or the age to come.
As far as I know, my question kind of blurs the two together.
So I was raised Catholic, so I have the image
of the lake of fire in my head for hell
and the garden for paradise.
Both just part of what I, as far as I know,
we're going to experience.
As I was Christmas and have been Orthodox for a while, what I've been hearing was no
experience of the H. DeCon is not going to be a created fire, but instead hell is going
to be those who hate God, feel the presence of God in a hellish way.
those who love God, experience that presence of God in a way of paradise.
But then listening to the spiritual geography that doesn't quite mesh well and that I'm back
to the lake of fire and guard enough paradise.
Yeah.
So you're kind of wondering what is the deal, right?
So this is something you see a lot on the internet.
this idea that hell is heaven differently experienced. I think that's the way I've
seen it summarized that view. So I don't know. I mean I I think the thing that
I'll say about this before I hand it over to Father Stephen is there are
different ways of trying to describe exactly what the experience of the life of
age to come is.
and they get at it from different angles sometimes.
Some are wrong, some are right,
and can be even if the particular images
aren't reconcilable with each other,
they can still be right,
but simply looking at things from different angles, right?
So certainly as we know,
Hell and Death do get cast in like a fire.
That's in the scripture, right?
That's not a made up idea from somewhere else.
That is part of the picture.
so we can't just throw that out.
because it's in Scripture.
But then again, the idea that there is this cartoon sort of caverns that are with lava in them
and there's demons sticking forks in everybody's butts and that's what damnation is about.
And that's not really true because that is a sort of materialistic understanding of what the age to come is about.
So, anyway, that's what I would have to say about that.
Father...
why don't you go ahead and help us all out here?
Well, you don't know what it's like to be a dead bat.
Right.
Right. That's the problem.
That's that is that is that that really is the core of the problem.
We, we, right.
So when we talk about the life of the age to come, right,
where we're going past a period where our human soul conscious
our life will be separated from our material body for a period. We don't know what that's going to be like because we haven't experienced it, right?
And then we're going to even pass that to the renewed heavens, the renewed earth that have been transfigured by the grace and glory of God.
And what that's going to be like and then what that's
going to be like for whoever it is, hopefully very few who experience eternal condemnation.
We have no way to get at what it's going to be like for the demons at that point, right,
in our condemnation because we don't know what it's like to be a demon now.
So because we can't know that, right, the Bible presents us with a lot of imagery, but
I think deliberately to keep us from being able to take any event.
to sort of materially, literally a lot of its contradictory, right?
Like a lake of fire and outer darkness are contradictory.
Right. Right.
These are two different images.
And then we have this other image of weeping and gnashing and teeth, which is actually an image of madness.
So they're competing images.
They're all bad, right?
Maybe I'll give us a negative idea of what that experience is.
kids is like, but they can't convey that experience because there's not an
analogy. There's not a way across the gap between our human experience in this
age and that until we get there. This is why, you know, why it says, you know,
what we will be has not yet been made known, right? We know we'll be like him
because we'll see him as he is, but, right? And St. Paul talking about seeing
through a glass darkly now right so we can't we can't fully know it so
So the problem with the sort of material like a fire thing is again, it's taking one of
those images at the expense of the others and kind of overly materializing and literalizing
it.
There are other, I mean a lot of that imagery related to two.
So for example, that we use the Orthodox Church in addition to, right, God's going to be
all in all.
So what does it even mean that someone is going to be outside of everything?
Yeah.
What does it mean for a person?
to not exist in the sense of madness and chaos.
But an imagery you'll hear is that in our salvation,
we become more truly human and more fully human.
And then the opposite of that is applied
to what happens in eternal condemnation
as people losing their humanity.
Well, what does it mean to lose your human nature
and not take on the nature of anything else?
Yeah, and you know I'll add...
this is that one of the problems that I've seen is taking these things that are in scripture,
which remember is given to us by God through the apostles and prophets for our salvation,
taking a certain image in scripture and using it essentially to negate something else.
Right?
So for instance, the idea that God is going to be all in all, there are some people who
use that to say, well then that means that there can't be any, you know,
damnation. That's not a thing. And yet it's very clearly says in other places that it is totally a thing.
Right. So the point is is that attempting to use human reason to reconcile these things and
usually the way it's done is they're not reconciled. It's just one part is pushed to the side.
Right. It's just simply not going to work. Right. You know, so we're not trying to fall back on the
bad thing. Although sure it's fun. But...
But it's true, right? It's true. Like we don't know what that's about and there's places
in the scripture that explicitly say to us, we don't know what that's about.
Or where we have these images, but we can't go past that.
And this is related to the hermeneutic issue we were talking about earlier in that, and
this is true quite literally from the first chapter of Genesis to the last chapter of
Revelation. The scriptures weren't written to answer our questions.
Yeah, at our curious.
and explain the mysteries of the universe to us.
Right? God didn't write or, you know, inspire,
give the vision to the Prophet Moses to write, you know,
Genesis 1 and 2, to explain to us how he created the world.
Right? That's not why that's there.
And the last chapters of Revelation are not there
because God wanted to answer our curiosity and explain to us exactly what
the life of the age to come is about, right?
So we got to go with not just how do we reconcile these images in a rationalistic way,
but what is each of those images being used to say?
And quick rule of thumb here, all those images are to say, don't let this happen to you.
Yes, right.
Don't repent.
Don't just be you.
Repent for the kingdom of God is a thing.
Repent.
I mean, that is the message of the Scripture.
Repent for the kingdom of God is in hand.
The Lord has arrived.
that that road of sin seems
awful nice now, but here's what's at the end of that road where you will end up if you go down it, right?
It's this very bad place. So it's not to give you all the details about exactly how bad it's going to be.
It's just to say this is really bad. Don't go there, right? Take this other road instead.
Does that answer your question, Alex? Both yes and no. Yeah, right. I've got new questions now. Yeah.
I might follow up on Facebook.
Okay, well we also have Pedro on the line.
So Pedro welcome the Lord of Spheres podcast.
Hello, Father's Christ is risen.
He truly is risen.
No, not the exact verbiage.
Exactly.
It has a certain ephonias quality.
It's euphonias.
Yes, to say he truly is risen.
is risen.
If you touch on this a little bit, both in your answer to the last question, and previously,
you know, we were talking about, for example, Boltman.
My question is largely about the value of, and you know, Father Steven, I apologize, if
this sounds like a loaded question coming from me because I promise it's not.
I'm not talking about toll houses.
No, no, I'm not talking about toll houses.
Okay, okay.
That was a one shot, you know.
Um, the value of engaging.
and that kind of secular materialist approach to making sense of the data of scripture and spiritual reality.
Right? So, you know, you have people like John P. Meyer who wrote a five soon to be six volume,
you know, thousands of pages on the historical Jesus.
You know, who, you know, in his process, he says that this is an impossible figure to reconstruct.
Right, you have people at the Boltzmann who have kicked off a great
of research in that same area.
And you have people who try to make sense
of what that historical data might actually tell us
about sort of quote the true story,
and quote behind what scripture has to say.
And so, you know, is there value in engaging
with that kind of scholarship?
And if so, what's the benefit for us
as orthodox, Christian, to where, you know,
we don't know what it's like to be a dead bat.
And I hopefully most of us are trying not to know
what it's like to be a 19th century.
German materialist. This is all you father Steven. Okay. I'm not even gonna I mean I could say
something but whatever you go ahead. Right. Let me start by heaping further condemnation on 19th century
no. Yeah. I want to be well I want to be clear before I say what I'm going to part of what I'm
I'm going to say an answer your question. I want to be utterly clear in
just how vain, void, and worthless,
I think that whole project is.
In case I haven't been enough.
But this modernist thinking,
in fact, even very conservative Orthodox people, right?
You, there are plenty of well-meaning good scholars,
good Orthodox scholars out there,
fine Orthodox Christians,
Holy
than me by a lot. That's not saying much. I'm a low bar, but still. Who take this approach
to the faith or take this approach to the scripture that, for example, you know, each biblical
text means this one thing. And if we apply the right methodology to it, this sort of pseudoscientific
methodology, we can extract that one thing, right? Or they may not even apply the methodology,
they may just pick up.
favorite church father or favorite group of church fathers and say, well, they said it means this.
So that is what it means, right?
No further anything necessary.
Each of you guys won me, we can establish it.
And so the Orthodox faith is, I have my spreadsheet and the columns are different areas of theology
and I need to fill in the correct values in each field and then I am truly Orthodox.
Right?
There's going to be a test.
Yeah.
And where you find those, right?
that same kind of...
modernist thinking and and going back and trying to reconsider like I'm going to go into church history and I'm going to
Reconstruct the history of this and that will tell me what the the accurate Orthodox belief is right that that I can then fill
Into my field and anyone who doesn't share it I will you know batter for not really being worth it
and and so I have
no love for this approach. I don't think it's worthwhile.
to actually exercise this approach in any field of scholarship at all.
Okay, so let me be utterly clear on that. Okay. Um, now that being said in terms of
why would I say somebody was doing a master's thesis that I recommended a
bunch of books to them by scholars using this approach, right?
Why would I be so unlikely?
Much has literally happened between the two.
Why would I do something like that? Right?
Well, because
Despite the flawed methodology, right, what that methodology teaches you to do is basically
go in and tear apart a text and go in there and try and look for all of the archaeological
data, all of the intertextual data, all of this stuff, and then based on your bad methodology
you will draw a lot of dumb conclusions from it.
You've also compiled all of that data.
of that information surrounding the text and related to the text. And there are things
that I have ideas or chains of thinking about parts of Scripture and stuff that have
really opened things up for me that I've gotten from some horrible, radical nutbag scholars.
But they said something where I was like, well, wait a second.
I feel like there should be some reference to stealing the adj-
Gold here, you're wondering the yeah,
yeah, wondering the Egyptians, right?
Where, you know, they take it to the total wrong place and I come to a totally
different conclusion, but they help me see some piece of data or they help me
make some connection between some extra biblical piece of literature and
scripture or some ancient custom and some culture, right?
or something right and so
they're doing a lot of work, right?
I mean, you said this yourself, right?
Myer, like basically says, I'm about to embark
on an impossible project and it spends decades
and thousands of pages on that impossible project, right?
So yes, he's right, it's an impossible project,
his methodology is wrong, it's not gonna bear any fruit
at the end, but you've got all those pages of research
and material that you can take and do something else with,
Something
better with. That is that is related to what God is actually saying in in scripture.
So that makes it. There you go, Pedro. Yeah, absolutely. I still have to read that stuff.
I'm going to say two quick talks. One, I get a few spoken through the Myer book.
And two, you know, so outside of people who hypothetically are working on a master's thesis,
Alright.
What is the, is there a thing for people who aren't engaged in being in, you know,
acupuncture, scholarship, sort of, you know, the general orthodox layman?
I, you know, what I would say to that is there can be, but it's super important to have someone
help you who knows what they're doing. Because it's so easy, it's so easy if, and I don't know,
I doubt that this-
applies to you, Pedro, because I know you.
But it's so easy.
I mean, I did this when I was younger a lot.
You read some book and it blows you away
because it's talking about stuff
you've never heard before.
Right?
And then that becomes your skill.
It's in key for everything else.
You judge everything else.
You're like, wow, now I have the key to the scripture.
Now I understand, you know, whatever it might be.
And like, well, while I wouldn't devalue
the experience of having a mind blown
by something you've never seen before,
like that's really cool and very helpful.
at the same
time it's important not to let it take you into really weird places.
Like I've watched people, otherwise smart people, utterly go off the deep end because they
became obsessed about aliens or about, you know, trying to figure out what it means
that God can, you know, right, predestination, you know, whatever.
They pick some peace, right?
And then their whole theology becomes about that thing.
right? Right. Right. Right. Right. Right. Right. Right. Right. Right. Right. Right. Right. Right. And I mean, I've seen people do this to like they'll pick a particular church father, for instance, and like everyone should be reading this church father. I'm like, he's great. The stuff he says is good. But what you just expected every Orthodox Christian to do. The vast majority 99.999% of them throughout the history of the world could never have done that. And even now most of them still couldn't and never would. Yeah.
know, so to make one particular teacher, one particular approach, whatever it might be,
whatever is rocking your world at the moment and make that the thing by which you judge
everything else, the single canon, that's a problem, right?
The scripture says that there's wisdom in many counselors, if I remember the quote correctly.
So that's what I would say about that.
I don't know if fathers Stephen have any additional corrects for that.
Well yeah, it's partially just an addition to that idea.
that orthodoxy is having the correct values of the correct fields, right? So people will
before they read a book, they'll be like, well, is this book orthodox? Is it fully orthodox?
Is everything in it orthodox? Is there anything in it that's problematic? And if there is anything
they won't read it, or if they find out it is, then they're like, okay, well, I'm just going
to believe every word, right? This is the truth then, right? So it's either the Bible or it's nothing,
right? I've said a few times that a lot of orthodox folks read the fathers the way
Evangelical fundamentalists read the Bible and read the Bible the way evangelical fundamentalists read the fathers.
It's either this or nothing.
And that's about to happen. It's about to break.
Right. The Orthodox Church is not here to teach you the precise and accurate meeting of each text of Scripture.
Right. The Orthodox Church, however, will help you learn how to read Scripture.
Right. So what to think it's how to think? Yeah.
And since we're on this long wonderful actually this is it's a digression
But this is actually a perennial thing we discuss in this show
An article that I read by father George Florowski really beautifully described and he said that these categories overlap
But he described three categories that there's dogma. There's doctrine and there's theology
You know with dogma everybody needs to be exactly on the same page
You know these are the core things of our faith right that Christ is God that you know father Sunhoi spirit is
God. You know, these things are core.
Doctrine is the way that you teach those dogmas,
and there could be a little bit more flexibility on that.
Teaching changes over the years in terms of the way that you teach something.
And then theology is reflection on those other two categories.
And the truth is that most of the things that are said by Orthodox theologians
and writers are in that third category, which means it's okay to disagree,
as long as what you're saying is consistent with the dogma of the church.
So, okay to disagree.
You know, it's all right. It's okay, everybody. It's okay.
So, you know, even this particular program, right, we're saying a lot of things that could be wrong.
People maybe never heard some of them before. Certainly stuff I've never heard before.
And that's okay. You know, take what's good, leave what doesn't help you, get on with your life.
So anyway, that turned into a rant but
Is that helpful to you Pedro?
Yeah, absolutely.
One last cryptic note that I won't expand upon here just to channelize everyone.
Maybe at some point in the future I will.
If you understand the Church Father's correctly, they never disagree about the interpretation of scripture.
There we go.
So done, done, done. Okay. All right. Well, thanks for calling Pedro.
Good to have you on the show tonight. Thank God. All right. Okay. So let's talk about
We're gonna finish.
up in this third half, we're going to talk about some of these appearances that St. Paul
lists off. Right? So the first one that he that we want to talk about is the merbarras.
And of course in the most orthodox churches, two Sundays after Pazka is the Sunday of the
merbarras. So we're talking about these women that came to the tomb of Christ to come in
anoint his body and then they discover that he's not there, that he's risen from the dead.
when they go back.
tell the apostles and they don't believe them.
Right?
You know, same Mary Magdalene, of course,
is called the Apostle to the Apostles
because she goes and preaches the resurrection to them
and they don't believe her.
My favorite bit is where when Christ is talking
to St. Luke and Clipus on the road to Emmaus,
and one of them says, you know,
they literally are talking about the resurrection.
You know, the some women of our company amazed us
and said that it's
He even seen a vision of angels who told him that he was alive, but these words seemed
to us on idle tale.
And as the one detail you pointed out to me, Father, when we were doing our prep is like,
one of the women who is one of the merbers is St. Mary, the wife of Clampus.
And Clampus is one of the two that are on the road with him to a man.
So he's literally saying, so my wife said, but that seemed to me to be an idle tale.
Dude, your own wife!
Your own wife!
Come on man
But there's something deeper in here actually right why is it the women get this first right and this may not
You know, we we're modern people and
So we want we want to it might not be apparent to us why it would be so shocking from an ancient perspective
That the first people to see
Christ risen would be a bunch of women
Yeah, and again if you were trying to write a propaganda piece
favoring Christ's resurrection.
from the dead. If you're in the first century, you do not put women as your primary witnesses.
Right.
Women can't give witness in the ancient world.
Right. They could not testify in court. They could not testify to the truth of the matter.
Because people's attitude toward them is exactly what you see reflected by the disciples,
by the male disciples. Right. Yeah. Yeah. Some women said this. We were kind of amazed,
kind of crazy. Right. You know women. Right. So that wouldn't be something you would
construct, right? But so why is it a description? Well, this is part of a
pattern that you see repeatedly in the Old Testament, probably the most famous one,
and people get super happy about me talking about the book of Judges.
But is with the prophet Isdemura and Barak, where Barak is called to be the judge of Israel.
I mean, he's not called to sit on the bench and hear cases.
He's called to be the man who steps up and restores justice.
Right, too.
Thank you.
to the people of Israel from there for interpressors,
and he chickens out and whips out and fails.
And so God does not leave his people to suffer
because Barak failed, but raises up the prophetist Debra
and another woman, Jail, this is the whole tent peg
through the temple thing.
Yeah.
To, he raises up these women to deliver Israel instead.
He does it through women.
And this is
to embarrass Barak.
Right, right.
The idea is they looked down on women,
considered women to be weaker,
considered women to be less than.
And so the fact that he went out
and that this woman came and did his job for him
is sort of putting him back in his place, right?
You see the same thing with Moses,
what he's confronted by his wife, Zapura,
about not having circumcised his children, right?
Where's Zapura has to go and do it?
with
which was his responsibility, and she has to go do it to stop God from killing Moses,
as how it's actually presented, in Exodus has to save his life.
And so it's not coincidental that while the murdering women, while the holy murderers
are on their way to the tomb to anoint Jesus' body, the male disciples are all hiding in
a room with the doors locked because they're scared to death, that they're going to get
executed too and so they're in hiding.
Whereas the women embark to go and do and give honor to Jesus.
And even though they don't have a good plan, right, they're kind of halfway there.
They're like, hey, who's going to roll away the stone from the tomb for us, right?
But they go in and they get to work, right?
And so, if what's happening, as we've just said, is that when Christ is appearing to these disciples,
He's making these disciples apostles. He's sending them all.
mission right he's sending them on a mission then who are going to be the first
people you said well the ones who take their duties seriously and who aren't
scared right so the women disciples are given this gift of being the first
disciples to become apostles yep yep awesome okay so the second one that we
wanted to talk about is when Christ appears to see Peter.
If I remember correctly if you're looking at the Eothenon Gospels, this is the very last one, isn't it?
The one, yeah, in St. John where
Christ restores Peter by asking him, you know, do you love me? Do you love me? Do you love me?
And so you might ask the question, well, why does he ask him three times?
times, you know, do you love me? And you know, number one, the question do you love me is not
Peter.
How do you really feel about me?
Right, that's not what love is.
That is not what love is.
That is.
Do you think I'm a good guy?
Yeah, right.
How is our friendship, Peter?
You know, that's not what it is.
Love is to sacrifice yourself for the other.
It's about loyalty, right?
So basically, he's saying, Peter, are you
going to be loyal to me from now on?
Because you left.
you know, um, and so he asks him three
times and as the fathers say, why does he ask him three times? Because Peter denied him three times.
And so it's to bring him back. You know, but there's something there's some fun
textual stuff lurking under there. In English it says, do you love me? Do you love me? Do you love
me? Some people look down and they see that there's two different Greek verbs in there
that refer to love and they say, oh, there's something going on here other than just the English word
love. Is that true, Father Steven? Yeah. So if you weren't mad at me about the judges
thing, get ready to get mad at me now. All right. Because I mean, this preach is like crazy.
People have preached beautiful sermons on this. Yes. Yes. Unfortunately, it's not true.
Yeah. And CS Lewis kind of writes a whole book about this is where we're going to make people
hit us. CS Lewis writes a whole book called The Four Loves, which is a lovely book. A
lovely book. Yeah and you can make this thing.
about love. I'm just saying they don't hold up grammatically, right?
Right.
Right. Right.
So the idea is something along the lines of when when Christ first asks St. Peter if he loves
him, he uses the verb ayapato, which is, you know, ayapi.
I got to be in the noun for which is, yeah, which, you know, they want to say is this is
love and then he uses
of Filleaux in the second two times.
He also switches lambs and lambs and sheep.
And sometimes people draw something out with that too,
but the love one is the one they tend to focus on.
And they say, well, Christ is sort of condescending
by switching the verb because they want to say
that Filleaux is sort of love like friendship.
Brotherly love, yeah.
Yeah.
And like.
Philadelphia. Yeah, just like in Philadelphia. So it's always sunny there. I heard. But anyway,
so in fact, not always, yeah, sunny in Philadelphia. Yeah. So here's the problem with that. If you're
going to argue that linguistically, if you're going to argue that contextually with St. John,
you have to show that St. John uses those terms different ways consistently in his writing.
Right, right, right, or at least in his gospel at least and say John's gospel you
have to be able to go through and say,
we'll see, look, when he uses his one verb,
he means this, when he uses his other verb, he means that.
And that's not what you get if you read St. John's Gospel
in Greek.
Yeah.
What you get is that he uses the two words interchangeably.
All right.
Right.
And then, you know, sort of exhibit A is that phrase,
again, we see in English, the disciple whom Jesus loved,
that gets described with those different verbs.
Yeah.
Loved in there, you don't see it in English,
because they both get translated loved.
but rate.
He alternates the verbs and that doesn't mean there's one disciple who Christ loves with divine love
And then another disciple who he's just friends with
Right
Or the relationship with John is going back and forth between you right right. Yeah, no, it's literally
It's literally a synonym. It's literally a synonym everybody and this is reflected by the fathers safe
John Chrysostom don't take my word for it say John Chrysostom's Greek was a lot better than mine
He says
very explicitly that Christ asked Saint Peter the exact same question three times.
Yeah.
So it just is or and I'm sorry I had to do that to people.
I hate that there's some Sunday school and humbly think I hate ruining for people.
Right. There's also no linguistic relationship between a layson and carrying a layson and olive oil.
But anyway, I won't go into that now.
But so that the key here is that
Peter is being contrasted with Judas.
Yes, both of them betray and deny Christ.
St. Peter, Repencin is restored by Christ.
Judas goes and destroys himself.
That's the key contrast that's going on here.
Yeah.
Which honestly, that to me is a much better homily than the agape Philea one.
But yeah.
Okay, so the next one we wanted to talk about, we sort of already talked about...
a little bit so we don't have to say too much about it I think is you know the
11 who Christ appears to them finally right what were they spending most their
time doing hiding and then later fishing like literally they saw the Lord
and then like and then they went back to their boats guys guys that you have a
job to do here you know right yeah yeah and you could say well Christ told
them to wait for the Holy Spirit it's like yeah he told them to wait
there. Right. Jerusalem, which is where pedicost happened. Yeah. Yeah. Back to
Galilee and fishing. And again, if this is apostolic propaganda, this is this
makes them look bad. So it's badly done propaganda. If that's what the claim is
that this is all just propaganda. Right. Because our defense attorney would say, oh, he
appeared to you, risen from the dead and sent you to go baptized and make disciples.
and that's why you went back to fishing.
Right.
Okay.
So another major appearance is to the saint who's called the brother of the Lord and that's
James.
St. James was the first bishop of Jerusalem.
Why do we know that it appears to St. James?
One mention of it.
First Corinthians 157, St. Paul says that it appeared to James.
doesn't say what that's about, but there actually is context from the
and church which does say what it's about. So what is going on there, Father?
Well, so we have these data points about St. James and Scripture. Right. We have one
data point which is in the Gospels that says that he and the other brothers of the Lord
did not believe that Jesus was the Christ during his earthly ministry before his crucifixion.
We then have this data point from St. Paul in first grade.
that Christ appeared to him after the resurrection.
There's a resurrection appearance to St. James.
And then we have in the book of Acts,
he's just in charge of the Church of Jerusalem.
Right.
So even if we had no historical record about what happened
from our forefathers in the Christian faith,
it seems like a pretty good, just Occam's razor
or way of working out what happened is that
But in that appearance, after the resurrection, Christ put St. James in charge of the church
in Jerusalem.
Yep.
Right?
I mean, that would seem to be a basis.
But the fact is we have all kinds of historical records, both in sort of pseudopagrapha, in
like Eusebius and his church histories and other church histories, that say precisely
that.
That when Christ appeared to St. James, he put him in charge.
You may have the overseer, the Episcopal, the Bishop.
of the the church of Jerusalem and then we see that he's in charge of the church of Jerusalem
unquestioned by anybody in the book of Acts that he's the one in in in charge. Yeah, I think
that last point you made is a good one like for instance when the Apostolic council comes up and he's
the one who kind of gives the sentence at the end you know if he had just been sort of appointed
there by the apostles like if he was a successor to the apostles you couldn't he wouldn't be
present.
hiding over them. You know, they would have said, well, that's
nice St. James, but sit down, you know, the older brothers are
talking here, whatever. But no, he's clearly the local, you know,
to use the the the common English room. He's the local ordinary,
right? He's the bishop of that place. So he's the one who's
going to give the sentence. So yeah, right. And so yeah. And so
there's a basically that we alluded to in answering Pedro's
question where for some reason
Well, I know why there's a historical reason, but we're at a state now where a lot of our Christian friends
Will believe everything pagans write about ancient history
But nothing that Christians write about ancient history outside of the Bible
Yeah, right
So if anything about the apostles anything about the theotokos anything about any biblical figure or the early church
that's written out. Well, that's not the Bible. So, you know, I don't...
I don't believe any of it, but you know, Plutarch's lives, oh yeah, yeah, Julie Caesar stabbed 23 times.
Florida Senate, oh yeah, yeah, all that happened.
Right.
So the pagans are all telling the truth that the Christians are all liars.
Does it make a lot of sense as a Christian perspective on historical restworthiness?
Right.
Okay, so a couple more appearances that we want to go over.
So here's the one that's numerically the biggest word.
Jesus appears to 500 people at a time.
What's that all about?
Maybe this seems like the best candidate
for being quote unquote evidence of the resurrection.
Look at all those people he appeared to, you know.
But that's not what's going on there.
Because again, it's not a test it in a way
that would sort of hold up in court again, right?
But something else happened.
He would have had to name three, right?
Yeah, yeah
He's saying, oh, he paid 500 people.
He paid 500 people.
And here are their names.
Yeah.
Again, it's bad.
It's bad evidence.
It's not evidence.
That's not what the purpose of it.
Right.
So yeah, yeah, it's OK.
So it's this vision of Christ being given to all
of these people at the same time.
This goes back to some of the stuff
that we've talked about before, about prophets,
and also about the people of God, like gathering,
for instance on a mountain to worship him.
So yeah, unpack this for us a bit.
Right.
Well, this, we went through a short list of people who saw God in the Old Testament.
Yeah.
Right.
And it was a short list.
It's these few prophets, right.
And a similar list, not to tease too much our Pentecost episode, but in four weeks.
But that list is roughly the same as the list of people in the Old Testament who were told
had the Holy Spirit dwelling within them.
Right profits the king
Maybe the high priest but not all of the high priests some of them right
It's this this few the select few right whereas what we see here in St Paul is emphasizing is now it's
Hey 500 in a time
Right, so there is this new accessibility the vision of God and we'll be talking about this much more in the Pentecost episode
with the coming of the Holy Spirit.
This is
something that's now available and this commissioning to be sent out is
something that's now available to everyone in Christ. Yeah, not just to this
select few. Right. Yeah, there's been this big change that has occurred that
everyone can now receive the Holy Spirit. Everyone is sent out as the
up Emma series of God to retake the world on his behalf. Yeah, it's it's it's
pretty cool stuff. Okay, last.
but almost certainly, certainly not least, the chosen vessel himself, St Paul the Apostle,
the patron of our church right here in Emmaus. He describes himself, what you get in English
Bible as he says, and to me last of all, as one born out of time or one out of time, which is frankly
a really sort of euphemistic way of saying an abortion. He describes himself as being like an
and abortion.
Like you know a child that is miscarried
Right that's that's how he describes himself in comparison to everybody else
He doesn't just mean oh, yeah, I was one of the last ones
That's not what he's saying. It's actually this very negative and kind of visceral
Image why would he use that word?
Right, well, this is this is Saint Paul taking something that was used against him by his opponents and owning it
So it was much like the word Chris.
which was like those little crates, you know, they're like,
oh yeah, we'll take that. We'll be called Christians.
And so he takes, this was both a way of mocking his physical appearance.
We have a couple places, extra canonical, of course,
that kind of describe St. Paul's personal appearance,
and it's not pretty.
And so it's partly that, but also this was a contrast between
between this familial language is what's being used in the early
church, right? We see this in the book of Acts, the brethren. The way of saying the Christians in a
place is the brethren of that place, right? Brothers and sisters because of the importance of the
sons of God, right, as what salvation is about, right? So if the other apostles are sons, right?
St. Paul is this abortion, this rejected child, right?
This, you know, lesser sort of.
And so...
St. Paul rather than being angry and oh man I'm gonna take him down and I'm gonna right
But as opposed just takes it and owns it in his humility and says yeah, you know
I it was me last of all yeah, I am compared to them, you know
I'll use all use the word abortion about myself
But in the next verse that we didn't read earlier he says because
right the reason he accepts it is because
because he was out there killing the brethren.
He was out there persecuting the church.
He was a murderer.
He's like, yeah, you know what?
I wasn't worthy of it.
I'm least of all worthy of it.
So yeah, I'll take that.
I'll take that.
I'm still a child, but I'll take the unwanted.
It's extreme humility.
Yeah, which is interesting how it's coupled
with his great boldness at the same time.
Yeah.
Yeah, so all right. Well, those are the we can't we could say post resurrection, but that's not really the right one. These are the resurrect the appearances of the resurrected Christ in glory to various people.
And again, you know, if you're one takeaway is, wow, I really need to go to Sunday
Mattins, then we have succeeded, right?
But we just want to offer some some final thoughts about this.
Yeah.
For-
For me, I mean, as I said, one takeaway is, you know, go to Mattens, okay?
On Sunday, it's such an amazing service for lots of reasons, but the gospel readings are
particularly powerful.
And to keep having them given over and over again is really an amazing experience.
And it's a ritual participation in those events that we are there with them, right?
And so what is that experience then?
As we said, this is not just an epilogue.
to like oh the big action already happened, you know, he suffered, he died, he rose from the dead. Yay
You know, that's not what's going on. It's it's not just a denumon. It's not just evidence like oh, yes
Jesus really did rise from the dead and here's the proof because as we showed
It's not very good proof. It's not very good evidence. So what actually is going on? So one of the central
claims of the gospel is this question of
Who is Jesus Christ?
Who is he?
And these resurrection appearances of Christ
answer that question.
Now they don't give all that you could say about it,
but they answer that question.
He is the Lord of glory, right?
He is one with his father.
All of that, he is the one who sends his apostles
out into the world to baptize, to teach, to exercise,
to make disciples all-
these things, that's who he is. And so we should really regard these gospel passages as very
precious to us because they reveal to us the risen Jesus Christ. Not just reveal to us
that he is risen, but who he is, that he is God, that he is truly the first born from among
the dead. Right? That is the one that they
revealed to us. And the whole point of this doing this thing we called Christianity is to
know Jesus Christ, to know Him who's sent by the Father and that Father who sent Him,
right? That's what Jesus Christ Himself says. This is eternal life that they may know
the only true God in Jesus Christ from that was sent. He said that. We don't learn who Jesus Christ
is as a kind of set of data like, okay, I've got this Jesus stuff down now. Now I'm going to move
on to other things about Christianity.
That this is Christianity.
to know him, to see him, to have this vision of him.
Now, it may be the case that you're not having miraculous visions of him the way that these people did,
but there are certainly people throughout the history of church, the church who have.
And we trust their testimony because it's consistent with the stuff that's came before
and because we see the fruit that happens in their lives as a result of those visions.
Right? It may not satisfy those who are using the historical critical method.
method but let's face it.
That method, while useful for certain things, is not useful for everything.
And it's certainly not useful for determining is this person truly the son of God.
It can't cover that.
It's just not a good tool for that.
It's a good tool for other stuff, but not for that, right?
So what I would encourage you to do is not just to read these
gospels, although yes, to read these gospels, but, but as you read the
scriptures and particularly as you look at those
or four books, Matthew, Mark, Luke, and John, that you look there to meet Christ, to know
Christ.
That is the point of what we're doing.
Again, it's not just Christianity 101, okay, I've got that down now.
Let's do something else.
That's not it at all.
This is the whole of what it means to be Christian, is to seek for the face of Christ,
to know him, to see him.
as he is. So those are my final thoughts, Father Stephen.
So we see this dynamic play out in in
Vespers and Mattens that we've kind of been talking about the
Mattens part of it, especially tonight. And you know,
Vespers is the service where at least some of the time we
have Old Testament readings. Right. And then we come into
Man.
We come to that procurement on before the gospel and we're calling out to God to arise and
Judge the earth we're calling for the day of the Lord to come
for Christ to come and
then we read in the gospel about it coming
About Christ coming and visiting as people about the Anastasis right and about how the Anastasis
how the day of the Lord entered into the lives of these people who had
these experiences after Christ rose from the dead. But all of that is preparing us for what's
about to happen in liturgy, for us to have that same experience. In liturgy, just like
out the road to Emmaus, we read and have explained to us the scriptures and Christ in them. We have
have the breaking of the bread of the Eucharist. And then after the Eucharist we
saying we have seen
true light. We have received the heavenly spirit. We have the opportunity to have that same experience,
but the experience isn't an end in itself. We don't pursue this vision of Christ as an end in
itself. We don't pursue coming to experience Christ's resurrection as an end in itself because it
wasn't for the apostles. It's what made them apostles. It's what started
something new. This is why we start reading the Acts of the Apostles at Posca. This is the sending out.
And so every one of us at the end of the liturgy is sent out into the world.
The reason we read the Eothenon Gospels, these resurrection Gospels to the north,
is not just to tell the demons that they've lost. It's because the Apost...
are proclaiming a warning that Christ is risen.
He's warning the demons and the spiritual powers of evil
that you're coming, that you and I are now going out into the world.
And they better look out.
And so this is what the resurrection gospels call us to.
Call us to when we've had that experience of seeing the true light.
when we received Christ.
when we come to see him and know him and know who he is,
to then go out into the world and change it and execute judgment
and start to restore and transfigure it, to change it.
And we, how do we do that?
Well, we go out when we find that there's strife we act as peace-spakers
where there's despair we come with love and with hope,
where there's loneliness we come with companionship and compassion,
where there's joy.
at God's blessings we rejoice with them.
When people are mourning, we provide comfort.
When we actually go out and do that,
we can literally change the world the same way
the apostles did after they saw Christ
and went out into the world
in the acts of the apostles.
But most of the time, we, myself included, don't do that.
We go to liturgy, we celebrate the services,
We have this beautiful experience.
and then we go home and watch some TV and maybe drive past a few homeless people on the way home and ignore them.
We don't then follow through.
And the place where we experience salvation is not in the beautiful experience.
It's not in the fulfilling spiritual experience.
experience, it's in faithfully answering the call that comes with that experience.
So those are my final thoughts for today.
Thank you, Father, and thank you, voice of Steve.
I keep in listening here and this has been amazing.
I just didn't know.
Just, again, Steve is not a guest.
He was a caller.
No, I may hang her on just so it offers a, offers good feedback.
Awesome.
Exactly.
All right.
so for tonight.
Thank you everyone for listening if you did not get a chance to call in during the live broadcast
We'd love to hear from you either via email at Lord of Spirits and Ancient Faith.com or you can message us at our Lord of Spirits
Podcast Facebook page we read everything but can't respond everything but we do save what you send for possible use in future episodes
and join us for our live broadcast on the second and fourth Thursdays of the month at 7 p.m. Eastern 4 p.m. Pacific
And if you're on Facebook and Father Stephen is weirdly back
on Facebook, but it's just to vlog his book. You can like our page and join our discussion
group, leave reviews and ratings everywhere, but most importantly, share this show with
a friend whom you know is going to love it.
Yes. And on Facebook, they say I'm the greatest, but it's because I'm not that good and they're
being sarcastic.
Finally, be sure to go to ancientface.com slash support and help make sure we and lots
of other AFR podcasters stay on the air.
Thank you very much and Christ is risen. He truly is risen.
You've been listening to the Lord of Spirits with Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew
Stephen Damick and Father Stephen De Young, a listener-supported presentation of ancient
faith radio.
And I beheld and I heard the voice of many angels round about the throne and the beasts
and the elders, and the number of them was 10,000 times 10,000 and thousands of thousands,
with a loud voice.
voice worthy is the land that was slain to receive power and riches and wisdom and strength
and honor and glory and blessing.
Revelation chapter 5 verses 11-12.