He will be a staff for the righteous with which for them to stand and not to fall,
and he will be the light of the nations and the hope of those whose hearts are troubled.
All who dwell on the earth will fall down and worship him,
and they will praise and bless and celebrate with song the Lord of Spirits,
1st denoc, chapter 48, verses 4-5.
The modern world doesn't acknowledge but is nevertheless haunted by spirits, angels, demons,
and saints. In our time, many year into break free of the prison of a flat,
secular materialism, to see and to know reality as it truly is.
What is this spiritual reality like? How do we engage with it well? How do we permeate every
day life with spiritual presence? Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew Stephen
Damick and Father Stephen De Young, host this live Colin show, focused on enchantment in creation,
the union of the scene and unseen as made by God and experienced by mankind throughout history.
Welcome to the Lord of Spirits. Good evening everyone. Welcome to the Lord of Spirits podcast.
My co-host Father Stephen De Young is with me from Lafayette, Louisiana, and I am Father Andrew
Stephen Damick in Emmaus, Pennsylvania. And if you're listening to us live, you can call in at 855 AF
radio. That's 855-237-2346. And Montesca Trudy will be taking your calls tonight.
But we're going to get to your calls in the second part of today's show. So Lord of Spirits
is brought to you by our listeners. That's you with help from St. Athanasius Academy of Orthodox
Theology. St. Athanasius is an online academy for a K through 12 offering live classrooms in
core subjects, foreign languages, various electives, and orthodox studies. To learn more about
St. Athanasius Academy, please visit at www.saot.edu. And I talk to Deacon Adam again. Oh yeah.
And I wanted to just address the elephant in the room. Oh yeah. Some people may look at the St.
Athanasius Academy tuition rates. And they may be concerned. But he assured me that no matter
how many courses you take at those low, low prices, you will not add a penny to the national debt.
Well, that was my biggest concern. I can tell. I can tell. You're a deficit hawk. I know.
Oh yeah. Big time. Yeah. So, you know, one of the more difficult practices to become accustomed to
for those who look into the Orthodox Christian faith. And even for some lifelong members,
is the keeping and the veneration of relics. Relics can present a jarring conundrum on the one hand
you're being confronted with the body parts of dead people. But on the other, there are miracles
associated with them. We can think of the bones of the prophet Elijah bringing a dead man back to
life in 2 Kings 1321. Or we can think of relics like the hand of St. Mary Magdalene, which I myself
venerated in 2018 at Semenopetra monastery in Mount Athos and can confirm is actually warm just
as the living hand of a human being is warm. Do we as Orthodox Christians just point the miracles
in the history and tell people just tough it out and accept it? Or is there actually a biblical
theological reason for this? So, Father Stephen, is there? Yes. Good night everybody. Yeah.
Yeah, so there it is. So, to get there though, we need to kind of loop back and head back to some of
our most mind-bending episodes where we talked about what a body is. So, let's do a little recap
last time on Lord of Spirits now. 15th from last time on the Spirit. We have to just do previously,
previously Lord of Spirits and then clips. So, we have to start all the way back with what a body is.
Because if we're going to talk about body parts, we have to start with what the body is of which
they were part. Yeah, exactly. And so, we had to find that as being a body, as being in the ancient
understanding, nexus of powers and or potentialities. Which I understand is now a t-shirt. There's
actually a t-shirt out there. You can get there that defines a body that way. So, yes, and you could
use it to cover your nexus of powers and potentialities. Yeah, that will let you go into circle K if
you're wearing a shirt. As you should. No shoes. No shoes also. I learned that in the hard way.
So, strange things are foot at the circle K. So, and we talked about how, right, we tend to think
purely when we hear the word body, we think in terms of physical body, in terms of meat, but we
talked about how the ancient understanding God has a body in that he has powers, right? And
the angelic beings that do not have material physical bodies still have bodies because they have powers
and abilities. And so, the potentiality part, and we're going to delve into that a little more as we
go on, comes in when we start talking about material bodies. But we also talked about, and we want to
sort of rehearse here and maybe even clarify a little bit because we got some, I'll call them
questions. Yes. Rather than objections or arguments, but questions, concerns, requests for clarification
yes. As do how that body's turb relates to the terms that most folks who reads some stuff about
orthodox theology would be more familiar with like nature and will and energy and those things.
Yeah, the stuff that you see from the like the Ecumenical Councils, for instance.
Right. And we had previously said that we're talking about a translation thing, right, that the
body language was primarily language that was used in the ancient period to sort of pre-Greek
philosophical even, right? And that that's a way of describing that very early, especially the
ancient Israelite and their pagan neighbors way of viewing this and understanding a body.
And then that gets translated into other terms. And we mentioned at the time that they're
probably better terms. And that's part of what we want to talk about now is how these terms sort
of clarify in a way that's just saying body doesn't. Even though there are times where you'll see in
the fathers, for example, where they'll talk about Christ's humanity and just refer to it as his
human body. And when they do that, they're not saying that Christ's humanity was just a physical
body because that same church father will expressly deny that in other places, but they're just using
that older language still. Right. And the older language, we see it number one in the Bible,
right? Referring to what we're going to talk about this more, but for instance, the body of Christ.
Again, we shouldn't assume that these things are just metaphors. Also, we see it in pagan
usage where idols are referred to as the body of the God. They don't think that the spirits that
they're worshiping, that's not a metaphor. And it should not be taken in an utterly material sense
in the sense that they think that the spirit is confined to that piece of stone or whatever.
So this usage does exist, but as you said, it's imprecise. And what happens with the use of
Greek philosophical language is it kind of makes the distinctions a lot clearer, so that a lot of
one, when the word body is used in scripture and patristic usage, for instance, they would then use
the word nature, even though they don't exactly, perfectly map, right? Because nature, like nature can
often have a more universal sense, like human nature, like you and I share human nature, right?
Whereas body can be something that belongs to a particular being and through which that being is
working. So it doesn't exactly map one to one, but it sort of clarifies things in the patristic,
the Greek philosophical usage. Right, those are, those are similar. And yeah, there's a,
what, what happens is as the, the ancient understanding of the Christian understanding of, for
example, the incarnation or of the Holy Trinity is challenged, right? They, they need this greater
precision, right? Because you could take body in a lot of different ways, right? So when a
Paulin Arius shows up and says, well, Christ just took a human material body, right? It was just
sort of animating it, right? Then the fathers have to say, well, what, what timeout, right? No.
And they have to use more specific terminology, right, to explain why that's a misunderstanding.
And we'll delete you in the wrong direction. So to kind of run through that quickly, right?
Nature, as you're saying, is probably the closest, the most overlap, the Venn diagram has the
most overlap with the ancient sense of body. And so nature is sort of a set of powers and potentialities,
and that's over against the way we often think about nature, which is as a set of qualities or
properties. Yes, right. That an object has. Right. So if you have, if you have human nature,
then you have all the abilities that a human has. Right. You can do the things, you know, and
that's going to include the material body, but it's also going to include things like your soul,
which is not material. Right. Right. And nature is this dynamic concept, not a static concept.
Right. You don't arrive at the nature of something by just describing it in ever more minute detail.
Right. Right. Right. Nature is a function of what it is doing.
Right. And so this is, this understanding is super important when you get to Christology.
We're going to end up talking a lot about Christology tonight and the incarnation tonight,
because if you understand, well, this is basically where people run into trouble in understanding
the incarnation, because if you understand nature as this set of qualities or properties,
then you understand Christ divine nature as this one set of properties of God properties. Right.
Omniscient omnipresent. Right. And all of all of these properties. And then you understand
human nature as another list of qualities or properties like finitude, weakness. Right.
And then you look at those two subsets and you find qualities or properties that conflict
with each other. And so now that you have this problem, right. And this is when you look at
Jewish and Islamic arguments against the incarnation, that's how they're all framed.
It's just coming up with a list of divine qualities and human qualities and showing that they contradict
each other. That's their whole argument. But then all kinds of bad Christology comes from trying
to resolve this unnecessary problem. Whereas if you understand nature in this dynamic sense
as powers, Christ possesses full and complete divine powers. And he takes upon himself in addition
our human nature, meaning he takes human powers and potentialities as well in the incarnation.
Because powers and potentialities cannot conflict with each other. Right. Right. Being able to go left
and being able to go right does not contradict. Right. Being tall and being short to qualities
of properties do contradict each other. Yeah. Right. Right. So that's nature. And then the idea of
the will in the ancient concept then proceeds out of that. Yeah. So will is not the way that we
tend to think of it. Like, like, what will I have for dinner? I will have the lasagna. I will have
ice cream. Yeah, it's not that's not what will is. That's right. Yeah. Yeah. That's not choosing
to go right. Yeah. Right. Which which I think if I'm correct on this doesn't seem maximum as
the confessors say that doing that actually is kind of the result of the fall.
You know, that's not yeah. And Christ Christ doesn't sit around going, man, I don't know what to do.
Let me think about this for a while. I've got some ideas here. You know, it's not the way he functions.
Right. Right. And he definitely doesn't have two different capacities that are both doing that
at the same time. Right. If you wanted a divine one. Right. Right. Right. So when St. Max was talks about
that, yeah, he calls that the nomic will. But if you look at his language close up, he describes
that as a second movement of the will in addition to the natural movement of the will. And so if we
understand will as a movement. Right. So if nature is then this set of powers and and
potentialities, then will is a movement in a particular direction, specifically towards sort of
the perfection of that nature. So if you have an acorn, that acorn already has the nature of the
oak tree. Right. Right. Right. And that nature is expressed in the acorn almost entirely as
potentiality and has the potential to become an oak tree unless it's dead. Right. And so then
it's will and Aristotle and other early philosophers do not hesitate to use the term will for even
inanimate objects in this regard. Right. That will then is the movement sort of the internal
movement that causes it to grow toward that perfection, to grow into the oak tree. And so
when the church says that Christ has two wills, they're not saying he had two separate decision-making
faculties that were both making choices. Even that they they always agreed, they're saying that
Christ possesses the perfect divine will. Right. Which is not a movement toward perfection. That's
why there's powers and not potentiality when we talk about the divine nature. Right. Because he
already perfectly possesses it. But also then a human will which is moving toward human perfection.
Right. Right. Which of course he also achieved. And so when we talk about free will with this
understanding of the natural will, we don't mean what Western theology means. Right. Which is
Western philosophy means. Make a decision. Right. You're able to choose between contrary opposites.
Right. You're able to go left or to go right. You're able to steal the candy bar or pay for
the candy bar. Right. Yeah. It's it's freedom. It's freedom to be what it is you're supposed to be.
Right. Right. Your will is not obstructed by anything. Right. Right. So the acorn is free to grow
into the oak tree. It is not obstructed by a lack of nutrients in the soil. Kind of arrested
development. You know, yeah. Yeah. Right. Like a lack of arrested development. Right. And so this
understanding of freedom is important. Right. So from from the perspective of Orthodox Christianity,
the reason once we're in the age to come, we will not be able to fall into sin again is that we
will have perfect free will. Right. Yeah. We will be free from sin. And so we will be free to
eternally develop and draw closer to God for all eternity, because there will be nothing
of structing us from achieving that human that purpose of human nature as it was created by God
anymore. And so then finally, the term energy, which you know, we hear energy as as modern people
who have studied science, and we think wam wam wam, you know, or or ray guns or gamma rays or
something. But this is just working in the world. So this is just the will actualizing itself,
meaning producing action in the world. Yeah. The externalizing of the internal, the internal will.
Yeah, the little expressing itself. Right. And all of that is kind is to a greater or lesser extent
contained within that older understanding of body. Right. This is just kind of breaking it down
in very precise terms. Right. It gets disambiguated because it needs to be to explain the problems with
bad theology. Right. It starts arising in the early church and to really clarify who Christ is
and how this all works. Yeah. I mean, the classic example of this kind of narrative playing out
is like in scripture, it says the Lord your God, the Lord is one. Right. And but then Nysia says
that the Son of God is homoucius of one essence with the Father, which at the time was an
you know, an innovative word and theological terms. And a lot of people opposed it precisely
because it wasn't in the Bible. And yet the the Father's determined that this was the word that
was needed in order to lay out precisely how it is that the Lord that God is one, you know, the
oneness between the Father and the Son in order to counter Aryanism. So this is just another
example of that kind of thing. Right. Yeah. And so, you know, as we as Christianity moves into
different languages and faces different kinds of opposition, we sort of rearticulate things.
Right. That's not a change. That's just a clarification or rearticulation, re-explanation,
re-appropriation because every, every culture and people needs to appropriate the truths of
Christianity for itself. Right. Yeah. And some of you different forms. And you've used the word
translation. I think that's a great word for this because anyone who's done any translating
knows that translation is not just a matter of finding the word that matches the word into one
language. It matches in the original language. It doesn't, it doesn't ever quite exactly perfectly
fit. So you have to come up with other ways of expressing things that are not simply
word-for-word literal translations because you can never completely achieve that from one language
to the next. Right. You have to, you have to move from the source language to the, to an encounter
with the object being described by the source language and then describe that same object in the
target language. Right. Right. You can't just go from source language to target language.
Yeah. And, and I won't, I won't rabbit trail here but this is where all kinds of bad biblical
interpretation comes from. Oh, sure. Sure. Going from pre-pick to English without, you know,
do not pass go to not collect $200. Right. And, you know, and even just in this particular topic,
the word body has not always met the same thing just in the history of English.
It's to say nothing about the history of Greek. You know, like we're tracking it across
the Hebrew and the Greek and the Bible, then on towards the Greek being used by the early
church fathers. Right. So it's, it's none of these words ever exactly map with each other.
Right. Yeah. And then you have Heidegger, for example, saying you could only do philosophy in
Greek and German. All of the languages unsuitable. Right. Right. Yeah. And, and you know, some might
raise the request for clarification. Again, we're not going to call it an objection that, you know,
why not just understand this language, for instance, in the Bible as being a metaphor, right? But
here's why because the Bible itself does not treat it as metaphor, it doesn't say, for instance,
when it talks about God's eyes, it doesn't say as if God had eyes. You know, it doesn't say,
it doesn't, it doesn't put it in a metaphorical language. It just simply means this is God's
power of sight. So if we understand it in terms of powers, then we don't have to treat it like it's
a metaphor. And it actually makes way more sense, it's way more consistent, you know, and, and,
and actually then has a real depth and richness of meaning within it. As we're going to see, for
instance, when we talk about the phrase, the body of Christ a little bit later. Right. There's,
there's an analogical sense, right? There's a sense in which it, which it's an analogy, right?
Because God doesn't see things the way I see things. Yeah. Or even the way a mantis shrimp sees
things, right? There's a, there's a qualitative difference in addition to a, sure quantitative
difference. But it is also a true statement. And this is the problem with saying it's just a metaphor,
is if it's just a metaphor, then it's not really a true statement. Right. It's just something that stands
for something else. Right. It's, it's, you're just equivocating, right? And, and so we can have,
particularly through Christ, actual knowledge of God. Right? And so you don't want to say, well,
this is just, this is just an analogy. But so yes, when it talks about the eyes of God,
you know, the eyes of God roam the earth looking for, right? There is a metaphorical element there,
right? In that it's not talking about God with physical eyes, actually looking around,
trying to find something, right? Yeah. So there is a metaphorical element. But there is also a
non-metaphorical element that God does indeed possess the power of sight. There's nothing that God
is not aware of that God does not see, right? In that sense. Right. Right. Exactly. Exactly. Yeah. So,
okay, so these are kind of recaps and clarifications from some of the things we talked about in our,
our episodes on bodies. So let's head to the, the mountain of God in Boat of Thesius episode,
where we started talking about sacred geography. And we're going to talk now, again, recap,
what does it mean for a thing to be a thing? And what does that have to do with the material,
the material world, right? Right. And I was, of course, being metta by changing ship to boat
and changing one element and asking if it was the same thought experiment. And all the homeschooled
children out there who recognize that reference are all pumping their fists and their parents are
smiling broadly. But, yeah. So the whole idea of the ship of Thesius, remember, is that, you know,
this thought experiment that Greek philosophers were always using, you know,
Thesius's boat is on display. Over time, the wood rots and they replace each board as it rots away.
Eventually, they've replaced everything as it's still Thesius's boat, right? Or is it now no longer?
And if you took all, and then secondarily, if you went and took all the parts, all the rotted wood
that it buffed and reassembled it into a boat, would that be the real one? Right. And so all of that
was getting at the idea that as much as it seems common sense to us and to parminities,
that matter is not what identity is about. Right? So it seems common sense to us that, right,
none of us wakes up in the morning and walks out into our house and thinks,
what if someone broke into my house last night and replaced everything with exact duplicates?
Something's not right. We don't think that, right? David Hube said,
you have no good reason to not think that, right? But it seems like a lot of work on someone's
part to see this. That would be my good reason. Yeah, to imagine that that's a possibility.
But the argument from laziness, if they're going to break into my house, that's not the thing they're
going to do. But, you know, I'm drinking coffee out of my mug. Even though I took my eyes off
of it several times today, I assume it's the same mug. And if you ask me, why is it the same mug?
I'd say, well, it's the same physical object that I was drinking coffee out of earlier, or yesterday,
or a week ago. But the truth is that we now know scientifically, right? Science has sort of thrown
this wrinkle into the ship of theses. And that's that we know, for example, the human body,
all of the matter that makes it up changes out about every seven years.
Right. But none of the matter that currently composes my body was part of my body 12 years ago.
At all, right? But everyone would say I'm still the same person, right? That wouldn't be a valid
defense in court. If I got caught for a crime, I committed 12 years ago to say, I'm not the person
I was then literally right, right? Or if you were the victim of a crime, and there's not a statute
of limit to, you know, the statute of the thesis does not run out after all the matter trades out.
Like, well, your honor, the victim doesn't exist anymore.
Right. Yeah. I could not hit any of that matter with my car.
Right. And in fact, it was not the same car.
Right. And it gets even more complex when we, like, okay, so seven years ago, I looked,
yeah, basically the same as I do now. You know, both flattering yourself.
Yeah. Well, thank you very much. Just a little. Yeah. I mean, I think there's a little bit more of
me now than there was then, but basically the same, basically the same. But, you know, 30 years
ago, I looked radically different than I do now. And yet we would still absolutely consider that
to be the same person, right? Still the same person. And, you know, we even recognize that the people
in our families are still the same people. Like, it's interesting. There is this kind of metaphysical
sensibility baked into the way that we interact with matter. Right. We don't tend to think day-to-day,
oh, there goes another molecule. Oh, there goes another one. Man, this process can take seven years.
Now I feel totally new. You know, like, we don't function that way. We just, we function as though
this is truly me. That's truly you. This is truly the table I'm sitting in front of.
You know, all these things are indeed the things that they are. And it would be madness to
function as though that were not true. Like, it just simply, it's no one could live that way.
It's impossible. And we have good reason not to live that way, you know.
Yeah. Yeah. Every three and a half years, you're half the man you used to be.
I think so. I thought I was told this happened suddenly. I'm not half the man I used to be,
but no, it's once every three and a half years. Right. And so, that means we have to look for
the identity of a thing in another place, as we talked about. What makes a thing what it is
has to be something other than just the matter that composes it.
And so, at any given time, there is a certain quantity of matter that is being a certain thing.
Right. So, right now there is, and I don't really know how kilograms work. So, I don't know exactly
how much mass of matter, but it's a lot that's making up my body. Right. And as we said, it's not
the same matter that was doing it seven years ago, but that is right now is being my body,
my physical body. I prefer to measure myself with stone, because there's a lot fewer of them
by comparison. But that's weight, not mass. Yes, that's true. That's true. That's right. So,
we need to be precise here. We don't want physicists, um, actually.
Do we have a lot of physicists in the audience, right, and everybody want to hear from you?
Yeah. If you're a physicist, um, actually us at Lord of Spirits at Ancient Faith.
There we go.
Right. So, but that's true for me, and for my heathen dogs, and for the windowpane,
and the lamp post, and, right, and everything else, right. There's matter that's being those things,
and it's not the same matter all the time. Right. It's shifting around. And so, we talked about in
the previous episode, we talked about how is, or being, is actually an active verb, that it's doing
something. It's actively being that thing. Can be being, right. Matter is being a thing.
Right. Yeah. Is being. And so, uh, and here's, this is a, uh, we're going to have some great
t-shirt phrases coming up tonight. Here's one of them. So, some matter is being a body of a
noetic being. Right now, um, in this case, me, or you, or any of our listeners, right, because
as we talked about the last couple episodes, angels and humans are noetic beings.
Right. Angels are noetic beings that do not have material
bodies. Uh, so, noetic beings with material bodies are humans. And so, some of that matter is being
the body of a noetic being. Right. Right. And, you know, we've occasionally people request
clarification and say, aren't the angels the bodyless hosts? Um, but when we call them bodyless,
what we mean by that is that they don't have material bodies. We're not saying that they don't have
powers and potentialities, because they clearly do. Um, and they are circumscribed, meaning that
there's a space where they are, and then there's a space where they're not, because they're not
omnipresent. Only got their vast cosmic. Cosmic. That's right. Yes, vast. Um, they cover a lot of acreage.
Right. Right. And, and, and, and, and, and, and, and, and, and, and, and, so, what, what this
telecoms? Yeah. So this, um, how many telecoms the Kessel run? Yeah. Wow. Wow. You have transgressed, sir.
I know. I know. So, uh, so in the case of the human material body to sort of boil this down,
and, uh, lead in a little into what we're going to talk about next, the, the, the, uh, the human
material body is basically a material pile, a pile of matter being used as an instrument of
consciousness within time and space. That's very, very sci-fi. So our news, our consciousness,
at that point of attention, we were talking about the last two episodes is making use of this
pile of matter that's currently making up my body as an instrument to interact within time and
space within the material creation. Right. And it interacts both ways in coming through the senses
and outgoing. Yeah. I, I think one of the places probably people might get tripped up is, like,
when you use the word instrument, um, you know, sometimes you might think of those mexudes, right,
from, um, Valtron and, um, what was the robot tech? Yeah, robot tech, robot tech. That's right.
We are children of the eight across saga, man. Yes. Exactly. Exactly. You know, people might think
about it in those terms, like, oh, there's, I, you know, I'm inside, you know, go full cartesian,
right? I'm inside this. I'm making use of this, this suit or whatever. Um, but, but that's,
so it's not quite that your body is you. Right. It, it is you. It's not, it's not a suit. Right.
Um, oh, I think we're getting the Mexican, the Mexican radio. Hey, this is a good sign. I always
take, I always take this as a blessing. There it is. Yes. It's been a while since we had Mexican radio on.
Um, well, that's great. Right. Yeah. So, so what a human is, right? In the, especially the
Israelite conception, the biblical, Old Testament conception, a human is an animated body,
an insoled body. Right. A body with life in it. Right. If you don't have a news, it's not a human.
If you don't have a material body, it's not a human. Right. This is why we say physical death is
unnatural. Right. Cause it splits those things apart. Right. Cause it, it rips those things apart.
And that's why the body then crumbles to dust. Right. Normally.
Normally. Yeah. That's, um, right. So that's, that's an unnatural thing that has to be repaired
and restored. Right. And, and it really important for setting things up. We're going to go to
break into just a second here. Um, is that that body is your body. Like it truly is yours. Even,
even at the point of, and after the point of physical death, it doesn't stop being your body.
It's still your body. It doesn't stop being you. Yeah. Right. Your body makes it sound like a
possession of thing you have that belongs to you. It's you. It doesn't stop being you. It's not,
yeah, it is being you. Right. Right. That's a key, key concept for everything they're about to
discuss. Okay. Well, we're going to come back, uh, just after a break and we'll start taking
your calls. So we'll be right back. Father Andrew Steven, David and father Steven DeYoung
will be back in a moment to take your calls on the next part of the Lord of Spirits. Give them a
call at 855-237-2346. That's 855-AF radio. No one of books these days offer us techniques for
self-improvement. But in the newest release from the ancient faith store, gratitude and life's
trenches, Robin Phillips takes a different tack. He shows us that God made us where we are in the pain
and heartache of the present moment. Instead of looking for a way to escape from hardship,
we can cultivate an attitude of gratitude, peace, and self-acceptance that will transform our
experience of suffering. Drawing on his own experiences and his work as a consultant in the
behavioral health industry, as well as stories of saints and sufferers, teachings of the fathers,
and recent discoveries in neuroscience, Phillips shows us that the journey to personal well-being
is one we can all travel, regardless of the hardships we may face. To find this book and others
like it, you can go to store.angentfaith.com. Again, that is store.angentfaith.com.
The second half, before we get to what we're about to talk about, we do have a caller. Michael
is calling. He's right here in Pennsylvania. Michael, are you there? Yes, I am. How you doing,
fathers? Good. How are you, Michael? Welcome to the Lord of Spirits. Thank you. Thank you.
What is your question for us this evening? My question is regarding relics. Just how we
believe that as Orthodox Christians, that grace can be in our bodies, in us, it's not just an abstract
thing, and we also believe it can be contained in objects. Does this also mean that an evil essence
or evil energy can also be contained in an object? And if that is the case, can that evil be expelled
from that object? Or should it just be burned? It's a good question. And the first thing that
occurs to me is to think about a house blessing. When we do a house blessing, the whole point
is to clean out the residue of sin. I'm sure you listened to our day of atonement episode,
in which there's atonement made for the altar, for the tabernacle, the whole space where the
people of God are, that sin actually leaves a mark, so to speak. It leaves a stain that needs to
be cleaned out. I wouldn't think of it in terms of a talisman, but then I wouldn't think of that
in terms of relics and crosses and so forth that way either. It's not like it's a kind of
like an RPG magical item. That's not how I would understand it at all.
But yeah, my answer to that is that yes, absolutely, the physical, the material world, even apart
from human bodies, can be affected by sin and can have an evil stain within it. But I want to
see what Father Stephen has to say about this. Yeah, I have a chalice plus one of smiting.
I don't know if you remember. Well, well, my sensor has plus six fire damage, so mostly to carpets,
I imagine. Yes, my experience says anything. But yeah, I would also, yeah, there's a tendency to
start thinking of graces stuff. And we need to push back against that. It's the Latin and
English languages tend to reify everything. They try to turn everything into a thing.
And some things aren't a thing. They're not even a thing. And so we're going to talk more about
that as we go on, about the understanding of graces, the divine energies and this dynamic
capacity. We're going to get into that later on tonight. But yeah, as Father Andrew was saying,
there's a taint that's usually referred to in the Old Testament as curse that is on and in and
taints, sort of material created reality that's been used for sinful wicked purposes.
Right. And that curse is removed through blessings, right? So not just house blessings,
but blessing objects. When we bless water, we're not making it magic vampire killing water.
Although I understand it does kill vampires. More on vampires this October.
Yes. But we're not making magic vampire killing water. It's that we're purifying the curse. It's a
restoring the water to what water was created to be for, which is healing, replenishing, purifying
cleansing, right? And the same thing when we bless people and when we baptize people.
So yeah, there is that kind of ontological taint. And as for the grace part, we'll be getting into
that the rest of tonight's episode. Yes. So stay tuned. Does that answer your question, Michael?
Yes, it does. And I'm looking forward to that episode on vampires.
Yeah. Yeah. You have to wait until October, though. Also wear wolves. Yes. Yep. Yep.
Monsters. Totally. Totally. All right. Well, thank you very much, Michael. And we do have
another call coming in. And it's Sarah, who I think is somewhere near Chicago. So Sarah, are you there?
Is that me, Sarah, for Michigan? Oh, well, your phone number apparently says you're somewhere
near Chicago, but you're the only Sarah we've got on the call board. Yeah. Oh,
up in the suburbs. So that's yeah, my, anyway, yes, your cell phone is from Chicago.
Yes, my cell phone is. I have an unrelated question to tonight's topic, but something that was
brought up a few episodes. Okay. So we were kind of talking a few weeks ago about women who are
menstruating or men who have emissions not being part of like holy communion. And I was that kind
of got my brain percolating on why are young girls not allowed to serve as an altar girl?
Like if they'll toco served in this way, why can't, you know, my orthodox daughter who's not
menstruating yet? And then kind of a related field of, you know, in the conversation is why do
young boys process around the holy table at their 40-day blessing, but girls are not taken past
the icon of staff at the 40-day blessing? Right, right. So non-controversial questions.
Yeah, right. Thanks, Sarah. Okay. So I want to take the second one because this is actually something
I've researched. Yeah, it's shocking. So, so here's the thing. There is a variety of practices
between different orthodox traditions on that point. Indeed his, yes, yes. A lot of people are not
aware of that because, you know, most of us tend to go to one parish most of the time and that's not
something, when you do visit another parish, it may not be something you see happening at that
other parish, right? So most of us tend to be exposed to only one way of doing that.
But the reality is that there are, I'm aware of at least three different versions of that.
So there's one version in which at the 40-day prayers that no one is brought behind through,
you know, into the, into the holy place, you know, neither boys, nor girls. I'm also aware of the
practice which you described, which is that boys only are brought back there and then brought around
and then handed back to the mother, right? But there is also a practice where both boys and girls
are brought through the the the Deacon's door, brought around behind the altar, and then brought
out the other Deacon's door and brought back to the mother. And I guess that might surprise you
that that is the case in some churches. If you were to look at, for instance, the most recent
official service book from the Antioch and Orthodox Krishna's Diocese of North America that covers
that, that is the practice that is indicated in that book. And there's a whole bunch of notes in
the back about how that's not something that the people who put that book together made up. It is in
fact a well-attested historical practice, actually, and that it seems like the limitation of
to only boys seems to be a somewhat later development. Now, all that being said, I am in no way
laying down any kind of judgment or criticism on any particular version of that. Every priest
you should do what your bishop tells you to do. And if they're not doing what their bishop tells
them to do, well, that's between them and their bishop and not my business. But so the question
then is, what's the point of bringing a person back there at that moment? Because a lot of times
people have this sense of, okay, only boys are allowed to go back, and some have this sense, all
males are allowed to go back there, and no females may ever. But clearly, this historical practice of
bringing baby girls and boys back there would seem to violate that kind of general idea, right?
The point of bringing babies back there is that they are being offered to God. That's what's going
on there. Some will say only boys can go back there because, well, someday they might be priests.
And I understand the idea behind that argument, but the truth is that the vast majority
of them will not. The vast majority of them will not. It does not make much sense to me. And maybe
once someone would disagree with me on that point, but it does not make much sense to me to say,
well, we'll bring them all back there in the hopes that one out of, you know, 10,000, whatever,
them will actually get ordained. And nothing in the prayers that are said, whatever version,
because there's, again, there's multiple sets of prayers between different traditions. None of them
say anything about the possibility of that person being ordained. It's all about offering this
child to God just as was done with the Lord Jesus on his 40th day. So that's my response to that.
I do the practice that my bishop gave me to do and that is in the book that is officially
promulgated by him and that's what everyone should be doing. But there is some variety in that practice.
I do not encourage you to go to your priest and say, I expect you to do this now because I found out
there's another way, you know, please don't do that. No one listening to this. Please don't do
that. Don't do that. You know, I'm in favor of liturgical variety. I think it's okay. So yeah,
that's like I said, I looked this up. I actually wrote an article about it that is on my blog.
It's a really interesting thing. And to me, what's really beautiful about it is,
whatever practice is being done, the point is to offer this child to God. However, it's being
expressed. Right. And again, it's an imitation of our Lord's being offered on his 40th day.
So if that makes sense to you, then I'm going to kick the more controversial thing over to
Father Steven and let him cover that question. Yeah. So I can grumpy old man all over it. Yeah. Yeah.
So it's worth noting that the Theotokos waited to the Holy of Holies, but she didn't go back there on
the day of atonement and assist the high priest. She wasn't sort of serving as a liturgical assistant.
But so yeah, so first of all, the thing we need to break is this idea that an insane number of
Orthodox people have that is that men are allowed behind the ecotostosis of women aren't
because that's not true. Yeah. At all. Like in any form, there's no element of that that is true.
The actual rule is that no one is allowed behind the ecotostosis unless they're there for a purpose
for which they've been blessed by the bishop. Right. So I'm a priest. So as a priest,
I am blessed by the bishop to go back there to celebrate services. I don't go back there and hang
out and like watch YouTube videos on my phone. Right. Like in the sanctuary. Right. It's not like
a privilege that I have to go back there. I'm only to go back there when I'm preparing for
or celebrating or cleaning up after one of the services. Right. That I have been blessed to
to celebrate. If you go to a convent, most convents when they have a priest or a bishop come to do
services, there are certain nuns, usually elderly well-established nuns who are designated
who will assist the priest behind the ecotostosis. Yep. Yep. The other example I like to give is that
during the Byzantine imperial period, at least sometimes I know the Empress would actually,
as far, I don't know if she went through the Holy Doors in the middle, but she certainly,
yes, she went right through the Holy Doors to go receive communion. At the altar. At the altar,
just like the clergy. Well, maybe not just like, but pretty similar. Pretty similar. Right.
So that's not the rule. The reason why we have altar boys in regular parish practice,
as opposed to like in a convent, there are other men around to assist or to clean or to do those
things. So particular women are designated for that task by the bishop. The reason we have
altar boys in parish practice is that contrary to our, this is where I go grumpy old man. Our
current modern practice is, doesn't he look cute in his little stacarian? Let's get a picture of him.
Oh, look, he's carrying the big fan. Oh, he's so cute. Right. That's not why. Right. That's not why.
And it's not even really just because the priest needs help. It's because for most of the history
of the church, they didn't have seminaries and they didn't have deaconal courses by mail
at late vocations programs. Right. They didn't have any of that. So the way people learn to
become subdeacons and deacons and priests was by celebrating the services. And so the idea was
that you're training the next generation of deacons and priests and subdeacons to serve at the
altar. So I, being a grumpy old man, have been no to tell people that if you're one of those
folks who by no means wants your child to be clergy, do not send them back to serve at altar.
There you go. That's what it's for. Okay. That is really helpful. Yeah. I love it when people make
that sound. That's good. I have lots to think on now. Thank you so much for taking my very
off topic question. I very much appreciate it. Well, when I saw it, you know, when I saw it on
the call board, I was like, okay, this is not on topic. But you know, it's something I know something
about. So here we go. And you're calling from what my people have long considered the promise
land. There you go. So that being a state of Michigan. It's a great place. It's a great
place. It's a great place. Yeah. Well, thank you. Thank you very much for calling in, Sarah.
Good to hear from you. Yep. Bye. All right. Okay. Well, welcome to act two.
Yes. And this being our relics episode later on, we will be discovering Montgomery Scott
trapped in the transport buffer of a Dyson Sphere. Yes. I loved that episode with the the green
alcoholic beverage. Yes. They did. We weren't sure what it was. Everybody. Wow. Anyway, that takes
me right back. So okay. So all right. Another, another little bit of. Isn't it sad just as it
aside? Isn't it sad that our generation, you know, previous generations experienced nostalgia
for rural life or for good times they had at high school with friends. We experienced nostalgia
for media content. I know. It's true. It's just the way it is. Yeah. Wither, wither, our generation.
That all subsequent. Hey, well, we built the internet. So I mean, that's I feel like that's a decent
a decent accomplishment. Yeah. All right. Well, the tower of Babel. Exactly. Just like that. Yeah.
Right. So okay. So since this is the first part of this episode has been recap, recap, recap.
We're going to do another little bit of recap and and where we can talk now about the news again.
And you're going to you know, you're all going to see how this all fits together very, very soon.
Right. So the news. It's the imaging capacity. Right. Sort of the retina of the soul. Can I say
that? Maybe, okay. Yeah. I'll have to ponder on that one. Okay. Okay. All right. I mean, that is
a metaphor. I think that is a metaphor. You've transgressed and now you must atone. This time we've
come to. Yeah. Yeah. But so yeah, we talked about how the news is not only sort of a sensory organ,
but also is reflects this imaging capacity, this capacity to to image God. And so as we were saying,
you know, at the end of the last act, humanity is the noetic material being. Right. Both the
noetic being and the material being. And therefore humanity bridges and potentially unites the
entirety of the created order. Right. Right. Both the visible and invisible creations or both the
spiritual and physical creation and material creations. However, you want to look at that.
Or parcel that out. And so angelic beings are noetic, but they're not material. Right. And animals
are material, but they're not noetic beings. And we talked about those other intellectual
capacities and other forms of reasoning that even dogs like mine have, for example, but they don't
have a news. They don't have that that imaging capacity. Right. Right. That that humans they have
retinas, but not the retina of the soul as it were. I'm trying to try try that idea on a few times
to see if it's good. Yeah, you're just going to keep selling it. No matter how hard you try, I don't
think you need to make it a thing. No, it's like streets ahead. It's not going to be a thing. It's
not going to be a thing. So right. Right. So what this means, what this imaging capacity means
is that the human person as a whole can function as a material body for another spiritual being.
Yeah. Another spiritual being. Right. Meaning, meaning or to try to help draw this out a little bit.
We were just talking about how our physical material body is the material body for our
news. Right. That it is the way in which our news interacts with material reality in time and space.
Right. Right. And so the human person as a whole can function in that way for another spiritual being
because of the news. So for example, the most obvious example of this that we've talked about a lot
on the show is theosis. Right. This this imaging. Right. When we are imaging God in the creation
in the created order, we are serving as a body. Right. We're serving as this as an image in the world
for God. Right. Right. We talked about that when we talked about creation. Right. Yeah. And if
if a body is again, the powers and or potentialities, then that means that when God's works are being done,
the person, if it's a human being doing God's works, they are being the body of God, the body of
Christ. Right. They're serving as an instrument in that way. Yeah. When you do the works of another
spiritual being, you function as the body of that being. Right. And so the same is true on the flip
side. And this is the, you know, the the focus of the epic giants episode. Right. On the other side,
what we've called demonosis, which I tried to make a thing. Yeah. It's not a thing yet. To me,
that sounds too much like halitosis. Right. Maybe some listerine could clear it up. But some holy
water or demonization, which is you pointed out to be, we usually use to refer to what we do to
our political opponents, right, calling the names and acting like they're Satan. Yeah. Yeah. But
you know, there's this, you know, what's the opposite of a saint? Well, a giant is the opposite
of a saint. But, you know, however you want to conceive that of that, you can do the works
of the devil. I mean, the scripture says this. Right. And we, we, we, we got to the end of that
in our giants episode, right, that the, the what we're talking about, where we're talking about an
effulom or a giant is we're talking about a person who has completely gone down that path and
become demonic themselves. And that's why there was this understanding, uniform understanding of
the ancient Jewish world that after they died, their spirits were the demons that were going around
possessing things. Right. Right. And, and you know, we, we've said that in the past, and we get occasional
requests for clarification about that. And sometimes people like it, that's church fathers don't see
that. But we actually have a lovely quote from St. John Chrysostom. And St. John Chrysostom
in his, in one of his discourses on the parable of the rich men and Lazarus. So this is discourse
number two, because there's four of them. He comments on a kind of urban legend. Right. That some people
think that someone who dies of violent death becomes a demon after they die. Which people still think
today. Right. There's, you know, oh, this person was murdered. So there goes now haunts the place
where they were killed. Yeah. Right. There's this. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Exactly. So this is, this is
what he said. So this is, this is the actual direct quote, quote, for it is a fact that many of the
less instructed think that the souls of those who die a violent death become wandering spirits,
that is to say demons. But this is not so. I repeat, it is not so for not the souls of those who
die of violent death become demons, but rather the souls of those who live in sin, not that their
nature is changed, but that in their desires, they imitate the evil nature of demons showing this
very thing to the Jews. Christ said, ye are the children of the devil. That's John 744. He said that
they were the children of the devil, not because they were changed into a nature like his, but because
they performed actions like his, where for also he has for the lusts of your father, ye will do.
End quote. So that's Saint John, no less than Saint John Chrysostom explicitly saying, look, you don't
become a demon after you die by experiencing a violent death. You become a demon after you die
acting like a demon. That's what he says. And just like theosis, it's not that just like in
theosis, our human nature is not changed into the divine nature. Yeah, you don't become the
whole eternity. They don't become fallen angels. Their human nature is not changed into the angelic
nature, but it becomes like it. Right. Right. And functions like it. Right. Yep. Yeah. Right. And so
what this means is, is that from the perspective of the scriptures, the works that we do,
the the the the the the erga produced by our inner Gaia. Right. The works produced by our energies,
which are related words in Greek. Right. The things we do are the actualization of spiritual energies.
Right. So when when we are doing quote unquote good works, we're doing the works of God,
when someone does evil works, they're not just choosing themselves to take a sinful action or
making a mistake. Right. But they are actualizing the sin of the demonic powers. Right. Yep. Yep.
And so this is why there is not a separation between the idea of morality and the idea of spiritual
warfare. Right. Right. It's it's it's completely relevant to the way that you live your life. And I
think that this is a really important pastoral point. We maybe have made it before, but let's make
it again. That often when people are struggling to live as Christians and they they find themselves
falling into sin, they may conceive of that as simply being, well, I'm just a failure. You know,
there's something wrong with me. Right. Or they may trivialize it. Well, you know, does God really
care if I do that? You know, like how big of a deal is that really? Right. But if we understand
correctly that when you do what is good, you are functioning as the body of Christ. And when you do
what is evil, you are functioning as the body of the demonic powers. Then that changes the whole
game. It completely changes our understanding of what's going on. And that's why you see so many,
for instance, the ascetic fathers just trying to purge every kind of even minor sin from themselves.
They don't make excuses for it. If they commit sins, they repent of them. Right. Because
when you sin, then you're engaging in demonosis. And certainly greater sins do that more than
lesser ones, for sure. But you don't say, well, you know, I'm just going to do all these little
things. And that's not that big of a deal. Because the truth is, is that it does accumulate. And once
you permit yourself a small vice, then you're likely to to permit yourself an even bigger one.
Because it was easy, though, you know, it wasn't that bad last time. And now it's going to be a
little bit easier to make it worse this time. Right. You know, it's, you're, you're literally
spiritually speaking, hanging around with the wrong crowd. And you become like them. You become like
them. So this is, this is a really, really critical concept. You're going to see how this connects
with Rolex very soon. But we promise. Yeah. Well, you guys know that this is our deal. So
right, right. Yeah. Human beings, human works as the actualization is, I say, of spiritual energies.
Right. And so, and we see this kind of approach all over the place in scripture, right? One
that we've come back to several times, and we'll probably end up doing an episode about,
you see this with, with Adam and Kane, right, where, you know, St. Paul says in Romans 5,
that, you know, sin enters the world through Adam. But notice that language, right, sin, sin,
not sins, not Adam sinned as a verb, as an action, but sinned, this noun, enters the world
through Adam. And that's commensurate with the way sin is talked about in Genesis 4, where God
comes to Kane and says, sin is crouching at your door and wants to master you. It's sort of this
power in the world that is unleashed, right? And it ends up mastering Kane, and it gets Kane to do
his, to do its works. Right. And this gets, gets brought out other places. This is our first
enich quote for this evening. First enich 10 verse 8 says, the whole earth has been corrupted through
the works that were taught by Azazel to him ascribe all sin, right? And this is
reflecting that same idea, right? That it's, it's the works of Azazel that are being done by these
people, and they're corrupting the created order, right? And that's what's going to now necessitate,
now necessitate the flood, that he's the one motivating it, even though the people are doing it.
And this is related to the understanding of atonement that we talked about in that episode,
that the goat for Azazel, the sins are sent back to him because he's where they came from.
Right. Right. And the same kind of idea is in scripture two, like we're not just,
we're not just quote unquote, getting this from Enoch, right? So first John, there's multiple
places. So first John 5.19, we know that we're from God and the whole world lies in the power of
the evil one. There's that sense of that demonic influence everywhere. First John 3.8, whoever makes
a practice of sinning is of the devil. For the devil has been sinning from the beginning.
The reason the Son of God appeared was to destroy the works of the devil. So there you go again,
it's you do the works of the devil and you're, you're becoming like him. You're a sinner.
First John 3.12, we should not be like Cain who was of the evil one and murdered his brother
and why did he murder him? Because his own deeds were evil and his brother's righteous.
Right. And so you see Cain's deeds are evil is a function of him being of the evil one.
Yes. And Ables were a function of him being of God.
Yeah. Adams, Adam releases sin into the world. And we sometimes get this request for clarification.
You know, did Adam sin? Yes, Adam did sin. But the word sin is not used to describe what Adam did.
It's a transgression. The word sin is used to talk about Cain being overpowered.
You know, what Adam releases into the world then leaps on his son basically and overpowers him.
And because Cain doesn't master himself, he's mastered by sin.
Right. And so this is another thing that sort of cuts to most of the debates in the Western
theological world, which want to talk about and argue about and split the church and kill
a third of the population of Europe in the 30 years war, over whether human works, human deeds are
meritorious. And that whole meritorious concept is kind of irrelevant. That whole merit concept is
kind of irrelevant, right? Because if we understand human works to be participating in co-operating
with actualizing these spiritual energies, then anything that can be called a good work that a
human does is really them participating in and being the instrument of grace, of the divine
energies of God working in the world. They're the hammer he uses to drive the nail. The hammer
can't ascribe merit to itself. The carpenter doesn't reward his hammer for having done a good job.
Right. And some of our reformed friends would say things like a human person cannot add anything
to his salvation. They'll say that kind of thing. It's like, well, any good thing that a human
person does is God doing it. And it assumes your salvation is like a pile of stuff.
This is that's not what salvation is, right? So the reason God can look at a work and call it good
is because it's his work. It's his work. Just like at the end of each day of creation in Genesis 1,
he looks at it and he says, it is good. Every good comes from God. Every good comes from there.
There is no independent good. Right. And so the alternative for humans is rather than
participating in the divine energies is to participate in the passions. Yeah. To bring to
fruition the works of the evil one, the works of the demons. So quote our friend, Bob Dylan,
you got to serve somebody. Yeah. Right. Right. You're going to have a master. It's not just that,
as Christ said, no man can serve two masters, but every man serves at least one. Yeah. And so you
can choose. You have to choose this day whom you will serve. Right. You don't get to be an
independent contractor. And whoever's works, you engage in, you become like that one.
So you are becoming what you do. The things you do are who you make you what you are.
Right. You know, I mean, just think from your own experience, people, right?
When you, you know, for instance, when you in one of the fast and you go to church a lot more often,
you're praying a lot more often, you become, you become much more engaged in the life of prayer,
right? It, it, you know, it alters your sensibility. You see things differently. You function
differently. But then like say you pick up a habitual sin, it starts to drag you down and you,
you have this clear sense that you're a different kind of person, you know, and repentance
you pull yourself up out of that and then go back and do the works of God. It changes who you are.
It's not separate from who you are. Right. But it's also not isolated. The things that you do,
you are participating in God or you are participating in the works of the devil. There's no,
there's no neutral ground. There's no neutral ground. Right. And this, this undercuts the whole
pathology of Western Christian culture, which includes people who aren't Christians who were brought
up in the culture. And that is guilt. Yeah. The entire obsession with the concept of guilt.
Is this a sin or not? Right? Am I guilty of something or not? Who's to blame? Who's responsible?
Uh, this happens even in our Orthodox churches. There's a problem and people will spend hours
and hours and hours arguing about whose fault it is. And it's definitely not mine. It's definitely
this other person. Right. It's their fault and argue about whose fault it is and who's to blame for
what and spend approximately zero hours working on fixing it. Yeah. Right. And so repentance is not
deciding who's guilty of what and how that guilt can be absolved. Repentance is fixing the damage,
fixing the problem, healing the wounds, repairing the situation. That's what repentance is. Right.
Because if you, it's not a question, there, there, there is no question as to whether something was
a sin for you. Right. It either drew you closer to God or it drew you farther away. Right. And either
made you more like Christ or less like Christ. And so it doesn't matter if it's on some list of
sins or if you can find a Bible verse to quote saying it's bad or okay, none of that matters.
Right. And this is what Saint Paul is always trying to get at when he talks about the conscience.
Right. Something can be a sin for one person and not for another person. Right. Based on what it does.
And if it does that, if it pulls you away from Christ, even a little, that has to be fixed.
You have to return to Christ and draw close to Him again and continue to draw closer to Him.
Yeah. Yeah. So, you know, to connect this with some of our other themes,
you know, the idea that another spiritual being can make use of a human person as their body,
I'm sure when we said that initially, people like, oh, is that what demon possession is?
And the answer is yes. That is what demon possession is. But it's also a literal sense.
Yes. Yes. Yeah. Exactly. But it's also what idolatry is. Right. Now, idolatry works with a kind of,
you know, two-factor authentication as it were where the demon is making use of the image,
the stone or metal or wood, you know, idol. And through that, through that, the interaction of
human beings with that thing, then they do the works of that demon. Right. But nonetheless,
it still is functioning as a body for the demon. And then those people become further extensions of
that body. Right. The idol becomes a kind of conduit to get people to do the works of that demon.
But yeah, I mean, you know, demon possession is a thing, both in the sense of a demon getting
control of a human person in a sort of very direct and horrifying way. But also, you know, when people
do the works of a demon, they are, in a sense, demon possessed. They're at their very least,
they're kind of embodying the demon with this understanding of what a body is. Right. And
the good news is it works the opposite way too, that we can, we can be the body of Christ also.
Right. And the reason for this, again, remember the goal of the demonic powers is to destroy
humanity. And humanity has, we have material bodies, we have materiality, which they lack. Right.
Right. And that materiality means that we can be shaped, we can change, we don't just have
powers. We also have potentialities that can come to fruition or fail to come to fruition.
That could be stunted or that can blossom. Right. And so this is why, one of the most common
questions we get, why can humans repent and angels can't? This is why, right. This is why St.
John of Damascus says that it's our materiality that allows us to repent because we have this
maliability, right. This ability to bring these things into the created order in a way that,
that the demonic powers do not. And so even in those rare cases, right, you can find here and
there these sort of stories. And as we've said before, you never base theology on sort of one
anecdotal story from the desert fathers and say, okay, therefore we have to rewrite our whole theology
because it's one story. Yeah, there's these stories of angels somehow repenting.
Like that's, it shows up once in a while, but, but it always happens with some kind of human
agency. Right. There's a human person involved with whom or through whom that angelic repentance
takes place. Right. And so even in these sort of minority reports where there is some demon that
repents, it is by way of a human. And you see the same thing with when you hear stories about
the departed who are in Hades finding salvation, it's through some living human with the material
body, praying for them and repenting for it and with them. That materiality is the vehicle through
which that that male ability and transformation is possible. Yeah. And that's why when you're the
material element of what you are, of who you are, what you are, whatever is separated from the
immaterial. At death, you can't repent after that because you don't have that potentiality anymore.
You know. Right. Yeah. So yeah. Yeah. And so all this has been at sort of the individual level
of individual imaging. But of course, the other big way this whole construct and idea is used
in Scripture is corporately, right, pun intended.
And the to refer to the body of Christ as in the church, as in the community, right, at the
community level, the entire church community serving as the body of Christ. And this in multiple
senses, right? Yes. Yeah. Yeah. So that the the the persons who make up the community, right,
when St. Paul gets into that relationship, he talks about members of the body of Christ. We think
of members either as jackets with weird snap tabs on the shoulders. Or we think of like being
the member of a club or both. Okay. No, those those. But this is members as in parts as in body
parts. And he further defines that. St. Paul talks about eyes and hands and ears and right. And so
members meeting each of us as a part of the body and they all function together to serve as this
this instrument. And so there are there are two primary ways that St. Paul uses that
that argument and and other New Testament writers. One is that as the body of Christ, we are the
way in which Christ comes to the world. The church is right. So salvation comes into the world
through the church. Christ works through the church. The the when people experience when people
outside the church experience Christ's love, it should be not that Christ can't do it directly
when we're messing up. But it should be at actual Christian loving them. Right. It should be the
hands of a Christian giving them things to help them with their needs. Right. And again, there's
that instrumentality. It's not you doing a good deed by giving a warm coat to a homeless person.
Right. It is Christ clothing this person through you as instrument, through you as his body
in the world. And you've got some references really. Yes. Yes. Yeah. We've got we got some good
Bible verses. So okay. So first John 417 by this is love perfected with us so that we may have
confidence for the day of judgment because as he is so also are we in this world. Right.
Similar idea is in Ephesians chapter 1 verses 22 and 23 and he put all things under his feet and
gave him his head over all things to the church which is his body. The fullness of him who fills
all in all the church is the fullness of Christ. And then I love this really cool expression from
Saint Augustine who describes the church as quote the whole Christ head and body and that's from
his on the epistle of John. Yeah. This close identification of Christ and the church is made
very clear in scripture and certainly the church fathers and it's it's it's in terms of
that that the church does the works of Christ that we are the presence of Christ in this world.
And of course I mean someone might object to that and say well you know what about bad clergy
or bad Christians. Again if you're doing bad things you're not being the body of Christ.
You're being the body of another spirit. Right. Right. And so then the other major sense in which
we talk about the church as the body of Christ is that the church as a community
is animated by Christ's spirit. Right. Because a human body right a human right and human body in
the sense we've been talking about body. The fuller sense is a material body that's animated
by a spirit. Right. And so in the same way because again corporately I'm going to keep punting it up.
We're we're animated by the Holy Spirit by Christ's spirit. Right. That makes us the body of Christ.
And so from an orthodox perspective when we talk about holy tradition we're not talking about
a bunch of secrets whispered by a telephone game from the apostles to their successors of some
traditional stuff that's not written down in the Bible. Some gnostic secrets we possess that
that know what else does. We're talking about the internal life of the church which is the Holy Spirit.
Just as we right have an internal life not just an external life. So also the church as the body
of Christ has an internal life the life of the Holy Spirit within the church and that internal life
through time and space. Right. You could look at it diacronically or synchronically. You could look at it
through history or you could look at it across the church at any given point in time. That is what
holy tradition is from an orthodox perspective. Yes. Yep. And that's what we protect and preserve
and cherish the same way we project and preserve and cherish our own in our lives as people.
Right. Yet to me that's a profound observation that the notion of the church as being the body of
Christ and the notion that holy tradition being the life of the Holy Spirit in the church that
these are really essentially two different ways of seeing the same thing. Right. Just two different
angles of looking at it. It's always beautiful and astonishing to me when concepts that seem like
okay I have a list of concepts that I need to make sure I understand these things when they merge
and show that it's really the same one thing. Just it's beautiful. It's beautiful.
All right. Well with that said we're going to take another break and we'll be back in just a minute
for the third half of our show. Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung
will be back in a moment to take your calls on the next part of the Lord of Spirits. Give them a
call at 855-237-2346. That's 855-AF radio. Saint Ignatius 1st century Bishop of Antioch called the
Godbearer is one of the earliest witnesses to the truth of Christ and the nature of the Christian
life. Tradition tells us that as a small child Ignatius was singled out by Jesus himself as an
example of the child-like faith all Christians must possess. In bearing God Father Andrew Damick
recounts the life of this great pastor, martyr and saint and interprets for the modern reader
five major themes in the pastoral letters he wrote. martyrdom, salvation and Christ, the bishop,
the unity of the church and the eucharist. For Ignatius martyrdom is really the fullness of
Christian life in a sense which that can be challenging for us because number one he doesn't seem
to have any reticence at all about going to martyrdom like there's no sense of well this is what I
have to do you know I wish I didn't have to but this is God's will for me he is going to it joyfully
to find this book and others like it you can go to store.ancientfaith.com again that is store.ancientfaith.com
we're back now with the Lord of Spirits the Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen
De Young if you have a question call now at 855-237-2346 that's 855-AF radio
welcome back everybody it's the third half of the show I just want to say I know I
have been seeing some reports out there that some people are having some difficulty with streaming
there have been some technical issues if you're hearing me say this please if you missed part of the
show at all make sure you tune in tomorrow morning for the recording we do have a podcast
this is a podcast you can listen to it recorded and it is all being recorded thank God and you
build a hear it all tomorrow so our apologies for any any technical difficulties that we've been
having I hope you guys will be Mexican radio yeah I'll just say I hope everybody I hope everybody yeah
I hope everybody caught the Mexican radio if not it will be on the recording so all right well it's
the third half of the show and here we are going to talk about relics now it really it wouldn't be
lord of spirits without at least a few technical difficulties here that's true yeah I mean we
were we were a concerned earlier I mean you were talking me yesterday like last night your power was
out because there was storms going on because it's storm season in Louisiana but but thank God it
seems like nothing's really super problematic on your end but oh well now that you've jinxed it
yes boom something my lights what no I'm sorry it's okay it's okay yeah okay so okay so the bodies
of saints now the bodies of saints yes and so the bodies of saints then remain the bodies of saints
right it's there that's it is still it's not just their body it's it is them right it is still that it
is still them it is still them and it's still therefore the body of Christ because the works that
the saints do our gods works so that body is being the body of Christ because it's doing his works
and that's even though even though it is a different pile of matter now that it was when that
saint was alive right it's not identical molecules and atoms right that doesn't affect that any more
than it affects it with with us as a living human person here in this world right as the the matter
changes out right and and this also applies this also applies to pieces of the true cross and to
holy objects in general once again even though even though it's different matter I mean pieces of wood
the molecules definitely still change out right certainly going to be changed out a lot of times
over the course of two thousand years and it and that's part of why it doesn't even matter if it's
quote-unquote authentic right because it is being the cross when it is being prayed in front of when
it is being used to bless someone when it is being venerated it it is the cross right yes yeah yeah
and so the idea of trying to scientifically authenticate everything is misguided yeah I mean how
could you like detect like okay let's detect whether this is being the true cross let's detect whether
this is the cross for the church like well I can detect it because look I saw someone venerate
right yeah and identity is not a question of the material right it's not for me or you either
what it is doing right yeah right what it is doing what it is being at that time and so
this also extends to icons right which are related not the exact same thing right because you know
an icon of Christ most likely it's not impossible but most likely none of the matter in the icon of
Christ you have on the wall was part of Christ's physical body like I said it is possible but
most likely not right when he walked this earth so but still it functions in a similar way right
that the the icon is being right the the presence of the the person or event depicted
um and that's this is why the the oh we're gonna get hate mail about this this is why the windows
to heaven language isn't quite right yeah because like it and and from what I understand I'm not one
of the people who studied this but from what I understand people who have actually studied this this
windows to heaven language is relatively recent um quite recent actually um and and the problem with
the window is it's a space that opens to let you sort of see through but what an icon actually is
being is the presence of the saint or the event being presented to you you know it's not a it's not
a telescope that lets you see back in time or you know into the other world or whatever right it is
being the works of that person or event or of God himself right right and um so yeah it represents
this a material object that has a sort certain capacity as a medium right and when you when you get
into uh Saint John of Damascus who I who see I said I said we're gonna get back to him later um
when you get to his defense of the the holy icons right when when he's arguing against iconoclasm
he doesn't focus on the type of stuff you brought up in your introduction he does talk about yeah
yeah yeah he talks he doesn't he doesn't just say look at these precedents I mean which I mean
fine I mean there's nothing wrong with bringing that up right like like like the there's icons in
the temple and tabernacle that he you know that's fine but he doesn't do 12 proof texts and then say
checkmate iconoclasts right that's right and when when you look at the core and structure of his
argument in all of his treatises of the holy icons the core structure argument he's talking about
matter for him the core of the argument is the relationship of matter of the material creation
to God and specifically to the divine energies to grace right to God's work right yeah I mean
there's this so there's this classic quote which I think if anybody knows any quote from
Saint John of Damascus that isn't one of his hymns this is the one that they've heard of um he says this
I do not worship matter I worship the God of matter who became matter for my sake and
daint to inhabit matter who worked out my salvation through matter I will not cease from honoring that
matter which works for my salvation I've venerated though not as God so he's talking about matter
being used by God being inhabited by God that the matter works his salvation you know it's again it's
not an independent good or independent agent it's God doing it God is making use of matter as an
instrument and that inhabiting matter just to clarify it's not some kind of pan-ntheism right where
God is just in all the matter um he's in the tree he's in the wind right it's it's specifically
talking about the incarnation uh as it's got a Damascus clarifies right right right right right yeah okay
so we've got another quote here again from the same work from his defense of the holy icons and he
says this the nature of God remains the same as before the flesh created in time is quickened by a
logical and reasoning soul I honor all matter besides and venerated through it filled as it were
with a divine power and grace my salvation has come to me was not the thrice happy and thrice
blessed wood of the cross matter was not the sacred and holy mountain of Calvary matter what
of the life giving rock the holy suppoker the source of of our resurrection was it not matter
is not the most holy book of the gospels matter is not the blessed table matter which gives us the
bread of life are not the golden silver matter out of which crosses and altar plate and chalices are
made and before all these things is not the body and blood of our lord matter it's it's a powerful
argument right and so he's saying everything in regard to our salvation all over the grace of God
that we receive is mediated to us through the material creation yeah there's there's not the sort
of projecting of of something from unhide that we bathe in you know whatever it's it's matter it's
matter it's matter it's matter it's matter right it's not over against the material right because
say job Damascus essentially that what he comes to most often with the iconoclast is basically
accusing them of being manacles accusing them of treating matter as evil or somehow unworthy of God
and thinking that God and matter have to be somehow kept separate right that that to him is
the opposite view right which the iconoclast view tends to but so right the knowledge of God that
we have is mediated through matter most especially in the incarnation yes right but the people who
see God in the Old Testament see him with their material senses right and and interact with them and
he you know touches them physically right they experience it they are they are material
noetic beings and the gospel right the gospel being what Christ did what Christ accomplished right he
did that as Saint John points out materially yeah he died out across made of wood right in a place
right in space and time materially he accomplished that with the material body of his own yeah right
and so so all of material reality has this sacramental nature right has this sacramental nature where
it is capable of being permeated by the divine energies by the work of God God is able to work
through all of it and and that's what the age to come represents yeah for us yeah you know I think
sometimes when when when people talk about the energies of God you know which is I mean this is a
classic term for orthodox patristic theology and it's in the Bible actually that you know living in
the modern ages we do I think sometimes people might think of the energies of God as being like a
form of radiation you know but it's really God working it's God's works in this world and
and it is as you said it's in matter it's through matter he's making use of matter and frankly some
of that is us we are the matter we are some of the matter that he's using to do his work in the
world and and and you know and and that means that we therefore it goes the other direction that when
we when when we respond to him we do it materially it's not just a meant internal mental thing where
I just think about God or feel really hard about God but but there are material actions of you know
worship offering sacrifices you know the beautiful icons and the everything in the church you know
like all of church buildings incense holy water I mean it goes on and on these are all things that
human beings are using to respond to God and to participate in his works it goes in both directions
right because the matter that God works through is transfigured it's not dissolved it's not
done away with right and replaced with spirit or something else whatever we want to call it
that's better right but it is transfigured and transformed and then becomes a suitable vehicle
for us then to respond through it so the medium of our salvation in both directions the medium
through which we interact with God is the material creation as a whole right and so
that is the medium and Christ is the one mediator between God and man because he is both God
and man both God and the material know what it being yeah that that man is yeah and that and that's why
then there is a bodily resurrection of Christ of humanity it's the ultimate
transfiguration transformation of all matter to be the instrument of God
right there's a resurrection the cosmos is resurrected yeah yeah so that's that's what relics are
everybody it's you know it's it's you know I wanted to to relay a little anecdote actually kind
of connected all that so I mentioned the beginning about venerating the hand of St. Mary Magdalene
and occasionally people ask me like why are you sure you know that it was warm or whatever
well number one I was kissing a whole series of relics right and there was a clear temperature
difference when we came to to kissing her hand it is it's warm just as the hand of any human
woman is warm and the skin is flexible I mean skin still on it's an incorruptible I mean it's 2,000
year old relic but it's incorrupt skin is flexible the hand is warm so on on Mount Athos many of the
monasteries there have the custom I don't know if it's all of them I haven't been to all of them
but I saw it a bunch of them many of the monasteries there have the custom that after dinner so you
usually have vespers and then dinner and then they serve comp line or a compliment as someone wrote
into tell me I should be saying instead I'm dutch so when I hear comp line I think that's where
you queue up to get free stuff comp line yes nice right so when when that service is being served
in the narthex which is where it's traditionally served then often in the nave of the church they're
at the monastery they'll put some tables in the middle of the nave and then they'll take the major
relics that they have at the monastery and put them out there for the veneration of pilgrims and
they'll do this cycle almost every night and you know on on Mount Athos the relics that they have
there most of them are not like the relics that we have here in America where most relics you
encounter here in America are like a tiny little speck you know they're really really small
or they might be something maybe the size of like a pea you know at at at biggest right
in some places there's there's bigger one you know like for instance if you're to go to joy of
all who sorrow cathedral in San Francisco you can see the full relics of St John the wonder worker
there the same thing with St. Mardadia at the monastery in liberty of Illinois but generally speaking
most of the relics you encounter here in America are tiny little specks well on Mount Athos
they have many major relics like whole parts you know whole skulls hands legs feet arms
you know that's pretty common there and so when we're at Semenopathra monastery which has the
hand of St. Mary Magdalene they the the a higher monk father Yakovos actually who's an American
actually so so he was there putting the relics out and then he explained to us in both English
and also in Greek for the Greek speaking pilgrims what the relics were who they belonged to you
know this is the hand of St. Mary Magdalene this is I think there was I think they have a leg
from St. John Chrysostom and some other relics there I don't remember them now it's been a few years
and one of our pilgrims was a little weirded out by this experience because again they weren't
little specks I mean you look in these these are bones right in front of you you know or in one case
a hand um and and he and he just we I just kind of heard him quietly say I don't know that I can do
this like he felt like he just couldn't bring himself to go and kiss these bones and I think a lot
of Americans have this sensibility when when seeing like relics um that that it's it's it's hard you
know because like I'm not used to encountering dead body parts uh and uh whereas you know a lot
of our ancestors would have been much much more used to that kind of thing and then um so father
theater who was leading our pilgrimage he said and to this day I I wish I could remember exactly
what he said but he said something to the effect of a relic is the presence of Christ in the saint
to us you know and that there's a sense in which this is a foretaste of the resurrection as well
and then then the pilgrim with the hesitation he he immediately just stepped forward and and
venerated the relics um and he to experience the fact that her hand is still warm um and you know
a lot of relics have miracles associated with them most don't frankly most do not but I mean
there's some where they're in corrupt the skin is still on them there's some where they're warm
I read recently that the body of saint spirit on his warm um and that his skin is flexible that
his hair and nails grow I mean he's been he's been dead for a long long time um you know there are
some that streamer there are some that have a beautiful odor but again most don't have any of those
kinds of miracles associated with them but if we understand that the body of a saint is being that
saint's body is being that saint and is therefore the body of Christ all of this makes sense all of it
makes sense so so you know I hope that um this kind of recap oh well I mean we did a lot of
recapping but you can see it all kind of flows flows into that um I have some final thoughts on
another related you know related topic whatever but but I know father did you want to give any kind
of concluding remarks about how this specifically relates to relics before we do each our final
our final thoughts well I mean just touching on you know what you what you mentioned about
our ancestors being more familiar with this and in a lot of old countries still today
um in in Palestine in the first century uh though this was only for a brief period in Palestine
admittedly um for example uh it was very common when uh someone's loved one was deceased they would
be buried but they'd only be buried or put in a tomb for a period of a year or two yeah and then
the family would return to the gravesite and to remove the the remains and wash the bones
and put them in an asuary um and there are other similar rituals and and if you're talking about
an orthodox old country like I know they still do this in a lot of parts of Greece yep uh there are
prayers associated with that um and this has been throughout human history uh you know um people have
cared for their departed loved ones meaning their bodies you know uh law you know after after
their departure uh we talked about back of the theolithic period the first human settlements people
buried their departed loved ones in the floors of their homes um they were they were still there
with them right they kept they kept them there with them um and so yeah that that are
modern especially american sort of squeamishness and you know get the body away from me as fast as
possible and make it look like a wax dummy if I have to see it at all and then get it into the ground
and I'll just have my memories of that person that's the weird aberration
yeah in terms of humanity uh not you know kissing the body of a loved one who has died that's not
weird that's normal for humans um the the the other is what's is what's weird and and kind of unnatural
so yeah just a more global perspective and a story perspective on that I think
helps a lot uh right and and and that are our psychological feelings sometimes we can't just trust
that they're the best thing to go by you know um I remember the late father Peter Gilquist now he
was talking about worship but he said whatever someone's used to that's what's normal for them
and it's it's really true you know that that's the thing that they're gonna call normal and
what everyone else does is weird right yeah okay so that that really nicely um uh segues into what
I wanted to say for my final comments then before you make yours father so we had several people that
contacted us um and and we're asked and there was a conversation within our Facebook group actually
about the practice of cremation right now if you if you've been listening to this whole episode
then you know your your mind is gonna start to work on this question right about cremation
and um uh traditionally speaking Christians do not cremate their departed they don't cremation
has been something that was much more associated with with paganism although even then most
pagans throughout history did not cremate um and you know one thing of course is that um a lot of
people don't really understand actually what's involved in most cremation especially here in the
United States you know it's not simply burning the body because um not everything in a human
material body burns up there's still bones left over and the cremation process also includes
grinding the bones up smashing and grinding the bones it's a it's a really kind of a violent thing
now not everywhere does cremation the same but that that's the way that it's done here in America
and of course if someone has any kind of prosthetic implants you know like a a new hip or a joint
or something like that that's tossed in a big bin to be recycled afterwards I mean you can go
down your local funeral home and ask them about this and I'll tell you um but Christians
traditionally do not cremate and of course orthodox Christians you know there are exceptions right
but but generally speaking the rule is that someone who's cremated cannot receive an orthodox
Christian funeral and um if you've wondered why well I mean listen to this this episode because
that body is if it's a Christian it's part of Christ's body you know Christ was not cremated
that body was still him while it was in the grave right he didn't go somewhere else and that that
body was no longer his it was still him it still it was him even when he was in the grave you
know we don't talk about him being gone we say that he was in the grave because his body was in the
grave right Christ was not cremated and that that body rose from the dead and the bodies of
Christians rise from the dead actually the body of everybody is going to rise from the dead but
but when you know Christians with the hope of the resurrection to then act upon that body in a way
that utterly dissolves it right sort of erases it you know especially this practice of sprinkling
ashes that's even more even more this kind of thing of kind of totally erasing the human body
um that you can see now how this is not this is not appropriate for Christians right um and
and now again it's not about the specific molecules right it's about the person and that body
is still that person right um the same understanding is going to extend outward to all human bodies
living or dead to all material creation what do we use it for what are human bodies for they are
for the works of God and dissolving them through cremation or whatever other process someone might
use is is an act of counteracting that right now if you you know if if someone you know has been
cremated I'm not saying that that means that they're damned or that the people who did that are
damned most people are cremating out of out of ignorance actually right because they just maybe
they think it's the cheapest option sidebar it's not necessarily the cheapest option again talk to
if you use a funeral home talk to the the people who run it it may not be actually the cheapest
option and you know there's a lot of considerations I have to go into that but
but if we understand that the bodies of Christians are them and are the body of Christ then
we're going to lovingly lay it to rest and you know as Father Stephen mentioned there's in many
cases um after a period of time the bones are removed and lovingly taken care of put into an
osuary you know like especially a lot of monastic osuaries bones stacked upon bones and it's
interesting you know there's certain ones that you'll see might be a kind of like a honey golden
color or sometimes a sort of scarlet color some will drip mer some will have a beautiful odor
because this is the sanctity of Christ in that person right and you know cremation acts against
that cremation destroys that possibility for that person right so you know this whole this whole
episode is not an argument against cremation but kind of has a has a a byproduct of talking about
relics you know we understand the term relics largely to refer to the bodies of saints but the
truth is is that every human every Christian their body is relics their body is being the body of
Christ for us and we should treat it that way that's how we should treat it so I'm not just talking
about cremation here but about the way that we attend to other human persons not just after the
material death but even as they are living amongst us that that body is relics that body is for us
the presence of Christ in our midst he is working in them they are doing his works because
God works in matter God uses matter for our salvation just like St. John of Damascus said
Father Stephen yeah so fun fact number 327 about me is that
my favorite novel is Albert Camus the stranger and at another point after World War II Albert Camus
gave a talk to a group of Dominican monks in France and he was asked to speak on the topic of
what the world wants or expects from Christians in the wake of everything that had happened in World
War II and Albert Camus having been part of the resistance in France and etc and in it he gives
albeit in a somewhat hopeful way what has been for a long time in the modern world the
primary criticism of Christians and Christianity from people outside of it which is essentially
that Christians only care about spiritual things and not about this world and that they do that
because of their religion they're just worried about going to heaven when they die and they don't
care about anything else so they don't care if the water and the air get polluted they don't care
if people starve to death they don't care about any of this stuff in this world because they just
you know they believe the right things so they're going to go to heaven when they die and they just
care about the next world and not about this world and Camus kind of lays that at the feet
that idea basically at the feet of the Dominican monks who he's kind of blaming for their silence
in the lead up to World War II and even during World War II when they had kind of cloistered
themselves but he concludes it by saying essentially you know we may never get to live in a world
where children aren't killed but we can work together to live in a world where fewer children
are killed and I think it's easy when we hear that response especially when it's put in a patronizing
or not very insightful way by an atheist on the internet it's very easy to rattle off a bunch
of responses like you know hey Christians built the first hospitals and the first orphanages
and you know feed people and all the charity Christians have done historically and that's all
true right and it's not that that's invalid but the people who make that criticism aren't getting
it from nowhere they're not just making it up it wouldn't sting and we wouldn't get defensive if
they were just making it up out of whole cloth you know even some of our very popular American hymns
I love all fly away it's super catchy but it's horrible theology right one bright morning when
this life is over all fly away goodbye body goodbye world I'm going to heaven I'm going somewhere better
and that is foreign to Christianity that idea isn't Christianity as it has historically existed
it may be some form of narcissism it may be something else but that's that's not Christianity
for Christians this world this material world right the matter that makes up the world
to come is not going to be a whole new set of matter it's going to be this matter rearranged and
transfigured and reordered and re-created in that sense and so for us as Christians as we
as St. Paul says work out our salvation with fear and trembling because God is working within us
to will and to do according to his his pleasure as we're doing that we're doing that in this arena
through this medium that is material and so we need to not be inspired by our reaction to
accusations from atheists but in response to the example set for us by our forebears in the faith
who came to new peoples and created written languages and taught people groups literacy so they
could read the scriptures and read and understand the prayers of the church and come to know Christ
and and and sometimes taught them farming methods while they were at it because if someone's starving
to death it makes it very difficult for them to learn about who Christ is and to focus on anything
else they did these things not in addition to and definitely not instead of preaching the gospel
but these are part and parcel these things go together right Christ says
not only blessed are those who teach little ones the commandments but also blessed are those who give
to the little ones a cup of cold water in his name those go together and so we need to care deeply
about this world this created material world and the people in it and doing good here and finding
repentance here and bringing other people to the knowledge of God here because it's through this
medium of this life in this world in all of its materiality that we're going to find our salvation
and our entrance into the next world which is really just this world fully transformed and made
perfect reaching its goal for which it was created in the first place amen well everybody that
is our show for tonight thank you so much for listening if you didn't get a chance to call in during
the live broadcast we'd love to hear from you either via email at Lord of Spirits at ancientfeat.com
or you can message us at our Lord of Spirits podcast facebook page we read everything but can't
respond to everything and we do say what you send for possible use in future episodes and join us
for our live broadcasts on the second and fourth Thursdays of the month at seven pm eastern four pm
and if you are on facebook you can like our page join our discussion group leave reviews and
ratings everywhere but most importantly share this show with a friend whom you know is going to
love it or if they're going to hate it we like hate listeners they're going to and finally be
sure to go to ancientfeat.com stroke support and help make sure we and lots of other AFR
podcasters stay on the air thank you very much and may God bless you all you've been listening to the
Lord of Spirits with Orthodox Christian priests father Andrew Stephen Damick and father Stephen
DeYoung a listener supported presentation of ancient faith radio and I beheld and I heard the voice
of many angels round about the throne and the beasts and the elders and the number of them was
10,000 times 10,000 than thousands of thousands saying with a loud voice worthy is the land that
was slain to receive power and riches and wisdom and strength and honor and glory and blessing
chapter 5 verses 11 through 12