I'm really glad we could listen to this song twice. I don't have anything more than I really want
to say about the topic of resiliency. Some of the traits emotionally that are associated with
resilient people is the first one is that they know the parameters. They know their boundaries. They
know where the end of the-
their hand stops and where the air or other people's presence begins and other characteristics
is of resilient people that they they're able to practice acceptance that whatever comes
down the highway there's a certain ability to know that there's more to all this.
There are many other characteristics of resilient people they know that they don't have all
the answers.
And interestingly when researchers take this, they find that these people considered more
resilient than others are able to sit inside it as well isn't that interesting.
With that I will stop and say this is Dr. Albert Rossi for Ancient Faith Radio saying once
again I and you the listener are called to support Ancient Faith Radio as best we can with
our prayer and with our finances.
Dr. Rossi is the author of-
the Ancient Faith Publishing Book,
becoming a healing presence,
available at store.ancientfaith.com.
This has been a listener-supported presentation
of Ancient Faith Radio.
Glory to Jesus Christ, glory forever, you're listening to ancient faithradio.com.
He will be a staff for the righteous with which for them to stand and not to fall, and
he will be the light of the nations and the hope of those whose hearts are troubled.
who dwell on the earth will fall down and worship him.
and they will praise and bless and celebrate with song the Lord of Spirits.
1st denoc, chapter 48, verses 4 through 5.
The modern world doesn't acknowledge but is nevertheless haunted by spirits, angels,
demons, and saints.
In our time, many year into break free of the prison of a flat, secular materialism, to
see and to know reality as it truly is.
What is this spiritual reality like?
How do we engage with it well?
How do we permeate everyday life with spiritual presence?
Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew Stephen Damick
and Father Stephen De Young,
post this live Colin show,
focused on enchantment in creation,
the union of the scene and unseen as made by God
and experienced by mankind throughout history.
Welcome to the Lord of Spirits.
Welcome back to the Lord of Spirits podcast.
It is...
one of all of our favorite things where we look at all that stuff that's integral to Christianity
But that does not fit into a materialist worldview because that worldview is garbage
I'm father Andrew Stephen Damick in Emmaus, Pennsylvania and my co-host is father Stephen D. Young who's with me from Lafayette, Louisiana
and if you're listening to us live you can call in at 855 AF radio. That's 855 237 2346
Matas Katruti, who is just back from Co-
it land. Yay, we'll be taking your calls tonight. We will get to your calls in the second part
of today's show. So, in our last two episodes, we talked about sacred geography, how the reality of
sacred spiritual place overlaps material place, including paradise, which is the mountain of God.
And last time we talked about the underworld, this episode is titled The Lord of Spirits Goes to Hell,
which some people apparently thought was repeatable.
But it is not, we are talking about what happens when the Lord of spirits himself.
That is, the incarnate son and word of God, Jesus Christ, makes the journey into the underworld.
That journey is a major theme of the Holy Week in Poska services that for the Orthodox Church are coming up
this very next week in real time. So this is also our Holy Week and Poska special.
I feel like it, we should call it like our season finale, but we're not stopping.
But um...
So to begin our journey tonight, we're going to do what we almost always do.
We're going to take a trip back thousands of years.
And we're going to arrive at an ancient ruined city in the Levant
in northwestern Syria, near the modern city of Latakia.
That's right.
We're heading back to Ugrit.
And that means we're going to be talking about our old adversary, bail.
So father Steven, take us to Ugrit.
You got it.
You betcha.
that's the tour of the slogan.
Yeah, right.
For people from the upper Midwest.
Yes, yeah, yeah.
Say, oh yeah, sure.
So, right, well, as you said, this is a city that has not been around in a long, long
time.
Right.
Like 4,000 years roughly or almost five, more than 5,000, more than about.
No, no, no.
This has been a round for a-
Yeah, for about 3,200 but there
Roughly yeah, give or take
But before that it was around for a long time
Garret was originally built settled I should say around
Well, it was early in the Neolithic period we won't get into that again the walls seem to have been built around 6,000 BC
Oh, it was pretty old.
Right.
And again, you know, if these dates are problematic to you, adjust however you need to, but that's the current archaeological data where the walls were built.
And then Ugarit was destroyed circa 1180 BC.
So this is a city that existed for thousands of years, but thousands of years, thousands of years ago.
it wasn't rebuilt, it was pretty much plowed up.
over and it was not discovered until the middle of the 20th century that the city was even
there.
Now were there indications?
I mean, did people know that it had existed?
They just didn't know where it was?
Not really.
Oh wow.
Because it's in an area that's now called Rashshamra and when it was found, a new language was
discovered and named Eucharitic.
because you've got it.
Right.
But which is a northwestern
Semitic language, meaning it's sort of a close cousin to Hebrew.
It's another one of the dialects that emerged from old Canaanite
around the time that the city was being destroyed actually.
but it's unlike
biblical Hebrew
It's not written with the Phoenician alphabetic script. It was written with the Kuneiform script that's used for
Akkadian and other
early Semitic languages. So
phonetically like if you read it in transliteration and you know Hebrew
Well, if you've studied any Semitic languages even Arabic even modern Arabic
You know basically the consonantle structure of
most of the vocabulary.
So the difference is between
Semitic languages are mainly vocalization meaning vowels.
So in transliteration, if you're good with Hebrew and
Aramaic, you can pick up
Euretic really quickly.
To read it in the Kineiform script,
you have to learn the Kineiform script,
which is a lot more difficult,
I can say, first hand attempts.
Right.
Because you've got a couple hundred symbols to learn.
Yeah, I'm 22.
I remember when I was you know a preteen seeing seeing that alphabet and going that's really cool
And then like learning three symbols and then giving up yeah, yeah, yeah, and they all look fairly similar
They're not right right different from what I know yeah
so
But the reason the language was so important is there are literally a ton of Hebrew words
That we did not know what they meant
Yeah, because the only tech
We had them in were sort of scattered parts of the Hebrew Bible. Yeah, so they just made guesses when they would translate.
Right. And that's why sometimes if you compare any of the modern translations of the Old Testament to parts of like the King James version,
you'll see that they're sometimes radically different and you're like, what is happening there?
And it's because the King James translators were doing their best. They were like at the Latin and they were looking at the
degree.
can kind of go in, you know, and their place is even in the Greek translation
where you could tell the rabbis centuries later we're kind of looking at it and
going, you know, and kind of approximating. Right, right. So we get the donkey
sentars? Sort of. Yeah, sort of. Okay, okay. Yes. Yeah. I'm just gonna throw that
out there for people don't get the topic for another time. Probably when we talk
about vampires. Just a further piece it.
But yeah, so you get a lot of weird things.
You get the edge of the bed of Damascus
versus a lion cub in one place.
There's a lot of really interesting things
that sounds like that.
So we found the same words,
albeit vocalized a little differently
in these egregoritic texts.
And so that gave us like a few dozen more examples.
Yeah, and it's piles and piles of clay tablets, right?
cable that are used to it's right.
because this is all written on Fire Clay tablets, but these Fire Clay tablets from the ancient
Near East, once they fired them, they're almost indestructible. Like if you hurled one at
your floor, you'd dent your floor before you'd break the tablet.
That's really convenient. So that's why we have so many.
Yeah. But I guess most of them are like useless, right? Most of them are like shopping lists
and whatever, right?
Right, right, and so.
If there are several places, oh listener, if you want to study further, there are several places where you can get a full ride to get a PhD in Subariology in the United States.
People writing is down right now, I can tell.
There are addowments and stuff for people to translate all this stuff.
And there aren't enough people to do it.
And part of it is that you had to translate it, you know, a
hundred grocery lists and trade documents before you get to something interesting, but
they're still turning up interesting things.
A few years ago, I mean, five or ten years ago, they discovered a whole new version of
the flood story.
Oh nice.
On a Babylonian tablet.
So there is interesting stuff there.
You just got to be willing to get into the weeds and to learn kudea form and do some language
study.
But so the reason we're talking about this is one set of tablets in particular.
Yeah.
Yeah, so it's not just relevant to biblical studies, but there's also.
It's broadly.
Yeah, right, broadly, right, yeah.
But there's also the, yeah.
One of those has been named by us, the Bale Cycle, because it's like an epic cycle.
It's like an epic poetry cycle.
And Bale, because he's the main character.
So this is...
We get all through the Old Testament,
we see bail worshipers, prophets of bail,
altars built to bail, they're kind of the bad guys
through most of the books of the kingdoms
or first and second Samuel and first and second kings.
And first and second Chronicles,
you see them turn up in the prophets.
So we knew about bail, we knew,
like for example, Queen Jezebel, who Mary's King A. Hab
the northern-
Kingdom of Israel is from the Phoenician Kingdom, which is in what's now Lebanon, right?
So we knew she brought the bail worship down from there.
So we knew this religion's there.
But this is the first time with these these inruidic texts, including the bail cycle that
we got sort of the other side of that where we got texts written by bail worshipers, four
bail worshipers.
Yeah.
Instead of the other.
of a pandemic bill worship. So we're getting to see how their religion looked from the inside.
And there's lots of ritual texts and lots of other stuff. But the bail cycle is what we're
we're here to talk about tonight. And bail himself.
Bale is both a title and a name of a God. Right. So the word Bale or Baal is
is just the word for Lord or master.
Right.
And that creates some funny things
for people who don't know that.
So the founder, for example, of Kabbalistic Judaism
is the Bail Shem Tov.
And you're like, wait, Bail.
Yeah.
Right.
Rabbi or whatever named Bail.
But it just means Lord.
It's the Arabic word for master.
Right, the same way that we use.
we use various versions of master when we address bishops, they did for rabbis, right?
Sure.
In Aramaic.
There's also a place in the minor prophets where Yahweh the God of Israel says,
previously you knew me as Baal, but now you know me as husband, which of course are German.
What?
century German friends jumped all over O.C. look.
Yeah, right.
polytheists, right?
They're bail workers, he's admitting it.
But if you read it in context, it's saying,
previously you knew me as master, now you know me as husband.
He's talking about the relationship with Israel,
that he's not just their lord, but he's also,
he also loves them and cares for them.
So yeah, but when we talk about bail,
like when you have the profits of bail on.
Mount Carmel with the prophet Elijah. The bail there was because a specific guy who was
just referred to as bail. And that's the person who the bail cycle was about. His father's
name is L, which is just which just means for God. A God, yeah, exactly. So yeah. Yeah.
There's the most high God is named God and his son is named Lord. Yeah. Right. Yeah.
And that's not...
coincidental, right? The idea that you have most high God and then a sun. We talked about this a
little in a couple of previous episodes, but oh yeah, right. Eating here. Yeah, like early early on,
some of our early episodes. Right. That this is this is a pattern you see throughout ancient
religion is that the most high God is the father to a son, a divine son who presides.
over the divine counsel. Right. Right. And then that sets up in almost every single
ancient mythology, not all of them, I think, but in almost every single one, what's
referred to as the succession myth, where you've got a son or some kind of lesser
god overthrowing his father or overthrowing some greater gods. I mean, the
details slide around a little bit depending on which one you're looking at. And
That's...
in the bail cycle, which until what was it the 1960s, 1970s?
No one had known those details for over 3,000 years.
Right, about bail.
About bail, in particular.
Right.
Yes, you've got the succession method in many mythologies.
So you've got Zeus killing Kronos, Kronos, Castering, Odin, his father.
Right, I mean, right, yep.
Right all the way through.
So when we talked about that in terms of the way the devil is portrayed in the profits
in particular.
exactly. The Old Testament that it's sort of correcting the record that well yeah you
maybe tried but you didn't succeed in making yourself the most I got right. Right.
In pagan myths generally there's a success that happens there but yeah. Right.
Right. And so this is what the story of the bail cycle primarily is. Right. The story of
a bail cycle sort of the through line of the epic cycle is this is the story of Bay
sort of insurrection. Yeah. And his father, we talked before also how in after a certain point in history in all of these ancient religions, the, all these forms of ancient religion, the, the most high God sort of recedes off into the distance.
Right, and you can really see this at the bail cycle because technically
Bales revolt is to make his father L the most high god
And for him to preside in the council, but L like doesn't do much of anything.
Yeah, right. Because so bail is actually revolting against
Yam and Nahar, right, who are the gods of the ocean and the rivers respectively.
And I think I think even in modern Arabic, Nahar means river.
Right in, let us know if I got that wrong.
uh...
yom is the word for c or ocean we talk about how that rip that chaos right
right
And he's the most high god at the beginning of the bail cycle. He's the one in charge. And then Nahar is referred to as the Prince.
Yeah, so the one the son who presides in the idea is to get a new dynasty in there essentially.
Right. Right. Right. Right. So yeah, so you know, especially for people who have read Father Stevens' blog, you might have heard some of this before, almost certainly.
certainly, but there's this very dramatic moment in the bail cycle where bail goes
up on, is it Mount Herman? Am I memory that quickly?
No, that's not.
No, no. Mount Zafon with Bale.
Zafon, yeah, okay.
Let's wait and get to that in a sec.
Okay, all right, that's fine.
Don't want to spoil yet. Okay, okay, sorry.
Yeah, I'm just so excited.
Hold your horses, man.
Keep it tight.
So, one of the primary things that the Bale Cycle illuminates is
one of the Psalms. Right. This is Psalm 24 in the traditional Hebrew numbering, Psalm 23 in the
traditional Greek numbering. Okay. All right. And so this, once we found the Bale Cycle, we could see
that this Psalm, this Hebrew Psalm, is sort of a response to the Bale Cycle. Directly references it.
Right, yeah.
Right. Right. And so in, yeah, one more thing about sort of the arc of the bail cycle before
we read this all. So just to get to give the broad arc, right, in the, the broad arc of the
bail cycle, the broad arc of the action, bail decides he's going to take charge and, and put
put his dad in charge. So he's going to overthrow Yamma Nihar.
We set out to stage this sort of rebellion,
and he totally wins by a lot,
but decides to go to the underworld
after he totally wins.
Yeah, and he gets stayed there.
Yeah, when he goes to the underworld,
he runs into moat to the god of death
who we're gonna be seeing a lot of tonight
and gets in a fight with moat,
which he also totally wins.
But even though he totally wins,
the sides.
stay in shiel and take up residence there.
Right.
So that's sort of the broad strokes
of the story that the bailwisherpers
were telling themselves in their Prodevil propaganda.
So now, let's go ahead and look at this all.
Starting to give it away now, okay.
All right, so this is Psalm 24.
You know, people, you should recognize a lot of this,
but I'm just gonna read the whole Psalm to you.
It's only 10 verses long.
Psalm 24.
The earth is the lords and the fullness thereof, the world and they that dwell therein.
For he has found it upon the seas and established it upon the floods.
Who shall ascend into the hill of the Lord, or who shall stand in his holy place?
He that hath clean hands and a pure heart, who have not lifted up his soul and divinity
nor sworn deceitfully?
He shall receive the blessing from the Lord and righteousness from the God of his salvation.
This is the general-
of them that seek him, that seek thy face, O Jacob.
Lift up your heads, O you gates, and be lift up, ye everlasting doors, and the king of
glorious shall come in. Who is this king of glory? The Lord's strong and mighty, the Lord
mighty in battle. Lift up your heads, O you gates, even lift them up, ye everlasting doors,
and the king of glorious shall come in. Who is this king of glory, the Lord of hosts?
He is the king of glory. Okay, everybody, you, especially if you're Orthodox, you've
heard this song.
You've definitely heard it, but you know if you're Christian if you read the Bible at all
You know this is a song. You should know it's song 24 all right. Well, let's talk about
All the cool things are happening in the song with regards to the bail cycle
Unbelievable you guys are not gonna believe this you're not gonna believe it even if you've read
You know the relevant post from Father Stevens blog which talks about some of this doesn't talk about all of it
But let's let's talk about a lot more of it. So first one, right? Yeah, so
So you read the King James.
game's version because yes, which is for the apostle Paul it's good enough for us right and
So there there's someone out there by the way who doesn't like it when I say right
I feel like I'm gonna say a lot more tonight
Probably just to mess with that guy
Anyway, first one. Okay, the earth is the lords and the full is there of such a risotto maw is not appropriate for a lent
That's true. That's true. I'll do respect
I'm going a little p-
I'm getting a little punchy here at the end of the sixth week of lint.
Okay, so I mentioned that because there are some things that are kind of obscured by English translation.
Right. This isn't so much mis-translated as just sort of obscured.
And so one of the big ones right off the bat is that English Bibles buy in large with some exceptions.
Don't translate.
Yahweh is Yahweh. Yeah, it's usually Lord they put Lord at all caps and all caps
Yeah, so you get the earth is the lords and the fullness there of but it's really the earth is Yahweh's and the fullness there of right and
Why I'm saying that's important is that sometimes what the text is saying and we're gonna see this over and over again tonight
sometimes what the text is directly asserting is that things that the
pagan nations were saying about their gods are actually true of Yahweh the God of Israel
and not of those pagan gods. Yeah, yeah, right. So there's a lot of smack talk really right going on
in the Bible frankly right so but if you don't know not not not your guy know you don't translate
that the name, right, then you kind of lose on that, you lose out on that idea, right?
So if you're saying, you know, no Charles is king, right?
Like as opposed to somebody else, right?
He's king, not this other guy.
Whereas if you just say, no, the king is king.
Yeah.
Right.
You don't get the, you know, right?
It's like, no, this is the right.
So that begins right away in verse one, right?
where it says, right, the earth is the lo-
towards the fullness thereof, right?
It's the earth is Yahweh's and the fullness thereof.
Yeah, it does not have anything to do with it.
The world that they dwell therein, right?
Meaning the world, the creation, the cosmos,
and everything in it belongs to Yahweh,
not to anyone else, right?
He's placing a personal claim on it.
That's why I think it's appropriate here
to point out the personal name.
And eagle eared, that's not a phrase.
year what would be years.
What's your equivalent?
I don't know.
Dog meat doesn't work anyway.
Yeah, I don't know.
A lot of animals have good hearing, but...
Yes, attentive listeners amongst all listeners.
Who, if Benchwood Orthodox funeral service,
might recognize that.
Right.
That said, right when the priest anoints the body with oil
and probably puts some ash or dirt depending on the tradition,
tradition right
It's usually done right at the end of the funeral service or sometimes it's done right before the burial.
Right. Right before the burial, right before the casket is sealed and the burial takes place.
Yeah, the earth is the Lord is the fullness throughout the round world and all they that dwell therein.
Right. That's the version in my head anyway.
Right. And so just hearing that in English, it might not be clear what any of that has to do with the fact that you're burying somebody.
Right, except maybe has something to do with dirt.
You're putting it in the earth, I guess?
Yeah.
Right.
But the point here, once we understand what the verse is doing, right, the earth, it's
saying that the cosmos and everyone in it, right, every sentient being in it belongs
to Yahweh and no one else, right?
Then you understand that when we do this in the funeral service, we're asserting a claim.
Yeah, that this person is not being handed over to the
God of death, this person belongs to Yahweh.
Right.
Even though he's about to go into the earth, he still belongs to Yahweh.
He still belongs to the one true God, right?
So that's where it starts, right?
So right off the bat, shots fired, right?
That no, all of this belongs to Yahweh and no one else.
First two starts with four, right?
It's because.
Yeah because
Why? Why does it all belong to him?
Because he founded it because he built it, right?
So it's his he made it.
And he did that by founding it upon the seas, which is
which is the word yum and established it upon the floods is how the King James does it in floods is Nahar.
What do you know?
So he built it on top of...
Yom and Nahar. Right, which is
basically saying
Remember now, Bale is going up against Yom and Nahar to try to defeat them so he can set his dad and himself up as the new dynasty
Up on the mountain, but but what God is saying here through this song
prophetically is
no, no, no, no, no, no, I'm the one who conquered the
chaos of the oceans and the seas and the
rivers and I built my world on top of them, you know, which is, you know, you got that
image of sort of submission and defeat, right? You know, just like if you level a city
and then build your new city up on top of it, that's what's going on here. So again,
it's a comment on the bail cycle. You know, there's no, yeah.
If you want power over chaos, right? He didn't have to defeat it and fight it. Right.
the images of him laying the f***
foundation for a building on the ocean. Right. Right. Right. Right. So this is
you get the same kind of imagery in the book of Revelation at the end.
The sea like glass. Yeah. It just obeys him. Right. It's just flat. Right.
Solid. It's their chaotic and choppy and out of control. So it all belongs to
the God of Israel because he created it.
Right? And he subjected.
the forces of chaos to order when he created.
As we saw what we talked about,
Genesis 1 at a couple of points.
So then, verse three, the smack talk continues.
So this continues.
Right, because it says,
it asks the rhetorical question,
who shall ascend the literally mountain?
Who will ascend the mountain of Yahweh?
Right?
This is the harm away.
This is the mountain.
paradise that we talked about, the Mount of Assembly, right? The place where everyone meets.
Who's going to go up the mountain? Or who shall stand in his holy place, right? The holy place,
the holy space of paradise, right? Who's going to come into paradise? Yeah. Not you, buddy. Yeah.
Right? Not me. He's at the devil who rebel. He can't go back. He's gone. He's thrown out. He's done.
It's great. Rise of the other world that you stay in there.
right? Right? Right. Yeah, but this is connected again once again back to the funeral because who's
gonna send this person by God's grace that you're bearing in the ground? They're gonna send the
mountain of God. Right. Bale doesn't get to do it. This guy does. Verse four verses four and five.
He that asked clean hands that appear heart who has not lifted up his soul unto vanity or so
or deceitfully, these feelings
of the blessing from Yahweh.
And yeah.
and righteousness from the God of his salvation.
Yeah.
So he's the one and that righteousness is literally he will receive justification for all right.
He will, he's the one who will be put in order.
That's that creation language.
The same way that Yahweh put the creation in order and restored them and built them and
blessed them.
He's going to do that to this human who does not belong to bail and he's going to do
it instead of bail.
So this is that replacement idea going on as sort of being rubbed in his face.
And so then it's clear then that this understanding of what the Psalmist 4 is preserved in orthodox liturgical practice by virtue of it being used in the funeral.
Right, right.
Yeah.
And now, as we come to the last four verses, are also preserved in orthodox liturgical
practice.
That's starting in verse seven.
Be lift up your heads, OU gates, and be lifted up,
ye everlasting doors, and the King of glory shall come in.
There's this dialogue, right?
Of who is this King of glory?
And it's Yahweh, strong and mighty, Yahweh, mighty in battle.
Then again, lift up your heads, OU gates, lift them up,
everlasting doors, and the King of glory shall come in.
Who is this King of glory?
Yahweh, Sabah, Oat.
That's the Lord of Hosts.
Yahweh, Zabo, Yahweh of armies as we talked about before.
Also known as the Lord of Spirits.
Right.
He is the king of glory.
So get the name is important.
He is the king of glory, not anybody else.
Right.
Not anybody else.
Um, and so this, these verses,
uh, which seem kind of weird,
taken by themselves.
Yeah, right?
Because gates don't have heads.
Right, they can't lift them.
say. Yeah. Yeah. It doesn't seem to have questions. It doesn't seem to have on its face. It doesn't
seem to have much to do with the six verses that came before. Right. Yeah. Right. And so it's
interesting. Sometimes you go and look at look at some of the weird exegesis of this you get from
certain services. Our friends in other groups. Yeah. The early modern periods of the 16th and 17th
centuries but I'll leave that.
to two others. But they didn't have the bail cycle. And in the bail cycle, and this is,
I'll give you the reference. So this is bail Roman numeral one period, Roman numeral two
period, 24 through 29. And the way that works is, that means it's tablet one column two lines,
24 through 20.
So if you're one of the folks out there who knows Kudaea Forum, you could actually go look at the tablet and find this.
Otherwise, you could find it in a critical edition with that information.
There is this episode during Bales Rebellion in which a group of angels, it's Malach, it's the word for angel, which also means messenger, of course.
come from
Yaman Nahar because they've heard rumblings that Bale is up to something. Bale is sort
of being a rabble rouser on Mount Zafon amongst the other gods and is trying to get them
to join his rebellion. So these messengers come to say, hey, we heard there's something
brewing here you better not try anything basically.
Right.
when they come and they enter the room, right, the representatives of Yamuna
are enter the room, all of the gods who are sitting on their little throes,
they all sort of put their heads between their legs.
Yeah, like don't hurt us.
We're sorry.
So we're not with that guy.
Yeah.
So they all sort of wimp out.
And so Bale sort of standing there by himself.
So then Bale has his sort of Braveheart moment where he gives his
Right.
Ah, easy to give us.
He's going to rally the troops.
He's going to tell the other gods, look man,
no, we can do this.
They can take our lives.
They'll never take our freedom.
You can't handle the truth, et cetera.
And it's not this day.
Yeah.
That's right.
So he goes to give this speech and he begins it
because they all have their heads between their legs
by saying, lift up your heads, oh, ye gods.
Yeah.
And be lifted up as he gives this sort of rousing
about how you know we're gonna go to Delaware and then we're gonna go to Pennsylvania and then we're gonna go to many screams
There's a reference for all the JLXers out there
Right so these are the words with which in the bail cycle bail rallies the other gods in his rebellion to go to victory
Yeah lift up your heads guys right got this and
And so what we see.
in the soul is that Yahweh the God of Israel is throwing those words back. Yeah,
bail. He's throwing those words back at bail slash the devil who even though he
totally won twice is some reason down in the underworld. I meant that I meant to do
that guys. Yeah. It's throwing it back at him. Right. He's throwing it back at his face.
the very
words that he used. So then the question is, well, why is it gates rather than gods? Right?
And this is related to a little bit of what we talked about last time, this palace in
shiol, this palace in the underworld that bail ends up building, right? With the brazen gates
that we talked about. So the reason Yahweh is talking to the gates is that
coming in, right? Bale hears him knocking and now he's coming in. Yeah. So and as he's coming in,
he's throwing these words back at Bale as a taunt, right? As Maul. As he comes to raid his palace,
right? Yeah. So when we understand that, you take the psalm as a whole, this psalm is prophesying
that there's going to come a day, that those, even the dead.
don't belong to the devil, they don't belong to bail, they don't belong to the Lord
of the underworld, they don't belong to Hades or she-old, they still belong to Yahweh,
the God of Israel, and he's going to come down there and get them.
He's going to come down there and break in and take them because they still belong
to him.
This is what we call the harrowing of hell.
Right.
then and then and well hundred or so years later it happens.
right? Yeah. Yeah. You know that you've got the the God of death, the devil, laying claim to these dead people
and God saying no actually they're mine. They're totally mine. Yeah. And so this is then a big part of
of what we're going to be celebrating
as we come to the end of Holy Week.
especially Holy Saturday, both in the morning and evening, we are going to be making
present again, you talk about Saber Time and Space, the day on which this actually
happened when Christ after his death on the cross, his soul descends into
Hades and goes there to kick in the gates and get those there who belong.
to him and his father and bring them out.
Yeah, and what's fun is if you look at,
you know, iconographic representations of this,
both East and West,
it is not depicted as being like a nice,
gentle, peaceful action.
You know, the doors are being not just open to whatever,
but smashed open and often,
various icons knocked on the ground.
And one of my favorite that I saw today,
The door just smashed on the...
and there's a demon who's been crushed underneath it.
You know, with his legs and arms coming out
and the other demons are off to the side going,
whoa, whoa, what's, hey, what's happening?
Yeah, no.
Yeah, right, right.
And yeah, so then, you know, if you're orthodox
and you've been to PASCA, you've seen this.
Now, it's minusing that not every single tradition
has the one particular part we're gonna mention,
but a lot of people will wear it
even if they don't have this in their tradition.
And if you're not orthodox people,
I'm just gonna tell you right now,
Go to pass.
you will see exactly what we're about to talk about.
Right, so May 1st.
Yeah, exactly May 1st.
Late at night.
Yeah, I make sure they, yeah, there's some poor people.
They swap like, and they're going to show up in the morning
of May 2nd.
Go so I understand this is your Easter.
I'm like, um, we're sleeping at all.
May 1st, 2021 will become March 26th 50 or 30 80.
Right.
So everybody's going to be outside the church.
there's
going to make a procession around the church and then there's going to be an entrance made.
And in many traditions, what you're going to see is the priest is going to go up to the
door of the church.
And he's going to bang on the door.
Now sometimes he does it with his fist.
Sometimes he does it with a hand cross.
I have broken a couple of hand crosses.
And he says, lift up your gate so you princes will be lifted up.
You everlasting doors and the king of glory shall enter in.
There's a voice from inside that says who?
who is this king of glory or as a good friend of mine once said about 20 years ago, who
is this cling of glory, which I have never let him to live down. I say to him, I text
it to him every single year. Who is this king of glory? And I see I'm going to mess up
and say it wrong. And then the priest says, the Lord's strong and mighty, the Lord mighty
in war. And this is done three times. And then at the very end, the priest then says,
the Lord of hosts, he is the king of glory.
Or Yahweh sabote, as it says right there in...
in my bad version of Hebrew. He's King of glory and then the doors are opened. So what you get
then is this liturgical, it's not a reenactment. Remember what we said about ritual participation,
a zillion times in the show. That moment, that place, it becomes the invasion of Hades. Truly,
and you are there. This is, this is the sun and word of God, the Lord of hosts himself,
of the Lord of Spirits.
invading how and because he's going in there to release those who are held captive
by the power of death and the devil. And so this understanding was preserved in the
liturgical tradition of the Orthodox Church, even though probably a lot of you out there,
this is the first time you've ever heard any of this stuff from the bail cycle.
It was new to me just a few years ago, but this understanding was preserved in the
the surgical practice that these
lines from this Psalm are about the invasion of the realm of death by the son of God himself
to come and rescue the dead. If that doesn't just blow you away, I don't know what's...
Well, there's a lot more to come.
Yeah, actually.
And more to come.
And to put a point on that, if you'd asked any Orthodox person,
who's the voice coming from it, they would tell you, oh, that's the devil.
That's the double.
And what is this? Well, this is Christ getting down the doors and recording this song, right?
So that interpretation, that context
for this passage of Scripture for Psalm 24, slash 23, the context for that, the original ancient context for that, even though Ugarit was buried in the dirt for 3000 years.
Right, right. That context was preserved in the Orthodox Church through its worship. And so
This is what we're talking about not to go all the way down this rabbit trail, but this is an exhibit A of what we're talking about in the Orthodox Church, where we talk about tradition.
Tradition isn't like some additional information that's not in the Bible that we add into the Bible. It's not just sort of folk customs that accumulated along the route of history.
But when we talk about holy tradition, we're talking about the way in which.
the worship, the practice, the theology, all of this of the Orthodox Church has preserved
the original context of the scriptures, the original context of the belief of the apostles
and of the prophets, and the authors of scripture and of generations passed.
And this is exhibit A of it.
about the only place you could get that original context until we
up Ugarit was the Orthodox Church and most people who encountered it in the
Orthodox Church until we recovered Ugarit just thought well that's a weird
allegorical interpretation or something. Right yeah right so that's the first
half of the show we've got two more halves to go and well let's have a break
and let's hear from the voice of Steve let's go to break. Father Andrew
Stephen Damick and father Stephen D-
young will be back in a moment.
Take your calls on the next part of the Lord of
Spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF Radio.
Doxamute Online, Tolkien, Enchantment, and the Christian
Life, an ancient faith event.
For the Christian, the enchanted or sacramental world
to a wholesome, full-life in Christ.
The work of fantasy author J.R.R. Tolkien
provides a shaping for the imagination and soul
that contributes to this vision.
Join the hosts of Ancient Faith Radio's
Aman Sule podcast in this special online event
that explores how this shaping happens
in partnership with the St. Basil Center
for Orthodox Thought and Culture.
The webinar will take place on Friday, May 7,
and Saturday, May 8, and speakers include
Dr. Cyril Gary Jenkins, Father Andrew Steven Daymick,
and rich and rollin'.
The cost is $30 and registration will close
on Wednesday, May 5th at noon, Easter.
To secure your spot, please visit store.ancientfaith.com,
slash doxamot.
That store.ancientfaith.com slash doxamot.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits, the Father-Anger Stephen Damick and Father Stephen
And young.
If you have a question, call now at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF radio.
Welcome back.
This is the second half of the show.
And it's where we begin to take your calls.
Just like the voice of Steve just said,
you can reach this at 855-AF radio or 855-237-2346.
And it looks like we actually have a couple calls coming in here.
Oh actually the
person I was going to take just disappeared off the call board.
All right, well, try to call back.
And we'd love to hear from you.
So all right, so just to recap, we were just
talking about Psalm 24 in the first half
and about how it is basically a whole bunch of smack talk
against bail worship.
Because ancient Israel was surrounded by bail worshipers
and occasionally bail worship even invaded
the life of the people of
Israel. Some of them began to worship bail. So bail is definitely a going concern in
that time and place. So, all right, well, let's go ahead and take a call. So it looks
like we have Eugene calling. And if I remember correctly, Eugene, you're somewhere in the
upper Midwest, isn't that right?
Yeah, sure. You bet, yeah.
There it is. You're ready to take your trip to you, Garret?
Oh, yeah.
Oh yeah, so
Eugene, what is it you've got for us tonight, Eugene?
Well, first I just gotta say that I'm very glad
to finally be calling into the Almond Sula Live call
and program.
Uh-huh, sure.
Let's cut this guy off right now.
Yeah, just kidding.
Just kidding, just kidding.
Is this the token, token call?
Yes, this is the guy who says
that they're the same podcast.
Oh, okay.
I mean, you've already referenced it a couple of times
of this episode.
That's true.
Anyway, so sometimes when you're talking to Protestants about the herring of Hades, they
will say that it's not anywhere in the Bible.
And you guys have already addressed this a little bit.
I think if you're, and I know there's a couple references to the New Testament, but I think
if you're taking, if you take the idea that you guys have been talking about about spiritual
geography. I think just the fact that Christ was buried in the ground is a biblical testimony
to him entering into Hades. Yeah, I mean, notice when people go underground, that means
something. Yeah, right. Yeah. Yeah. So is that your commenter? Do you have a question in
I was just asking if that was correct.
but I do have a correct.
If I ask another question, but it's not that's okay.
No, no, go ahead, throw it out. You're on the line. You might as well. This is your chance.
All right. All right. So I was explaining to someone in an arch in the, that I know who's Orthodox,
about the, the ritual that you guys were just talking about, the knocking on the doors of the church and reading the phone.
And he hadn't heard about it before, but he seemed to...
have a problem with the idea that the church becomes Hades.
And it's kind of been a quite, I mean, just come up in my mind too, but
I'll just listen to your guys and put on that.
Well, what do you have to say about that, Father Stephen?
Well, the church isn't becoming Hades.
What you have is the event being collapsed, because there's really two parts.
and the other part is all
depicted in iconography though that iconography is less common. So the the common
iconography of the resurrection you have Christ's invasion of Hades, he's grabbing
Adam and Eve and and you've got the Old Testament saints there in St John the
Forerunner. The other half of that is Christ then leading them into paradise.
Right, and that iconography usually you'll see like this big
crew of people behind Christ walking into like a garden through a door and
Abraham will be hanging out there with a bunch of little kids representing
people who died as children and there's a guy holding a cross that's
St. Dismissed the wise thief those are the people who are already in paradise and
And then Christ's leading sort of everybody else.
Right.
into there. And so when we do that ritual on, you notice we don't do that on Saturday morning,
we do it on Saturday evening because we're collapsing it into the second part of that event.
Yeah. So let me add this though, Father, there actually are some places I understand
like in Greece where they do that the night before. Okay. So there is a little variation.
Yeah, yeah, they're not very each other point
Yeah, they're not collapsing it. They're doing it as the entrance into Hades, whereas we're collapsing the event when we do it on Saturday night.
And so the church, right, you're outside and you're in the darkness and then the church has been, hopefully, if the guy you told to do it does his job that year.
It's completely illumined, right?
So you're coming from the darkness into the light.
So the part of coming into the church is...
the second part of that, of that, the coming into paradise.
And so when you make the procession, the procession in the darkness with just the small light of the candle,
is the waiting and hades of the departed saints, right, which then culminates in Christ's rescue of them
and they're entering into paradise, which is sort of collapsed there at the end.
Yeah.
So does that answer your question, Eugene?
Yes, it does.
Yes, thank you.
Excellent.
Well, thank you for calling.
We are happy to hear from you.
All joking aside.
Thank you so much.
90% of joking aside.
Yeah, I still thank for both of you.
Most joking aside.
Yeah.
All right.
Thank you.
OK, so we talked Psalm 24 last time.
We talked about the invasion of Hades by Christ
and the smack talk against Bale.
So let's move into another group of gods
That term, we're gonna...
Throw some more smack down on you know people sometimes like you know how can you be so sarcastic like that is that biblical? I'm like yes
You know they got the prophet Elias who's a patron saint of sarcasm
There's a lot of sarcasm Christ is actually sarcasm very sarcastic on several occasions. It gets by the neutered in the English translation
Yeah, you know, but yeah, that'll have to wait for another episode. Yes
Okay, all right, so let's let's
How to head on over to Egypt.
Right, let's go put the smack down on those guys.
We're at this point, we're probably bailed out.
So we're going to move on now to the Egyptians
and specifically to the song of the sea in Exodus 15.
This is the biblical song of the sea, not immigrant song
or a sea shanty, which I guess are in with the hepcats
these days.
but this or pirate rap that was
in about 15 years ago. There was a trend. Anyway, I had just blocked that out and now you're opening up old wounds.
Yes. You're just picturing, you're picturing Jamie Bennett with an eye patch now. I know you are.
I am. So, Jamie.
Exodus 15 contains the song of the sea, which is, the reason it's called the song of the sea is that
This is the song.
which we're told the children of Israel led by Miriam Moses's sister,
saying after Israel has passed through,
we'll say for now the Red Sea.
Yes. Just put a pin in that name.
And then they sing this song of victory.
And this is...
While recorded in Exodus 15, this is one of the oldest pieces of anything that are in the scriptures.
Yeah, it's kind of almost in another language, isn't it?
Yes, it's in a kind of paleo Hebrew, so it's even hard to translate.
The other very, very old one is Deuteronomy 32.
And we talked about you around me 32 a little bit before we
to talk about some more in a little bit, but those are the first two Oads of the Canon.
They're the first two Biblical Oads in the Orthodox Church, and they are also the sort
of ancient.
And when I say that, because I know we're going to get all the angry Moses wrote the Torah
people showing up at my house with pitchforks and torches.
So I'm not saying Moses didn't write the Torah.
You're right.
But what Moses wrote, first of all, would have been on paper,
would have been on tablets.
It wouldn't have been in Hebrew because the language didn't exist.
It would have looked a lot more like Exodus 15 to Deuteronomy 32, frankly, than the rest of the Torah.
So it's better to talk about the mosaic origin of the Torah or Pentateuch.
pen to tube.
authorship. authorship. Because what we have is not exactly what Moses would have written down.
Right because he didn't speak that language. Right. Wasn't that alphabet? You know, like this has
been handed down through some hands. Right. Translated. Translated into Greek. If you're an Orthodox
Christian, right. We give just as much, at least just as much authority to the Greek which was a
language that didn't exist when Moses lived.
right as we do to any other version so there shouldn't be a big problem for
people but there are places where this is made plain where in the text of the
Torah or Pentateuch you know it'll say he went to this city which used to be
called this other name right well that had to be written by somebody later right
that he has been updated for a later audience.
And then the big telling.
you know is is when you get to the the funeral of Moses right where Moses dies
yeah and it says his body has not been found until this very day right which I
mean I guess you could say well he was writing this prophetically you know but
then that makes no sense to say his body had not been found to this very day if he
had died yet when you were there was that yeah right it was the day before he died
right so right don't get too hung up on that yes the Torah the Pentateur
because we have it come
down to us from Moses, right? But these two pieces of the text, the one we're going to focus
on now, Exodus 15, the song of the sea in Exodus 15, has come down to us with little
to no editing. That's what we mean by, it's the oldest part. It hasn't been edited, the
language hasn't been updated, the vocabulary hasn't been updated, so much so that it's
very difficult to read and translate.
Yeah, it contains words from other Semitic languages and stuff, right? So
That's all we mean by that right right so and and you know if you're happen to be listening to this in the recording
Then I just suggested you because we're not gonna read the whole thing to you
But I just suggest you pause and then go read Exodus chapter 15 and then come back. Okay. Welcome back
So now the other thing that's going to have people throwing things at me, as we
court controversy. Part of the problem in terms of interpreting this
text and understanding this text is that in our contemporary world, almost all
of the literature and time and attention that's devoted to this text is
is devoted to history.
historical concerns, right?
Meaning, did the Exodus happen?
Was they really a Moses?
What year did it happen?
Who was the Pharaoh?
Where did it happen?
What body of water did they cross?
This is the stuff that is what history is now.
Like this is what the way history works now.
It's about trying to figure out what is in text
is trying to compare against archeology.
And I mean, listen, we're not saying
those are bad things to work on.
Right? I mean, we talk about archaeology. We talk, you know, we're, we're, we're looking at those
details in this very show, but it's not really what's actually important. And it's not really
what's being represented in the texts. Right. Some of my best friends are PhDs in history.
So we're not out to get you. But, um, but we have to realize that what we call history
came into existence in the 19th century in Germany.
Yeah.
It did not exist as a discipline before that.
There was something they called history,
but it's not what we call history.
Right.
What we call history, the Germans in the 19th century,
beginning at the beginning of the 19th century,
decided that history should be approached as vizenshaft,
meaning it should be approached as a science.
Yeah, kind of forensic, you know,
Dissection.
say, positivist, if you read anything from the 19th century, this positivist approach
is everywhere.
You read Hodges systematic theology from Princeton, who is a Presbyterian, wrote a systematic
theology.
His whole introduction is about how theology is a science.
If you start with the right principles derived from Scripture and follow logical inference,
the findings of systematic theology are just as certain as the findings of physics or
chemistry, right? And you're kind of rolling your eyes, right?
Right.
But it was the 19th century, especially the 19th century Germans.
They say we can approach this, we can know the essence of things, we can know the essence
of events through the scientific method.
So you get people like Hegel and Fuerbach and Marx who say, hey, we can discover the laws
that work themselves out in history the same way the scientists are discovering the laws
of physics or the laws of nature.
history works the same way.
way, right? There's rules and principles that we can scientifically arrive at.
And that's our guarantee of a history. Right. There's this sort of attempt to have a
totally, you know, the word would be objective quote unquote, but really what that means is
a kind of perspectiveless take. That's just a contradiction in terms. But the idea is like,
well, no, this is what really happened. It doesn't matter. No one's opinion about it or
experience of it is what we're discussing. We're talking about what really happened.
essence, the essence of the event. And to quote Thomas Nagel of what is it like to be a bat fame,
there is no view from nowhere. Right. There is no there is no viewpoint that is no place.
Like this is one of the points that for instance that are good friend Jonathan Pajot makes when he
and like he has an article which I recommend you check it out called most of the time the earth is flat.
And by that he does not mean that he
thinks that the Earth is a flat disk. Sorry, flat Earthers. What he means is that your
experience of it is that it is flat and that you experience it the sun rises. But I mean
we've said some of this kind of stuff before. But so this is but this is important for us
to review it just a little bit because of what we're about to talk about. Right. And we
said that I was just going to say we set up for this in the last couple episodes. Yes,
exactly. There is an objective historical event. We're not in any way denying things
really happen. Yeah, we're not spot.
We don't have access to the essences of things,
including historical events.
What we have are the record of human experience,
of humans who experience those events.
And there's an interaction between their human consciousness
and the event.
And the record we have is the interplay of those two things.
And so if the person is telling the truth
about their experience, then their account
is true. It doesn't matter if we have another person talking about the same event and those
things don't match up perfectly. They could both be true. They could both be telling the
truth if they're describing their experience accurately. And so this is...
Yeah, go ahead. I was just saying, and that's what the Bible is.
Right. Yeah, and like I mean a lot of you have probably heard this before, this argument,
about for instance the four gods.
Okay, so if you read the four gospels, you will notice that there are some details that don't quite seem to
Exactly reconcile with each other which clearly means they're totally made up totally. Yeah, right right exactly
whereas what what what St. John Crisostom actually says about this is what was new to me
I didn't know that he made this argument
I was so delighted to discover that he had he basically says look if there's a conspiracy and
And, you know, you have a group of people that all give the exact same testimony in court.
And it's exactly the same.
You can tell that that is a conspiracy,
that they're lying together in the same way.
But when you've got these different perspectives
that don't all quite line up of various people
who witness the same thing and experience the same thing,
that actually is an authenticator
for the truth of what actually happened, right?
And that is just a beautiful way of describing the problem
that we're addressing right now because...
You know, this sort of scientific method approach to history and so forth would suggest that
the only true account would always perfectly line up.
Like you said, they're sort of these laws of history that kind of play out.
But the truth is, you know, that that's actually exactly wrong.
That's exactly wrong.
That if everything lines up, that's probably an indication that a whole bunch of people
of all are all telling the same lie.
You know, it just would never be that way.
Right.
it's like a big.
traumatic or dramatic or violent event or something like that, you're going to get very
different perspectives as to what occurred.
Yeah, and let me not very humbly suggest that this is the orthodox answer to the great
impasse of Old Testament studies.
The 19th century ruined Old Testament studies because with this new positivist definition
of history and understanding of history.
What you got
thought was very quickly our German liberal friends who would come up with this idea of history
start applying it to the Old Testament.
And they say, well, okay, we have these written documents and yes, those are evidence, but
those are evidence from one perspective.
Therefore, they aren't the essence of the events.
They aren't the reality of the events.
And so we're going to now construct our laws of history, and we're going to go and we're
going to do archaeology, and we're going to gather all the other evidence we can find
documents from surrounding cultures.
And we're going to reconstruct what actually
happened. And if that could flex with what the Bible says, then we'd just say, well, the
Bible's got it wrong, right? Or the Bible's biased, or the Bible doesn't have the truth.
So that's their approach. And so to this day, if you go to a biblical studies conference,
you'll have people who go to the book of Joshua and say, well, look, this is just Israelite
propaganda. None of this happened. And we're going to reconstruct what actually happened.
the sense
We accept the Marxist laws of history that all of history up until the 19th century was the history of class struggle.
That's what's going on here, and there was really a Canaanite peasant revolt led by some escaped Egyptian slaves.
That's what really happened.
And then that was mythologized by the later Israelites into the book of Joshua.
That's to this day, that's a very common view of what's going on with Joshua in academia right now.
Right
In reaction to that, your conservative Old Testament folks, mostly conservative Protestants,
reacted to the exact opposite extreme.
They didn't reject that definition of history.
They accepted that definition of history.
They just said, no.
What the Bible records is the literal actual essence of the historical events with no bias
and no perspective whatsoever.
Right.
So it happened exactly as it says.
which is why then you get like...
Okay, so we're actually about to start talking about the crossing of the Red Sea, where you
then get people coming up with theories about strong winds, and all of this kind of stuff
to try to figure out the physics of how this worked.
Right.
And so when they do archaeology, you've got the King James Bible in one hand at a spade
in the other hand, and you're out there trying to prove, I'm going to prove that this is
literally exactly true.
Well, if it's the King James Bible, I mean.
So...
And this is the impasse that Old Testament studies has been in for 150 years.
And I think there's a very orthodox way right through it, which is to understand that
we don't know the essences of events, and we can't know them, especially events of the
distant past.
I mean Aristotle can have told you this too, but we know how those events appeared to the
people who experienced them.
Right.
That's what it acts as to.
particular
accounts of those experiences, which are authoritative and which have been handed down to us.
Right. And that, especially as Orthodox Christians, we believe that the Holy Spirit had something
to do with that. Right. And we seek to share the experience of the people who experience
God directly. Yeah. These events not to get at some reality that lies behind the experience.
Right now that might seem like a long sort of rabbit trail
whatever go down. But it's well number one, this is actually one of our kind of overarching themes
for this whole podcast, right? But in particular for tonight, since we're about to start talking about
the crossing of the Red Sea, it's really important so that you know that what we're about to talk
about is the experience of the people who were there and how they recorded it and how that was
was then handed on within the context of the people of God as guided by.
the Holy Spirit God himself. That's what we're talking about. So okay, well, let's, should we talk about why red sea is not the name?
Yeah, yeah, not the red sea everybody. It is the red sea, but it's not the red sea. Well, it's sort of is the red sea. Yeah. Yeah. So, it was the Greeks who started calling it the red sea. We'll start there. Right. So, so the name red sea would have meant nothing to Moses or the Israelites or the Egyptians.
That's what they called it.
That's what the Greeks called it. And so when the Septuagint gets translated, which is the Torah in Greek,
gets translated, they said, what body of water is this? Oh, that's the red sea. So they translated it as red sea.
That gets into English Bibles because as we were talking about earlier, the King James translators,
for example, we're kind of scratching their head at the Hebrew, saying, what body
waters this, they looked at the Greek, they looked at the Latin, they said, oh, the Red Sea,
we know where that is, right? So they carried that over into English. So in terms of colors,
we'll do a call back. There we go. To our friend, the mantis shrimp. The Egyptians not
only didn't refer to it as the Red Sea, but they referred to all big bodies of water
as the great green.
That's what the Egyptian...
really means the green green because they didn't see blue they couldn't see blue there's our callback
but so they they referred to the Mediterranean as the great green to the north or the great green of
the north right because they're in Egypt and they referred to what the Greeks called the red sea as
the great green of the east which I feel like that that should be you know on 1950s superhero
exclamation great green of the East Bay
you know yeah yeah yeah yeah great
Caesars ghost yes indeed Caesars Ghost
just appeared a paper editors at random
like how does that work but that's
another episode great green of the
ease yeah what Caesar Annapulum is that
what's going on anyway oh
So...
Um...
Now what's actually there in the Hebrew is Yamsuf, which you know
this is this is one of those tidbits that people pick up off of Bible documentaries, right?
There's a few tidbits that people get and
Then sometimes depending on what they do with them cause people great consternation like they hear that Satan is a title
Not a name or something and they go and start bothering people on Twitter
but
In this case it's at Yamsu for being to see you
reads is what you're usually here, which is not wrong, as we're about to talk about.
But although it does mean see of reads, soof, give me reads, the earlier meaning of the word
soof, if you go back further into the middle kingdom in Egypt, soof meant the end or the extremity
or the border or the edge, the edge, the edge, sort of the extreme part.
And so...
So in that context, it would have meant something like the sea at the end, the end of the
the NC or the border sea.
And that makes sense for that same rough body of water because it's at the eastern border
of Egypt, right? It's sort of marked off the Eastern border.
to get even more specific about the body of water.
Thanks to the Google Earth, we've now seen from satellite imagery that in ancient times,
there were a series of locks connected to the, what we now call the red sea.
Yeah, right, to control the flow of water, which is super important.
if flooding is input.
is a key part of your agriculture,
which in Egypt and the ancient world,
it definitely was.
So yeah, right, so it's this border water
that's got a series of blocks.
Right. This, this sea of the end.
And so anybody exiting Egypt is going to have,
that heading east is going to have to cross through
these, this system of blocks, right?
In order to get out, right?
They're going to have to move through them.
Yeah.
Yeah, yeah. So yeah, I was gonna say so what's interesting then is
you know most people when they think about the crossing of the Red Sea they see one of two images in their head
One of them has Charlton Heston
Uh the other one is probably the animated film uh
about Moses um and it it's you know the people of Israel all
running away from Pharaoh and his his soldiers so that they don't get killed
and they
they cross it and then it comes in on Pharaoh and his soldiers and they all die.
And yet weirdly then, Exist 15, the song of the sea depicts the whole thing as being a
battle.
So what's going on there?
What's that all about?
Wait, yeah, I just thought it was a battle.
You know, a last desperate escape, you know, that they got away just in time.
They didn't actually fight the Egyptians.
And this is part of the fallout, I think, of that.
That whole impassant debate we were talking about right is that it becomes about well did this miracle happen
Right, right. This is this miraculous absurd thing that we modern science people can't believe right and then you know
other people react and say no we must
believe that this literally happened exactly like this this vehicle
But yeah, that's not how the saga the C season it's not just like wow God did this cool thing with the water
There was a whale swimming around inside the water.
I mean, that's cool. I mean, I love those, you know, it's it's it's it's pretty neat. You know,
Cecil B. Demille and whatever. But yeah, that's not the focus of the saga. The saga. The sea is
Yahweh just laid the smack down on Pharaoh and his army and at all. Right. Because
and God, God telegraphed this move.
At the beginning of the whole incident, God says,
I am now...
judging the gods of Egypt. Right. That's at the path. That's what he says he's
doing at the Passover which is what leads to the Exodus. Right. That's what that's
just the throwdown happens. This is what I'm about to do. And so this is as it's
presented in the song of the sea. This is sort of the crossing of the sea is the
last battle of that war. Right. With the god of Egypt. And that's why right at the
beginning. In verse 3 it says Yahweh is a man of war, Yahweh is his name.
which would make a great book title.
But God is a man out there.
Yeah, it's a nice book.
Interestingly, now people find that kind of controversial
because we don't like war.
That was actually controversial the ancient world
because of the man part.
Oh, people are like, wait, y'all a man?
What?
Right?
Well, they tuned for a later episode
on the second person of the Trinity.
Yeah, right, right exactly.
So actually, yes.
Right, and so this is this sort of climactic battle.
And you see that in some of the other language used also,
there are repeated references to Yahweh's right hand
and strong arm.
Yeah, over and over, it's there.
Yeah, like verse six, the right handle Lord
has become glorious in power.
The right handle Lord has dashed in pieces the enemy.
By the way, that's the verse that the priest says
as he puts on...
his right cuff when he's getting his
vestments on. How about that?
Right. So this this language is
right out there and you know it's
easy to just kind of say, Oh,
that's that's an allegorical thing,
right? Like, Oh, you know, most
people are right handed. So that's
your strong arm, right? So it's like,
yeah, he slugged. But this actually
has a very specific Egyptian
reference. Yeah. Yeah. We're not
just making we're not just coming.
using language like we used in the body episodes everybody you know the right
hand of the Lord is his strength that is true but that's not all that's going
on here because once again we're talking about divine smack talk against demonic
gods right so yeah so what's the right hand and strong armed stuff the God of
war in this period of Egyptian history is the God Montu and Montu was seen as
sort of an aspect of
of Ray, the son God, the most high God of the Egyptian.
Right.
Egyptian, what we now call a pantheon, but of the Egyptian gods, he was the one who was
the, of their counsel of gods.
He was the most high God.
And as an aspect of Ray, Montou was particularly depicted as Ray's right arm.
He's raised right arm and he's the war God. Right?
They're God of war. Right.
And this became a title because in this period I
mentioned to you when we were we were talking about
About this episode that I have like a 300 page book on the naming conventions of the pharaohs
Throughout the various periods of Egyptian history. I think it is a real page turner. Oh, it is
And one of them this period was every pharaoh had what was called his horus name because
the Pharaoh.
was seen to be an incarnation or aspect of Horus, the son of Ray.
And so one of the Pharaoh's titles was Horus of the Strong Arm.
How about that?
So this is an important, this is a way that the Egyptians expressed their power in war,
their might in battle, the way the Pharaoh himself expressed his might in battle.
And so we have it respons-
you always saying, oh yeah, I just trashed Pharaoh with his Arbizdi Egyptian gods with my right arm.
Yeah, right.
And even centuries later, the prophet Ezekiel is still rubbing this in.
Oh yeah, all right. I love this. So Ezekiel chapter 30 verse 21,
Son of man, I have broken the arm of Pharaoh King of Egypt and
and low it so not be bound up to be healed to put a roller to bind it to make it strong to hold the sword.
So it's still the smack talk continues.
And notice, notice, right, the right arm is broken, can't hold a sword, can't make war.
Yeah, right. This is about war. Right.
And about defeat. And we also have this in referred to in the Epoetitian of the resurrection in tone three.
Right, right which says that the Lord has done
a mighty act with his own arm. And that own there is again, this is that like pointing
out the name. It's his arm that's mighty. Yeah. So anybody else's the smack talk continues
even now to the very present day. Until this very day. Right. Yeah. And what is and just,
you know, since this is our heroing of hell episode, what is the
the act that the Lord has done with his own right, his own arm, destroying death. That's right,
destroying death. So, right. Right. So, yeah. But now, going a bit further. Right. And this is about
the Reed Sea. The Reed Sea, Yamsu. Because we've set up the idea of sacred geography. Right. So,
We've talked about, yes, there's this border see.
Right? There's this Yam Suf, this border see.
that they have to cross. But we've also talked about how places, these material places,
become in time and space spiritual places, spiritual geography. And there is a spiritual place
called the Sea of Reads, called the Yom Suf. This is in Kew in Egyptian. Yes, that
for syllable is okay, like Mr. Mackie.
But the, this is, or not, I'm not, I'm sorry, I gotta hit it myself.
So the Reed C, the Reed C is the sort of Egyptian equivalent in the middle kingdom.
You see this in like the pyramid text of the River Sticks.
It's the body of water you have to cross after death to get to the place of your abode, right?
Right.
And all of you symbolic world people will recognize when you see some kind of border with
water on
it, you should be thinking about entering into a realm of chaos and death. Like it's just
that's, that's, you know, the margin, right? The margin, right? Right. Right. And so if
you can get past this, this watery body, the sea of reeds, then you'll get to the other
side and you'll have this shadowy existence in the presence of the Egyptian gods. Yeah.
Right. Just like in Greek mythology. And so the period tech, the pyramid texts are burial
will take.
with spells and invocations and that kind of thing to help get the spirits of the
gods to guide the Ka, the soul of the departed person through the sea of
reads to the other side safely. If you don't, this is where I got ahead of myself.
If you don't make it, you become one of the Mk.u. The Mk.u. are the drowned ones.
is what that literally is.
means. These are people who get tangled in the reads and get pulled down into the sea
of reads and sort of lose their identity, right? And become the drown ones. They're the
damned for Egyptians. That's what you don't want to happen to you.
Sort of could they be called the dead marshes? Just putting out. Yeah. Why are you trying
to prove that guy right? But I mean, it's the same. But I mean, okay, well, you know,
if you don't mind if I go there for a second,
it's the same thing.
Yeah, it is.
same thing. So you've got Frodo and Sam and Gollum crossing over this marshy area and
there's what do you know there's dead people down there in the water and what's on the other
side of it? Mortar, the place of death, the dark, the land that's governed by essentially
the local Satan. So I mean, yeah, obviously this is not the Tolkien podcast but I mean Tolkien is
working in these exact same images in there. He knows this stuff. So yeah, I mean, you know,
So Eugene is wrong but he's not...
not totally wrong. There are definitely touchstones between these images. Right. You know,
that there is this sense that human beings have that there's a watery thing that you cross
over and on the other side is the realm of death and there's a big, big bad death got over
there. Like that's something that kind of mankind has always thought in one way or another.
So yeah.
Right.
And so the whole promise.
of Egyptian religion. What they're working towards is they serve their gods, right, and
do these rituals and everything. Is this idea that perhaps, you know, and especially
the Pharaoh has the best shot at it, of getting across the sea of reads to this, this shadow
existence safely. And lo and behold, look what the song of the sea points out happened.
Yeah, Barrow and his soldiers are the drowned ones the drowned ones, but wait I thought that all
religions were just trying to get everybody to heaven. Isn't that what they're really all about? Aren't they the same? No. No. No.
So the drought ones are Pharaoh and his armies. Yeah. The ones who were guided through to the other side were guided through safely to the other side to go in dwell with their God in the
the proletarian by Yahweh.
Yahweh is the one who did that.
Right, and it's important to note here that they don't...
like take the long way around, they don't hop over, they don't tunnel underneath, they
go through the realm of death in order to get to the other side.
Right.
They go through it.
That's really important for this.
Right.
So they, so when we talk about PASCA, which means Passover, and passing from death to life,
That's not an allegorical thing.
What they're telling us in the song of the sea is that the people who were there who experienced this the first time
Had the experience of passing through death
Passing through the realm of death and being brought through safely to the other side to new life
By Yahweh that got a Israel
Yeah, and that's the experience we're sharing in
When we celebrate Passover we celebrate Paska exactly. Yeah, and so this stuff then
again, we're going to connect this
directly to the critical stuff that Orthodox Christians are experiencing in the next week.
Or if we do have at least one listener I think in Finland who experienced it a few weeks ago.
But anyway, next week, next week, okay.
So there is a canon that is the canon of Holy Saturday, so it's first sung on Holy Friday
night during that Matt and Service, which is what the funeral of Christ essentially.
but then that same cannon actually gets repeated.
during the midnight office at the Pascale Services.
So it's reused.
And in the sixth ode, which I shouldn't say always.
Well, yeah, it always thematically connects in one way or another with Jonah.
So often the sixth ode has references to going underwater and this kind of thing.
And experiencing death.
In that sixth ode you've got this line.
The children of those who were saved hid underground the God who made the
persecuting giant of old to disappear in the waves of the sea. Right? So that
means that the fathers who wrote these hymns deliberately picked this image of
of passing through the sea of reeds and and describes Pharaoh as
a persecuting giant of old comes right out and calls him a giant and made him disappear
in the waves of the sea.
So this image that we were just talking about now is specifically appointed in our liturgical
hymns to be appropriate for the events that happen with Holy Saturday and with POSCA
itself because POSCA is Passover, it's the Christian Passover, these things are all connected.
It's right there.
What do you know?
There's a giant right there in the midst of it, you know, who is this demonized King Pharaoh,
down in the underground. Right, right. Yeah, and then, of course, you know, this is how, this is why
St. Paul sees this connection between the crossing of the Red Sea and baptism because he understands
And right, Christian baptism as dying and right.
with Christ, passing from death to life in the waters, which is exactly what Exodus is talking about.
There's no allegory here. That's what it's talking about. And so that's why we read slash chant,
depending on the parts, the story of the crossing of the sea, and the song of the sea,
at the baptismal liturgy on Saturday morning, when you do the whole baptismal liturgy
with the 15-year-old Testament readings, which I always try to schedule at least a
the prismation so that we can do that.
the longer version on Holy Saturday.
And this again, this is again part of that,
the darkness and light imagery we were talking about earlier
at the Rush service on Pascanite
and this whole idea of again,
sharing that experience of being brought through death
into life on the other side.
Yeah, they're not avoiding death.
They're passing through death to life.
it's it's
resurrectional. That's what's going on here. So, all right, well, that is the second half of our show, but since it's Lord of
Spirits, there's a there's a third half. So, in our first half, we talked about the invasion of Hades and the smack talk against
the Bale. Second half, we talked about Passover going through the Sea of Reeds, passing through death to life. What's going to happen on the third
We'll be right back after this
Here's the voice of Steve.
Father Andrew Stephen Daymak and Father Stephen DeYoung will be back in a moment
to take your calls on the next part of the Lord of Spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF Radio.
You can't fake publishing presents I live again.
A memoir of Ilyana, Princess of Romania, and Arch Duchess of Austria, who, in later life, became Mother Alexandra, founder of the Orthodox monastery of the Transfiguration in Pennsylvania, who wrote this memoir shortly after relocating to the US in the 1950s.
It tells the story of a life full of suffering, tragedy and exile.
But all is diffused with the author's deep faith, hope, love and even joy.
This reprint includes additional...
material collected by the nuns of her monastery that sets the memoir in the context of Mother
Alexandra's Later Life.
To find this book and others like it, you can go to store.ancientfaith.com.
Again, that is store.ancientfaith.com.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits, the Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father
Stephen DeYoung.
If you have a question, call now at 855-237-2346.
That's 855 AF radio.
Welcome back. It's the third half of our Holy Week in Pazka Spectacular, the hearing of how
you're in the Lord of Spirits. Wow, so that's a lot we just went through but we've got even more,
but before we get to that, I actually want to mention something that I know that a lot of you have
have been waiting on.
very anxiously and demanding pre-orders and wanting to even see if you could possibly buy the bibliography.
Yes, people are asking to buy the bibliography, Father Stephen.
Father Stephen's book that's coming out and just about God willing about a week and a half.
It's supposed to come out during bright week.
We can't give you a precise date, but it is on track to release when it's intended.
It's called the Religion of the Apostles.
It's about 300 pages long, is that right?
give or take give or take yeah and and it is not Lord of Spirits and print okay
that's not what the book is but if you like this podcast you will love the
book I know that sounds very cheesy but it's true because a lot of the things
that we talk about in the show fathers even is written in the book in a much
more systematic kind of way but there's also a whole lot more in there as well
and there is indeed a bibliography this is probably the question we get every
single day, you know, can you give me some suggestion for further re-
Well, it's going to not be there in the back of the book and the book is indexed.
It's fully indexed.
That's a really important thing for a book like this.
So God willing, it's going to come out.
As I said, during bright week and I hope everybody will order a copy, order 10 copies.
We have a sort of competition going on in the Lord of Spheres Facebook discussion group
trying attempting to try to out buy the supply.
We encourage you to do that if you possibly can.
We will only just order up a reprint so
You will not defeat us at ancient faith but it is it is very important that everyone listening right now and everyone hearing the recording
Contact father Andrew by any means that you're disposed of
Ask to pre-order the book because they might run out
I don't want a panic anybody, but
Here's things. Thank you so much. Yeah, thank you. Thank you so much for that
Alright, we'll be-
Before we get to the third half of our show,
we have a call coming in from Aaron,
who has a question about the Sea of Reads.
So Aaron, are you there?
Hi, can you hear me?
Yes, welcome to the Lord of Spirits.
Aaron, we are really happy to have you.
What is your question or comment for us tonight?
Okay.
Oh, there's this common story with the Greeks
and the Egyptians about this watery abyss,
You
We'll have to travel through in order to get to wherever it is they get to.
Now that Christ has rated Hades and taken all of the souls out of there, both good and bad,
Dan and righteous, I want to know where we fall into that now as Orthodox.
You believe that there's this 40-day period where we pray for the soul.
I wonder if there's some kind of light.
parallel there the 40 days that happened that we pray for the departed and this previous notion
of how to kind of go through this intermediate phase on our way to Hades for if that whatever
the answer may be how that applies to both Orthodox and non-Christians and what you can make
of that question.
Well, I have some ideas, but I know that Father Stephen has much more co-here.
ideas about this because we've talked about it so I'm gonna punt on over to
Lafayette Louisiana. Okay well if you're trying to get me to talk about tollhouses
you don't mess up a right I'm joking I just wanted to make the few of you to
joke anyway so yeah a couple things first of all Christ only got the righteous
out of Hades.
This is a place where our English translations fail us a little because you're
probably thinking of a lot of our himnography will talk about like with
himself he has raised up all the dead, right? And you're like, well that that
sounds like all the dead. Sounds like everybody. But one of the tricksy things
hidden in St. Paul's Greek is that he puts a definite article in
of the word necros, sometimes and sometimes he doesn't. So when St. Paul uses the word necros,
dead, the noun dead, without the article, without what we would call a the, without an article,
he's referring to just everyone who's dead, dead people in general.
when St. Paul puts the definite article in front of it, so it's V-dead.
He's referring to departed Christians.
He's referring to the departed faithful.
And he distinguishes that very carefully.
And so in our himnography, when you hear like he has raised up all the dead,
it's all V-dead. It's all the faithful.
It's the Old Testament. So he brings them to Paradise.
The others remain in Hades.
So but
to the main thrust of your question.
We do believe that there is no, you know,
there are theories, which I won't go into more detail on,
but there is no sort of dogmatic structured way
of looking at the sort of 40-day journey
that a soul takes on its way to paradise
or hate ease to await the resurrection.
We know that there is a 40 days
period because that's part of the experience of the faithful that's been handed down to us.
How exactly that works, we don't know. We probably can't know because you know you don't know what
it's like to be a bat, you also don't know what it's like to be a disembodied human soul.
Right, and how that you know I mean our experience of time and space that everything is related
into our material bodies. So without that, what, how is that experience changed? We don't know.
We'll find out. But there is that period. And that there is that journey that on that journey
the faithful Christians are protected and guided by their guardian angel and by angels.
That there are demons involved going the other way. We have those kind of things but there's no
sort of very firm detailed.
thing
Related to that now of course that would mean that in our understanding before a Christ's harrowing of 80s
Everyone was going to the same place
Different parts as we talked about last time different parts of the same place, but the same place
And that's why the language that you get in the old testament profits is all about
You know the Lord will not abandon my soul to Hades or to the chill
Yeah, right beating up
I'm gonna go there, but even when I go there,
God will still be with me and he will not leave me there,
right, that there will be some rescue coming,
which is the prophetic element that points
to the reality of the harrowing of Hades.
But so now there are different quote unquote places.
Of course, we're using the term place metaphorically,
right, because wherever Christ is, that is paradise.
So when Christ is in our midst and the liturgy,
that is paradise and that means that all of the
and all of the faithful departed are there with us.
Yep.
Does that answer your question, Aaron?
It gives me a lot more questions, but...
Yeah, right.
Yeah, this is not easy stuff.
Is it not easy stuff?
Yeah.
Bill Will have a kingdom down there and...
You know, because when Christ returns...
and we're all with him...
Well now they're good at it.
I was gonna get they're gonna get dumped in the lake of fire. That's what Hades gets emptied out
Oh yikes, okay
Well, we'll yeah, we'll probably talk about all that horrible horrible stuff in a future episode
We like to say that a lot, but it's true. It's true. We love horrible things
Yeah, somebody's got to talk about it
So all right, well, thank you very much for calling Aaron. It was a privilege to have you on the show tonight
Thanks, fathers, all right, good night
Alright.
Well, for our third half, the smack talk continues.
Now, again, we're connecting with stuff that everybody should know,
who's Orthodox and goes to church in Holy Week in Paschua,
because you're going to go to every single service you can this next week.
There is, of course, one of the very most memorable moments is the
Paschal sermon of St. John Chrysostom.
And as it gets towards the end, he-
quotes from 1 Corinthians chapter 15 verse 55, O death, where is thy sting, O grave, where
is thy victory? And it turns out that that actually is a quote from Hosea 13, although a
little bit reworded, what's going on there in Hosea chapter 13 that St. Paul is quoting
it in first Corinthians 15.
Yeah, specifically, Josea 13 verse 14.
Verse 14, yes.
And yeah, I think more people have read first Corinthians
than Josea for some reason.
Yeah, which I, like Josea is awesome people by the way.
It's beautiful.
It is beautiful and not long.
Yeah.
So I'm going to give my own translation
of Josea 13 verse 14 because they're all over the place.
Yes, I looked this up and I was like, what?
What?
But, yes.
And part of this is because what we're going to bring out
tonight here in the third half is that there are a bunch
of proper names, specifically proper names of,
to quote Winston, or to paraphrase Winston Zedmore,
moldy old Kate and I gods,
who are mentioned here.
And so what happens is most translations you pick up
are not going to translate them
the names of
these can and I gods, but are just going to try to translate them as words.
Right.
And so you get a variety of interesting things.
So like, for instance, if, if, if, if my name were in an ancient text and they,
they did that, it would, it would not say Andrew Steve and it would say, you
know, manly crown, which would make no sense.
Or the crowned man.
They'll try to make sense of it, right?
The crown, right.
The crown, who's this crowned man?
No, it's, it's interesting.
So yeah, so this is the, this is the, this is the de Young standard version of
Thank you.
I don't know that it's standardized really.
It's got the young intuitive version,
the provisional, I won't stand by it.
Anyway, Jose A1314 is roughly,
I will ransom them from the hand of Shioll.
I will redeem them from moat.
O moat, where is Deborah?
O Shioll, where is Ketab?
Compassion is hidden from my eyes.
And we'll just leave it there.
That's, I think that makes,
that makes total sense, everybody good night.
Yeah, yeah, no.
So, okay.
Right, so, so a lot of times, for example,
this is similar to something we were just talking about,
the song of the sea, that first part
where it talks about the hand of Shio,
they'll say like the power of the grave.
Yeah.
Because they're translating Yad their hand,
or well, that means might or power,
if she all meets the...
grave, right? But of course, she all is not just the grave, it's also a place and it's
also personified either as a God or as sort of a creature with a big gaping mouth, right?
Yes, swallowing. Swat's iconography has the big mouth of hell. The helmet hole or
Hades or the Big Mouth.
So this is...
This is Yahweh saying, I will ransom them from the hand of sheol.
So if we think about this personification,
this is an actual hand, a grip, right?
They're being held, right?
These people are being held by sheol.
And then in parallel with it,
this is how Hebrew poetry works, right?
You have these parallelisms.
So that's parallel, that ransoming them
from the hand of sheol is paralleled with,
I will redeem them from moat,
which is then translated into Degreek as Thanatos,
which is also the name of a God.
Right. And for Arabic speakers, you know the word al-Maut, right? That's death, you know,
but it's not just death, it's moat, the God of death.
Right.
This is the one who Bale was tangling with earlier when he totally victoriously went to the
So it's not just that, well, I'm going to redeem them from death in some allegorical or
I'm gonna...
a fourical sense but
Mothe the God of death who rules this realm has them and I'm going to come get them right right and so then
Right and this makes sense when in the next sentence
Oh, moat where Yahweh the God of Israel speaks to
Death again. This isn't an allegorical thing. He's talking to moat right the God of death the Lord of the dead
And he says to him where is Debra?
Right, and that he talks.
to shiol, it says, oh shiol, where is ketep? Compassion is hidden from my eyes. So who's
Debra and who's ketep? He's asking, moat and shiol, where these other two people are,
right? Where these other two beings are. Right. And this is the part that parallels
then, 1 Corinthians 1555, oh death, where is they staying? Oh grave, where is thy victory?
And so, you see this pairing.
by the way of death and sheol of fanatost and Hades also in Revelation 6 verse 8. The last
of the four horsemen is death and Hades follows with him. So he's a horseman, these are
getting personified. In the inevitable four horsemen episode, we'll talk about how all four
of the four horsemen are moldy old Canaanite gods.
In the book of...
of revelation. But so these two are paired there. The idea is that death sort of feeds Hades.
Hades is this creature with this maw. He's this beast who follows death. Right. And death sort
of feeds people to him. Right. He's sort of the rank or keeper. Right. Who's throwing
that was unexpected that was yes so he's throwing me
He's a Bosch code feeding feeding the people okay, so is the job of the hut in this scenario? Yeah
That's what I guess I don't know. There we go. All right. All right, so good fortune that we won't go there anyway
so
Debra and Ketab then are the servants of
Moat right Debra and Ketab are also
Canaanite gods who are mentioned a whole bunch of places
When
their names are translated they're usually translated as pestilence and plague. So you may
already be thinking about the forehorsement again. But the idea is that these two sort of work for
an accompany moat, right? So moat wants to feed shiol and he does that by sending his boys round,
Debra Ketab who are going to go out there, plague and pestilence and kill people, right? Kill
Chill people with famine, chill people.
with disease, kill people, then moat gets a hold of them, feeds them to sheol, feeds
them to haze, feeds them to health.
Right.
We see that accompaniment idea in Habakkuk 3, verse 14, and I know everyone is read Habakkuk
if they haven't read Hosea.
But Habakkuk 3 is actually the fourth biblical ode.
going through a lot of the biblical oaths that's tonight.
And in that, it describes Debra and Ketebe,
sort of part of this posse.
And this wasn't just a thing with Moe
in Canaanite thinking, this was also a thing with Marduk.
This was Babylonian.
Yeah, but who was the Babylonian Bale essentially?
He's the one who went and took out his parents
and took over the Dio Babylonian Empire.
So, and Marduk had Nairgal.
You know, he had a-
posse who went out and killed for him. But in Habakkuk 3, which is also Svakhtak, it's
talking about how Yahweh actually has Deborah Ketab in his entourage. That he's the one.
It's Yahweh the God of Israel who has control over pestilence and plague.
Yeah. And then this connects us with this theme we've seen before, which is that these
afflictions right?
demonic afflictions that are loose in the world, they obviously have their own agenda,
but ultimately they are to use St. Gregory, the greats language, the left hand of God.
You know, they are the demons, they're doing their will, but ultimately still they're
doing the will of the Lord who is trying to bring people to repentance.
That's the whole point.
Right.
So none of these pagan gods could be appeased in order to protect you from plaguer pestilence.
Right
They're not the ones who wield them. They're not the ones who have control over them.
We also see Ketab shows up in the second mode, second biblical mode, in Deuteronomy 32.
He shows up there with Reshef, who will find out in that inevitable episode is one of the forehorsesman
who is the guy who shoots arrows of plague. There's actually a very early catholic
version of Apollo who's basically Reshift.
brought over into Greek thinking.
And at Judorod v 32, their ketchup is hanging out with
moat.
How about that?
And then these folks also show up in Psalm 91
and the Hebrew number of the Psalms,
90 in the Greek number of the Psalms versus five and six.
And if you've been to any of the great complement
services in
Lent or at the Orthodox Church or if you go to sixth hour you'll also hear about this both of the prayers
And in the reading of the psalm, but in verse five and six if you translate the names as names
It refers to Deber who walks in darkness and Ketab who destroys it noon
Right or as probably most of us have heard the demon who walks in the darkness and the
and the demon of noon day or something like that.
The noon day demon.
Right, and doesn't that get read also in the funeral?
Isn't it the Psalm that's at the beginning of the funeral?
Yes, they were asking God to save this person from Debra and Ketab.
Right, this is, there were in the second temple period in Judaism.
We find these, for example, in the Dead Sea Scrolls.
There were six Psalms that were considered Davidic Psalms of exorcism.
that David wrote to be sung over someone who was demon possessed in order to...
exercise them. This is the only one of them that's a canonical
solve. The other five are not canonical. But so this was at
exorcism solve from very early. And from as far back as we know,
was used at Orthodox funerals as well. So you've got exorcisms
at baptism. And now an exorcism again at the funeral.
Yeah. And by the way, the reason it's translated as demon of
the Dune Day is that the Greek translators of what was for them Psalm 90.
realized this that these were proper names.
And so they translated it, they didn't say the plague
that destroys it noon, right?
He said the demon who destroys it noon day,
the noon day, because they realized
what it was referring to.
And also with that, Psalm the arrows that fly by days
referenced to Reshef again who we mentioned earlier,
but as it aside.
So the idea here in when we piece together,
her back at what we-
look at what's going on in Hosea is that God has disarmed death, right? The God of death,
these weapons that he thought he had, right? I've been taken away from him and God now has
them. And so he's literally in Hosea sort of taunting him. He's like, hey, death, where's
your boy, uh, Debra. Uh, wait, wait, wait, oh, he's over here with me. Oh, uh,
Where's where's where's cats out? Oh yeah, he's here. He's here with me too. Right. You're all alone. Right. Right. And you know, another thing I wanted to mention, as we've been kind of moving along this,
You know, so, okay, you've got this line from Chris Ostens, homily where he's quoting for
Screnthians 15, oh, death, where is they staying, oh hell, or oh grave, or hateys, whatever,
where is they victory? That's what this is referring to.
talking directly to these demons and saying that their power has been stripped from them.
But at the same time there's another liturgical connection.
If you understand these references to moat to the God of death, right?
So if you sing the Paschola-Politikian, Christ's isn't from the dead.
If you sing it in Greek, Christosanastieachnecron, Thanato, Thanaton, Patistas, that means, so
we transit as
you know, trampling down death by death,
but it's, but a more, a clear reading of that
might be trampling down Thanatos, the God of Death
by the means of death.
That's what's going on there.
And of course, if you see in an Arabic, you know,
you've got Mal, Al-Bamout, right?
So again, moat to the God of Death,
being trampled down by means of death.
So when...
That said, when demon with the door on his face.
Right, the demon, the door,
whose face is smashed in by the door.
when the Lord busts his way into Hades.
Right, so, you know, like when you sing,
so next week you're gonna sing this hymn.
Christ is from the dead,
trampling down death by death,
and upon those in the tombs of bestowing life,
when you get to that line,
trampling down death by death,
understand what you're singing,
that Christ is smashing the God of death
by means of his own death,
his own entrance into Hades.
Right, and this...
This idea of disarmament and stripping of power
is exactly what St. Paul does with it in first Corinthians.
And you have to understand this to understand
what he's doing.
Because what he says immediately after quoting Hosea
is he says, now the sting of death is the law, which
is sort of like, wait, what?
Like, where did that come from?
Because he's talking about the resurrection.
But if you think about this, the imagery we have here
that Hosea is working with is that death
is laying claim to people.
through.
through plague and pestilence, through his minions,
it's like claved to people and dragging them
to Hades, to Shio, right?
That's what death is doing, right?
So for St. Paul, how is the devil
laying claim to people and dragging them into Shio
and to Hades, into death?
Through sin, right?
Through sin, through the violation of the law, right?
But the law...
the Torah for St. Paul is not evil, it's neutral, and so Christ has taken it back.
And has now made the commandments, has now made, ready to tour something which gives life
instead of death. This is one of St. Paul's ongoing themes. So he's using it in the same disarmament
sense. And then he makes that quite literally plain in Hebrews chapter 2.
If you want to read that.
Yeah, yeah, yeah, sure.
So in Hebrews 2 verse 14,
for as much then as the children are partakers of flesh and blood,
he also himself, likewise, took part of the same,
that through death he might destroy him that had the power of death,
that is the devil.
Yeah.
So pretty direct.
Right, right.
Well, that is the third half of our show and Father Stephen is going to give his closing remarks and then I have something to share with you.
But before we do that, I just want to wish all of you a very, very powerful, holy week and posca coming up.
And our next episode, which will be again, it'll be the second Thursday of May, so it's
going to be three weeks from today if you're listening to us live, is going to be a Q&A episode
where we're just going to hammer one...
question after another. So, you know, especially if you've called in and and you know, your
question wasn't directly applicable or we couldn't answer it tonight. You know, Colin, for that time
and we'd love to talk to you. So, all right, Father Steven, your final thoughts.
Yeah. Well, people may or may not have noticed I didn't make as many
pop song references tonight. That's because Father and Andrew and I had a discussion.
Do you remember this discussion, Father Andrew? No.
Oh, okay, well we had...
We had this discussed because I made a reference to screaming trees that I nearly lost you.
And so then I was like, well, can I make like a space hog or a helmet reference in the meantime?
And you were like, no.
But then you suggested that I make an oasis reference and I said maybe.
I said maybe.
But 90% of kidding aside again.
Thank you.
So, I think...
Though it may not seem so at first, I think an important thread running through what we talked about tonight,
not directly related to Holy Week in Pasca, is the issue of what sometimes gets called the problem of evil,
specifically the way it takes the form of the problem of suffering in the world.
Even though we've talked about one element of it that we came to again tonight, the idea that
that these evil powers are indeed evil but are not outside of
God's control. That God has control of them and God can ultimately use them to bring about his will and to bring about good.
He can bring good out of evil. That's what God does. But another important aspect of that is something that we just sort of touched on
when we talked about the song of the sea. And that's the idea that as Father Andrew said, you know, God doesn't take them around the sea.
He doesn't take them around death.
He doesn't just sort of swoop down.
strike Pharaoh in his army's dead on land. He doesn't break all their chariots so they
can't catch up with the Israelites. He doesn't spare them from danger. He doesn't spare
them from the experience of death. And I think often when we look at our lives and when
we look at our prayer lives and when we interact with God prayerfully, we treat it as if
God is supposed to spare us from sorrow and spare us from pain and spare us from pain
from death and when these things enter our lives we act like they're these weird foreign intruders
and why is God doing this to me or why is God allowing this to happen to me and we've got it exactly
backwards, right? Because the sorrow and suffering and pain and struggle and sin in our lives
is a foreign invader to God's creation but it's not a foreign invader to our lives and to our
Consciousness.
because we continually invite and bring it in and bring it about and cause it.
Where God intervenes is not to stop us from choosing it, not to stop us from bringing it
into our lives, but to graciously bring us through it and out the other side to something better.
That isn't going to stop us from suffering.
He's not going to...
make us immortal so we never die on this earth. He's not going to make it so we never get sick. He's not
going to make it so we never suffer loss or hardship or any of those things. All those things are in
the world because of us. But what God is going to do, what He's promised to do and what He is actively
doing is bringing us through all of those things and out the other side to light and to peace and to
joy and to life that is eternal.
with him, not to some kind of shadowy existence, but to rule and reign with Christ for eternity.
And so that is the promise.
That is where our joy is Christians in suffering can come from.
That's why Lent is a bright struggle, not just a struggle.
why all of our efforts can be conducted with joy because as the salt
says that we read at the end of the pre-sangtified liturgies we've been having in
land. Many are the tribulations of the righteous man, but the Lord will deliver
him from them all. Well to close I want to share with you one of my favorite
passages of anything that I've ever read so this comes from a text that is called
the gospel of Nick.
decademic. And it is, as far as I know, I think it's a dated generally to the fourth
century, but it comes out of traditions that are certainly older than that. And there's
a portion of the gospel of decademic that the best way that I can understand how to describe
it would be that there's all these things that we go through together, for instance, during
week and this is what's described in the Gospels. Right? And you know, Christ's passion is suffering
his death and so his resurrection. Well, there's a portion of the Gospel of Nicodemus that's called
the Descent into Hell. And it's probably best described as what's going on down in the underworld
while all these other things are happening on Earth. Okay? And right before the passage of
about to read to you.
Hell and Satan are having a conversation.
So, you know, we've been talking about a whole bunch of these various gods, right?
So, you think this is as, you know, moat and sheal, you know, having a conversation
or Satan and hell, you know, however you want to talk about it, right?
There's just different names for these beings.
And it's being set up so that Satan is basically saying, you know, hell, open up your gates
Because I'm bringing Jesus in here. You know, we got him. We finally got him, right?
The devil thinks he's finally got him. So they're having this conversation. It's going back and forth and
it picks up right here.
Hell answered and said
Thou has told me that it is he that has taken away dead men from me
For there be many which while they lived on the earth have taken dead men from me yet not by their own power
but by prayer to God.
God, and they're Almighty God that's taken them from me.
Who is this Jesus, which by his own word, without prayer, have drawn dead men from me?
Perchance it is he, which by the word of his command, had restored to life Lazarus, which
was four days dead and stank and was corrupt, whom I held here dead.
Satan, the Prince of Death, answered and said, it is that same Jesus.
And hell heard daddy said unto him, I adjure thee by the strength.
and mine own, that thou bring him not unto me.
For at that time I, when I heard the command of his word, did quake and was overwhelmed with
fear, and all my ministries with me were troubled.
Neither could we keep Lazarus, but he, like an eagle, shaking himself, leaped forth with
all agility and swiftness and departed from us.
And the earth also which held the dead body of Lazarus straight way gave him up alive.
Therefore now I
know that that man, which was able to do these things, is a God's strong and command, and
mighty in manhood, and that he is the Savior of mankind. And if thou bring him unto me,
he will set free all that are here shut up in the hard prison and bound in the chains
of their sins that cannot be broken, and will bring them unto the life of his Godhead
forever. And as Satan the Prince and House spoke this together, suddenly there came a voice
as a thunder and a spe-
ritual cry.
Removal princes, your gates, and be lift up ye everlasting doors, and the king of glory shall
come in.
When hell heard that he said unto Satan the prince, depart from me and go out of mine
abode, if thou be a mighty man of war, fight thou against the king of glory, but what has
thou to do with him, and hell cast Satan forth out of his dwelling?
Then said hell unto his wicked ministers, shut ye the hard gates of brass, and put on them
the bars of iron and with stand still
least we that hold captivity be taken captive. But when all the multitude of the
saints heard it, they speak with a voice of rebuking unto hell. Open thy
gates that the king of glory may come in. And David cried out crying, cried out
saying, did I not when I was alive upon earth for telling to you, let them give
thanks unto the Lord, even his mercies and his wonders unto the children of
men who have broken the gates of brass and smitten the bars of iron and
and Sunder, he have taken them out.
to the way of theiriquity. And thereafter, in like manner Isaiah said,
did not I, when I was alive upon earth, for telling to you the dead
shall arise, and they, there in the tombs, so rise again. And they,
there in the earth, so rejoice, for the dew which come at the
Lord, as they're healing. And again, I said, O death, where is
thy sting, O hell, where is thy victory? When they heard that of
Isaiah, all the saints said unto hell, open thy gates,
Now
Now shall thou be overcome and weak and without strength.
And there came a great voice as of thunder, saying,
Removal princes, your gates, and be lift up ye doors of hell,
And the king of glory shall come in.
And when hell saw that they so cried out twice,
He said, as if he knew it not, who is this king of glory?
And David answered hell and said,
The words of this cry, do I know, for by his spirit
I prophesied the same.
And now I stand to thee that which I said.
before the Lord strong and mighty, the Lord mighty in battle, he is the King of glory.
And the Lord looked down from heaven that he might hear the groanings of them that are
in fetters and deliver the children of them that have been slain, and now, thou most foul
and stinking hell, open thy gates, the King of glory may come in.
And as David thus spake unto hell, the Lord of majesty appeared in the form of a man,
enlightened the eternal darkness, and break the bonds that could not be loose.
And the sucker of his everlasting might visited us that sat in the deep darkness of our transgressions,
and in the shadow of death of our sins. When hell and death and their wicked ministers saw that,
they were stricken with fear, they and their cruel officers at the sight of the brightness of so
great light in their own realm, seeing Christ of a sudden in their abode, and they cried out,
saying, we are overcome by thee. Who art thou that art sent by the Lord for our confusion? Who
What the hell?
that without all damage of corruption and with the signs of the Imasian blemished,
dust in wrath condemn our power. Who art thou that art so great and so small, both humble and exalted,
both soldier in commander, marvelous warrior in the shape of a bondsman, and a king of glory dead
and living whom the cross bears slain upon it? Thou that disly dead in the Sepulchre has come down
unto us living and at Thy death all creation quaked and all the stars were shaken and
Thou has become free among the dead and disaroued our legions.
Who art thou that set us free, the prisoners that are held bound by original sin, and
restores them into their former liberty?
Who art thou that set us thy divine and bright light upon them that were blinded with
the darkness of their sins?
After the same manner, all the legions of devils were stricken with light fear and cried
out altogether in the terror of their confusion, saying,
Once art thou Jesus, a man so mighty and bright in majesty.
so excellent without spot and clean from sin. For that world of earth which had been always subject
unto us until now, and it paid tribute to our prophet, had never sent unto us a dead man like thee,
nor ever dispatched such a gift unto hell. Who then art thou that so fearlessly entrest our
borders, and not only fear us not our torments, but besides assay us to bear away all men out of
our bonds. Per adventure thou art that a G.
Jesus, of whom Satan, our Prince, said that by thy death of the cross thou
shouldst receive the dominion of the whole world. Then did the king of glory in
his majesty trample upon death and laid hold on Satan the Prince and delivered
him unto the power of hell and drew Adam to him unto his own brightness.
And that is our show for today.
Thank you for listening.
If you didn't get a chance to call in during the live broadcast,
we would love to hear from you, either via email at LordofspiritzNationFaith.com,
or you can message us at our Lordofspiritz podcast Facebook page.
We read everything, but we can't respond everything.
We do save what you send for possible use in future episodes.
For Thursdays of the month at 7 p.m. Eastern 4 p.m. Pacific.
And if...
If you're on Facebook, like our page, and join our discussion group, leave reviews and
ratings everywhere, but most importantly, do what I know a lot of you are doing.
Share this so with a friend whom you know is going to love it.
If you join our Facebook group now, you can be sworn as a space monkey before Project May
him begins.
And finally, be sure to go to ancientfaith.com, slash support and help.
Make sure we and lots of other AFR podcasters stay on the air.
Thank you very much.
God bless you.
you a bright and glorious
You've been listening to the Lord of Spirits with Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew
Stephen Damick and Father Stephen De Young, a listener-supported presentation of ancient
faith radio.
I beheld and I heard the voice of many angels round about the throne.
and the beasts and the elders, and the number of them was 10,000 times 10,000,
and thousands of thousands, saying with a loud voice, worthy as the land that was slain to receive
power and riches and wisdom and strength and honor and glory and blessing. Revelation chapter 5
versus 11 through 12.
Archprized Gordon T. Walker served
God for his entire life. From his childhood as a Baptist in Alabama, through years as
a Protestant pastor and finally, after decades of searching for the true church, as an Orthodox
priest.
One of the founding leaders of the former Evangelical Orthodox Church, Father Gordon
had a special heart for youth and founded Grace Ministries to facilitate serving them.
In the course of his ministry, he touched hundreds of lives with boundless love and grace
of God. This memoir, compiled and edited after his repose by his brother Father
Philip Walker reveals the servant heart of a dedicated man of God.
Even back then, I remember him saying, you know, we need to find the New Testament Church.
We need to follow the example of the New Testament Church.
To find this book and others like it, you can go to store.enchantfaith.com.
Again, that is store.enchantfaith.com.
Welcome to the Thursday edition of The Path.
You are connected to the path, offering strength for our journey toward salvation.
Here's Father Tom Siroka.
Today's first reading is from Genesis, chapter 46, verses 1 through 7.
Israel took his journey with all he had, and came to the well of oath, and offered a sacrifice
to the God of His Father Isaac. Then God spoke to Israel in a vision of the night and said
Jacob, Jacob, so he said, Here I am. So God said to him, I am the God of your fathers,
do not fear to go down to Egypt, for I will make of you a great nation there. I will go
down with you to Egypt, and I will also surely bring you up again, and Joseph will put
his hand on your eyes. Then Jacob arose from the well of oath.
And the sons of Israel carried their father Jacob, their baggage, and their wives in the
carts Pharaoh had sent to carry him.
So they took their livestock and their goods, which they had acquired in the land of Canaan,
and went to Egypt.
Jacob and all his seed with him.
His sons and his sons sons, his daughters and his sons daughters, and all his seed he
brought with him to Egypt.
St. John Chrysostom reminds us that Israel, Jacob, was faithful to God's promise.
He writes,
See how whatever the good man longed for, the Lord promises him, and in fact much more.
That is to say, in his generosity, he exceeds our requests out of fidelity to his characteristic
love.
Do not be afraid to go down to Egypt, he says, because Jacob dreaded the length of
the journey, accordingly he says, have no regard for the weakness of your old age. I will
make you into a great nation there. I will accompany you and make everything easy for
you. Notice the considerateness of the expression, I will go down with you to Egypt. What could
be more blessed than to have God as a traveling companion? Then he spoke the consoling thought
that the old man had particular need of Joseph's hands will close
your eyes in death. That dearly beloved Son of yours will personally prepare your body
for burial, and his hands will close your eyes in death. So, quite happy and free from
all concern, Jacob took to the road. Consider at this point I ask you, with what cheerfulness
the good man makes the journey, being so reassured by God's promise.
Today's second reading is from Proverbs, chapter 23, verse 15, through chapter 24, verse
5.
My Son, if your heart becomes wise, you will also gladden my heart, and your lips shall
spend time with the words on my lips.
If they be upright, do not let your heart envy sinners, but be in fear of the Lord the
whole day long.
if you keep these words, you shall have...
offspring, and your hope will not depart from you.
Hear my son and become wise, and direct or write the thoughts of your heart.
Do not be a wine-bibber.
Neither provide contributions of meats or goods at drinking parties.
For every drunkard and fornicator shall become impoverished, and every sluggard shall
clothe himself with tattered and ragged garments.
my son, your father who begot you. And do not despise your mother because she
is grown old. A righteous father rears his child well, and his soul rejoices in a wise
son. Let your father and mother be glad in you, and let her who bore you rejoice. My son,
give me your heart, and let your eyes observe my ways. For a house of prostitution is a pierced
vessel, and a strange and empty well. For he shall perish suddenly, and every lawless man
shall be destroyed. Who has what?
Who has tumult? Who has condemnation? Who has unpleasantness and gossip? Who has afflictions
with no purpose? Whose eyes are pale? Is it not those who linger long with wines? Is it
not those who hunt for the whereabouts of drinking parties? Do not be drunk with wine, but
keep company with righteous men and keep company in public walks. For if you set your eyes
to the bowls and cups.
Afterward you will walk about more naked.
it then ground meat. And at last he stretches himself out as one bitten by a serpent, and
the venom spreads throughout him as one bitten by a horn serpent. When your eyes behold
a strange woman, then your mouth will speak twisted things, and you will lie down as in
the heart of the sea, and as a pilot in a great storm. And you will say, they beat me,
but I did not suffer, and they mocked me, but I knew it not. When will it be morning?
And I may go seek those with whom I may company.
My son, do not envy evil men, neither desire to be with them, for their heart ponders a lie,
and their lips speak of sufferings.
A house is built with wisdom, and it is built up with understanding.
Storehouses are filled with perception, from all honorable and good riches.
It is better to be a wise man of strength, and a man having discernment, then to be a man
you
a large estate.
We are reminded in today's reading from Proverbs to give wisdom and every good thing our heart.
The blessed Augustine writes, If you don't give yourself, you will lose yourself.
Charity herself speaks through wisdom and tells you something to save you from panicking
at being told, give yourself.
If anyone wanted to sell you a farm, he would say to you, give me your gold, and if it
was something else, give me your coppers, give me your silver.
Now listen to what charity says to you, speaking through the mouth of wisdom.
Give me your heart, son.
Give me, she says.
Give her what?
Your heart, son.
It was ill when it was with you, when you kept it to yourself.
You were being pulled this way in that.
by toys and trifles and wanton, destructive loves. Take your heart away from all that.
Where are you to drag it to? Where are you to put it? Give me your heart," she says.
Let it be mine, and it won't be lost to you.
Remember that you can download all of the daily messages by visiting our website
at AncientFaithRadio.com and clicking on the path.
We'd also love to hear from you.
You can write us at the path at ancientfaithradio.com.
That's the path at ancientfaithradio.com.
Now here with some final thoughts is Father Tom.
As we grow very close to the end of the great fast, the church reminds us to give ourselves
entirely over to God.
Israel trusted in the promises of God.
cries out to us to give our hearts. Let us do so so that we may behold the resurrection
of the Lord. Now to Him who is able to do exceedingly, abundantly above all that we ask or
think, according to the power that works in us, to Him be glory in the church by Christ
Jesus, to all generations, forever and ever, Amen.
This is a daily presentation on ancient faith radio.
You are listening to the morning offering with Abbot Trey Fon.
Glory to God in the highest and on earth peace, good will among men.
We praise thee, we bless thee, we worship thee.
the mystery of the church. There is a certain emptiness in trying to live the Christian life
outside the life of the church. This is because it is impossible to truly live as a Christian
without the church. The reading of the Scriptures and our commitment to prayer are important
foundations in the life of a Christian, but they are incomplete without the mystical and
sacramental life.
is found within the church. If we hope to grow spiritually, we will take advantage of the
mystery that is found only within the church. Without the mystery of penance and the
absolution of the church, we have no hope of transformation and holiness. For without
the corporate life of the church, our sins keep us kept.
adaptive. Without the mystery of Christ's body and blood received during the celebration
of the Church's Divine Liturgy, the healing of the soul remains undone, and salvation
is next to impossible. The center of the Church's Eucharistic liturgy is to be found in the
descent, the appearance in the divine presence of the resurrected Christ.
and is central to every moment of the liturgy.
As believers, the partaking