He will be a staff for the righteous with which for them to stand and not to fall.
And he will be the light of the nations and the hope of those whose hearts are troubled.
All who dwell on the earth will fall down and worship him, and they will praise and bless,
and celebrate with song the Lord of Spirits, 1st denoc, chapter 48, verses 4-5.
The modern world doesn't acknowledge but is nevertheless haunted by spirits, angels, demons,
and saints in our
time many year into break free of the prison of a flat, secular materialism, to see and
to know reality as it truly is.
What is this spiritual reality like?
How do we engage with it well?
How do we permeate everyday life with spiritual presence?
Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew Stephen Damick, and Father Stephen De Young
host this live Colin show, focused on enchantment in creation.
the union of the scene and unseen as made by God.
and experienced by mankind throughout history.
Welcome to the Lord of Spirits.
Welcome back to the Lord of Spirits podcast.
I am Father Andrew Stephen Damick
in the burrow of a maus in the beautiful snow blanketed
Commonwealth of Pennsylvania.
And with me is my co-host Father Stephen Dianne
in Lafayette, Louisiana,
where it never really gets truly cold.
And if you're listening to us live,
you can call in at 855-AF radio
that.
855-237-2346 and we will get to your calls in the second part of today's show.
So have you ever noticed that worship is never defined in the Bible? There's no place in
which it says, and this is what worship is. Now we do get very detailed instructions for
worship, especially in the book of Leviticus, and then there are bits and pieces in the
New Testament. But worship happens along before any of those texts are written. In fact,
We see it happening in Genesis chapter 4 with the sons of Adam and Eve.
Cane and Abel offer sacrifice to God.
It's not explained, not defined, not placed within any existing religious ritual context.
Cane and Abel make sacrifices to God.
If we're going to understand the sacrifices of Cane and Abel as well as worship in the
ancient world in general, and indeed Christian worship up until our own time, we need to understand
the ritual context.
of the ancient world, what did the earliest worship look like?
Was there a lot of variation?
Did different cultures come up with very different ways of worshipping their gods?
So let's think back now as best as we're able to thousands of years ago
to the earliest known human settlements.
And they happen to be found in what is now modern day Turkey and the Holy Land.
So, Father Stephen, take us back.
So first I'll have you know it is a deeply chilly 46 degrees here.
And the UBS driver brought me a package earlier and was literally wearing a
parka and gloves. So the cold is just a different standard down here.
And also before we get started tonight we should probably let people know that like
That goal or discussion of sacrifice has been divided in three parts.
Indeed. Right. And not just three parts in this episode. This is the first of three episodes
about sacrifice. So we can hear there's a whole bunch of cheering happening all over the
world right now. I'm sure in response to that. So yes. So this is part one where we're
going to be talking about sacrifice in the ancient world.
Yeah. And as is our want, we're going to go back and start at the very beginning. As you
you mentioned.
which is in the Neolithic period, the Stone Age religion.
So I'll do our date disclaimer.
That's important, yeah.
I'm going to give dates, which are the dates established by archaeologists.
This isn't based on carbon dating or paleontology.
We're talking about human settlements.
So this is standard layer archaeology.
Some listeners may have a commitment to the idea that the earth is not as old as some
of these settlements are purported to be.
Right.
If so, do not allow this to trouble you.
These are circuit dates, adjust them accordingly.
But however long or short you feel the timeline is, these are the earliest human settlements
either way.
Right.
And it also doesn't.
Right, it ultimately...
does not matter to what we're going to be talking about exactly how old they are.
You know, so anyway, yeah.
Just the oldest ones we've found.
Exactly.
Yes, right.
So now we get to say some phrases and words that are very hard to pronounce unless you happen
to be from Turkey.
Yeah, yeah.
Then I don't know.
They may hate to be.
Yeah, if we have any actual Turks listening over like, oh man, they're saying that so on.
We're sorry.
So
The three earliest sites, and we're going to discuss two of these in some detail, the
oldest continuously inhabited human site that we've uncovered is actually Jericho.
Right.
And the Holy Land.
Which is in the Holy Land, the Jericho that's in the Bible, but although it's where exactly
the settlement is has shifted around a little bit in the area, there's been human settlement
they're dated by archaeology.
back to circa 10,000 BC.
Right.
So that's how far back we're going.
So we're going back at least some millennia
before the civilizations of Babylon,
before even Sumerian civilization.
And there's no writing at this point, right?
That anyone is aware of.
Right. There's no writing.
So we don't have written texts.
We have sort of the remains of people living and doing things.
Yeah.
And these aren't really cities.
That's why we're saying settlements.
Right.
Sumeria is where you start getting cities as such.
So these are just places where previously nomadic people
put down roots.
And we'll be talking about that more in a minute.
Yeah.
So then the two that we're going to discuss in more detail,
The first is go back to the tap.
which is one of the sites in what's now Turkey in Asia.
Yeah, South Eastern Turkey right near the Syrian border.
And that site, again, is dated by archaeologists,
the beginning of the settlement to somewhere around 91-30 BC,
flourishing around 9,000 BC.
and then
The second one is Chattelhoiak, which dates from a little later from around 7100 BC.
Just a couple thousand years later.
Right, so yeah.
So one, go backly-tappy represents one of the first permanent human settlements.
And then Chetelhojik represents a sort of later,
a little bit later phase of the development of...
of human settlements and villages.
Yeah, based on what we actually find there in the dirt, right?
Right.
Yeah.
So go backly, Tepi.
In some sense, I'm about to try and do TV on the radio,
because I'm about to talk about modelists, which, of course,
I can't show you pictures of.
Yeah.
But if you happen to go onto our Lord of Spirits podcast
Facebook page, we actually
Dead pro-
some pictures from these sites so you can see some of this if you go to Facebook
and look at this there are a few things there so but yes right now we're gonna
play imagine if you will.
It's the feeder of the mind.
Exactly.
So there are very early monoliths, monolithic structures, stone, standing stone
structures at Go Backly Tappy.
There are arranged, it will be reminiscent to some people probably when you look at
pictures of Stonehenge is probably the closest thing.
And I have wistful feelings about Stonehenge.
Oh, is this where we get you, where you finally tell the story?
No, I'm not going to tell the story, but I have been banned for life from Stonehenge.
The exact circumstances will remain a mystery for now.
But you know that's going to be a Lord of Spirits t-shirt at some point.
Band for life from Stonehenge.
Band for Stonehenge.
But what's really striking about these particular monolithic go-backly tepis is the carvings, I think, for everybody seeing them.
If you look at our Facebook page and see these pictures, and also there's a Wikipedia page which is, you know, there's lots and lots of pictures.
and there's animal carvings on these things.
on these standing stones.
Yeah, and it is unclear to archaeologists and anthropologists
exactly how to interpret the animal carvings,
or even if they should be interpreted, right?
Because interpreted implies that it's
some kind of pictographic language,
and it may not have been that.
It may have just been representations of animals.
But there are ranged in a way that suggests
that they were used for some kind of astralod.
observational. Yeah much like Stonehenge much like much like Stonehenge was in
in the ancient world but all of this point what all this points do is that the
remains there are not the remains of sort of a village that was constructed to
do commerce right right or that was pulled together because someone set
himself up as a chieftain or a king.
Yeah, it's not setting your sum.
natural resource, right?
Yeah.
Right. And so what it is, it's the remains of a ritual site.
Right.
And so there had been in the past sort of a consensus among scholars that the first human
and settlements developed for practical material reasons.
then once that happened they started developing religious beliefs and other elements of culture.
Yeah, just like, you know, and happened in the early American West, they built a town and then
oh, I guess we should probably build a church or something. Right. And what they're finding with
go backly, Tappy, and a few other cell prolific sites is that the exact opposite is true,
these first side
were actually ritual sites and began as places of pilgrimage. So, nomadic peoples and
people groups, tribes, clans would make some sort of periodic pilgrimage to these sites
and so the need to service those pilgrims and the ritual needs of the site actually then
gave birth to the settlement.
So what we're talking...
about here is, it's not really a single event but a development in history that's referred
to as the neolithic revolution. And that's the move from humans being nomadic and hunting,
food and gathering food. And if you're going to hunt and gather food, you sort of have
to be nomadic because you have to move with the seasons in terms of being able to gather
food and you have to move with the migration of animals.
if you're going to hunt food.
Yeah, right, which, which, you know, if you think about the ancient world, being nomadic
is the smartest way to be, right?
Because if you stay in one place, then you know, you could get attacked easily by your rivals,
you know, staying in one place also means you're subject to all the seasons of that place,
right, you know, as I think.
just out to migratory animals, you know, it doesn't make sense not to move around. So,
we think that the way human beings live now is normally, I mean, obviously most human beings in
this world right now are settled. They live in places and they don't move around. So it seems
obvious that that's the norm. But it was really not the norm early on, really, really not the norm,
and not really a very good idea. So it would have to be a really important reason for you to actually
build something somewhere and then sort of stick with it.
Right. Right. And so it happens sort of in the reverse of what was previously assumed
that this ritual site has it for people to dwell there permanently and it has a need
for food. So you got to supply it.
for the pilgrims, add for sacrificial rituals,
as we're gonna be talking about for most of tonight.
Those things have to be provided.
And so that causes the shift then to agriculture
and to the domestication of animals
because we have to be able to produce food at the site.
Yeah.
Regardless of the season, regardless of the,
we have to be able to, and then after producing food,
we have to be able to store it.
right? There's going to be guests all the time, so you got to keep the place stocked.
Right. And so these material changes to life are the product of the religious significance
of the site, which suggests something further. Right. And this this shift that I'm talking
about to seeing the religious and ritual significance of the place first and then the settle
is a shift that's being made by scholars who are atheists, right?
This isn't a religiously motivated thing.
This is where the evidence points.
But as religious people, right, we can assess something further,
for this site to become a pilgrimage site,
for it to become a religious site to which people would travel
from different clans and different groups that are otherwise
nomadic. There had to be some kind of actual spiritual or religious experience
there. There's a significance to that spot. Yeah, that that was experienced by
people. It can't just be like one person, right? So I mean, if one person is out of the
woods, it says, Hey, I met the great God, you know, Pazuzu out in the out the woods,
right? That's not going to cause even the members of his own group to all go out
You
the woods and try and find it.
Right.
It has to be a repeated thing, you know, like, you know,
when people discovered, and on a much lesser sense,
when people discover the Grand Canyon,
hey, come take a look at this
and people have the same experience every time they go.
But in this case, it's an experience where people
are saying that they encountered a being, a spiritual being.
Right.
It's an experience of spiritual reality.
in the ancient world that causes then this to become a pilgrimage site and then leads to the settlement.
Yeah. Yeah.
Yeah. And even now, right. So, I mean, there are parallels to that, for instance,
in Orthodox Christian experience where, like for example, Trinity St. Sirgeus monastery in Russia, right.
This was founded by...
St. Sirge's of Rado Nezh who basically went out of the woods to pray by himself.
But now if you go there, it is not only a massive monastic complex, but it's a city.
Like it is literally a city.
And the reason why the monastery was formed was because of St. Sirge's being there, who,
you know, because he's a saint, he becomes a vessel of grace, right?
So people go there to experience that as well.
And then the city grows up around it.
So it's exactly the same pattern.
It's exactly the same pattern and it makes a lot of sense.
And once again, this kind of just shows that modern people tend to think, even if they
are religious, they tend to think of religion as a kind of add on, even of maybe the most
important add on in their life, but a kind of add on.
Whereas what makes you in the ancient world where everybody's mobile wants to actually
build something and start to raise crops and that kind of thing, it must be something
super important, you know.
And all signs point to that super important thing being a spiritual experience.
Right. And you see something similar to this in the scriptures as well, where the patriarchal narratives in Genesis,
right, you know, Jacob has his experience at Bethel and he builds an altar of 12 stones.
Right. Joshua setting up the stones at the place where the Jordan River was parted.
and people coming back to see those spots
and see the stones that are erected.
Yeah.
And then of course the church building churches on top of all the places where great events
in the history of salvation happened, right, about table or an on the church of the Holy
Sepulchre.
So yeah, the idea that these spiritual experiences sort of consecrate a place is not just an
ancient stone age thing.
It's a universal human thing.
Yeah, and I...
And I think there's also a problem for modern people trying to apprehend this because,
especially those who live in say the United States because our population tends to be so
mobile and so uncommitted to the places that they're from.
People tend to move for whatever reason, usually a job or whatever.
And the idea that you would, that place actually is an important thing is just not, it's
just not a thing.
I mean, just for instance, right now, you know, you're in Louisiana.
I'm in pencil
Slovenia, headquarters in Indiana, and people are listening to us all over the world.
And I mean, this is a good thing, but it is a fundamentally displaced thing, you know,
and so I think that's another problem with, you know, like the modern skeptical mind,
if you say, well, this is the place where Jesus was born.
And so there's a church here.
The modern skeptical mind would say, is that really where he was born?
Because we tend to think that place is actually not that important.
Right? Whereas in the ancient world, it was super important. This thing happened here, and it keeps happening here, so we better pay attention to this.
Yeah, our tendency to a theory-alive religion and make it a mental and intellectual exercise.
Right.
Which has nothing to do with place, space, time, stuff, things, yeah, objects, reality.
Um...
So moving on to the next one, right?
Chalhojak, which as we said, is a couple millennial later sight.
This we have more permanent structures in the form of domiciles.
These aren't sort of separate houses.
These are sort of buildings broken up into rooms, each of which room was a residence,
likely for a family.
and um
There's all kinds of interesting neat stuff, but of religious significance is there are
already burial sites there where people are burying their dead.
And the custom at that time was apparently to bury their deceased family members under
the floor.
It was of course a dirt floor, but bury them in the floor of the family.
the family. So they're kind of always with you. Right. Yeah. Actually in the in the floor. But in those burial sites,
we find what are called grave goods. Yeah. Stuff. Yeah. Look, you're gonna need this in the next world. So
here you go. I mean, most people probably are aware, for instance, that the pharaohs are buried inside
the pyramids with all kinds of stuff.
It's the same thing.
It's exactly the same thing.
This is well well, this is much less stuff.
Yeah, a flit knife than you know.
Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
Don't forget your sack lunch, you know.
Not, and there's your thousand sleeve.
Yeah, about 20,000, 20 tons of gold.
Yeah, right.
Yeah, but but also found with them are animal remains,
which suggests that they're found with the human...
remains, right? So it's not that they had a pet sheep and they really loved it, so they buried it
with grandma. Yeah. It's, it's, these were sacrificial animals. Yeah. That were being sort of sent
along with the burial. So we know that sacrifice was taking place at this, at this point already.
And then we also find their
our sort of earliest window into what spirits they were worshipping at Chattelhojik.
Yeah.
At this ancient point.
Yeah, it was interesting to me to look at the photos.
And like the one thing that I noticed the most often was the heads of Bulls.
You know, like, and it seemed like they weren't,
They weren't bull skulls. These were like carved bullheads.
You know they were images of bulls with huge horns with huge horns right and and I collected for instance inside one of these dwellings
They have at that at that's at Chetolhojik
they have
A sort of a recreation of a domicile and one of the pictures and again we posted this on our Facebook page
One of the pictures you see a whole sort of vertical row of these bullheads in the corner of the the home
you know and and
This is not
You know, this is not someone showing off their hunting trophies.
Because again, these are images that are made.
They're not actual bull hordes.
Right.
Yeah.
This is a, this is a chalcolific icon corner.
That's what this is.
The, the, and these bull heads are founded almost every domicile, almost every home.
Usually in a specific area.
Alright, so applying...
that is sort of a home shrine that has this bull head in it.
And so the depiction of a male god as a bull,
while we find it here, is ubiquitous in the ancient world.
So you get in the epic of Gilgamesh, the bull of heaven.
Yeah, or in Greek myth, you've got the Europa,
Zeus appearing as a bull and the Minotaur.
One of my favorite stories from when I was a kid.
Yeah, and the bull bail, there's a whole segment of bail worship that surrounded bail as a bull.
That's the golden calf, right?
Right.
The golden calf may have actually been an apis bull from Egypt, but again, that's another
instantion of this idea, right?
Yeah, of this great bull.
The form that that bull takes in terms of its name that we find in, for example, the Hebrew
Scriptures is...
This is where behemoth comes from, which is actually Bahaimot in Hebrew.
Bahaimah is the word for like cow or cattle.
It's actually grammatically feminine.
And Bahaimot is the feminine plural, but it's a plural of majesty.
Like sometimes people will point out that God is referred to as Elohim, which is technically
plural, and it's a way of elevating him.
This is a
It's sort of like a way of saying this is V-Bull.
Yes, yeah.
Or, yeah, I mean, much like even Royal, you know,
are sort of stereotypes of royalty referring to themselves
as we, you know, we are not amused.
We, you know, yes, right, right.
So this is V-Bull, V-Bull, but he moat.
But even though it's this male figure,
and it's this sort of image of sort of male power
and strength and rule, it's radically feminine.
And then the other figure that we see already at Channel Hoyuk is a number of carved
goddess figures
and
the goddess figures there are related to another figure
that's pretty much
ubiquitous and that's not a mother goddess figure actually
It's actually a figure related to the sea
Yes, to the waters and thereby to chaos. So this is a sea monster and
it's dragons. And this takes the form in the Hebrew scriptures of Leviathan,
which is an English transliteration of what's actually more like low tan in
the Semitic Roots. But this figure, again, appears everywhere, bail fights it.
Tiamad is sort of the Babylonian form.
Yeah, I mean, or would the midgard serpent be a, you know, in Norse mythology?
Sort of. A little bit, yeah.
Yeah, Gaia in the Titan Gaia in Greek myth is actually closely related to this.
People point out, well, that's the earth, so people think of her as this earth-mother figure.
but who actually read the stories.
She's all about getting revenge for the Titans, her children, and she does that by bringing
monsters up out of the sea like Typhon.
Right.
And so you have these sort of two figures, and Leviathan or Lothan is actually grammatically
masculine even though it's a feminine figure.
Yeah.
So, both of them have this swap.
So you have these two figures and the sort of the day new model.
of those two figures in our Bible is in the book of Revelation where they
turn up as the beast from the earth and the beast from the sea. Yeah. And
myethin. Right and you know so while Leviathan kind of represents this chaos
which I mean which if you think about this symbolically right you look at the
the ocean that is an image of chaos. Constant movement it's uncontrollable it's
destructive, you know. And then, and then behemoth is this image of
tyranny. And when we were having a conversation earlier to prepare for this, you know, there's
sort of the idea that one is what you might describe as kind of toxic masculinity, the sort
of tyrannous image, and then the other sort of toxic femininity. You know, that and again,
toxic, not normal toxic. Yeah. Yeah. Right. Yeah. Yeah. Right. And so, yeah, these become sort
of you big with this thing.
years in ancient religion and knowing that that's who they are provides a lot of
contour right so the gold not just the golden calf but Jeroboam's golden calves
at Bethel and Dan and sort of all the undercurrents that are running all through
the scriptures of these two sort of spirits being these sort of primary
spirits opposed to yelling.
I got a Israel.
And we already see evidence of them being worshiped
this far back at the end of the Neolithic age
or the beginning of the Chalcolithic.
Right.
Yeah.
And it's an interesting question.
And we'll get to this in a second,
but I just want to raise this.
Why would you want to worship spirits that
are so horrifyingly problematic?
Yeah.
Well, there wasn't cancel culture yet,
so they couldn't get rid of them.
That's right.
Exactly.
This is no social media.
to ban them. Yeah, and how do you, yeah, yes, how exactly would you cancel?
Look, see monster. Yeah, exactly. But so this is what we see regardless of what
culture we want to talk about, whether we're talking about early Greek culture,
ancient near eastern cultures, early Canaanite culture, Egyptian, Mesopotamian,
The earliest shrines are these kind of
places before there even temples per se where they start building a building around it.
You have some place, be it a high place, an elevated place, or be it a particular tree
or a spring of water where these encounters with spirits take place and then a hedge or
or a fence or some kind of border is constructed around.
it. Right. To designate it as a sacred space. Yeah. And this this persists
throughout the entire history of humanity. Right. Like I've I've been reading lately
both Finnish and Norse mythology and you know the Finns had what they called
I'm sure I'm gonna mispronounce this sorry Finns. He see H. I. I. S. I. which the
most ancient version of that word refers to a place. But then eventually the word
came to refer to a spirit that kind of...
inhabited the place. And sometimes, you know, most of the time people would avoid them. And sometimes they would go there specifically to kind of encounter them. And you get the same thing. And again, in Norse mythology, where like there's a particular, I think in Northern England somewhere, there's actually a particular bog or something like this where there's indications. It's either Northern England or maybe in Scandinavia. There's indications that people were being sacrificed to Thor. And but, but the place was named as a place sacred.
to Thor because that's where you would go to encounter him.
It was a specific sacred place, you know?
Yeah.
And every religion, every single religion has stuff like this.
Whatever permutation you're talking about.
Right.
And this is what then develops into the idea that, again,
these are high places and these sort of designated sacred
spaces and groves and natural features.
the idea of the God's living in.
gardens and or on mountains. Right. Because those are the places where they were encountered
by people. And this is where the whole idea, the whole word paradise, the whole idea of paradise
as this walled garden, yeah. On top of a mountain comes from that imagery. Develops from this. So
So as we prepare to segue into our next bit, our
next part, our second half.
You asked about why you'd want to worship these?
Well, it's a good question.
Like why not just avoid?
I mean, these are big scary monsters of chaos and tyranny.
I mean, why just run away, right?
Right.
So if you think about it, if you're a nomadic tribe or clan
or family group or however you want to construct it,
of this group, this social unit that's nomadic.
And you encounter other humans, right?
Another group of humans.
You have various options, right?
The two most obvious would be if you think
your group is bigger and stronger, you
could try to subdue them, conquer them,
kill them, take their stuff.
But now if you encounter Leviathan, the queen of the Stone
page.
proverbially, right? Like you can't kill her and take her stuff, right? Right. So that
option's right out. So the option that remains to you is the option that would remain to you if you
met a bigger group of people, or just another group of people who you didn't want to attack, and that's
to make peace and make friends, and establish a relationship and some kind of fellowship and some
kind of communion with these other people you've encountered. Right. Because they're a threat
Oh
because you want them, you know, but in the case of, you know, demons, as a Christian
would understand these beings to be, you just don't want them to destroy you.
Right, right. Yeah. You want to try and be on their good side and be friends with them,
even though we know from a Christian perspective that's not possible. And it's kind of a bad idea.
Yeah. And so establishing that relationship and that rapport, especially through the
offering of hospitality becomes the purpose of the rituals that happen at these ritual sites.
Yep, right. Yep, it becomes a guesthouse for spirits and for all those who want to eat with them.
So, well, having said that then, we're going to go ahead and go to break and when we come back,
we will start to take your calls. So we'll be right back. Father Andrew Stephen Daimic
and father Steven DeYoung will be back in a moment.
Let's take your calls on the next part of the Lord of Spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF Radio.
So here's a question for you.
What does it mean to think Orthodox?
What have the unspoken and unexplored premises and presumptions underlying what Christians
It's believed.
Orthodox Christianity is based on preserving the mind of the early church. It's
Thronema. Dr. Gini Constitito brings her more than 40 years experience as a
professor, Bible teacher, and speaker to bear in explaining what the Orthodox
Thronema is, how it can be acquired, and how that Thronema is expressed in true
Orthodox theology, as practiced by those who are properly qualified by both
training at a
relationship with Christ. Thinking Orthodox, now available at store.enchantfaith.com.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits, the Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father
Stephen DeYoung. If you have a question, call now at 855-237-2346. That's 855-AFF
radio.
All right, well welcome back.
This is the second part of our show, and it's where we begin to take your calls.
So we just talked for a little bit about why anyone would want to have a relationship with
the demonic chaos monster.
Or giant bull.
Right, right.
Kind of depends.
Are you inland or are you near the ocean?
You know and and we ended up by saying
that it's because you don't want to be destroyed by them.
And so then the proper response to that is hospitality,
for hospitality.
And so that's what we're going to be talking about now
in this second part of our show.
So please do call in.
Again, it's 855 AF radio, 855-237-2346.
And we would love to talk to you.
So, all right.
So father, I mean, in these ancient, ancient, super
and sites that we've just been talking about.
There's no writing, we just have kind of material stuff to kind of go by.
But it gives a pretty clear picture that there is dedication to these beings and so forth.
But we don't know what exactly that looks like. What are the actual actions? I mean, archaeology doesn't
can't show you what people do. When's the earliest that we actually begin to know,
have some clue about what this hospitality that was
offered actually looked like. Right. Right. Well, we have, I mean, we have lots of
ancient ritual texts. But the way ancient ritual texts were written, for example, in the ancient
Near East, is interesting because it's not the way we write liturgical texts today. Yeah.
The turtical texts today are based around. They're written sort of like a script.
right where it's like this person says this person says that and then they have rubrics which are like the stage directions. Okay now you walk over here.
Yeah, say the black do the red. Yeah, right. Yeah, because it's because the the the spoken parts are traditionally you know if it for especially for those of you who are not clergy have never looked at
liturgical books that clergy use. The parts that you're supposed to say are written typically in black ink and the parts you're supposed to do are written in red ink at least in a better
better service book so yeah say the black
the red. Right. And so it'll say, you know, save this prayer. And then, you know, swing the
sensor in this direction three times and then that direction three times and then right. Yeah.
Exactly. Yeah. Exactly. Right. And so ancient Eryster ritual texts, sometimes are written as stories.
So rather than for example being written as instructions, it will tell the story.
of some event in the life of the gods and or the people performing the ritual in ancient days
that the ritual is based on reenacting and participating in. But it's just telling the story.
Yeah. So we don't know exactly what they did at various points.
Or we'll have prayers and hymns, but we don't get, you know, we'll have like this is the hymn that
that they sing when they offer the incense.
Okay.
When did they do that?
How much?
What kind?
Right?
Right.
Yeah.
So before we kind of get into those kinds of interesting details, we actually do have a
caller.
We have Ryan who is calling from Florida.
And Ryan, are you there?
Can you hear me?
Yes, fellow father.
Welcome Ryan to the Lord of Spirits.
It is good to talk to you.
What?
your question or comment for us tonight.
Yes, well, it's tangentially related to the topic, I suppose,
but it's more related to something that Father Stevens
talked about in the five-ish fall of angels
and on his own podcast as well, something that puzzled me.
And he's talked about the angels that
were assigned to the nations and how there was this,
I guess you could call it an angelic apostasy.
They began accepting worship.
and interacting with humans and not so kosher ways.
I guess my question there is,
was this fall of these angels?
Was it universal?
Did they all experience this fall?
And if so, what made it so universal?
And then just to follow up,
what would it have looked like had that fall not occurred?
If they had done their task rightly,
rather than accepting worship
and encouraging this idolatry.
What would that have looked like?
Okay, well father Steve
I'm definitely gonna let you address the first part because you were called out specifically
But yeah since there is someone who listens to this show who's convinced that this show and the Amman's full podcast are truly the same
I'm gonna throw him a bone and say that what would it what would it have looked like if they hadn't fallen?
Fallen
I think that it would look like the way that the Valar function the soul meridian now Ryan. I don't know if you're a talking fan
I had to do one with a huge talking fan.
I came to
basically came to Orthodoxy through a month's school. I'm not Orthodox, I'm not even a
catacomint, but I'm not perfectly good at it now.
Yeah, that's right, Father.
So there we are. No, I mean, I'm serious. Obviously, there's a lot of non-talking readers
out there who are like, what is he talking about, the Valar, whatever. But it's an image
of angelic beings. So, Jair, talking in the author, he writes this, this isn't the
So this is not his most well-known work.
It's second tier in terms of being well-known.
But in that work, these angelic beings that are created by the One God,
they help to take care of the earth and also human beings and elves, of course, as well, who are sort of two different versions of one species, so to speak.
And they help to beautify the earth and to form it and to teach things to mankind.
And it's a good relationship.
I mean it has...
has its problems, but they don't fundamentally go off the deep end. I mean, one of them does.
So I think that that's a good image of what it would have looked like. Right? And maybe we can
understand Tolkien's version of this as what it might have looked like before, after the tower
of Babel, but before this fall that was being discussed. So that's my idea for the second part.
So father Steve.
and why don't you address the first?
Yeah, well, it seems to have been near universal.
Saint Denis' Theary Apaguy and others.
You see this in, you see this as accessory
as explanation of the gospel also, for example.
The exception is Saint Michael, who was the prince,
of Israel as Daniel says, right? Daniel talks about the Prince of Persia, Gabriel talks about the Prince of Persia.
He talks about the Prince of Greece and that he says, Michael, your Prince, right? So the angel assigned to Israel,
say Michael the Archangel, is sort of the one exception to that. And so I think, you know, building off of what Father
Andrew said, I think the best image we can get,
biblically, in terms of what that would look like,
is Israel.
That doesn't mean that, for example,
the people didn't fall into egregious sin.
Obviously, they did.
In terms of their behavior and faithfulness,
there was not a lot of difference between most of Israel
and the neighboring nations.
See, with though there was supposed to be.
But there was always...
a sort of a different relationship between God and Israel. And I think the
the intercessions of St. Michael and of Abraham Isaac and Jacob and others were
part of part of that difference in terms of the long suffering that God showed,
not to say that they influenced God, right? But that God chose to work
through their
prayers and intercessions to extend his mercy to Israel in a way that now God also showed
according to St. Paul in Romans. He showed a certain amount of mercy to the nations in
overlooking their sins for a period of time right until the gospel came, not immediately
punishing them for the wickedness and sin that abounded among the nations. And that sort
of Seat Paul's theme.
when he speaks to Gentiles in X-17, you know,
in the past God has overlooked all of this,
but now the gospel is coming to you.
Now you're accountable, right?
Now you need to hear the call.
And I think what's in the background,
what we've been talking about already tonight
is the material side of that, right?
So when we talk about, well, these,
these angelic spirits started to appear to an interact
with an encounter, the people
of the world and started to influence them and then we talk about how they started to give them
these cultural innovations and these kind of things, right? What we've been talking about
anthropologically in the first part of the program is the material side of that where we see human
beings encountering some kind of spiritual reality at these places and then that being the engine
that leads to agriculture, the first city, right, cane builds the first city, right? The first kind
of permanent settlements.
the first domestication of animals, all of these sort of innovations that start
metalworking starts in the chalcolithic period that we're talking about.
Just like the genealogy of Cain says.
So this is really the flip side of that, right?
We were talking about the spiritual reality of that in the five-ish falls,
and now we're sort of talking about the historical human side of that.
Does that make sense to your Ryan?
Yes, definitely. That was an excellent answer. I really appreciate all that you do. This is such an enlightening podcast and blessings on it for sure.
Thank you. By your prayers.
Yeah, you said you thought that your question was tangential but actually it fed directly into what we're talking about because this does connect back to that earlier stuff.
and now we're looking at what is the human interaction response to when...
Fallen angels do their thing. So thank you very much Ryan. Thanks for listening.
Thank you. All right father. So we were just talking rubrics. Right. And so we don't
start getting sort of a more full-orbed picture until we get to Greco-Roman
sacrifices where we could piece together from a number of sources and
descriptions sort of the details of how some of these things played out.
Right because now you've got written texts for instance
where you can get this kind of detail.
And so now we're fast-forwarding again thousands of years
to, you know, 500 BC to around AD 150, right?
The sort of high Roman period, you know?
Right, Greek is Roman.
Greek is Greek.
Yeah, exactly, exactly.
But, I mean, these aren't things that they made up
when they first started writing them down.
No, right.
They were practices in the Indo-
European world and we'll probably talk about a specific case of this in the
third half, but even the terminology that's used in Greek to describe these
things is our borrowed Semitic words. So there is this sort of direct continuity in
terms of religious ritual at the Earl level between even the ancient Near Eastern
and Mesopotamian cultures and Egyptian cultures and then what we're about to
talk about now in more detail.
in the Greco-Roman sort of pattern.
Yeah, yeah.
That emerges.
Yeah.
So now we're going to talk about what does an ancient sacrifice look like.
It has generally some recognizable parts, pretty universal.
How does it actually work?
So the first part is a procession.
People walk in and align.
People process.
Yeah, where are they going?
they're going to the
place where this needs to happen, it could be a temple, it could be a grove, it could be,
I mean, there's all kinds of possibilities, but it's a desiccated altar on top of a hill,
right? High place, a hill or a mountain. Right. Right. But it's a designated spot. And
it's like we said earlier, it's because this spot has a spiritual significance. There's
been actual experiences there. Right. Right. And so, of course, the most, the most common
form that hospitality.
takes is the sharing of a meal.
Exactly.
And we've become a little disconnected from this
in modern American culture.
A lot of times now families don't even eat meals together.
Let alone gather with other families
or other people to have communal meals.
And now you've got even Uber Eats.
Who can just show up at your doorstep.
But in a lot of our orthodontists,
brothers and sisters from other cultures could actually help us out a lot with this because
in a lot of other cultures, Greek culture, Middle Eastern cultures. And even Slavic cultures,
there's more of a sense of this has been maintained, of the importance of sharing a meal together
and the significance of that. It's the thing a family does and to get invited into that is huge.
right and so this is how like community is
built. And so the way that hospitality is going to be offered to a God and some kind of fellowship
and communion with that spirit is going to take place is going to be in the form of sharing a meal
with it, primarily amongst other forms of hospitality, but primary a meal. And so that's what sacrifice is.
And so this procession sort of begins the process, pun, semi intended.
of doing this.
And so in these processions, the practical side of the
procession is you have these elements that are going to be
sacrificed.
That's not necessary.
We tend to think of animals primarily, and it's some more
horrible cases humans.
But we tend to think of animals as the primary thing.
But there are also plenty of sacrifices.
the fact most psychrified.
did not involve killing animals. The majority of sacrifices were, for example, wheat cakes,
or rice cakes if you're in Asia, depending on where you are, grain, right? Cakes made with grain.
It would also then include food animals. These were domesticated food animals, not like wild animals.
right?
That's your wild animal.
Yeah.
To sacrifice.
You're gonna have someone over, you know.
Yeah, you bring out this is what we've been preparing.
This is what we've been working on.
You know.
Right.
You're offering them something of yours.
Something of yours that you're offering to them.
And it's notable, it's notable that it's always food.
Sacrifices are always food.
It's not, you know, I think you made this point,
but I just wanna underline this,
a lot of people have this sense that ancient-
sacrifice was always about killing an animal, putting it on an alter, whatever, but it wasn't even always an animal.
But it was always food. You know, you know, sacrifice a chair.
You know, you sacrifice something that can be eaten because it's a communal meal. That's, that's exactly what's, what's going on here. So, yeah.
When I, when I read in Wizards of the Coast, then in fifth edition Dungeons and Dragons, Dwarf Priest, sacrifice metal.
I was just like...
this is so unrealistic please. So so so related so I don't know if I'll recover from that one.
So related to that is we do have a caller. We have Samuel calling from the God protected
Dominion of Virginia where I happen to have been born. And he has a question specifically about
this. So Sam, you can, are you there? Yeah.
I'm there. Thank you for taking me, call fathers. You're welcome. It's good to hear from you. So
so what's on your mind, Samuel? I'm wondering what it how it changes things because obviously does
when God himself is the sacrifice, the sacrificial meal being offered. That's a that's a really good
question. I'd love to say we'll just tune in next time because that's what we're talking about
Among other things, but I mean just to just you know
We don't want to leave you with nothing.
I'll just say this.
So all of the stuff that we're talking about with regards to paganism now, which is kind
of what this particular episode is about, it becomes fulfilled completely in the Christian
context where not only are we having, you know, sacrificing to our God, sharing the meal
with our God.
but that he himself is the one who is sacrificed and shared.
So how does that change?
There's a hundred things we could say about this,
but it's that the life that we receive,
for instance, this is the first thing that Chris
had me to say, the life that we receive from this
is eternal life, it's not temporary.
And it is deifying, it changes us.
So it's not like...
puts us in communion with him as all sacrifices always did to whatever God.
But, but makes, you know, and not only makes us like him, as all sacrifices do to whatever
God, kind of getting ahead of ourselves, you're a little bit, that's okay.
But, but, but, you know, grants eternal life and elevates us to become, as we've said
before, the sons of God.
So that's the response I would give initially to that.
Father Steven, is there anything you want to add or correct or whatever?
Oh yeah, to shore cards a little bit for the next couple of episodes.
We're laying some groundwork here in terms of what sacrifice looks like in the world at large.
And what we're going to see next time already in the Old Testament sacrifices is that God is going to take a lot of the spiritual quote unquote wisdom and understanding of the nations and invert it in the sacrificial ritual that's done in Israel or that's prescribed for Israel at least.
and then
And Christ's sacrifice that we're going to be talking about more two episodes from now
and our third episode is sort of the fulfillment of that and the ultimate inversion of what
pagan sacrifice is.
And one of the key elements is exactly what you're hitting on that rather than it being
a spirit taking something from humans or seeking to be appeased by humans, God meets
us and sacrifice with self-offer.
He offers himself to us, which is a direct inversion of this pagan idea.
He's the one giving the hospitality.
But yeah, so just hang on and keep listening Samuel for two weeks from today and then
four weeks from today because this is a first in a series of three I'm so excited.
Does that make sense Samuel?
Yeah it does.
And Father Stephen, when you mentioned Dungeons and Dragons is the right before taken by
call it.
I'm actually playing as a dwarf cleric as one of my current characters that I often get nitpick
any about that sort of that exact thing in fantasy settings. Yeah, you need to do you need to do
beer and ale drink offerings and keep it real. Keep it real. Exactly. All right. Well, thank you very
much for calling Samuel. Good to talk to you. Yeah, you two fathers. Thank you. All right. Okay, so
So we've got food being offered.
It's brought in a procession.
It's domesticated animals, it's wheat cakes, it's wine, it's oil, you know, if you're a dwarf.
All cleric, it's beer.
It's all food.
Yeah, it's all food.
Exactly.
So what's the next thing that has to be done with it?
The practical element of the procession is you need to get that stuff to place where
you're sacrificing it.
Right.
Exactly.
So, right.
So, there's that practical element.
So then in the procession.
The procession is not just made like, okay, well hey, take all the stuff over to the altar, right?
It's done as a festival procession.
So there's incense, this being offered, there's music, at least singing, sometimes instrumentation,
as the people process to that place.
And if there's animals involved, those animals are still alive at this point.
right at our
and are being brought and transported.
Probably led unleashes or whatever.
Yeah.
One biblical element of this is people may be familiar
with the Psalms that are labeled as the Psalms of Ascent,
ASCETNT.
Those are the Psalms that were sung by people
as they made their pilgrimage to Jerusalem
with their animals, with their things
that they were bringing to sacrifice.
So that pilgrimage was turned into a grand procession
of this type.
Right. So then once they get to the place,
the elements, they're going to be sacrificed,
need to be sanctified. They need to be made holy,
which means they need to be designated for that purpose.
Right. Like this is going to be used for this.
And and not and this over here is not going to be used.
Right. So it's not it's not that everything that's broad is
necessarily used. Sometimes it's just pieces of it. Right.
Right. Sometimes. Yeah. Yeah. Exactly.
Okay.
Um.
So they have to be designated. That's usually with the laying on of hands.
There's also this idea that's embedded of the animals involved being sort of willing participants.
Yeah, that's kind of an interesting element. And as we were talking about this,
there's actually a token of this to sort of prove this.
And so the idea, of course, is that animals are like,
yes, I'm happy to be sacrificed to the zoo,
so whoever.
Yes.
I'm glad I was chosen for this noble purpose.
Right.
Now obviously, the animal is not saying that,
but it's richly sort of tokenized by a tuft of their hair
being cut out.
And then that hair that was cut off
is then placed in the incense.
So
but it's that the animal is offering himself now
by this little gift of this offering of hair
that has been cut off and is being burned up with the incense.
We're gonna talk about incense more later.
But yeah, I thought that was a really interesting thing
and animals are not tortured in the process.
It's really a peaceful sort of slaughtering, frankly.
And that the killing itself is not
really part of the ritual. It's just a necessary element. If it is going to be an animal sacrificed,
it's a necessary element in order for the sacrifice to be possible, right?
To be eaten. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. You know, eat alive animals. Yeah. So, right. So, and that's
important because Western theology has put into our heads that sacrificing something is killing it.
Killing it. Yeah, that the death that the death is the key element and that there's suffering involved
somehow. But what we see in ancient
saccharis is the exact opposite.
Yeah.
Not only is the killing not ritualized,
there's no instructions by and large
for how to kill things.
Yeah.
You just have to do the Old Testament
or in these ancient rituals.
There are ways that they tended to do it
with certain animals just for ease
of handling in terms of the procedure.
Right. But there was no specific
ritualization of the killing and this
this little bit of ritual.
with the tough of hair being grabbed and cut.
But that ritualization of the animal offering itself
is signifying the exact opposite of the animal suffering
or being afraid or being killed.
It's sort of voluntarily offering itself as well.
And I'm told, and I'm not a butcher, or a farmer of any kind.
I'm told that an animal that's tortured before it dies.
Actually that it does bad things to the taste even so like if it would be not it would be against your
Best interests, right?
You know if you're offering hospitality to your God you're gonna offer an animal
That's freaked out and sort of tastes the worst you know
So you wouldn't you wouldn't want to do that again
Not a farmer not a shepherd so I don't know if we've got any cattle ranchers out there
He's like oh no no no that's completely an urban legend father. I don't know
But it is something that I have heard.
And it's something that I have heard.
So the you've heard pun nut intended.
So the other bit that we know a little about in terms of how the animal was killed is based
on the fact that the blood was going to be collected.
Right.
And so that means that in a lot of cases the animals throat would be slit because that
was the easiest way to drain all the blood out of the animal before it was butchered.
The blood would be collected.
in a bowl, blood, it's not just Leviticus that says that blood is life.
That's not even the blood.
Universal ancient things.
So there were minority of rituals.
This was actually more common in human sacrifice than animal sacrifice,
where the blood would be drunk by the participants.
far more
commonly and especially in Greco-Roman practice, at the various shrines, in addition to the
shrine to the God or Spirit or Muse or whoever, right, the Caesar, whoever, there would
also be a grave of a hero.
And hero was kind of a technical term in Greek, right?
It's not just, we say someone is my hero, but heroes were the founders of cities, people
like Perseus, Theesius.
Who do these great deeds?
in the past. But no matter how great the deeds were that you did when you died, you still
went to Hades and became a shade. And you had this sort of shadowy existence as a shadow
of your former self that lasted until everyone had forgotten you. And then you just sort
of ceased to be.
It's like Tinkerbell. She just appears if you don't believe in her.
Yeah, sorry. So you would have these these grave shrines in part to keep their memory alive.
life. Right. And then the blood would be taken and would be fed to them by pouring it
out into their grave. Yeah. The blood from these sacrifices. And this happens in the
Odyssey, doesn't it? Yeah. In the Odyssey, there's a point where Odysseus needs to talk
to Achilles who is dead, of course. And so to do this, he goes to one of the many places
where there's a gateway to the to Hades to the underworld.
See our future.
episode on sacred geography. But he goes to one of these places and sacrifices some black goats
and pours their blood out into a pool and the blood sort of attracts the shades up out of the
gateway to come and drink the blood in the Odyssey and that ultimately lures out a kill ease so that
Odysseus can communicate with him. So that is in story form what's going on in the
the sacrifice.
ritual with the grave of the hero and the blood. So blood being drained, right? You now have an
animal if there's an animal involved and the cakes and the wine and the oil that are being
sacrificed. Those were then brought to a place called the Prothesis. That was the Greek name for it.
And that's the place where the elements were further prepared.
So the animal would have to be butchered and
Divided up into the different parts there would be parts that were gonna be offered
To the God or gods or spirits
There would be a portion that was gonna be eaten by the the priests and celebrants and then there was a portion that was gonna be
Eaton by the people
Right, right there's this cutting celebrating the sacrifice and so those pieces had to be divided out
Yeah.
And if it's an animal right you're basically doing butchering you're cutting cutting an animal
But if it's you know cakes or something like that you're kind of saying okay
Here's the best cake. Here's the not as good cake, you know
Whatever cutting them out and you're pouring the oil and wine onto the cakes or onto the
Meet it's going to be offered yep. Yep, and then the
the elements that are going to be offered to the
God were taken to the altar.
Right.
And the word, just as a side note, in Latin, the word aura means both altar and table.
These aren't two different words.
There's not a difference between a sacrifice and a meal and an altar and a table in the
ancient world. I say that and our Protestant friends will understand why that's
Yeah.
that there's not a difference between an alternate table.
But so those elements are brought
and the ones, what's going to be offered to the gods
is emulated.
Burnt up.
Right.
And yeah, which like, you know, I remember,
this was a long time ago actually,
I was doing some fiction writing
and I was asking you questions about this.
Because like, okay, I, you know, burning up
parts of an animal, fine.
I've burned plenty of roasts in my time.
I know how you do that.
But like what about burning a cake or something like that, you know and and and and that's one of the point when you said
That's what the oil is for yeah
So if you've got a cake, you know, and these are not cake. This is not cake like birthday cake. Okay, these are that flat. Yeah flat
You know crunchy or whatever
But if you put oil on it there, it's much more likely to light on fire and the wine is
Little higher proof than
Alright, a lot of everyone.
which also causes it to burn.
It gets poured out and that's the idea,
that's the way that the God consumes it,
is when it's lit on fire.
Right, the smoke rises up into the heavens, right?
And it's an aromatic kind of thing,
because even actually people realize
that smell and taste were closely connected.
Right. As senses.
Right. Right.
And there's this cool element in the midst of this,
which I thought was really...
interesting, right? Which is, there's a specific act when the stuff is brought to the altar, right? And what is that?
The last thing before the portions for the spirits being offered to is burnt is, and the language that's used is that the gifts that are being given to the God or God's
or spirits are touched and elevated.
Touched and elevated.
And that's the
That's fine.
thing before what follows which is the burning of what goes to the spirits and
then the following feast which is the elements that go to the priests and the people.
Yeah okay so before we get to that I want to go ahead and take another break and
when we get back we actually have someone calling from Indiana who has a
question about guardian angels.
First, we're going to go ahead and go to a break,
so we'll be right back.
Father Andrew Stephen Daymak and Father Stephen DeYoung
will be back in a moment to take your calls
on the next part of the Lord of Spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF Radio.
Are you struggling in your walk with Christ?
you want to rediscover your reason for living.
The person you were created to be.
Renewing you, a priest, a psychologist, and a plan
gives you the keys to unlock areas of your life
that hold you back from fully experiencing
the renewal and transformation God has in mind for you.
Co-author by a priest and a psychologist,
Father Nicholas and Dr. Roxanne Lowe.
Renewing you combines principles of spiritual growth
with psychological tools to help you become your best self,
fully connected with God's purpose for you.
To purchase this book, please go
to store.ancientfaith.com.
That's store.ancientfaith.com.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits,
the Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Steven DeYoung.
If you have a question, call now at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF radio.
Welcome to the f***
Third half of the Lord of Spirits and yes, we're saying that quite on purpose the third half
Before we get to the feast that comes as the next part of the sacrificial ritual
We have a call from I think it's Cristiana from Indiana. Am I am I saying your name right? Are you there?
Uh, yes, I'm here and yeah, it's uh, Cristiana. Oh good
It's it's always tough when someone mispronounces your name, so yeah
Yeah, people come.
Christina so often that my aunt who is actually named Christina I say yes what when I hear her name at family reunion
Well, it's lovely to talk to you Christina and what is the question that you have for us this evening?
Yeah, thanks so much for taking my call so it's actually three questions
But I promise they're all great
Well, we've got the time
Yeah, so
Guardian angels. What happens to our guardian angel after we die? Do they get assigned to a new person?
Do they cease to exist? Do they go up to heaven and join the heavenly host and sing praises?
Do they hang out with us on the new earth? Do we have a relationship with them? Do they?
Do we ever get to meet them face-to-face in heaven now that we can see angels up there?
Yeah
Okay, well do you want to give all three?
us at once and all three your questions at once or okay yeah what I can answer that one
real quick it's yes no no yes no yes all right next no I'm joking just kidding just
Yeah, okay, well, all right, well
Father what what what was all okay? Yeah, cuz I don't really
I don't really know the answer to this one, so Father Stephen, why don't you take a crack at it?
Right, well, yeah, so
As we talked about a little bit last time
What is it like to be a bat, right?
Angels don't experience sort of space the way we do
Right, so it's it's not like they're either here or
In heaven, right or right
So, you know, Christ.
says about guardian angels, about the guardian angels of little children that their angels are always before his father in heaven.
But that doesn't mean they're like not with the children, right? That's just saying that they have this prominent place in the Divine Council,
meaning God is very attentive to what's going on with these children and he's protective of them.
is what that's indicating.
So...
We don't necessarily have an angel who's like only our guardian angel and has never been
the guardian angel of any human before or of any human in the future.
And that's okay just like we have a patron saint who's the patron saint of a bunch of
other people and has been the patron saint of a bunch of other people.
And so I think the last piece of that that I didn't answer yet is that yes, we will be
able to get to
know them in the world to come.
All right.
Okay.
What else you got, Kristiana?
That's inspiring.
That's so exciting.
Yeah.
Okay.
So second question.
Does our gurney, nasal carrier soul to heaven after we die?
I saw this on a page that sold icons.
And in the description, it was a, I was looking for some pro-life
some pro-life rid of icons.
And there was one where...
It's a guardian angel and a baby.
You know, one that had died in the womb
and in the description it said that
the guardian angel's career,
your soul's a heaven after you die
and I'm like, wait a second,
I've never heard that before.
I've got to ask this.
Yeah, so I mean, it's certainly the case
that we see in saints lives
that angels come to take the souls of the righteous
It's a parody.
I mean that's now whether I don't know whether you could say oh oh here's the Guardian Angel and then six other friends he's brought with him
You know they're not usually named in the same size I've read
But the idea that that angels do accompany the soul to paradise is pretty pretty well established
I would say I don't know is there something specific about the Guardian Angel father Steven?
Well, that's yeah, I mean we as as earth are Christians we believe that a person.
and soul takes a journey after they die, usually corresponding to 40 days.
But yeah, our guardian angel accompanies us on that journey on the way.
Yeah. Yeah.
Better than Beatrice and Dante.
Boom. That's that's for Richard Roland.
I know you're listening.
I think you were, I think you were thinking of Virgil and Dante.
Oh, excuse me.
You're right.
Well, Beatrice is the one who comes to my think in the putty.
So right.
Yeah, but that's the boring one.
Nobody reads that far.
They're reading about purgatory, please.
That's right.
All right, Cristiano, what's your third and final question?
Yeah, yeah.
When do we get our guardian angels?
Do we get them when we're born?
When we're baptized?
Or when we're Christmas, if that's different from when we're baptized?
Well, definitely at baptism, right?
Because in the baptismal service, it's specific.
specifically prayed for as part of that,
especially the part actually right before the baptism itself.
You know, the exorcisms and so forth at the beginning.
What else, though?
I mean, there are certainly cases where angels are,
I mean, I think part of the problem right is that
God assigns angels to take care of us, to guide us,
to pray for us, to defend us, all these kinds of things.
And we have this concept of a guardian.
But I wouldn't necessarily say it's like okay, this one has this hat on right?
so
Certainly angels are involved in people's lives at every point
But there is definitely this kind of connection that happens with baptism. I don't know
I don't know if I'm making any sense here father Stephen. Please help me
This is kind of a porque no less trace. Yeah, yeah, why not all three yeah
Um.
Because again, we keep coming back to what it's like to be a bat.
We experience time as humans, right, as this succession of moments, right?
And we could try to literalize that when we're talking about God, right?
So we say, well, okay, this is the point where I really came to understand the gospel of
Christ.
If I died five minutes before.
for that, what would have happened, right?
See, we can think that way, right?
But we're kind of assuming that like God and the angels
are on this parallel track with us,
it's experiencing time the way we do, right?
Or like God didn't know, or whatever.
So there are events in our lives
that we experience in our lives
at a particular period of time, right?
At a particular point in time.
But their reality
isn't limited to that point in time. So something changes for me at that moment.
Something doesn't change for God and something doesn't necessarily change for an angel.
So for me at my baptism or chrysmation, right, there's a guardian angel who I enter into this
relationship with, but that doesn't mean that the angel was sort of sitting around waiting to be
assigned up until
that point, right? Like in a waiting room, like outside, you know, what I was being born,
you know, pacing with my dad, right? Or that God was, you know, getting ready and thinking
about which one he would sit right like that silly. For me, yeah, that's the point, but
the reality of it extends not just forward from there, but also back from there.
Does that make sense, Cristiana?
Yeah, that does.
Oh, but I'm a little...
Do we have one guardian angel or do we have many that kind of like hang around?
Also pray for other people.
We have a guardian angel.
Yeah, we have a guardian angel, but we also can have a patron saint, our family can have a patron saint, our church can have a patron saint.
If you go to my church, that's Archangel Gabriel, right?
So.
he's sort of the guardian angel of my whole parish.
So there's a lot of overlap.
Yes, there's lots of folks praying for us.
But our guardian angel is an angel, right?
Who is connected to our life.
Yeah.
All right, well, I hope that that helps.
And now you've got four questions, Cristiana.
So that is literally more than anyone else has ever gotten
in the whole history of this podcast.
Well, I'm going to say something biblical about demanding something and then God listens.
Oh, yeah, the righteous, the unrighteous judge.
Something like that.
The persistent widow.
There you go.
The judge.
Well, there you go.
All right.
Well, great to talk to you, and I hope that helps.
Thank you very much for calling and for listening, Kristiana.
All right.
Thanks for taking the question.
You're welcome.
So we've just burnt a
calf liver and now it's time to party. Yes, right? Right? Yeah. Because what
follows that burning at the altar is the feast. Right. Where everyone's going to
eat. And this isn't just a question of eating the things that were actually
sacrificed, right? Like the other pieces of the animal, right? Right. There's
There are cakes.
Yeah, there's-
There's side dishes, right, at these feasts.
And this is the word for today.
Right, the word for today is trapeza mada.
Trapeza mada.
Which literally means table things.
But all stuff.
Yeah.
Because trapeza is the table.
And so those are the other things
that we're eating along with the sacrificial feast.
And so for example, the Temple of Demeter in Corinth
had huge dining halls.
banquet halls. That wasn't to rent out for wedding receptions. That was part of the
sacrificial worship was everybody going and eating.
And the important, at least one of the important things to get from the fact of side dishes,
is to emphasize that this really was a meal. It was really a meal that was shared together.
And this created a
the the
Kenania in Greek the fellowship the communion it it formed the community
Right and that included the God or gods or spirits and
and the humans bound them together and
We'll probably talk about this more in a further episode, but
This is in the background of what St Paul is talking about in Corinthians to the the
I'm Christian.
at Corinth about not eating at an idol's temple,
not eating food off her side, and also about becoming a
communicate, having communion with demons by participating
in these meals.
Yeah, it's not just about don't eat the bad food.
There's a ritual event that's occurring.
And it is a religious...
is quite literally a religious experience.
Right.
Yeah, yeah.
And usually if I recall correctly, especially once you
get to the Greco-Roman period, the next thing that typically
happens is a lot of immorality along with it as well.
Well, right.
Because yeah, it's not just a feast like, hey,
let's sit down and have a potluck.
It's a party.
Yeah.
In the worst possible way.
Yes.
the full-orbed 1980s sense.
Yeah, yeah, and and all of this especially like the detail of it kind of just underlines what priests were in the ancient world, right?
Like nowadays we tend to think of priests largely as pastors, which is why there was this wonderful rumor that went around as soon as long as I was no longer a pastor that I was no longer a priest anymore
Not true still you are still frocked. Yes, the frocking continues
Yeah
But that priest in the ancient world were largely
not pastors, they weren't doing pastoral counseling, they weren't, you know, all that kind of
stuff. They weren't administrators. They were a kind of ritual technicians. They were specialists
in exactly how you do all this stuff precisely, exactly how you do it in the way that the God
expected, right? Because like there was the idea that you could do this wrong. And also there
There is often...
Divination that went along with it, right? Like, you know, parts of the animals being cut open and
Reading what's in the entrails and using that to predict the future and and that kind of thing and and that's
What priests did that's what their job was?
Was all of that and and and and I think you know, and then one of the things that's underlined by that is
You can't get it wrong like the God might decide
he wasn't into the sacrifice. He might reject...
your invitation to dinner or having tasted of it, you know, say, no, you did this wrong.
Right.
We've all been to a dinner party that went bad where things went sideways.
And that could happen with the gods too, right?
Someone could say the wrong thing, do the wrong thing, offer the wrong type of food, make
some kind of...
faux pas in terms of the manners required at such a function.
And so, yeah, a big part of the reading of entrails that a priest
called a Harrow Specs would do.
And we've got one of the things we find a lot are these hardened,
fired clay models, like scale models of like livers and kidneys
from animals, like today form writing on them,
indicating
what to look for in the different parts.
Part of it was, his job was to read
whether they were doing it right or not
and whether the offering was being accepted or not
because they believed there would be signs.
Probably one of the most dramatic of these
is once before the Roman armies
went into a really disastrous battle.
The priest who was doing the butchering at the prosthesis
discovered that the animal they just killed had no heart.
Oh, it's a bad sign.
Yeah, that was big.
Literally.
Really bad sign.
and lowered the whole day lost, right?
So they were looking for those kind of things.
So it did.
I was gonna say, this makes me think of like
when you go to the doctor, right?
And like now I'm gonna have to make
heart respects jokes.
The next time I go to the doctor and they're looking at
an X-ray or something like that.
I'm like, so, you know, what do you read their doctor?
You know, as he quietly chuckles to himself.
Yeah.
Yeah, alright.
All right, so, okay, well, we've taken up most of our time, but there's something that
kind of goes along with all of this, right?
And that's a question that probably a lot of people would have like, okay, well, okay,
the offering of food, whether it's meat or cakes or wine or oil, puts you in communion
with the God.
That's an offering.
It's a shared meal.
It's a communal experience.
So...
But what about all these incense that comes along with it?
What's the deal there? Is that a sacrifice too?
Right?
Right, and we've already mentioned in the procession
and some of the details there that incense was being
used there and incense is offered. That's the language we use
incense was offered on altars. There were altars of incense
right in
all cultures right?
but also, as we'll talk about more next time in the tabernacle in the temple, there's an incense altar,
and that altar was actually used more than the altar of burnt offerings.
Because that was the incense offerings were the basis of the daily cycle, right, at morning and evening,
with prayers. And so incense is taken to this altar, it is offered, and the language that's used
about the aroma and the smell rising up is the same language that's used
about the aroma of the burn offerings rising up and and the smell. So there's
that piece where it's being offered as this pleasing aroma it's being offered
with prayers are being attached to it. So it's just pleasing that goes you know
you're trying to please the God just as you're trying to please someone you're
offering hospitality to. Right. You're gonna ask someone for a favor you bring
the McGift, right?
Yeah, right.
Right.
And so that's the one side.
And the other side of incense offering
is there were sensors just like we have now,
in the Orthodox Church, in the ancient world,
that were, they took various forms,
but they were basically mobile means of offering incense.
Right?
And it's alter is a fixed thing, at least relatively.
So you would comment, you would
would take some of the coals and some of the incense from the altar and place them in
a censor.
Right.
It is how it was done.
And then the censor could be used to carry that incense to other places.
And that could be used in what was called in Mesopotamian religion, fumigation rituals.
Because the idea was you were sort of smoking out the area in order to render it sacred
pure
And the Egyptians are really specific about this.
They believe that there were sort of aerial spirits, literally.
There were spirits in the air that might be malicious or at least tricksters and had to
be sort of driven out of the presence of the God of the temple.
Right.
So this is like setting off a bug bomb in your house and all the cockroaches go scattering,
right?
Except their demonic cockroaches.
demonic cockroaches that's gonna be our new meme everybody
sense is the demon cleaner right so right is it cleans out cleans out the
area so there's this this purification element and just a note if you
understand this you know why you got to keep scooping that incense during
services if you can still see clearly it's not enough anyway you gotta get
that leave the line at head height.
Right.
Through the building.
But I totally agree.
And this is so embedded, I mentioned earlier that sort of at the oral level, the Greek words
that describe religion are borrowed Semitic words that ultimately come out of Akkadian roots.
So the oldest altar we know of at the La Cayenne in Greece is with
referred to throughout Greek history as the Bimos, which is from Bima, the
subitic root, which is the word for alter. And in Greek it just became the name of
that particular one because they lost sight of the etymology. But more
pertinent to this is the Greek word, Cate roe, which is the verb for to cleanse
or to purify.
Yeah, and the origin is with the arses.
Yeah, right, catharsis.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
And so...
Authorities.
And that word is derived from the Semitic Conor, which is usually transliterated as QTR.
It's Qatar, the verb in Hebrew, and just the root cutter in Ugaritic.
And that is the verb that means to offer incense.
Yeah, so it's interesting that some of these key
sacchar-
official terms, as you said, come from these
semitic practices of the ancient near East
and then make their way even into Indo-European
languages like Greek, get borrowed straight in
and sort of Hellenized or Latinized or whatever
of the case.
Right.
And so to sense something is not to
metaphorically cleanse it.
To cleanse something is to metaphorically sense it.
In my drop.
Yeah.
Yeah, it's exactly inverted. Yeah, right, right.
That's going to want a t-shirt too. Yeah. Yeah, it's catchy.
It's a chiasmus. Sorry, it's a chiasmus, so it's gotta be cute.
So that brings us to, and I think this is going to lead into what we're going to talk about in our next two episodes, that you see this clearly with insets.
this with all forms of sacrifice in the
the Old Testament, the New Testament,
atonement, that there are these two elements.
The one element that is usually described
by the Latin term propitiation,
to propitiate someone means to make them propitious,
and to be propitious means to be happy or well-disposed,
or pleased towards someone.
Yeah, not a word we tend to use in everyday speech.
How are you doing today?
I'm very propitious actually, thank you.
Yeah, I actually find the word propitious.
to be quite pro-pinkant to my everyday.
Boom!
But, um, but so, so that's what propitiation means.
It just needs to please someone to make them happy, right?
Right.
Whether they were angry before or not, you're pleasing them and making them happy.
And then the other element that's usually described by the Latin word expiation, which
is like purification, right?
There are these two elements.
And these are present in all sacrifices we can see them in.
since offerings, we'll see them in the other sacrifices that we're going to go on to talk about.
Yeah, yeah.
Well, this has been our first episode of three, and so we're just going to give some closing
thoughts here.
And we appreciate all of those of you who are anticipating our next couple episodes.
This is so fun already.
So I'm just, I don't know.
I'm just happy to be here.
I just wanted to say about this context of
pagan worship that we've been discussing.
You know, if you listen closely,
if you know anything especially about Orthodox Christian
worship, there are probably a whole bunch of times
during this episode where you thought,
wait, wait, I know that word, or I know that action,
or whatever.
And then we didn't make the connection for you.
We're going to make those connections for you,
but we wanted to lay this specific groundwork here initially.
And it's not just about a kind of heuristic
So, progress.
depression, right? It's really about, again, reorienting the way that we understand what
it is that we do, and reorienting the way that we understand what we ought to be doing,
right? And how we ought to be doing it. When you understand that sacrifice in the ancient
world does what we just described. And when you understand how it's conducted, then it...
It kind of makes a sort of flat, secular world view
almost impossible, right?
You can't... once you know that you can have a meal with your God
and be in communion with your God, then that takes what it means to be a religious person,
or Christian in particular, completely out of the realm of
this is what I think and feel and believe, right?
Although those are important things, it's
much more primal and visceral, no pun intended.
It gets you down in the stomach, quite frankly.
And I think that that's a really important place to aim
when you're talking about the stuff
that actually is the most important.
I mean, I'm being a little redundant here.
But the kind of faithfulness that keeps you returning
to God over and over again,
No-
faithfulness that is always making your love for Jesus Christ grow is the kind of
faithfulness that even connects to your body, which is very much an element of who you
are. And I'm talking about the material body here, right? And that there is the whole
human person is brought into contact with God through exactly what we've been talking
about. Now we've been talking about it in terms of pagans. But if you're if you listen closely,
I'm sure you...
So you heard a lot of stuff that has everything to do with also the worship of the one true God.
And that continuity should leap right out at you.
And we're going to get to that a lot more in the next couple episodes.
But just tonight, we want to just sort of show you what does worship in the ancient world look like.
And you probably notice it does not look like what a lot of people call worship now.
And it universally looks almost the same in every culture with just some of...
adjustments here and there, but it's always centered on the offering of food and sharing
it with your God, the accompaniment with incense to both please your God and to purify
the space and the actions that you're engaging in.
So this is really, really important stuff everybody, and I hope that this has been valuable
for you, Father.
Yeah, so this was
this episode maybe even more than some of the previous ones,
especially where we started out was in some kind of
rarefied air, right?
Yeah.
Big sites from the neolithic and calcolithic periods
with names we could barely pronounce in Turkish.
And this may seem kind of disconnected, right?
And this isn't just that I should be allowed to shoot my mouth
off and I should have a...
and everyone should listen to my interesting opinions
about fascinating old historical stuff.
Because frankly, other than the handful of nerds like me
who would be expected to care about what things were like
in 10,000 BC.
But the reality is this cuts to a big part of our mission
in this podcast as a whole.
and we've
talked before about how disconnected modern and postmodern life is.
That was sort of digitally disconnected.
And how disconnected from just reality we've become.
And how this is affected, how we view meaning and our lives and the world,
how it's affected human morality, human sexuality,
the human understanding of God and of religion.
and this sort of disconnection.
There are four main ways that humans interact with reality.
The first one's language and we're pretty good at that.
We're very much in our heads.
We're very linguistically oriented.
When we go to worship services
of the Orthodox Church or elsewhere,
we focus really hard on the words
and try to determine what they mean.
Then there's music and art are the next two.
and
Those have been lost to varying degrees
and we try to rediscover them.
But the fourth one has almost been completely lost
by modern humans, and that's ritual.
Ritual is not just smells and bells.
We were talking about incense.
It's not just a performance, a sort of theatrical performance
that I enjoy watching.
It's not something that induces an emotional experience.
in me, it's a way of connecting with reality. And that's why we see that worship and especially
sacrificial worship, especially sacrifice, this community building around sacred and shared
meals and hospitality, is something that is basically human. The earliest humans we can
find evidence of, we're practicing it. Humans today can still practice it if we find
our way back to it.
And this is a way for us to reconnect with the whole element of reality to which we are least and now connected, which is the spiritual reality around us.
One of the questions we can ask a lot is, okay, I believe what you're saying on the show is true, but how do I really connect with that?
Ritual is the way.
And we attend Orthodox Church services as they're conducted.
This isn't just something that's being presented to us, to watch, or to hear, or to think
about.
It's something to participate in, and that participation will produce actual communion.
It will make us into a community with one another.
It will bind us together with our fellow Christians, and will bind all of us as Christians
and our Christian communities together with our God.
with our Lord and God and Savior Jesus Christ.
That's what this is all aimed at.
And so it's not just about me showing off interesting stuff I learned from books about
Neolithic religion and boring lectures I sat through that you don't want to.
It's about finding our way back into reality and reconnecting with it and reconnecting with God
in a real experiential way so that all of this becomes real and true to us.
and true to us.
and not just something we think or believe.
Well, that is our show for tonight.
Thank you for listening, everybody.
If you didn't get a chance to call in during the live broadcast,
we would love to hear from you either via email
at Lordofspiritsatantfaith.com
or you can message us at our Lord of Spirits podcast Facebook page.
We read everything, but cannot respond to everything.
And we do save what you send for possible use in future episodes.
Join us for our live broadcast on the second and fourth Thursdays of the month at 7pm Eastern 4pm Pacific.
Hopefully in the future I will not be picking up Mexican radio on my microphone.
Also, if you're on Facebook like our Facebook page, and join our Facebook discussion group.
And leave reviews and ratings but most importantly, share this show with a friend whom you know is going to love it.
And finally be sure to go to ancientfaith.com, stroke support and
and help make sure we and lots of other AFR
podcasters stay on the air.
Thank you very much and may God bless you always.
["The End of the World"]
You've been listening to The Lord of Spirits
with Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew Stephen
and father Steven DeYoung, a listener supported.
presentation of ancient faith radio.
And I beheld and I heard the voice of many angels
round about the throne and the beasts and the elders.
And the number of them was 10,000 times 10,000
and thousands of thousands,
saying with a loud voice, worthy as the land
that was slain to receive power and riches
and wisdom and strength and honor and glory and blessing.
Revelation chapter five verses 11 through 12.