Glory to Jesus Christ, glory forever, you're listening to ancient faithradio.com.
He will be a staff for the righteous, with which for them to stand and not to fall, and
he will be the light of the nations, and the hope of those whose hearts are troubled.
All who dwell on the earth will fall down and worship him, and they will praise and bless
and celebrate with song the Lord of Spirits.
Christine Ock, chapter 48, verses 4 through 5.
The modern world doesn't acknowledge but is nevertheless haunted by spirits, angels,
demons, and saints.
In our time, many year into break free of the prison of a flat, secular materialism, to see
and to know reality as it truly is.
What is this spiritual reality like?
How do we engage with it well?
How do we permeate everyday life with spiritual presence?
Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew Stephen Damick, and Father Stephen DeYoung.
host this live Colin show focused on enchantment in creation, the union of the scene and unseen as made by God and experienced by mankind throughout history.
Welcome to the Lord of Spirits.
To the Lord of Spirits podcast Christ is risen. He truly is risen on this podcast. We laugh in the face of secular materialism even though it's not very funny.
I'm Father Andrew Stephen Damick in the bright and beautiful Améas Pennsylvania
and my co-host, Father Stephen D. Young, is with me from one of the tastiest places on Earth,
Lafayette, Louisiana, right in the middle of Keijing Country.
And if you are listening to us live, you can call in at 855 AF Radio, that's 855-237-2346
and Matras Katruti will be taking your calls tonight.
And this episode is all the questions all the time.
This is our first ever dedicated Q&A episode, so we want your cues.
We can call right now.
Now, while we wait for that call board to fill up.
Before that before that.
Oh, yeah, go ahead, fathers even.
Yeah.
Let me say I'm somewhat disappointed
that you didn't do a monologue.
Oh, I'm sorry.
I can start to question the OED.
It finds a question.
No, I never, I never start anything with the OED.
Yeah, I don't start that way.
I don't, but you didn't write anything.
So now you get this pedantry from me.
That's good.
Now go for it.
Yeah.
No.
You could have done the kill.
Sunstrider monologue, you know, the power by people crave it, right?
There's all kinds of ways you could have gone, but it's just like, hey,
questions. I could have read something in, I could have read
Cadmins him, which I'm starting to memorize from my old English class, which I'm taking with
Father Anthony Cook. Hey, Father Anthony. Watch this transition. You're really
phone in it into night and you should phone in your questions.
So you can talk to a couple of phonies.
All right, all that being said, while we wait for the call board to fill up, number one,
do you have a copy of Father Stevens book yet if you don't go to store it on ancient
faith.com and get one.
But while we wait for the call board to fill up, I wanted to read an email question that
we got from our listener, Celia.
And I want to put this one in because it's probably the only one that I have a really
good chance at being the authority on.
So this is what Celia had to say.
How do you talk to your kids?
I am Cradle Orthodox and have learned more by listening to your podcast than I did at
all my Sunday school years.
I am starting to undo the materialistic view of the world and slowly trying to see the
spiritual world.
It's easier for me since I am Cradle Orthodox to understand that it is there, but my
American upbringing and education did some serious damage for the past 40 years.
In any case, I'm afraid that I have already started the corrupting of my 12, 9 and 6 year
old with mature
I'm just wondering how you talk with your kids daily in order to overcome this.
Of course, we talk about our guardian angels and pray to family since
since daily, but I'm wondering if I can do more.
So before I go off into my lengthy rant or, you know, discursus about this
father, it's anything you wanted to say first.
I, you know, as far as you know, I don't talk to your kids.
Right.
That's probably not what you mean.
You could talk to me.
my children, it's probably best we keep it that way. So we'll just we'll just let you go ahead and take it.
Okay. So right, um, this is a question that we actually get in our Facebook group every so often.
And um, um, it's interesting to me because I think that a lot of people feel like, um, that the
The Lord of Spirits is advanced theology or advanced biblical...
exegesis or something like that. And that is one of the things that we are
precisely saying is actually not true. That we're not talking about weird esoterics.
We're talking about stuff that's simply mainly right there in the Bible and
that the people who received those texts initially would have understood to be
part of their their normal context and would have certainly talked to their kids
about and and participated in these rituals with their kids, right?
So, you know, so I just want to set aside that idea that this is sort of like advanced knowledge
that's only for really, really, you know, super academic people or whatever, because it's just not true.
If it were true, then the church would not have embedded it so deeply in all the church services
for one thing, which are meant to be attended by everybody, right? So, all that being said,
the question of course is how do you talk to your kids at home? And I have experienced
that
But children often are actually much more prepared to understand the spiritual life in the kinds
of mythic terms that we talk about it on this show than adults often are.
Actually, as adults we spend years trying to convince ourselves that these are just metaphors
That's really good.
can't possibly be true or, you know, I don't know what to do about that or, you know, that
kind of thing.
Yet, like we often say on this show, you know, it's not just a metaphor, right?
So all that said, I just wanted to point out that kids have a better time, connected
with this stuff. And I do talk with my kids and the way that I talk about it is in
his clear kind of mythic terms, right? Okay, so, you know, is there such a thing as a dragon?
Yes, there are dragons. Do they look exactly like you see in picture books for kids? Probably
not. I mean, we don't know. No one's taken any photos of them. Are there demonic presences
that ancient peoples experienced as being like dragons.
Yes, absolutely.
There are those experiences.
For instance, in our last episode,
we talked about Christ's invasion of Hades.
When I tell my kids, okay, there's this depiction
of something called a hell mouth that swallows the dead
and Christ comes and he pulls people up out of that.
They immediately can connect with that,
especially if you show them a picture,
and you know what, there's a lot of pictures of these things.
If you show them a picture,
they can connect with that very immediately
and have an honest
of it. And you know, yes, I may say to them, especially the older ones, like, look, this
picture is the best, it's the best that people can do in terms of trying to explain what's
happening. But we don't know exactly what this experience was like. But this is, these
are the testimonies that we have, right? So we could either discount those testimonies
because it's hard for us to believe that stuff. Or we could simply say, well, man, people
keep having this experience and they keep describing it in basically these terms, right?
So, yeah, I mean my kids, my eldest is 14 and
We have three more we have an 11 year old and a nine year old and a four year old and
They this is the way they experience the spiritual life, you know
When I described to them about when we go outside for Posca and bang on the doors
This is what this means. This is what's happening. This is what we're connecting with they're like yeah, I'm participating in that
that. You know, so, so really, I mean, that's.
That's one of the things that I would say, but also like I would say, don't neglect to bring
your children to church and to have them participate in as much as possible. I mean, I know that some
people have a barrier to connecting with church life and it can be hard, but I would say bring them
as much as you possibly can to everything. That's what I do with my kids. They don't come to every
single service they can.
right. You know, if one thing their mother is tired, but I try to bring them to as much
as possible, especially during Holy Week and all that kind of thing and certainly to surround
them in the home with with icons to pray together as a family. All these things, you know,
to the biggest thing really is to incorporate it into your own way of being and they're
going to see that. They're going to see that. So, Celia, I hope that you're listening
and I hope that that helps.
God bless your kids, pray for them that they would be able to see and to experience all
the glory of God because they're just as capable of it and more than capable in many cases
of it as you are probably.
So it's a good question and definitely one that's good to my mind.
Part and parcel of all these things, like when you read the Torah, this becomes really clear.
There's a concern all through the Torah.
It's not just...
Well, here are some intellectual truths we want to communicate to adults.
Here are some things we want to tell you, how to do and how to live your life.
Over and over it says, when you teach your children, right, in future generations,
the most obvious example being Passover.
When your son asks you, how is this night different than all of the nights?
You say, this is the night on which, Lord delivers us.
Tell the stories from the stories right so
part of the adult reception and experience of these events built into the
ritual of experiencing and representing these things is the
tradition of them is the handing of them on to the next generation exactly you
can't you can't you're not completing the ritual if you aren't passing it on
Yeah, to the next generation in the process, right?
Exactly. All right. Well, I see that we have a full board of calls. This is good.
God willing, it's going to be wall to wall calls. So our first caller is James. James, are you there?
I am here, Father.
Christ is risen. He has risen indeed. Excellent. Well, welcome, James. We're glad to have you.
What is your question, comment, weird poltergeist experience that you want to share with us tonight on Lord of
spirits.
I'm not sure if he's
right. And I first have to say I
did that. If we have I should
have said truly he is risen as
he truly is risen. Don't get
father Andrew. Don't get me
started. Yeah, that's true. I
have a whole canned rant. I'm
just ready to pull out. He
truly is risen. I would love
to hear that I was. Alright,
questions for you guys.
But I narrowed it down to one set of questions
revolving around ritual and spiritual identity
of nationhood.
Because I've heard, I've been reading through the book
by Father Steven, and I've read through all the Father Steven
blog posts.
That was a fun project.
And I've worked into a lot of stuff.
And so I clear that there isn't just a permanent number
of 70 nations, or 70 plus one, 50, et cetera,
that.
metaphorical in revelations and all that kind of stuff.
And that number changes.
And we also see the nidsrael, right,
when it splits into two.
And God judged those nations separately in effect,
because you didn't have all of them going
going to exile at the same time.
You're judging them separately in effect.
So there's that.
And then I was also remembered from Father Andrew,
you talking about the docks of moot about how
storytelling and language create nations in this set about,
so they don't have to call it all out within one.
And I can't get that back to how
Luther and his translation of the German Bible effectively
created Germany out of a mess of tribes
creating a one national identity out of them,
the language, and then also of course,
I've divided the by-nate my languages
in the Tower of Bible, so there's a connection there.
So I'll try to figure out what specifically though,
which we identify as the nation.
that those, this year was called out of Egypt as you discussed and created it and that included,
you know, genetically included Egyptians and Abraham Lincoln and so on.
And it was very clear that it made a very clear that it's not genetic, it's not ethnic.
It's a ritual, the signing of a nation. But how does that work?
What specifically can you just like go create a new nation ritual? Like you created a new family
Virtually or new church, Virtually he's going to create a new nation.
in that same front. And then I have some follow-up questions from
that. I'll leave you with a third of that.
To find the universe give three examples. Sorry. Yeah, okay. So I'll just address the
thing that I said I'm glad to hear that you went to Doxamute. I'll just the
thing that I said there. So I was echoing something that JR Tolkien said, which
which is that he regards peoples as basically being defined mainly by their
language. Right. And for him, that doesn't just mean the words that they say. That also
means the stories that they tell in those words.
Exactly. Right. Exactly. Because he's a philologist. So, and you know, that I'm not a philologist.
I'm sort of like a wannabe philologist. But I just like being near those people. But I think
think that there's something true about that and even while languages
is not itself, sort of by itself, ritual.
There's something ritualistic to it.
And especially when you're telling stories to each other,
that increases that character, I would say.
So what you were saying about the Sacramento
imagination is like that, that tradition of
an imaginative set of stories.
Right, right, exactly, exactly, exactly.
And then the other thing that I would add,
because I wanna leave, I know that Father Stephen
things to say about nations here.
But the other thing that I would add is
that one of the things that struck me liturgically
over the last almost 25 years of being an Orthodox Christian
is how often the phrase the race of Christians
and then also the phrase a new nation
which is called by thy name,
how often that gets used are liturgical services, right?
So there's in a sense, then,
and this is not to denigrate any cultures or whatever
that exist, I have love for lots of
of cultures. I'm getting to know cultures that I'm
and descended from, but it didn't receive anything from.
You know, but that the nation now is the Christian race.
That's the nation that every single person is called into.
And clearly it's ritual participation that makes that what it is.
Doesn't matter what color you are, what language you speak,
what your accent is like, what your background is like.
Everyone is called into this.
everyone can be part of it.
And thus, that's why it's a new exodus, right?
It's a new Passover.
It's the ultimate Passover in the sense of being final,
not just in the sense of being the very best,
but final, like the ultimate.
That's always the thing.
There's that game called Final Fantasy,
but there was 16 of them.
How does that work?
But anyway, we stopped the throttles,
some popcorn
Yeah, I mean, I think the term people as an A people people being used as a collective
now sort of functions a little better in conveying the idea.
You know, we've talked on the, on this show before about how there's four main ways that we
Interface and interact with and shape our world as humans and those are language
music art and
ritual and
So I think you find those four things
constituting any given
people, right
Um, um,
And in most cases, that occurs sort of naturally.
It's a shared thing within a people who are living in community.
And so that then develops into a people.
But and this usually ends up being very dark.
There have been especially in the postmodern era.
I don't wanna go all geek aboard on everybody.
But you know, you can try to do that from the top down.
Right, you can create this sort of
Rather than it being people interfacing with the world in reality as it is
You can from the outside pipe into people
Here is the world sort of as a spectacle, right?
So this this mix of
Propaganda and advertising and all of these other things to create this
sort of collective hallucination.
that you then impose upon people that uses art and music and twists and shapes the language
and even rituals.
And you've seen totalitarian governments do this.
So that can happen.
can decide I'm going to create or reshape this people.
through these kind of means.
And when that's happening, and this is sort of what, you know, even though there weren't
sort of the totalitarian states that we think of today, when you hear in the New Testament,
the New Testament authors talking about the world, right, in that negative sense, right,
of the world, the flesh, and the devil, right?
they talk about the world.
world, that is in part what that is. Right? The world says the world, right? The world
out there, they're not talking about created reality. They're talking about this system
that is trying to be sort of imposed. And so Christian iconography, Christian liturgical
music, Christian use of language, even though there are a lot of different languages used in
the church.
We also have sort of our own language.
There are words we use that don't mean anything to anybody else or that mean something totally
different.
And obviously, most obviously Christian ritual are all a way of fighting back against that
encroachment of that kind of imposition of a people, an identity as a people or an identity
as a community that's trying to be thrust from outside, that's trying to say humanity
is one thing. This is what it means to be here.
and we're saying no this, right?
Yeah, in response.
Yeah.
All right.
I know you said you had like a whole set of questions, James, but you do have to let the other kids have a chance.
Yes.
I have to one follow a question.
Okay.
You get one follow-up.
Because yeah, I was thinking about that in connection with like having the different patients saying of different nations.
I think maybe like provinces under that maybe.
but so in scripture we have the idea of the land.
being defiled by specifically the shedding of an appendix blood but of all the different
horrible sins that are going to be the cause of the 18-year-old. Talking about the
land spewed out of the nature that report you, don't do these things or you also get spewed out.
And so you have this idea of the guilt, the sin, contaminating the land and that's tied to
a national guilt in this set.
No, I was worrying like, is it possible?
Because I'm...
because they can't come to the buy the blood of those who shed it.
And let me ask the specific list that's in there.
And what do we possibly say?
Well, we're this community inside of this nation,
and it's the land of the file.
We don't agree with this, but they're not listening to us.
Can we just like go say, all right, we're going to go
be our own nation over here,
because we don't agree with all the horrible stuff they're doing.
Like, you know, I can try basically,
the hazard on identity saying,
we don't want to be part of this. We want to
to be a Christian province effectively.
And not to that, can you escape?
We, because now the land that is owned by those people
is now no longer being the land of that other nation.
Yeah, I think I get what you're asking.
And so I would say this, I mean, in the first century
and the second century, this was Christianity, right?
Right. There was not...
Christian, it means like if you ever read the epistle to Diagnosis, for instance, one of the things it says is Christians are not
Distinguished from other people by the way that they dressed way they talk what they eat
Whatever they live among everyone else their citizens, but they're also citizens. They are truly citizens of this other world
At the same time so you don't see
Christian separatist movements
In the early church even though they had way more reason to do that
that, then we do in the 21st century.
I mean, think about talk about.
to file the land, like come on, it was a vile, awful, pagan, debauched place. It was the worst,
right? So yeah, I don't know if that response what you were saying, but that's what I would say.
St. Paul was conducting his missionary journeys under Caligula, for example.
Yeah, you know, um, and Nero obviously was a colleague of the one that defied his horse.
I'm trying to remember.
Yeah, well, he made his horse a senator.
There you go.
And yeah, the, but in addition, in addition to succession being the wrong way to go, the
whole time that Israel was going wrong, which was pretty much the whole time, right?
We know from the Old Testament.
There works.
faithful priests who were going every day and serving the sacrifices and offering the
incense for the sins and the ignorance of the people.
They were atoning to purify a space within that contaminated land for God to continue to
dwell.
And we talked about this in one of the very early episodes.
The role which Christians...
have in since that's where I am. We'll say the United States. The role of
Christians with respect to the United States is the same as is directly
parallel to the role that a priest has with respect to his parish.
Yep. Yep. All right. Well, I hope that's useful for you and gives you something to
chew on James. Yeah. Thanks very much for calling. Okay. Well, we're going
and walled walled car
We have a call from Greg. So Greg, are you there?
Yes.
Welcome, Greg, to the Lord of Spirits. Excellent. Good to hear your voice.
Okay. I guess my question is a little odd, but...
You are... You come to the right place.
I've talked to Mormons and they basically tell you that their version of Heaven will be a paradise where you get your body back
body back but it will be when it
was in perfect health and you were young and fit and you will you will get that
course they also promise in multiple wives too. But you were you were your own
planet. I was just saying when you were young in your heart was an open book. Yeah
something like that. Yeah. You're perfectly fit and and I don't know probably
like 21 or something. Oh smart enough that but I guess my I've heard I saw a
a couple of
evangelical books on pets. And
they try to say there's a case
that you'll be reunited with
your pets in heaven if you
really want them because that
would be paradise. I mean,
God give you that. And I guess
um, if you had hobbies with
pets like horseback riding and
things like that, would you
be able to do that and have it?
It's just a spiritual realm.
All right. Well, I'm going to let
you take that one. First
Father Steven
but I mean I have some things to say but let me ponder that first.
Right, so the question is it do all dogs go to heaven it's do some dogs.
Does my dog go to heaven? Yeah. Yeah. Mine are all heathens we've established this.
And you can't baptize them. Yes. Well yeah they run like crazy.
Anytime I bless the house to throw holy water. Right? So he's trying to get away from it.
that kind of proves my whole thesis. So here we go.
Yeah, maybe the most controversial thing I've ever said on this podcast
And that is maybe
Everybody loves your yes or no answers. No, that's why this is the most controversial one because I said maybe
Are you gonna be the one that's so a couple of a couple of things on why I say maybe
Say Gregory Pala Moss
Uh uh
actually has a work on this on the souls of animals.
Because he affirms, it's pretty much everyone
did in the ancient world, that plants and animals,
like humans have souls, is just a different type of soul.
It's not the same type of soul.
And that's because soul basically means life.
That's what the word means.
So when you're reading in Genesis chapter 1
and God creates the fish and the birds, right?
literally says he created all the souls that swim in the sea and fly in the air.
So, so just means it's alive. The Latin word for soul is anima and that's where we get
animate as opposed to inanimate. Right. So, so they do have souls but not not human souls.
And so that's why St. Gregory says, well, you know, animals aren't, you know,
go to heaven or hell or any of that because
it's a different type of soul. It's not a human soul. However, here's the other piece.
The other piece is, and I've used this before to illustrate what fiosus means as a common
illustration. If you take one of my dogs, even one of my even dogs, and you compare it,
you take my dog Shelby name
after a commander shall be.
And you can really hurt her.
Yes.
How about that?
You didn't know that?
And you know, I did this one.
She, and you compare her to a wolf or a dingo or a wild dog in general, right?
You would not think they're the same species.
They don't behave the same way.
They don't act and interact the same way.
Yeah, we had dogs like that on Guam.
Like they were awful. Yeah, yeah, yeah, they're scavengers and yeah, they're gross
so she
Makes facial expressions right not cuz she experiences human emotions
But because she's learned that you know, we think it's cute and we're warped her with treats right and
She has come up with these ingenious solutions to problems like she will literally if someone has food and they're sitting there eating it
Go and run to the front door and start barking like this.
someone there to get you to come look so she can keep around and get it to food. This is what I mean by
heathenism. So what's the difference? Well there's no genetic difference right between
while dogs and domesticated dogs, right? But she's spent her whole life living with humans
and interacting with humans and in a human house.
not with wild dogs.
And so she has in a certain way been humanized, right?
She has become different because of that relationship
with a higher level of being.
And I've used that, as I said before,
as an illustration of part of how theosis works,
that when we are spending our time
with sort of the
wild humans that we start out as and could very easily become but with God in the presence
of God we also become more like a higher state of being.
So that to be opens up the possibility that potentially some of these somewhat humanized
animals.
We know there are going to be animals.
The world to come is this creation transfigured.
That includes plants and animals and all the things that God creates.
So that to be opens up the possibility. I'm not going to say yes, right? I'm not saying this is a fact.
Say this is a possibility. It's like what St. Paul says, you know, I have not heard from the Lord on this. This is but there you go. This is my speculation.
That there is a possibility that perhaps some of these animals who have become somewhat humanized
might still be around in the age to come.
So the thing that I would add to that is I've heard
people say things about paradise that are like this,
except maybe like in other categories.
Like, well, it wouldn't be paradise
unless they have lasagna there.
Something like that.
Bacon.
Bacon, yeah, right.
Bacon, lasagna.
So.
But I think that the key thing that people have to understand
that the life of the age to come if you're with cry
and it's paradise and you're the kingdom of God,
it is not going to be disappointing in any way.
Like there's nothing about it that you're gonna be like,
oh man, this is paradise.
They don't have, you know, Milky Way bars,
you know, whatever, it's not gonna be like that.
So, whatever it is that you love about this world that,
you know, and by that, I'm not talking about addictions
or whatever, you know, I mentioned food,
but you know the things
that are genuine joy, right?
Whatever it is that you love about this world,
that same, the joy is gonna be there,
but multiplied times an infinity.
You know, it's not gonna be a bummer.
No matter what you encounter,
whether or not your dog is there with you.
And I think, I mean, I like the point
that you made Father because about it being
a potential being within relationship,
because we tend to...
at least within the West we tend to think in terms of categories. Like again, all dogs
go to heaven, right? Well, I mean, having encountered some feral dogs in my time, I would
prefer that they not be present there, you know? So, but if it is possible than out of
relationship with human beings who are in relationship with Christ makes the most sense to me.
But at the same time, it would be hard, especially like to say to a kid who has just lost their
favorite pet.
you know, well your dog doesn't have a soul so that you know doesn't have the time that
kind of soul you have and Jesus didn't die to save your dog you know I like right so
the way I often approach that is I'll just say look I mean whatever it's like paradise is
going to be awesome whatever it's like you know because I think that because that is true everything
that we know about it is true so I don't know if that answers your question Greg and there's this
This is part of a...
Be glad!
I thought about, I know some of this stuff because I live for a short period of time I live in
Davidson, Wyoming right on the Utah border.
So I got to know a lot of Mormons.
Yeah.
They believe that you get married for eternity.
And then I saw in the Bible where it says somebody asked Jesus if a woman was married and two of her
her husband's thigh. She gets married to a third guy and he dies and they both die or whatever,
then whose wife will she be in?
have been Christ said, well, there won't be any marriage in heaven.
Yeah, he says, you air knowing neither the Scriptures nor the power of God and, you know,
that God is the God of the living and not of the dead because they were trying to
just prove the resurrection is what that conversation was particularly about.
But yeah, I mean, I think that, you know, the point being that a kind of, like,
paradise is not simply a really great version of this.
you know, we don't know exactly all the ways it's going to be different, but it's going
to be different for sure. It's not going to be simply like a permanent resort, you know,
that's for sure, which to me is...
Yeah, right. Well, yes. Yeah, I will not do my Ricardo Montabon impression. I promise
I will not. But if you do, if you do, I'll yell con, really. Right. See, that would be
required.
But, yeah, so like, I mean, I'm not an expert in the LDS approach to paradise, but my sense
is that it is much more materialist.
And by that, I don't mean that they don't believe in spiritual reality, but that there's
as a much fleshier kind of paradise is kind of my understanding of it.
I don't know.
Father Stevens, anything you want to...
Yeah, they promise you your own planet, you know, build and have multiple lives.
So, believe it or not.
They never have to change the docs.
It just don't talk about it when they come to your door with the white shirts and ties.
Right, right.
Yeah, I've never gotten one of them to sing for me if you could hide to Colab, even though that's really a lovely, a lovely hymn.
Father Steven, what do you want to say on that?
Well, I was just going to say, yeah, and beyond just this particular thing with pets or spouses.
But it is true that the creator or the material order is not sort of abandoned.
Right, we don't want to go in.
other direction of having a bodyless or a a a a a antherial kind of
eternity that gets rid of the created order, right, but it's that the created
order, it finds its fullness and is transfigured through humanity, right,
through humanity. That's part of humanity's role. But it's through the
relationship of humanity
the created order and then humanity to Christ, right? So humanity is again, same as we
said with the last question, has this priestly role? It's kind of taking the material order
and through humanity bringing it into union with Christ so that the whole creation is transfigured.
So it's not done away with and on the marriage thing in particular.
Right. So Christ is countering the idea that there's sort of sexuality in heaven, right?
Because the question is whose wife is she? Right? Meaning who has her is literally the language, right?
And Christ is saying, well, you're not gonna be having each other.
Right? It's just like that's not how this works.
That's not how any of this works.
That doesn't mean that like you and your spouse are just gonna be strangers. Right or something or that
that best.
The...
the intimacy and the relationship that you built on this earth is just going to vanish.
And you're just going to be like, hey, two people who are good pals, but you're going
to be pals with everybody because it's heaven, right?
So we all love each other, right?
That's not what it's saying.
But it's saying that that relationship, too, is going to be transfigured and exalted and
lifted up and is going to lose all of those elements of possession, jealousy, any other things
that might take the...
relationship on this area.
Yep.
All right.
Well, hopefully that answers your question, Greg.
OK.
Thank you.
Thanks for calling.
OK.
We're going to take one more call before we go to our first break.
And that call is from our friend, Footenie, up in the frozen
Tundra.
Footenie, welcome to the Lord of Spirits.
I mean, it is me.
Hi, Abuna.
Yes, I am from the Twin Cities of Auckland Warpwork.
And in the second episode, I was known as Ashley.
And for the two slides, the ways of color,
I de-called me out on it.
It told me not to make up big names when I called in.
That's true.
Yeah.
Well, now you're now, you've cleaned your slate now
by coming out with your true name.
So that's true.
Oh, that's true.
That's true.
So people found out I was in queue and sent me their questions.
So I'm going to be nice.
I've got two questions that are related
that you can answer together.
Oh, thanks.
Thank you for that permission.
That's good.
I'm just saying they're related.
Wait.
So there's a lot of space and a cult activity.
So one question is, for the mind, their neighbor
is apparently engaging in rituals and sandses
and psychic activity next door.
And this makes them very nervous.
And they don't quite know what to do about it,
and are what they should do about it,
but it makes them uncomfortable.
The second question is kind of related.
And this person says I'm just going to read.
this. My dad confronted me recently about DND. I know by experience that it isn't inherently
demonic, but in his opinion, it is ritual participation in magic, which makes it so. He says,
all same needs as an inch to get in and invade your home. And in his opinion, I might as well have
a Ouija board in the house. Wow. So these people were hoping for some insights from our from our
Are giggling fathers?
Well, it's giggling is only laughing that you don't want.
All right.
That's what I, that's, that is the truth.
So all of you, all of you hate listeners out there right now,
who are complaining about quote unquote giggling,
it's just laughing you don't want.
Yeah, don't let's go.
Exactly, exactly.
So see, that was a, they might be Giants reference I caught.
Yeah, well, that's because it's from flood, isn't it?
I think that's the only way I actually know.
Yeah, that's the only one I know.
It's true.
Right, okay, so the next door neighbor that's doing
doing bad stuff over on the other side of the fence and D&D as the devil's funnel into
your life.
Right.
I mean, my temptation obviously with the neighbor would be like to go all Jericho on
him.
Now you just march around your own house, okay, blowing the trumpets and, you know, but
no, no.
I mean, so obviously that's a real problem.
And I would simply say that the key then is...
to just really to increase your prayer life in your own home and pray specifically for those
people because they're not the enemy. It's the garbage they're conforming with that's the enemy.
Right? They're not the enemy. They've been fooled. They've been enslaved. They're not the enemy.
You know, so, you know, increased prayer life at home, find ways to be kind to them,
especially without them knowing it. You know, love them anonymously and somewhere another. And I
And I don't just mean like feel them.
happy feeling in your heart about them, but like do kind things for them.
You know, that's what spiritual warfare consists of.
I mean, the devil can't deal with humility and love.
It's self-sacrifice.
Because that's not what he's, that's not his deal.
So that's what I would say to that one.
And with regards to role playing games, you know,
There are there are bad ways
to do role-playing games. That's for sure. But if you're talking about what
essentially amounts to cooperative storytelling, which is what a role-playing
game is at its basis, where one person is kind of managing the story and other
people are participating in in terms of playing roles and that sort of thing,
then that makes the theater just as demonic. Now some people might argue that it
was. But I think anyone who would say that role playing games are in
demonic. Most of them are doing things like watching television and they might go to plays.
You know, other kinds of cooperative storytelling that they themselves are just, you know,
watching rather than participating in. And there's nothing inherently evil about that. That's not,
that does not constitute ritual participation in a demonic world. Definitely does not. So that's
what I would say to those two things. So, Father Stephen, I know you have opinions.
in general. But also yeah right yeah on this particular yeah
also on this. Yeah. So, yeah, we would father Andrew said about the first case is is is basically right.
Yeah, one. You don't have to get them actually done.
But yeah, because what they may find is that if they do those things in terms of intensifying their
own prayer life and prayer life as a family and those kind of things is that the stuff they're trying
you do next door will stop working.
Yeah.
Um, that we have actually it's interesting.
We have some writings from the third century where uh,
pagans at the time were trying to figure out like why the oracles had stopped working in some of the smaller towns.
It's as Christianity was spreading stuff just stopped working the way it used to.
Uh, and they come up with all these bizarre theories like one of them was that well maybe
Day mode just get old and die
We need to find a new one, right?
Maybe they're on vacation.
Like they were?
Yeah.
They've heard the bathroom.
They've heard this one before.
I know this one.
They've logged in with us, but maybe not forever.
Who knows?
Yeah.
And so there are reports up to this very day
of that kind of thing happening, right?
We'll just stop working.
I've also had a case where I advise someone to pray for the people
and
to do those things and they literally moved,
they just up and moved to like something happened
that where they just decided we can't live here anymore
and moved.
So you know, we, the important thing is that you don't
fall into a mode of,
we need to be afraid of what's going on over there
finds a way to protect ourselves.
Yeah.
Right? We're not as Christians on the defensive spiritually. We're on the offensive. We're on the winning team.
Right? D-Day's already happened. We're in mop-up time. Right? So they don't have anything to fear from their neighbor.
Their neighbor actually has something to fear from from them.
All of this that they're doing is going to is going to stop working and they're going to have to confront some things.
And that then relates to the D and D thing, right?
in this case, I do have to, I'm actually father Andrew a little bit that
that
Peter was a bad example to break up because Greek tragedy was very much derived
Yes, Greek tragedy but I'm talking about like modern
Yeah, I'm talking about you know going to Phantom of the Opera on Broadway
Okay, well how how many steps are there between Greek tragedy and Shakespearean tragedy?
It's true.
But so just.
not the best example. But, yeah, so yes, obviously, if you're playing a role-playing game and you're
playing characters who are evil and you're doing human sacrifices and other horrible things
that you're fantasizing about doing, that's bad, right? But a bunch of nerds like me when
I was a teenager getting together and drinking Mountain Dew and doing math is not evil or sinister.
the area.
way right I don't know enough mountain do though we get a little wired we'd get a
little beat up but it was okay we get to sleep eventually so so the bigger issue
is that again that's falling into this defensive thing right this is like well
the devil's gonna find some way into our house and it's gonna be like a hairy
Potter book or you know watching the Witcher on Netflix or something.
That's not how the devil gets into your house.
It's not that difficult.
He doesn't have to trick you into buying the wrong novel.
Right?
He gets in there because you're proud and you're angry
and you're envious and you're lazy
and through the pipeline of lust that you have coming in through the internet to your PC.
Right?
That's how he gets into your house.
Yeah, right?
But we don't want to deal with those that dealing with those things is very hard and again forces us to confront things that we don't want to confront
It's much easier to sort of go for these sort of obvious cultural things like oh that has magic or a wizard in it
So it's evil so I get that out of my house and now we have a nice pure house
Right and and you're white washing the tomb right you're washing the outside of the bowl
to use Christ's terminology.
right to the Pharisees. And the problem isn't that you're cleaning the outside.
The problem is you're not doing anything about the inside. Right. So we shouldn't
be sitting around being afraid that we might watch or read or bring into our house
the wrong object. We should be actively again proactively on the offense
inspecting our own life for the places where the devil's already there and
already has a hold.
of us and through repentance, getting rid of them because the saints could get together
and play a game of D&D and it wouldn't be a problem.
That's better things to do, but hypothetically.
Right.
All right.
Does that answer your question for Timmy?
That absolutely does.
Thank you so much, Father.
As you know, time after time I find myself referencing things that I have heard on the podcast.
Sometimes I wish I could turn back time to some orthodoxy my youth, but I think your time
about my side I've had the time of my life for kids.
the Facebook group. I prayed to a
goodness state wherever young
because I was totally listening
when I was 64. Father's
blast. Have a good evening.
Thank you very much. All right.
We're gonna go down. Go ahead.
Go ahead, Father. She said she was
64, but I think she was really 28.
I see your references and
with I counter and with that we are
going to go to our first break.
Father Andrew Stephen Daymak and
Father Stephen DeYoung will be back
in a moment to take your calls on
next part.
of the Lord of Spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF Radio.
St. Ignatius, 1st century bishop of Antioch, called the God-bearer, is one of the earliest
witnesses to the truth of Christ and the nature of the Christian life.
tradition tells us that as a small child, it
Ignatius was singled out by Jesus himself as an example of the childlike faith all Christians
must possess.
In Beringod, Father Andrew Damick recounts the life of this great pastor, martyr, and
saint, and interprets for the modern reader five major themes in the pastoral letters he
wrote.
martyrdom, salvation and Christ, the bishop, the unity of the church, and the eucharist.
Ignatius martyrdom is really the fullness of Christ the Almighty.
sense, which that can be challenging for us because number one, he doesn't seem to have any
reticence at all about going to martyrdom. Like, there's no sense of, well, this is what I have to do.
You know, I wish I didn't have to, but this was God's will for me. He is going to it joyfully,
gladly. To find this book and others like it, you can go to store.AncientFaith.com. Again,
that is store.enginefaith.com.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits, the Father and
Steven Daymak and Father Steven DeYoung. If you have a question call now at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF Radio.
Welcome back everybody. That was probably my favorite commercial we've ever done.
What's a really good one? It was a good commercial but they seal that quote from you in a copy
What was up with the audio?
I don't know.
I think I feel like I didn't even know...
they were gonna play that commercial.
So thank you for that little surprise, Judy.
But, no, I think that that was from when I did
a little interview after that book came out.
And I think that that was before,
like I think I did it over the phone or something like that.
So you were talking to a can on the end of a string.
And they were reporting it at the end.
Right, long before I had been,
I'm perched in the great tower of podcasting
where I currently am.
So yeah, okay, so this is our Q&A show.
We're taking all calls all the time.
We want to hear from you.
If you call and you're not able to get through,
just call back.
The lines are full.
This is really awesome.
So, okay, so our next caller is David.
David, are you there?
Yes, I am here.
Welcome, David to the Lord of Spirits.
Thank you very much, fathers.
My question is about the book of Enoch
and whether we should be cautious
about incorporating doctrine derived.
a book that's not accepted by the Calesonian Church and sort of I mean if if the doctrines that
we are talking about in the Lord of Spirits are not necessarily derived in the book of Enoch but
also just also happened to be present in that book as well. What should we be cautious about in
reading the book of Enoch so that we don't...
incorporate anything that isn't scriptural into our lives. My second question is from my five
year old and he wants to know why do the demons try to drag the people off of the ladder of divine
ascent? So I think we should answer that one first. Yeah, yeah, because they hate us,
That's what it is. They misery loves company. They're in rebellion again.
God, they're trying to snatch us away from God. That's why they're doing that.
But they're not powerful enough to do anything to God.
Yeah, yeah, but they could attack us.
Right God loves us. Right, right. So as the first one, you might think this is
something that I have nothing to say about and should all be
plunged to the Father's even. But before he goes into a 20 minute, you know,
thesis about this, I wanted to say that. So the things that we talk about on this
the show and then
And frankly, the things that are embedded in canonical scripture and in liturgical tradition
are not derived from the book of Ynach in the sense that no one knew about this.
And here's this book and they discover it in the same...
Hey, is that the five-year-old?
And...
Read-er-old, actually?
Oh, high three-year-old.
These are sounds at my house too.
So it's not that you know
They're uncovered from this book and we're like, okay, now let's put this in our church services
Right, that's not what's going on. It's not the way that this works
Rather what we're looking at is
multiple witnesses to the same
tradition
That is the faith of the people of God
right, so of course it's going to appear in lots of different places and
You know and that's because the Orthodox church does not look at any text the way that for instance
you know
So, the Scripture of Protestantism treats the Bible, which is largely that it's a book and you derive things from it and that's your religion.
That Christianity is derived from interpreting that book and using that book well.
I know I'm simplifying a little bit, but that's generally the way it's seen.
So it's not like we're pulling stuff out of there in order to try to incorporate it into our faith.
Our faith is what it is and that book witnesses to some elements of it.
So then as to the second part like
what
But in reading that book, should we say, okay, we're going to just leave that to the side.
I will definitely punt that one over to Father Stephen.
Right, well, yeah.
So there's, I mean, agreed with what Father Edgerton said, yeah, we don't derive doctrines
from Scripture and then construct Christian theology in that way.
That is the conservative, Protestant approach to doctrine.
But that's not how we approach it.
as there's there
Christ when he talks about the truth going forward in St. John's Gospel, he talks about
there being two witnesses, right?
He established any truth through two witnesses in the Torah.
He says the two witnesses are the apostles and the Holy Spirit.
And so we have in the first and second centuries, it's very common for the fathers to refer
to the New Testament as the memoirs of the apostles, right?
This is the account.
of their experience. So we've got in the New Testament Scriptures, we've got the one witness,
and we could say in the Scriptures as a whole, we have the one witness. And then the other witness is
the Holy Spirit who was alive and active in the church. So we have the record, the inspired record,
inspired by the Holy Spirit of the experiences of people in ages past. And then we have the Holy
spirit who causes the saints in every generation to share in that experience.
as our two witnesses. So what we're trying to do on the show when we talk about things in First
Enic or Jubilee's or the testament of the 12 patriarchs. Who are any of these texts, which the
church has preserved in her monastic settlements in most cases, is not to say these should really be
scripture. What is canonical and what isn't? Is an objective thing?
you literally can't argue about it because to be canonical means that a
text is read and has authority in your community. So a text either does or it
doesn't. Right? So my parish we don't read first in the liturgical services. It
does not have that authority. So me arguing that it should is kind of
nonsensical. It's not. It's an objective thing. It's objectively not part of the
Canon. That said though.
When we're reading, say, second Peter or Jude, and Jude quotes Enoch.
And we say, well, wait, where did the Enoch say that?
I don't see that in the Old Testament.
Or when in second Peter it refers to the angels who sinned.
When these things are referenced, when the Lake of Fire comes up in St. Matthew's Gospel
and in the book of Revelation.
And we haven't heard that.
terminology before and we're trying to understand what is meant by that in the New Testament.
Well, then it helps a lot to know about the religious and spiritual life of the people who
wrote the New Testament.
And part of that life was reading a whole lot of texts that aren't part of the Bible.
Just like for us, in our spiritual life, we read a whole lot of books other than the Bible.
I mean, I think most of us should read the Bible more than we do, but we
also read the fathers and we read other spiritual books and we read other
spiritual things by doing that and even by quoting them sometimes we're not
saying they're part of scripture or they're the same thing as scripture but
they're valuable and very often they're the context we use to help us
understand the scriptures right so but those things are not claimed by others as
as scripture. So why that all makes sense to me.
what the difference with the book of Enoch and other apocryphal or pseudocrygrapher.
Those are not claimed by other groups to be scripture like these are.
And so to me, it's most likely, it makes sense to me that there would be something in them
that we should caution ourselves in reading them because they were sort of actively chosen not to be scripture.
I disagree that they were actively
chosen not to be scripture. There was never a vote taken. That's a myth.
Yeah. Yeah. The reason why the Ethiopian church considers Firsteanate canonical is that Ethiopian Jews
considered Firsteanate to be canonical. And so when the Christian church began in Ethiopia, they took the canon of the Ethiopian Jews as their old testament. They just received it.
They didn't argue about it, they didn't discuss it, they just received that.
Right? That was different than the Palestinian Jewish canon and the
Alexandrian Greek Jewish canon. And so in the Orthodoxy we have different. So for
example I can't go to one of my Russian Orthodox brothers and say, hey look
the the Greek-speaking church rejected fourth Maccabees actively as part of
the Old Testament. Why do you have it in there?
for for Ezra, right?
Like I can't do it because that's not what happened
historically, right?
It's functioning differently in different churches.
But so basically what I'm arguing for is in terms of the caution, right?
Yeah, just like when I read a spiritual book,
or even when I read one of the fathers,
I don't assume that every single word is absolutely true, right?
The fathers disagree sometimes.
I can't say that both of them are 100% literally accurate.
They disagree, right?
So I like try to understand why they disagree and that kind of thing, but I don't elevate
them to the level of scripture where I think every word that St. John Chrysostom ever spoke
is inspired by God, the way that St. Paul's epistles are inspired.
The church has never sent that.
And so the same thing with like Firsteanek.
I mean at least the parts that get quoted in reference to the New Testament are true, right?
the rest of it there's probably some things that are true and some things that aren't, right?
Just like any other book that isn't part of scripture, right? And so you have to read it in that
same sense. You take what's helpful and useful and you discard the rest, right? Yeah, and in the east,
it's also important to add that in the east, traditionally, when you look at the eastern fathers,
if you look at the canon discussions in the east, and this is a difference with the west,
In the West, Canon was seen very much as a binary thing.
One or zero, right?
It's either...
canonical and it's true and good or it's not canonical and said it aside right get rid
of it. In the east there were always three categories. There were books to be read in the
churches which is what we call canonical right they used in the liturgical worship. Books
to be read in the home right and and books not to be read so your heretical stuff is the
books not to be read, the Gospel of Thomas, right? But I would compare these old
Testament book.
that are in some canons and not others, right?
Or that were preserved in a monastery.
Like Mount Athos, they copied and recopied for centuries
the testament of the 12 patriarchs.
They never read it in the liturgical services,
but they kept it and they copied it, right?
I would put a book like that in the same place
that I put like the epistle of Barnabas
or the shepherd of Hermas or first clement,
the Apostolic Fathers, right?
Not part of the New Testament.
We're clear, that's not part of the New Testament, right?
You can find P.
of the early church who thought they were part of the New Testament, who argued for them
being part of the New Testament. We're clear they're not, but we still read them.
And they're still helpful to us and useful to us. We just, we don't treat them like they're
the Bible. They're in that second category. And so the disagreements between the Greek church and the
Slavic church and the Ethiopian church and the Comptive Church over the Old Testament
is really a disagreement about whether certain books are in the canonical.
category to be read in the church, or if they're in the category, these are books that
shouldn't be read in the church, but are fine to read in the home.
That's our disagreement.
Not whether they're canonical or heretical.
Right.
Yeah.
Does that make sense?
That does.
Yeah, that that that really helps a lot.
Thank you very much.
Excellent.
Well, thank you very much for calling.
Before we take our next caller, I got a message over Facebook messenger with a question that
actually thought was a really good question.
And I just thought I would bring it out.
We've kind of addressed this a little bit in the past.
You realize now everyone is going to Facebook messages.
Yeah, right. Don't just open the can of work.
I know, man, this is the last one. Okay. No.
So, all right. So this is from John. And John says this,
this program has opened my eyes and my heart to the powerful reality,
not only of the spiritual realm, which always knew in some way was there
all long, but also to the importance and truth of the Old Testament.
I'm loving the ability to read the story.
the Old Testament and understand that they are not just important stories but that they tell a true
story that is the foundation of our faith. But, and this is a big but. I am struggling with some of
these assertions made about the mindset of the ancient world. When you say that the ancients weren't
referring to the sun, moon, and stars themselves but to the gods which controlled them, this is
difficult to accept considering the fact that to them they were simply bright lights in the sky.
They didn't have telescopes, they couldn't tell, they were huge balls of...
burning gas and nuclear reactions.
My point is that there are at least some things in the old testament and in the ancient
worldview that have been proved utterly wrong by scientific inquiry in the last few centuries.
So the question is, what do we do with that?
And I would, the way that I would begin getting into this question, because I think it's a
good question, is I like to point out to people that ancient people believed both that the
the world.
was flat and that underneath it was water and the underworld and the heavens were above, and
that the world was round at the same time. And they didn't try to make those two images reconcile
with each other. Like there was a sense that they were different ways of looking at it, right?
And I think the problem comes when we attempt to say, okay, so this is the material model that we
all need to be using. And let's try to figure out how to make all these elements come together and
and reckon.
style, you know. So I don't know, that's where I would begin this. So it's a good question
I think. What would you say that father?
Yeah. Well, I mean, I think we have to get it out of our head that ancient people were
unfrozen caveman lawyer, right? You're modern ways, frightened and confused. You know?
That's kind of in there in the question, oh these are just bright lights in the...
guy, we don't have a telescope, what is it? And now we know better. Right. Now we have
a telescope. Right. Now we know better what they are. Yeah. I mean, it's an honest, it's
an honest question. Like I get it. I get it. Right. Right. Yeah. But so this is, this is part
of what we're, we're trying to attack is that the, the, the agents were less sophisticated,
right? than us that they were somehow different than us, right? In that regard, right?
a difference in approach, but like a
difference in cognitive level or something.
And this is what leads to,
not that the person who asked this question
thinks any of this, I'm not imputing this to them,
but this is what leads to stuff like ancient aliens.
Right, like there's no way ancient people
could have built the pyramids.
Right, right.
Right.
You know, there are a bunch of primitive screw heads,
right, they don't know anything, right?
And that's...
simply not true right so they understood for example the sun and moon to be the
bot one of the bodies of gods right so the sun we'll talk about Egyptians
right the sun is one of the bodies of Ray okay we may have a more developed
view of what that body
of Ray is made out of, right? But that has nothing to do with their belief. Yeah. A modern
pagan could say, yes, the sun is a massive incandescent cast or a miasma of incandescent plasma
they're using the new version. Right? Right? It's the body of the God that I worship.
Yeah, right? Just like they believed that a court statue was one of the bodies of the God they worshiped.
They crafted this statue and then they did the ritual of the opening of the mouth and they said,
this is now one of the bodies, one of the localizations, one of the places to interact with our God, right?
Right? We can come in now with our more sophisticated
with an electron microscope, we can tell you all about the quartz, we can tell you all about the molecular structure.
They didn't know about any of that, right?
Yeah. But that has nothing to, they could know all that and still believe the same thing.
Yeah, and, well, and think about it, like, don't we already accept that with regards to the human body?
Like, we know way more about sort of how the human body works, and yet we still believe it's our bodies.
We still believe that it belongs to this person, right?
say, well, we know so much about it now that there's no way that there could be a soul in there,
that there's no, you know, like, like, yeah, so I, yeah, yeah. Yeah. And so that's, that I think is
the key, right? Right. Is that the myths, the stories, the religion is not a primitive form of science
that science has replaced. Right. Right. Right. It is not trying to do the same thing. It is doing a
different thing that science doesn't do.
Exactly.
Exactly. So yeah, it's a good question. I'm glad we had an opportunity to bring that up. Okay. So we're going to take a call now from Brett. So Brett, are you there?
Yes. Thank you, fathers for taking my call. I've got the question. It's actually back from the Christmas episode.
So, had some time to mull it over.
And I guess I'm just kind of after that episode.
I'm curious.
You know, obviously you talked about, you know, some of the different constellations,
all of that kind of stuff.
I guess I just kind of left with what do we do with astrology nowadays?
Is there really anything that could be looked at still?
like oh you know this thing points to Christ or
I don't know the time I'm really making sense in now that I'm asking it.
But I guess just like, you know, what about modern astrology if there is anything that
could be good or beneficial that we could glean from?
Does that make sense?
Yeah, that makes sense.
That makes sense.
I mean, I would say number one, first we have to realize that there's Christian astrology,
And then there's what you refer to as modern astrology, which is this kind of...
new age store, you know, like I don't know, newspaper, whatever, this sort of future-predicting thing,
right? And the biggest difference between those two is that Christian astrology, biblical astrology,
is a way of understanding God's creation and His salvation and His plan for mankind. All is being
one great thing that is evidencing innumerous places and innumerous ways, right? Whereas what,
but people who are trying to...
to read their sign and predict the future and this is what your day is going to be like
and all this kind of thing it's really about it's a kind of divination on some level.
Now most people don't take it very seriously but there certainly are people that do so I
don't know father do you want to add anything to that? Yeah I mean I think the key is that
that we as Christians, especially Orthodox Christians, believe that...
God is constantly, right?
I mean, the Psalm that we spent so much time
within that episode, right?
Day after day, the heavens pour forth speech, right?
God is speaking to us and communicating to us
and communicating his grace to us and acting in our lives
through the whole created order, not just the sky,
but everything.
And there is, I think the important element to take from it
important element to take from it is...
to be attentive to what God is saying to us and how God is communicating to us.
Even if that's just at the level of going out at night in a place where there's not a lot of
ambient light and beholding the beauty of God's creation in the heavens.
The problem as Father Andrew was pointing to is that ancient divination and astrology,
Whether you were looking at the stars or you were looking at the entrails of a gun.
right? That you're using technique, right? You're using a technique, right? You're using
an art, right, to try to divine and foretell the future in order to be able to control it,
right? Or you're looking for omens because you believe that the omens, the stars, control
in a fatalistic way, right? The course of your human life and you're trying to be sort
for warned and for arm.
about it and neither of those is sort of valid. Most of the places where astrology shows
up in the scriptures, it's either to use the stars and the sun and the moon as symbolic
of the reality of angelic beings and therefore of the destiny of humanity.
or it's being used to actively invert pagan
and especially Babylonian astrology,
to say that actually Yahweh, the God of Israel
is the Lord over the stars of the heavens,
not vice versa.
Yeah.
That's right.
Sorry, I don't want to ask a ton of questions or anything.
But you can do a follow-up if you want.
Okay, thank you.
We'll allow.
Steven had to share it.
You mentioned about the, oh I'm forgetting exactly how you worded it now, but basically
just that whole idea that the stars determine your future kind of a deal.
And a brother of mine had mentioned to me while he was actually visiting for Christmas.
And so that Christmas episode was a fresh on my mind about how he started looking into
start charting and all of that kind of stuff.
how it deals with people's personalities.
And so I mean, I guess, you know, I wonder if that is a modern way of trying to be maybe
a little fatalistic about, you know, these consolations were around when you were born.
And so that makes you this kind of person, right?
Yeah, our faults are not in our stars, they're in ourselves.
There we go.
I came up with that.
Did you?
I give up with that all in my own.
All right, well thank you very much for calling. It's great to talk to you tonight. Thank you,
Father. Okay, well next we have John calling. So John, are you there? Am I there? Yes, we hear you.
You made it. All right, so I have a simple question, simple question about Sarah Finn and
CIRPANTS.
Buy it.
I'll be best.
I'm at it the long way around like a serpent I guess.
In one of the first episodes you talked about the serpentine Eden being related to the
seraphim, so the seraphim are the, you know, one of the hybrid, sort of hybrid-throne guardians.
It's like the serpentine, you know, the royal serpent.
And then you have this, the serpentine Eden is in a sort of inverse row instead of
starting the throne, starting the holy place.
in the garden garden center is trying to find cooler adamant to the center before they're ready for
putting them in the holy place before they're ready for it. And so then you have this fallen serpent,
you have this ultimate hybrid monster, the dragon at the bottom of the world. But then at the top of
the world you also have those ultimate hybrid, both in the Arab and with their four faces and
I know the church has found so much.
So much meaning in that, you know, from the vandalists.
So John, if I can interrupt you there for just a second,
you're kind of breaking in and out a lot.
So if you could just go ahead and kind of cut to the chase,
that way we can, yeah.
I'm given there.
So the chair of the market picked it in our iconography often
with four faces and the six wings.
And the center of the market did in almost the same way,
just with one face and the six wings.
sometimes also hands holding signs saying holy holy holy.
And so here's a question because the
um, Sarah Finn and the iconography are
they're like all face and wing which is the opposite of a certain
it's like so do do Sarah Finn have anything to do with
certain really and how or why or
okay that's a good question father Stephen I'm definitely gonna let you jump on that
one
yes yes
Yes! Okay, I know.
one of those. No, they do. So there's a, yeah, so there's there's a there's an interesting shift that
well, interesting to me at least, a shift that happens here, when this is carried over from the
Egyptian context to the Israelite context. And so in the Egyptian context, when they talk about
the throne guardians being winged serpents.
The wings they're talking about are not like flying around wings.
Their wings is in the cobra's hood, right?
Which is what you see, like if you look at,
probably most famous example would be King Tutankham and Spariel Mask, right?
Where not only does he have the cobra on his forehead,
but his sort of ferronic headdress is like the hood of a...
Right? That's what they're talking about with wings.
And the other element, of course, the other interpretation of
Seraphim would be burning ones.
And that burning was not referring to a fire, but was referring to the venom of a
cobra. Right? So the direct serpentine imagery is what's brought to the
in Egypt but what's interesting is
And this gets brought over into the Israelite context.
It gets brought together with the old Canaanite word
for serpent, which is Nakash.
And we talked about this I know before on the show,
that Nakash, those consonants, depending
on whether it's an adjective or a participle or a regular
noun, can mean different things.
Right?
It can mean serpent.
It can mean that us.
Shining one or it can mean clever or deceitful one and you can see all those ideas are related kind of with service other than maybe the shining one part
And so if you look at the earliest
Seraphim iconography that we have in ancient Israel
Which is actually coins from the northern kingdom in the eighth century near the collapse of the northern kingdom
picked, there's sort of a depiction that everybody thinks is supposed to be
Yahweh the God of Israel, right? And it's like, wait, you're not supposed to
depict them. We're talking about the Northern Kingdom.
Right. We're likely fortunate that it's not a calf. But what it is, it just looks
like a round disc, right? Which most people assume it's supposed to be a
solar disc but it's not totally clear. But it's like a round disc.
And that could relate to Solomon having brought back
Sun worship to the Jerusalem temple is how that could connect. But more importantly for these purposes is that
On either side of this depiction of the god of Israel and thrown are
Two serpents, but the serpents now have actual wings
Huh, they have sets of actual wings right and so this would have been around the time Isaiah was having his
So there is a transformation of the iconography of seraphim from the sort of Egyptian pattern,
which is what we see referenced in Genesis 3, which is what we would expect if the Torah goes back to people who left Egypt.
Right?
Right.
From that Egyptian pattern, it over time becomes the...
the depiction that we now still have in the church, but it becomes that depiction we now have in the
church before probably in the Persian period. So we're talking about the beginning of the second
temple period. It's already taken on sort of the human face with the wings where you can't see what
the what the body looks like. Yeah. And I think this is most likely because the iconography of any kind
of serpentine being.
became associated with the devil essentially.
Yeah. So you still see that when you see descriptions of a
zeal and second-temple Jewish literature, he's usually
scaly. Now sometimes he ends up turning into kind of a
raven creature. But you still get, you get the scales, you
get some of that applied to him. So that's a transformation
that happens in order to iconographically distinguish.
the Seraphim who still guard the throne of God, right?
And remember, Seraphim and Cherubim are two different forms
of the same kind of being in the ancient world, right?
So if you're gonna make a change to your iconography
of Seraphim to distinguish them from fallen demonic beings,
how would you do that?
Well, you'd make them look more like Cherubim.
Yeah.
Right, the ones who didn't fall would look more like the Cherubim,
who didn't fall, right?
So that-
sort of how that happens and develops I can aggrapically as best we can understand it.
Cool.
Alright well it seems that John's unfortunate connection got the best of him but hopefully
he was able to hear the response there.
We'll just assume that I nailed it.
Yeah, there you go.
So thank you very much.
Alright, well before we go to our next call we're going to go ahead and take a break
so we'll be right back.
Father Andrew Stephen Daymek and Father Stephen DeYoung will be back in a moment to take
your calls on the next part.
of the Lord of Spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF Radio.
Here is Mother Alexandra of Blessed Memory.
It seemed to me that in this modern life of ours,
everything is...
The Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen De Young.
If you have a question, call now.
855-237-2346. That's 855-AF radio.
Welcome back. It's the third half of the Lord of Spirits here on Ancient
Faith Radio and we're doing a Q&A episode and I've just seen some comments in
our Facebook group because I've been keeping my eye on that. You know people
saying it's really hard to get through. Yeah, so if you call, you know,
you know and you hear something that says you know please
message. Don't leave a message.
Call back and God willing will get through but a lot of people are calling so it's not
super easy to get through right now.
But we do have someone who has successfully gotten through and that is Kavya. Are you there
Kavya? Hi, I'm here. Thank you so much for having me on the show.
Welcome. You made it. I made it. I know.
Hi. What's your question or comment or weird thing bumping in your closet?
Um, nothing weird about that.
in my closet luckily. That's good. That's good. That's good.
I asked my question all of the people on Discord who are on the divine council podcast Discord have asked me to give them a shout out.
People are having a lot of fun. People are discussing this episode and it's a lively group. So shout out to the Discord.
I've heard of Discord. It's a thing that the kids do these days. Yeah.
It is what it is. Yeah. Yeah.
Father Andrew actually is unfrozen caveman lawyer.
That's fine.
Oh man. Oh man. Okay, so what's on your mind there, Kavya? There's like a thousand people
behind you in line. Oh dear. Okay. No pressure. No pressure. Got it. Okay. So the question that
I've had since the hell episode, and I've been I've been saving it until this episode
because the voices see you've told me to, is how do you all understand? Keep your mind
and hell but despair not. The thing that God said to St.
Silo and the Athenite because
I've always been confused about this.
And I can see how, on the one hand,
meditating upon our own sensleness
and keeping our minds in hell so to speak, I guess,
or meditating on the day of judgment all day long,
which is also a thing that many orthodox resources
say to do.
I could see how on the one hand
that could lead to useful, fruitful repentance.
On the other hand, I could also see how it could be,
you know, it could be a thing that leads us
to become fearful, obsessive about...
are thin in a way that is not productive or helpful.
And so I'm kind of wondering how you all interpret
Keith or Mike and Hel, but this is fair or not.
And the place that that does or doesn't have
in our circle is.
Yeah, it's a great question.
So the first thing that I would say in response to that
is something that was said by St. Sylvain's own disciple
St. Sephironius Sikharov, elder Sephironius of Essex.
And someone came to him and asked him essentially
this question like we you know what
what happens when you're like in the depths of almost despair, you know, and, and, you
know, you feel like you're about to be cast on and hell. And he says, uh, he said,
standard the brink until you can take it no longer and then step back and have a cup
of tea. And I love that because, um, it, it, it expresses a lot about what orthodox
spirituality is about. It's not about being hardcore. Like there's some people,
There is a
horrible I've seen this online. I don't know if it's a real bumper sticker. I hope not, which says
orthodoxy. It's Christianity only tougher. That is utter nonsense. Scarbage. That is not what
orthodox Christianity is. But, you know, so Saint Silawon, okay, he was practicing a very intense
kind of spirituality. And I think that like what he says is true. Keep your mind in hell. And that's
really it's not about think that you're about to be damned because he talks a lot about the love
of Christ and the mercy of Christ.
He's not saying, you know, think that you're damned, right?
Rather, it's it's it's generally about humility and a kind of intensity of repentance is what it comes down to and frankly, you know
Most people even though that's good what he said most people are not ready to live the kind of asceticism that he did I
Think that a lot of people would be driven to despair if they attempted to imitate him
in the particulars of what he was doing
And that's why God gives us our own our own
pastors and confessors.
to lead us into what's appropriate for us.
And I think it's really interesting
that his own disciple, St. Sephironi,
who knew him better than anyone
and wrote his biography.
He's the one who wrote St. John the Athenite.
He's the one who gave that,
what seems like a contradictory kind of saying,
but actually it's within the same thing.
You know, he's kind of emphasizing
the do not despair side.
Right?
Everyone always wants to know about
the keep thy mind and hell part.
But don't forget he also said,
Do not despair.
So that's what I would say to that.
So, Father, did you have anything you wanted to add to that?
Well, I'm not going to actually say Sephironi.
Yeah, I could say that.
Right.
Talk about front-loading.
Anyway.
Oh.
But, yeah, I think in general, one of the issues we have in Anglophone orthodoxy is that almost
everything we have translated into English is monastic literature.
And most of it, if you read the parts that we usually skim over to get to the meat, like
say for example, the introduction to the latter of divineism.
Say John Climic has basically says, yeah, I don't tell married people to do any of this
stuff.
Right?
He basically tells, he says there what he tells married people to do.
And he says, now the rest of this book is for monks.
And we all skim over that, go straight into the stuff for monks, and then tire ourselves
That's what I was about to do.
How do I do this in my own home with my kids?
These monks in the prison who are,
you know, doing these in one way,
how do I reconcile this with the grace of God and all that?
Right?
And we're reading stuff that we can't directly apply to ourselves.
So I try to always encourage people to read less
monastic literature and more like homilies from the fathers.
Right?
Because St. John Chrysostom preached his homilies to people
like you and me who showed up to church, right?
Yeah.
So they're sort of aimed right at us,
including the kind of much more basic stuff we need
than the people who monastics are writing to D.
They're on the advanced track, right?
They're playing advanced D&D.
We're unlike the basic set,
where we can only get to level three,
if we work really hard, right?
Oh man.
And so you have to start,
you have to start somewhere like that, right?
And I think there's a similar.
idea to what so on is expressing that's expressed to us in a lot of ways.
It's in the prayer of St. F. DeSsyrian, since some of the other sayings for the
fathers, right, where consider everyone else to be a saint and yourself to be
the worst of sinners, right? That idea. You know, that that's the beginning of
keep your mind in hell and despair not. That's just keep a real view of who you are,
right? And not look at other people. That's a place to begin.
you
Right, that maybe is a place to begin.
And maybe someday when we're more advanced,
we can get to the full on,
I'm going to walk into hell part.
But for now, let's just keep in mind that I'm a sinner.
And stop when we say during the liturgy,
Christ came to save sinners of whom I am chief,
actually thinking in our head.
Well, of whom my cousin is chief, but I'm pretty bad too.
Right.
You know, right, that if we could really come to that,
I think that's the first...
that's going to be a
little bit more.
So I'm going to step toward
what. Say Silo on it say
Sephirone is talking about.
Yeah, and we'll get there at
some point. Lord, well,
all right. Does that does that
help out? Cavia? That very
much does. Thank you so
much. Thank you very much
for calling. Okay, let's just
keep going next. We have
Jesse calling Jesse. You
called 40 times. You made it.
I did. That's very
call. I think that it had to do something like that in order to get in. So, you know, yeah.
All right. So, so, so, so Jesse, what is on your mind this evening?
I am a question that is actually from my husband, but we were talking about this and it's about
blood and ritual purity as it was kind of discussed in the sacrifice episode.
But you explain that blood is used to purify things like altars and bi-
Why is blood also seen as having something that can make something unclean for like a woman who's menstruating or who's given birth and
This is also connected to you know why so significant that when Christ was born, you know
Not only was it painless, but it was bloodless
When we see blood as being that purifying
element
It's a good question and I know that anything I might say to about it.
would be much better from said in the mouth of father Steven so
So I'm I'm I'm the good to be the one who gets this kicked off the air for what I'm about to talk about here
We go. Yeah
Hey, you know, this is my job by the way, so like don't ruin my job. I'm good. I have to
The questions I ask it's true. It's true
So there's there's two pieces here. So there's two pieces here
One is the safe one that we're going to talk about first.
and then the second one relates to bodily fluids
and that's where we're going to get into trouble.
So we'll start with the safe one.
Everybody put your kids to bed.
The safe one.
I'll try to use technical terms.
The first one is that something that is holy or sacred
in Old Testament ritual that is taken out
of its appropriate context becomes something
which makes things unclean. Right, like the Torah scrolls, right?
Right, you just handle those and that makes you unclean. When you handle the
Torah scrolls your hands become unclean. But also a very pertinent example. What
do you do with the blood from sacrifices, right? You're using this blood, it's
with interesting things about the the day of atonement rituals. Again,
interesting to nerds like me. You're using the blood, right, to purify all of
all of you.
these material objects in the holy of holies of the tabernacle.
But if while you're doing that, that blood gets onto your garment, right?
Which is also a material object, right?
But if it gets onto your garment, that's not where it's supposed to be.
And so your garment has to be burned because your garment is now unclean.
The purifying agent makes your garment unclean because it's outside of its proper place
in context.
Hmm, right?
The same as you would have with communion.
It's like, communion gets on something you'd have to burn it if it's supposed to be.
Yeah, okay.
Right.
And so, this also applies blood because the, something's blood is its life.
It's seen to be sacred, especially human blood in the Old Testament.
And so, when it is out of its context, when it's outside of the human body, it becomes
comes unclean and makes things unclean.
Right?
So when you're bleeding, that blood is making things unclean.
When your blood is in your body giving life to your body, it's not unclean.
Right?
And it doesn't make your body unclean.
So that's part one, that's the non-controversial part.
Okay.
Here comes the fun.
So.
I know it is a big issue currently.
and for good reason that concerns and sometimes even rules in the
contemporary Orthodox Church relating to menstruation, right, and childbirth
and the uncleanestism. Okay, so the same rules apply both in the
scriptures and in the cannons of the church to mail emissions.
So whatever reason in our modern American culture, we are much more comfortable talking
about women's menstruation than we are about male emissions.
I think it's related to the same reason why you can show female nudity and not male nudity
in movies.
But I don't know why that is.
I just know that it's a cultural thing we...
have. Right. So we don't want to talk about male emissions. We don't want to talk about
nocturnal emissions. I'm using the most technical terms I can. We don't want to talk about
that at all. And so since we don't talk about that, women especially feel like they're
being singled out with their issues. But those same things apply to men. The same rules
about administration and receiving the
Eucharist also applied to men who have had nocturnal emissions.
This is why men are to refrain from marital activities with their wives, priests, for
example, before serving the liturgy.
All of those things are related.
And so we talk about one, we don't talk about the others.
And the reason for that, the idea behind that before presenting.
venting yourself with the church, coming into the presence of God, was not that there was
something gross or unclean about sex or about femininity or masculinity. It was that
when you've had one of those emissions or expulsions of bodily fluid, when you give birth
and there's the placenta and everything, that you were seen in the Torah as being depleted.
You are not in your fullness.
You are not whole.
And so when we come before God and come into His presence,
we are to present ourselves to Him whole and not and not depleted.
And so those things applied to both men and women.
It's just in our modern practice, we talk about one and not the other.
Sometimes people try to enforce one and still don't talk about the other
so they don't try to inform.
course it. But those things are closely linked both in scripture and in our tradition when
you go back into past centuries. So do you think we're canceled? I think that's the bullet.
I think I still have a job probably. Okay. Okay. I can just jond away in. Yeah. Does that
Does that designate your question, Jesse?
Yes, thank you so much.
Be careful with follow ups.
Yeah, right. Yeah, let's yeah. Okay. Let's go.
All right. Thank you very much. Okay.
Next we are going to hear from Brett.
Brett, welcome to the Lord of Spirits.
I hope this is a different Brett.
Is that so?
I want to go to another question back from my Christmas episode
speak pipe.
Yes, I recognize this fret.
Hello, fathers.
Welcome welcome
My question relates to going back to the episode about astrology, the Acadian Babylonian,
mispachamian general, God of Shammosh and sin. Shammosh being the sun god and sin being
the god governing astrology and the night. How do we relate that to a modern day or Christian
theological concept of sin? And particularly, I guess, a Jewish-loaded concept of a particular
with Hanukkah.
the Shamosh candle and Shamosh being kind of turned to a helper or
of sorts from a
keeper's camp.
Point.
It's a good question.
Yeah, and you did send this to us earlier and it was recorded and we
kept it and we actually had it as a backup for tonight.
So believe it or not, that was one of the questions we were going to answer.
If one of the questions calls, right, if we got no calls, so here you are asking
questions.
So when you're recording you ask this question like
What is that? How does that connect with the word sin? Right?
Well, number one, so this is the part that I can answer.
So though the English word sin has nothing to do
etymologically with the God that you were referring to.
It actually comes from a Latin word that refers to guilt.
So that's that's etymologically where it is now.
All of you out there who's saying, see, I knew sin met guilt.
I knew it.
Just because something etymologically connects to a former word
does not mean that that's what it means now.
or what it means, theologically.
So, all right, so the rest of all the,
that complex of ancient Semitic deity,
I will leave to Father Stephen.
Right, right.
Well, I mean, Kimash, of course, is also the main,
the primary Moabite deity, the moon deity, Kimash.
and then Shamash as the the son in Canaanite.
religion, but that comes out of a Canadian religion, you know, and proto-Semitic. But so,
I mean, that sort of subsumed within our general understanding of the Sun and the Moon, right?
And what we see is that while on the one hand, we have the worship of the Sun and the Moon
still going on in the pagan context of those gods. We also see in early Christian literature.
and even second temple Jewish literature, we see spirits associated with the sun and moon who are also portrayed as being sort of unfall under positive spirits.
Now sometimes it's sometimes it's hard to know for sure because even if something is a demonic fallen spirit, it's still under God's control.
so it may be acting in certain ways by compulsion.
Right. Not by not by its own not by its own will.
But for example, since we just got done with Holy Week, all that stuff about the sun and the moon hiding their faces and all of that
isn't just poetry and allegory.
That is referring to, you know, when they're depicted in an iconography with faces, like in the iconography of the crucifixion, that's
a very
literal thing. That's from the perspective of the church and our hemnography. And the Bible at
no point chiseled away from that. The Bible at no point demithologizes the Sun and the Moon.
So when you get to the fourth day of creation in Genesis 1, it literally says that Yahweh created
Shemesh and Kimosh. There you are. Right, it doesn't say...
He created their bodies.
It doesn't say, it says he created
Shemesh and Kimash and appointed
Wonder Rule the day and Wonder Rule the night, right?
Which rocks and my asmas of plasmas can't do.
All right.
Does that answer your question?
Brett, I know it probably sprouted 10 more for most of us,
but let's say yeah, I think it opened more than it answered,
but I did answer my question.
Yes.
Thank you, father.
All right.
Well, thank you very much, Brett.
Good to hear from you.
you. We gotta keep people coming back for future. Yeah, exactly. Yeah, on a future episode.
Um, it's so okay. Next we have someone with one of the greatest names ever. So welcome Andrew
to the Lord of Spirits podcast. Hi, um, I have a question on giants actually. Yeah. About
time. Yes. So in Matthew 25, it says the rulers of the Gentile watered over them and the
great ones are tyrants over them.
And I've heard a couple times and I think it's in the book too about the demons not having
hierarchy or bureaucracy but just bringing things to chaos.
So it seems kind of a paradox where they use rulership to bring chaos in my following
this.
Yeah, yeah.
Okay, well, I have some ideas, but Father,
Steve, why don't you go ahead and take a crack at this first.
Right.
So two things.
First thing is, right, where we're interpreting what Christ said,
and I think you're right to do that in this context,
we're talking about the relationship that those spirits would have with the people.
So if we're talking about the gods of Rome and the people of Rome,
the gods of Egypt and the people of Egypt, right?
That's...
the tyranny and the Lording it over them, right, to bring about their destruction.
So there's this interplay we talked about when we were talking about the beginnings
of neolithic religion and how that pans out.
We talked about how there are these two principles that correspond to Bahaimot or Bihemoth
and Lothan or Leviathan, right, in the Old Testament.
the bohemo
the bowl of heaven, right? This is sort of the, the, who becomes the beast from the earth in the book of Revelation
is associated with tyranny. It's associated with sort of that kind of tyranny and domination, right?
Which, what does tyranny and domination produce? I mean, ultimately it produces destruction in chaos, right?
It's not order in the sense of God's divine order, right? It's not sort of
like goodness gone too far. It's this kind of false order, right? This false
order that's imposed, that sort of grinds humanity in its gears, right? And then I mean,
I would say I would add to that, if I'm sorry for interrupting, but I would add to that,
that no created thing can be truly perfectly chaotic.
right because it's been put into order by God,
even if it's functioning in a very distorted way.
Right, so yeah, exactly.
So a drunk man in a bar who's like the Hulk
and going around and smashing stuff
and hurting people, he is functioning in a certain orderly way.
You know, like his brain is sending signals
to his nerves, to his muscles, to do things.
It's very orderly.
like on a certain level, but it's against the order of God.
That's just what I would add to interrupt the room.
Leviathan would be the principle of abject chaos.
Both are evil. Both of them are aimed at destruction.
You can, I mean, you look at the Holocaust in Germany.
IBM made punch cards. They manufactured punch cards for the death camps, indicating this person is a Jew, this person is a Gypsy, this person is a homosexual, this person is a quote unquote defective.
Right. Why they were there to schedule the execution. There's plenty of order there. Right. You've got your IBM punch cards. You've got your bureaucracy. You've got your system. Right. And it's bringing about destruction.
Right.
And then you've got just abject chaos of war out on the battlefield of men and women
and children being killed and cut down and hit by Schrapnull and which is producing the
same result.
You can produce the same result either way.
And in fact the two tend to go together in this kind of dialectic, the beast from the
earth and the beast from the sea, the hemath and leviathan, they go together and they have
this inner
play with each other. Live you famously said about the Roman Empire, you know, they've
made a wasteland and called it peace. Right? They go out and destroy and create this wasteland
and then say, Oh, look how peaceful and perfect and beautiful it is and orderly. You know,
so those two there's an interplay there in evil, right? Between sort of order and chaos.
It's not order in the sense of the divine order, the order that comes from God, the hierarchy
that God establishes.
right in the universe and in terms of of being right it's it's order in the
sense of regimentation and tyranny and bureaucracy in the modern age even
does that make sense Andrew?
Yeah so it's kind of like the chaos that Soran's order brought.
There you go.
No, I wasn't the one who meant you brought Tolkien up, but there you are.
Thank you very much for calling
Andrew. That's a good question.
Okay, so next we have
Kristen on the line.
So Kristen, are you there?
Yes, sir. I'm here.
Welcome, Kristen, the Lord of
Spirits. What is your deal?
Well, I'm just going to say
thank you for even giving a
maybe on the all dogs might
go to heaven. You've never
given me such a good excuse
to adopt freedom. Very
good excuse to adopt a red and gray animal in my life.
Let me tell you, my dogs are all heated, but my mom's dog is such a holy dog.
She once ran away and literally spent 40 days living in the wilderness and then returned
to the promised land.
I literally spent 35 minutes prying a cat out of my engine this afternoon, now in my house
and I'm like, okay, why not?
Why not?
Anyway, to my actual question.
You can't eat them by the soft food.
I'm sorry. Sorry, Kristen. He's not a pet person.
No, no, no, I'm not a pet eater either. So I mean, I'm not going to eat you know.
Okay, go ahead. His wife will cook your guinea pigs.
That seems likely.
Okay, then.
And pivot. All right.
I had about 15 questions, but I'm going.
to just pick.
So the story, you've mentioned in several episodes
where no, actually no, that's not it.
All right, so Vanessa L.M. being the unclean spirit
in the news estimate.
So I've looked at, I've read your whole council blog posts
on it about how we got some of that from Jubilee
and send it that.
was kind of inferred from, you know, they're described as unclean spirits.
They're not described as demons specifically, but unclean spirits.
And based on that, that means they're mixed, which in the Torah.
So I'm just curious, is there other like scriptural, like in our canon,
holy scriptures evidence for that?
Or is this one that you just kind of have to go, okay, well,
This is what the church has treated.
and you know, it's consistent with these inferences in the old
testament.
That's a good question.
So,
probably you want to expand on that?
Yeah.
I mean, unclean spirits do show up at other parts of the New Testament.
I don't know if that's what you were asking.
At least part of it, but they do.
Like,
yeah,
no, I think she was particularly their origin, their origin, the origin question.
Yeah.
So,
you know,
the only nerd
to a certain extent.
Right? To a certain extent, there are a whole bunch of things that when we get to the New Testament,
they just kind of pop up. Right? And they're not really there's not really much of it in the old
Testament. Right? You know, all of a sudden there's Pharisees and Sadducees. Right? All of a sudden,
right? There's a bunch of things that have cropped up. But one of those is there seem to be demon
possessed people running around all over the place. Right? When you get into the Gospels, Christ is
is doing these exorcisms all the time all over the place.
And you see some unclean spirits coming.
upon people in the old, like Saul in the Old Testament and there's the possession in
Tobit, right?
If you're using the longer Old Testament can and you've got Tobit there.
But there's not a ton, right?
And you don't even get a lot of stuff in the Old Testament.
Well, you definitely don't get a lot of stuff in the Old Testament that talks about, oh,
the Messiah when he shows up, he's going to exercise all these demons, right?
So we're not sort of ever directly told in the pages of Scripture, well, here's where
come from, right, all of a sudden, right? And here's why Jesus is so concerned with casting
them out. That's why the exercise now that's interestingly Saint John's gospel. He doesn't
do any exorcisms, but in the synoptic gospels, a major emphasis on Christ doing these exorcisms.
So we have to look at, well, if it's not spelled out, right, here in the pages of scripture,
explanations are there from the Jewish world, right, in the second temple period.
Where did they think they came from?
And when you do that, that's where you come to the Nephilim explanation.
And in fact, that's the only explanation you come to.
There weren't sort of like competing stories, at least that we still have, right?
So which means that either that was just what everyone believed or that if there were
other competing stories. The one
that we still have is the one that everyone accepted,
and that's why those texts were passed down
and the other ones weren't.
And it's not just a question of,
well, this is the only explanation we have,
so I guess we should just go with it,
but the details of that explanation are referred to in places.
I mean, it's oblique, it's not spelled out,
but are referred to in places in those exorcism stories.
So the demons who Christ cast into the pigs say,
have you come to torment us before the time?
Great, great.
Right. Yes, it's consistent with the Jubilee. Right. So it's sort of like, well, what's that referring to?
Well, if you've read Jubilee, you say, well, that, that is, that is then consistent with that version of the story. That makes sense.
And so these are inference type evidence, not deductive type evidence, right?
And with the fact that, you know, they're talking about being cast into the ambience, right, is consistent, right?
So, so we have this one explanation for the ancient world, all of the evidence that we do have in the scriptures.
is consistent with it. If you want to read more about this, a fella named Archibald Leach
wrote a book called The Origin of Evil Spirits, which is, I believe, developed from his
doctoral dissertation and put into a select. That is a fantastic name. Yeah, that is just like
the most amazing Archie Leach is like the most amazing British name ever.
But yeah, his book The Orish
of evil spirits, which is based, I believe on his doctoral dissertation might be based
on a monograph, but he's the guy on that. I mean, he goes all the way into, aren't you
right? Sorry, right? W W R. Yeah, I was thinking of carrying Grant. Anyway, that will make sense
to like five people. But yeah, are, are, are too right. Sorry, archival right. The he goes
all the way in on this.
So he goes into all of the sources, all of the details, right?
Exhaustively just on the origin of the demons of the synoptic gospels.
So that's the place to go if you really want to do a deep dive and go all the way down the rabbit hole on that.
Well, of course I do.
Yeah, all right. Why wouldn't you? Yeah. Yeah.
Well, okay, well, thank you very much for calling and nice to talk to you.
Thank you so much, brothers. Have a good evening.
You too, okay, we've got-
Vince up next. So Vince, welcome to the Lord of Spirits.
Thanks Father. It's my name is Vincent. I'm a recovering Calvinist.
God bless you.
And it can be overcome. There is hope.
Okay.
So because I was going too deep into the reformed rabbit hole,
I'm trying to wrap my mind around different views of the tone.
So I haven't re-listen to your episode yet but...
My question is about cosmic geography and the atonement after the cross and there's
sort of two related questions I hope.
So is Christ dying for the sins of the world more kind of cosmic geographical language
with reclaiming the nations rather than specific individual sins in a kind of works contract
Lutheran failure kind of atonement because
because we become sacred space, so Christ died for the nations.
Yes.
We also died for us to become sacred space where God's presence could
dwell like in Eden.
Yes.
Okay, next.
Okay.
I mean, it's great when people got this stuff figured out for themselves.
It's good.
Yeah, you've got it.
No, I mean, that's exactly it.
That's exactly it.
Like so, did you reach...
I'm sorry, this isn't the second follow-up question, but just...
That's okay. Yes, so I have to...
That was a short answer, so yeah.
Okay.
So, but Christ, he died for the sins of all of humanity because he took upon death the wages
of sin.
Well...
Not like every sin I ever committed as in some individual callying system.
But where are you getting the
sins of all of humanity. So this is part of the translating one John 2 2 correctly, which
is it says he died not only for our sins but for the whole world. There is no those of
it. Your English Bible may tack that in, right? So. And this is Mother Stevens doctoral
dissertation that you wrote a thousand pages unlike the last of the person. I'm slightly
exaggerated. It's not there.
for free online, but I couldn't have slew that out.
But yeah, so it's translate that.
So this is understanding the element of salvation
that is universal and the element of salvation that isn't.
And part of the problem with atonement in the west
is that this isn't clearly distinguished.
and so you end up trying to say
that one thing is both universal and not at the same time. And that's where you get
sufficiency and efficiency, that's where you get redemption accomplished and
redemption applied. You know what I'm talking about, right? And that's where you
destroy your assurance because how can you ever really know your elect then? Right,
right. So the two elements are two separate elements, right? So Christ defeats
death on the b-
half of all humanity, right? In the resurrection icon, Christ is grabbing Adam and Eve, right?
All of humanity, death no longer has a claim on. Every human being is going to rise on the
last day to be judged by Christ and no one else because Christ is now the Lord of the
living and the dead, right? That part is universal. The sin part is not universal. There is no
icon of Christ redeeming Cane.
Right. There is no icon of Christ redeeming Judas. Right. So that part is not universal.
Right. It's not that the whole thing is somehow universal and then not universally applied.
It's that there's two elements of it. Right. And then there is actually a third element that's also universal.
It's also universal, that's Christ's defeat of the devil.
right and the the hostile powers which affects everyone right but this is why St. Paul can say Christ is the savior of all men but especially those who are faithful
right because two out of three affect everybody
but the third one is only the faithful
right the sin is about the faithfulness it's about the the repentance and
salvation from sin purification and Christ blood all of that takes
place within Christ Church. So right. And that's because those who don't repent don't receive
atonement. Right. Don't receive the purification that comes from Christ blood. Cleansing. Right.
Okay. Praise God. If I have time, I have a sort of related fast follow up question about
Okay, you got a quick one.
We'll allow it.
Okay, so with cosmic geography and the reclaiming of the name.
when a nation like, for example, Turkey was Christianized and later, you know, Constantinople
falls in 1453.
There's sort of a legend.
I don't know whether it's historically true, but I've heard it from Muslim sources that,
you know, lightning struck the Hagia Sophia and there were sort of portents in the sky
when the city fell.
So you know, that area has sort of been almost like reconquered.
that's a great commitment to
have to be prepared by a.
Fallen. You know, one of the
the fallen gods, the one of
the other Elohim. And so does
that mean that territory has
now sort of become unclean in
a sense and like we have to
go re conquer it for the great
commission to have covered that
territory. I was hoping you were
going to ask about the marble
Let's go look at it.
If you don't know what that is, go look it up.
If it were to happen, of course, we would re-consecrate the Haggis of Ia.
We would go in and purify it and re-consecrate it as a Christian.
Yeah, there's a kind of tension where the whole world belongs to the Lord and He's made it clean.
But at the same time, there is the way that people in particular areas are participating or rebelling against that.
Right?
You see that with Israel?
I'm a native, like, in a way that it's almost like a power
change over where, you know, if the church is in the ascendancy
or in the majority, we've sort of restrained evil and cleanse
that space by our presence.
But then when we get kind of conquered, you know,
does the demonic influencing crease and polluted in a way
that we have to like, reconquer it again?
Yes, but I would emphase.
I sometimes people have these wonderful fan and I'm not saying you're saying this but sometimes people have these wonderful fantasies
They're like we need to retake constants and opal. I'm like great. It's a great idea job number one
Learn Turkish job number two come to my missionary training school
Because that's that's how you retake constants and opal
Yeah, yeah, and think about it in terms of the Old Testament
Right? Why did the Assyrians in the Babel
these pagans come in and take back the land from Israel and Judah, right?
God allowed it as a judgment.
Yep.
Right.
God allowed it as a judgment.
And if you read the monastics, the spiritual writers writing at the time of Fall of Constantinople,
they're very clear that it fell as a judgment from God.
Yeah.
That's what people then said.
Alright, well, thank you very much Vince for calling in.
We are going to take one more caller before we call it a night.
And that's Jordan.
Jordan, you are the fortunate person who made it in
right before the wire.
Welcome, Jordan.
Thank you, Father.
What's your question or concern or
odd location?
Oh, okay.
I have a door.
Thank you, section.
Incentuation.
Well, it may be some knock.
I think that my door with this question, when I was in high school, I was just learning
about the more liturgical aspects of Christianity, such as Catholicism, and then later orthodoxy.
I grew up a Protestant, and in that I found, quote unquote, Christian witchcraft.
And for some reason, that really connected with me, dare I say that.
I started practicing it on a minor scale, although I don't think any...
which craft is minor, but such as putting a cost within a pentagram and writing a
cell, I hope you've had term now, directed toward God and have a friend on Facebook who
identifies as a Christian shaman using native and Nordic tradition mix in with
Christianity. So I was wondering.
just how that would end up,
within the Christian things,
and how to explain the difference
between the surgical worship
and daily prayer,
versus witchcraft
to Protestant to a very
adverse to repeated prayer,
like the Jesus prayer,
or making the sign of the cross,
and you got it, witchcraft.
Yeah, that's an awesome question.
I'm so happy.
it's our last one. Right, okay. So not to not to puff you up. But okay. So so lots of things going on here.
Number one, you know, what fellowship path Christ with Boliol, right? You don't mix these things. So obviously it's a big no.
But so then the question is like, what about people who can't tell the difference between liturgical worship and witchcraft and just say that's dark and evil and pagan, demonic, whatever. I've
I haven't heard that many times.
So here's the difference.
And this kind of goes to one of the things that we've talked about a lot, which is that in some
sense Christianity and paganism are not two different games. They're two different teams playing
the same game. Yeah. And so ritual participation and the worship of your God is how you worship
your God for the vast majority of the history of the world, no matter where you are, right?
And the difference between the worshipers of...
the one true God, the God of Israel, and everyone else is largely based in who they're aiming their
worship towards, who they are worshiping, you know, who are they offering their sacrifices to
and having that communion with, right? That's the biggest difference. Now, there is also a qualitative
difference that comes in as well. I mean, there's all kinds of qualitative differences. One is morality,
I mean, pagan morality is way different from the morality of the God of
Israel, but also the other thing about witchcraft in particular is that it is about manipulation.
It's about control, right? And I mean, often, I mean, it depends on what exactly you're
talking about. Like there's something called, you know, Christopheganism, Christian
Wicca. There's even a book called The Path of a Christian Witch. Like, this is all this
kind of stuff you can find.
And in some cases it's about inv-
other spiritual beings, right?
So literally, it's a kind of, literally, it's syncretism,
where you're worshiping more than one thing at a time.
You know, in some ways, it's a kind of exploitation
of Christianity, like, oh, this cross is a powerful thing.
I'm gonna use it in my magical spells.
You know, I just can't help but think of that.
The ending of Indian and Jones, sorry,
the Lerators of the Lost Ark,
where they wanna take the Ark of the Covenant
and use it for their own stuff.
What a bad idea that was.
You know, so, so, so yeah, I mean, I think the thing to do is,
because I mean, I come from evangelical prison background before I became Orthodox.
And, and ritual often in certain evangelical circles is looked at as being
this dark and terrible thing kind of in and of itself, right?
And so when I talk with people like that, I say, look, I get what you're saying,
But the truth is that we you engage in rituals all the time.
You do things that are that are gestures and actions that don't sort of accomplish anything you tell a tear in in themselves
Like why shake hands that doesn't do anything
Why shake hands?
It's an action that that ritually
Indicates a meeting or a friendship or trust or whatever
But you can have those things without the shaking of hands
But why do you do it? You do it because that's the ritual you do and that's the way that you participate in this relationship
Right or why when you're in a cemetery or you quiet
it.
Why are you respectful? Why do you maybe let a candle? Why do you maybe leave a flower?
Why do you do that?
Again, it's not utilitarian in any way. It's not like the dead are
You know going to be mad at you if you're running around and yelling in the cemetery
I mean, maybe they would probably not
You know that's that's not what's going on
So people act richly all the time they often they just don't see it or like anytime someone gets married
Right?
Do they just go down to the courthouse and just sign a thing and then that's it?
You
the people who are the most sort of atheistic and secular want at least some kind of I do
before they do that. There's still a need for some kind of ritual. Oh, and someone graduates,
or when we inaugurate President of the United States, boom, outcomes are ritual. So we do rituals.
It's just that we've reduced the number that we do and the way that we do it and so forth.
And of course, again, if ritual is bad, what is the deal with all that ritual that God directly
commands in the Old Testament.
It can't be inherently bad or else God would never have commanded it. It's not like suddenly became evil
You know, so I mean that's that's what I would say I think about worship a lot and especially since like as I said
I have an evangelical background and people been asking me these questions for the last 25 years
So father Stephen you get the last word
Okay, well, and your dogs your heathen dogs. Yeah, my heathen this that's Emmett in particular for the record
So
Yeah, the problem with which craft is the same as the problem with pre-scraft, and that's the craft part, right?
The technique and the fact that it's trying to get God or the gods or spiritual forces or nature or what have you to do what you want them to do.
You're trying to change God, right?
And...
are perfectly capable of doing this too without resorting to any of that, right?
If your prayers are mostly you reading your list of demands to God, if that's how you think about prayer,
if that's how you think about getting people to join you in prayer, well if we get enough people
praying for it, God will have to do it, right? Any of those kind of things where you're trying to change
God or get God to do something and you're trying to figure out how to do it, then there's a,
there's a basic problem because
Because the reality is, a ritual doesn't change God.
Whether you're trying to or not, it changes you.
So when you do ritual, it changes you and your world.
When your community does ritual, it changes your community and its world.
That's what it does.
Whether you're trying to do something more or less, nothing, it doesn't matter.
That's what gets changed.
And so when we're in
in the divine liturgy when we're praying with our families when we're praying alone, right?
That's to change ourselves and
Our world in which we are living every day. That's what's being transformed through it
God isn't doing something different or becoming something different toward us or looking at us differently or however
Else we want to think about it. God's perfect. He doesn't need to change
right? Whereas we're being transformed and so the
problem is when you're doing another kind of ritual other than the rituals God laid out for us that are going to lead us
Deeper and more fully into our humanity. That's why he laid those rituals out for us and established them for us
It's for our salvation if you're doing other rituals that you've come up with to try and do other things
Those are also changing you and also changing your world the world you live in every day
They're changing your community and your community's world and your community's life together.
and they're changing it in ways that are drawing you away from the fullness of your humanity,
that are making your world less human, less filled with God's grace and goodness.
They're leading you in the wrong direction.
So that's the key problem with it, right?
Is the destructive nature.
And this was the big temptation for Israel all through the Old Testament, right?
It wasn't that they were going to reject Yahweh the God of Israel.
It's just that
They were going to put them in a corner, keep doing the sacrifices to keep him happy, quote
unquote, and then also serve these other gods and do these other things and sort of cover
all their bases and just sort of mix it all together to try to get what they wanted
out of the world and out of life.
And that led them in very bad directions.
And it wasn't just a question of, oh God was mad at them, but it actually transformed their
world and their communal life.
God comes to them and talks about the results.
What they've done he doesn't just say well I'm mad at you and you did bad things
He talks about the corruption within Israel and how that plays out the oppression of the poor and the weak and the needy
Right the the hatred between brothers the divisions and families the division within the state
Every two kings in the northern kingdom. There was an assassination in a new dynasty
There's complete political turmoil. They were losing wars and losing territory. They're being conquered by other people
Right, all these things have these...
effects because they were changing themselves and their world in this way by trying to mix and
match and do these things. So that I think is just as real today as it was in the Old Testament.
Indeed. Does that answer your question Jordan? Yes Father, thank you so much. Excellent. Well thank
you very much for calling and thanks to all of our callers that tonight we planned for the
the past.
that we would only get like one or two calls, but boy, you guys really jammed it up. I'm really, really happy with all of you.
So I think probably, I don't know if father, we didn't talk about this, but I think maybe in the, at some point, and you know, down the road will do this again. What do you think?
Maybe. Maybe. Okay. Maybe.
Well, we'll send some kind of goal and use this as a reward. We'll send it.
There you go, exactly.
So, alright, well, since it was just kind of a, you know, free for all this evening.
There's not really, you know, any, I don't have any closing kind of statement to make
Connective with all that but it sure sure was a lot of fun
I will say this though before we go into our credits and that is if for some weird reason you have it yet bought a copy of father
Steven's book the religion of the apostles
What's wrong with you?
Sorry, here's the thing
Here's this about it. It's about to sell out
Yeah, right. That's right. That happens about so
you need to order now because once they're gone, you're going to have to wait and you're going to have to contact father Andrew directly to pre-order the second printing.
Nope. I'm a reporter now before that happens because you don't want to have to deal with him on the pre-orders.
That's right because you'll get nothing. I'll take your money, but you'll get nothing. So all right. Well, that is our show for tonight. Thank you everyone for listening.
If you didn't get a chance to call in during this live broadcast, we still want to hear from you.
You can see...
And as an email at allortofspiritsatentfaith.com,
you can message us at our Lord of Spirits podcast Facebook page.
We do read everything.
We listen to every message you send.
But unfortunately, we can't respond everything or include everything.
But we do try to save some of it for future episodes.
Join us for our live broadcasts on the second and fourth Thursdays of the month
at 7 p.m. Eastern 4 p.m. Pacific.
And if you are on Facebook, you can like our page
and join our discussion group.
Leave reviews, ratings everywhere.
but most importantly, share this show with a friend whom you know is going to love it.
And finally, be sure to go on ancientfaith.com, Stroke Support, and help make sure we, and lots of other AFR podcasters stay on the air.
Thank you very much. God bless you, and Christ is risen.
Yeah.
You've been listening.
to the Lord of Spirits, with Orthodox Christian priests,
Father Andrew Stephen Damick, and Father Stephen De Young,
a listener-supported presentation of ancient faith radio.
And I beheld, and I heard the voice of many angels
round about the throne, and the beasts, and the elders.
And the number of them was 10,000 times 10,000,
and thousands of thousands,
saying with a loud voice, worthy is the land
that was slain to receive power, and riches,
and wisdom and strength and honor.
honor and glory and blessing.
Revelation chapter 5 verses 11 through 12.
Hi, this is Father Evan Armitas, priest at St. Spirit on Greek Orthodox Church in Lulang,
Colorado, and the host of the Ancient Faith Radio Sunday Night Call and Show Orthodoxy
Live.
I am pleased to announce today the release of my first book for Ancient Faith Publishing,
title, toolkit for spiritual.
a practical guide to prayer fasting and arms giving.
It seeks to provide a guide to the three basic and primary disciplines of Orthodox spirituality.
Through these disciplines Christ opened for us a path that frees us from the disordered way of life
has become normal for many, even though their hearts and minds tell them otherwise.
Please join me in exploring the three-legged stool of Orthodox spiritual practice.
And the title once again is Toolkit for Spiritual Growth.
I look forward to sharing it with you.
God bless.
Welcome to the Thursday edition of The Path.
You're connected to The Path, offering strength for our journey toward salvation.
Here's Father Tom Saroga.
Today's epistle reading is from Acts, chapter 4, verses 23 through 31.
And being let go, they went to their own companions, and reported all that the chief priests and
elders had said to them.
So when they heard that, they raised their voice to God with one accord and said, Lord,
You are God who made heaven.
and earth and the sea, and all that is in them, who by the mouth of your servant David have said,
Why did the nations rage and the people plot vain things? The kings of the earth took their
stand, and the rulers were gathered together against the Lord and against his Christ.
For truly against your Holy servant Jesus, whom you anointed, both Herod and Pontius Pilate
with the Gentiles and the people of Israel were gathered to
together to do whatever your hand in your purpose, determine before to be done.
Now Lord, look on their threats and grant to Your servants that with all boldness they may
speak Your word.
By stretching out Your hand to heal, and that signs and wonders may be done through the
name of Your Holy Servant Jesus, and when they had prayed, the place where they were
assembled together was shaken, and they were all filled with the Holy Spirit, and they
the word of God with boldness.
In commenting on today's reading, St. John Chrysostom speaks about the synergy between
the gift of the Holy Spirit and the gifts born by the Apostles.
He writes, and when they had prayed, the place in which they were gathered together