He will be a staff for the righteous with which for them to stand and not to fall, and
he will be the light of the nations and the hope of those whose hearts are troubled.
All who dwell on the earth will fall down and worship him, and they will praise and bless
and celebrate with song the Lord of Spirits.
1st denoc.
Chapter 48 verses 4-5.
The modern world doesn't acknowledge but is nevertheless haunted by spirits, angels,
demons and
In our time, many year into break free of the prison of a flat, secular materialism, to see
and to know reality as it truly is.
What is this spiritual reality like?
How do we engage with it well?
How do we permeate everyday life with spiritual presence?
Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen De Young
post this live Colin show, focused on enchantment in creation.
union of the scene and unseen
as made by God and experienced by mankind throughout history.
Welcome to the Lord of Spirits.
Welcome back to the Lord of Spirits podcast.
It is good to be with you tonight, everyone.
I am Father Andrew Stephen Damick, and I am in Emeas, Pennsylvania.
And with me is my co-host, Father Stephen DeYoung,
who is broadcasting from the middle of Cajun Country in Lafayette,
Louisiana.
And if you are listening to us.
live. You can call in at 855 AF radio. That's 855 237 2346. And we're going to get your calls
in the second part of today's show. So tonight we're going to be talking about Mary, the
Thayotokos, the mother of Jesus Christ. Most Christians love and venerate her while some
and prefer to marginalize her as much as possible.
And some just don't know what to do with it.
assuming this year is important at all, most who love her point to a natural affection
and affinity for her based on love for her son Jesus Christ and how she directs us to him.
And they may also add something about the church's long experience of her intercessions and care
often miraculously over the centuries.
And while all of that is true and beautiful, it does not root very deeply what the church
teaches about the theoretical course and how the
to the church interacts with her.
So those who are unconvinced remain unconvinced,
and those who are convinced may not have very deep roots
when it comes to their knowledge of her.
What many don't seem to realize though,
is that it turns out that the role and veneration
of the Virgin Mary, the Theotokos,
is not established by hints in the New Testament
or experiences from subsequent Church history,
but rather finds foundations in the very heart
the all-testimate experience.
of God that her place is intimately connected with the Lordship of her son, Jesus Christ.
I'm getting ahead of myself though, we can't jump right to that. Instead, we have to go all the
way back to Genesis, to the creation of man and his placement in the paradise of Eden. So,
Father Stephen, take us to Eden. Yeah, let's begin at the beginning because it's a very good place to
start. Indeed.
I feel like at some point we should record the voice of Steve saying, last time on Lord of Spirit's part.
There we go.
So Steve, if you're listening to his notes and play clips, you know, from the last couple of shows.
But in the last couple of shows, two shows ago, we kind of mentioned when we were talking about sort of the saints and glory, we mentioned the idea of them imaging God.
We talked a little bit more in our last step.
episode about giants, about how the Nephilim were sort of images and imaging, and that's
how they were sons to the demonic powers.
Yeah.
Bringing their works to fruition in the world.
And so what we're going to do tonight is really take a deep dive into what that means
and how that works for believers and for saints and for Christians.
And we're going to be using the Theo Toco's.
of it A, but we have to start if we're going to talk about being the image of God, as you
said, we have to talk about man being created in the image of God in the first place.
Right.
And what that means.
It's because there's a lot of theorizing about that.
Right.
Popular books and even scholarly books and even going back into church history where
re-
is what makes him to be in the image of God or language or these things.
And then you get into these protracted discussions because we find out,
hey, guess what? There's a bunch of species of animal that have language.
Or are they in the image of God?
Yeah. Or maybe we should eventually do a show on this.
Sometimes people speculate, well, if there's alien life out there and their
sentient does that mean they're in the image of God?
what level of sentience would they have to have?
Like if you find a dog on another planet,
well, maybe not, but where does it cross the line
into being human level?
If that's your view of it.
Right, attributes.
And that views problematic for a whole bunch of reasons
because as soon as you start assigning it to qualities,
that opens up.
historically that is opened up. The ability for sinful humanity to then marginalize
certain people, people's types of people who may not possess those faculties as fully as others.
Right. Right. So an unbored child doesn't have reason or language. Right.
The disabled sometimes don't have whatever those things are and historically people have used that to
to try and argue.
you against the humanity of other humans.
Yeah.
But it betrays this kind of biological understanding
of what human beings are.
Not that biology has nothing to do with what we are,
but it's reductionist.
And it's missing a lot of what's going on in Genesis,
especially in paradise.
that like I remember you know I know I often say on this show when I was a kid I
thought whatever whatever and but it turns out that a lot of the things that I
thought when I was a kid are in fact the sort of generic version of what a
lot of people believe about things so like what do people say what was the
Garden of Eden like right well the sort of this tropical paradise although there
was one there is actually there's a the the Greek Orthodox Cathedral in
and Worcester, Massachusetts has paradise.
and it's dome, but a lot of it, you know, it does look very tropical, but then there's parts,
if I remember correctly, that actually has like pine trees and stuff. So there's, you know, what is
paradise? And a lot of people think of paradise as being, you know, sort of tropical resort, right?
And, you know, Adam and Eve are kind of walking around in this beautiful tropical, and we use that word
paradise, don't we?
To, and just, you know, it's just beautiful
and there's all kinds of food available.
you don't have to work and it's like this extended vacation, right? But that's not actually
the image that Genesis gives. Right. Yeah. And it wasn't paved over nor did they put
in a parking lot. But yeah. So that's a pop culture reference I did get. Okay. When
you mentioned pine trees, I was going to throw in C is for Konafer, but no one would get
that one. So I'm not me but um
So, yeah, so the difference between a human and a chimpanzee is not a handful of genes.
Yeah.
And that's not how Genesis presents it.
And so this is where we have to go back to the creation of man and why the big thing is why humanity was created.
And so when we go back to creation of humanity, of course, is the culmination of the creation account.
creation account.
in Genesis 1. Technically it bleeds over into the first couple verses of Genesis 2, but
everybody shorthands it as Genesis 1. And so we get this picture in Genesis 1, and we're
going to talk about it in a couple different ways because there's a lot going on there
to say the least. And we're not going to talk about how long ago it was. So sorry.
Yeah, sorry everybody.
This is not that show.
Yeah.
But so one of the sort of trajectories through it is that much of the language that's used over the course of Genesis 1
regarding the creation of the world is language that you also find in ancient near Eastern accounts of the building of temples.
Yeah, right.
This is cool stuff.
Listen to this, everybody.
This is really cool.
This is, again, you're never gonna read the beginning of...
Genesis the same way after we did.
I love this part.
So sorry.
That's okay.
So the ancient Erees, these accounts
of the constructions of temples,
I'm not talking about like the contractors diary.
Like day three, we put up the studs.
You know, like, you know.
But there are these tax about the constructions of temples
where the constructions of these,
especially the ancient temples,
We're seeing it.
as sort of these mythic events that the God whose temple it was took part in with the
people building it.
So, there are these accounts.
Sometimes the temples almost build themselves, right?
So, this is, that's the kind of text I'm talking about, though, to give you an idea.
So, these are these important myths and the sense of stories that people participate in
These temples would be dedicated and
and re-dedicated ritually with celebrations that participated in these stories and re-enacted
these stories.
But so once the temple was built, in terms of the actual construction, and these temples
took the form, gods were believed in the ancient Near East to live on mountains and in gardens.
or sometimes gardens on mountains.
Right, that's what I mean, yeah, both.
Yeah, yeah.
It's a garden at the top of the mountain,
and that's where the god lives.
Right, which in many ways explains why it is
that you can find temples and churches,
which are just temples to Yahweh.
Often as possible, built up on hills
or in the highest place of a city,
Right.
Yeah, right. Exactly. Exactly. You know that and and I've heard sometimes heard it explained like well
That's just so they're you know, they're visible from everywhere. I was like well
Not exactly. It's actually because of this ancient belief about sacred geography
That gods live on high places. I mean you think in Greek Greek religion the gods live on Mount Olympus
right
And so there's this participation.
with human-made temples in this sense
that the divine resides upon top of mountains
or in gardens, and even within,
like even within an Orthodox church,
usually the altar area is physically higher.
So even if it's not built on,
even if the church isn't built on a mountain,
there's kind of a mini-mountain of sorts
within the church, right?
That the altar itself at least
is sort of elevated above everything else,
if it all possible, which is why, you know,
when a
I've gone to, you know, not usually Orthodox churches,
although I've been in one or two Orthodox churches
where this was the case.
But some other kinds of churches
that are actually shaped more like theaters
where you get a raked house, so to speak,
you know, where all the pews are.
And then the lowest point in the place
is where the worship is being centered.
That's just, that's kind of messed up.
Yeah.
Well, I'm end.
I know people love...
what we do this. The relationship between, for example, Greek tragedy taking place at a
low place and its connection to ritual is a discussion for another time.
Yes, right. We will get to that in a few years.
But so this is why you have Ziggurat and Pyramid structures all over the place because it's
a man-made mountain of God. Right. Right. Right.
And then so mountains are places that are inaccessible.
Gardens, I mean, if you know anything about the Middle East, right?
Lush gardens are not common, especially not naturally occurring ones.
Right.
But so this would be the place where the gods enjoy their life.
And so this imagery is taken up obviously in Genesis with the whole idea of the Garden
of Eden.
Right.
And it continues throughout the Scriptures.
Additionally, in the ancient Near East, God's typically lived in tents on top of those
mountains.
And so again, we'll discuss this at some point.
The Tabernacle and Moses entering the Tabernacle on top of Mount Sinai and St. Peter talking
about the Tabernacles at the Transfiguration on Mount Teibor, but that'll be in the future.
But so this temple imagery carries on.
So when Solomon...
the temple, there's all of this garden imagery around it. So in Genesis 1 we
have this construction of the temple and in these temple construction accounts
sort of the last step is that the the image of the deity, what we would call
the idol which was seen to be a body that was created for the God, would be
brought in and installed at the center.
And then they had a ceremony called the opening of the nostrils of the image, the idol, in which they believe the spirit of the God would come in
to inhabit it and be sort of trapped there.
Yeah, so what, I mean, what would that ceremony look like?
Like what would they do to make that happen?
Well, there were a whole series of things.
The odd just the physical installation of it.
It would be dressed in certain ways, not all that unlike the vestments of the high-prease
later in Exodus, but again, that's a topic.
Interesting.
Yeah, yeah.
But it would be dressed, they would bring food for it because the trade-off was, once
you had the God sort of trapped there in the image, you then would come and take care
of the God by feeding it, changing the clothing.
caring for it right and in return you would expect it through doing the rituals
you would expect that spirit to do certain things for you. Yeah to account for
that and so the ritual of the opening of the nostrils was sort of the beginning
of that right so the first dressing the purification of the space usually
with incense and a lot of blood and purification of it.
and then that would then allow the spirit to enter in.
Right. And then the relationship of that to what's happening in Eden is exactly reversed
that instead of mankind building a temple or a garden and putting his idol in it and
and opening the nostrils to...
trap the God inside the idol, you get God builds paradise on a mountain. The Yahweh, the
Father, Son, Holy Spirit builds this, puts his own image into it, which is man, and then
breathes the breath of life into him and establishes him there to image him.
right? So it's so it's yeah exactly so
So, you know, idolatry, rather than, so, you know, Genesis is not imitating idolatry,
rather what's happening is that idolatry is actually reversing what happened in reality
in Genesis. You know, that it's a kind of inversion, you know, that idolatry is inversion of God's creation of man.
you know, and so instead of God creating man for himself as his own image, you get man
creating
an image to trap a God for his benefit.
You know, the other way, it's very selfish, very man centered.
And I remember when I first learned about this,
again, I blew me away, and I thought,
wow, I never saw that happening there.
But it's interesting, the kinds of details
that are there when you actually then look at it, right?
Then the idea of God shaping man out of the dust of the earth
and breathing into him, all of these details
make way more sense within
this context of how ancient peoples understood the way that a temple was set up and what you
did in it when you were there. And of course, again, like another detail, that instead of mankind
having to dress an idol and take care of it and feed it, you have God taking care of his
image, feeding him, providing for him. It's exactly the opposite of idolatry. Idolatry is the mockery
of the creation of man and Genesis.
really cool. Yeah, it's completely inverted and turned on its head. Yeah, the idea of
pagan religion, the idea is here are the rituals you do and the things you do to make,
get the spirits to do what you want them to do or need them to do. Right, right. As opposed to
God creating an image for himself within his creation.
to do certain things for him.
Right?
Yep.
And so yeah, that is a...
That is a complete switch.
And this is what's behind,
this understanding of idolatry is what's behind most of the critiques of idolatry.
Well, we're all of them in the Old Testament and most of them outside the Old Testament
that come from a Jewish perspective.
Right? What's being critiqued is...
It's like okay so
you went and you cut down a tree and you took some pieces of that tree and you
built a fire and cooked food and you took some other pieces and you used them to
patch up your roof and then you took another piece and you carved a god out of it
and then you took it and you brought it to this temple and put it there and you
had to you know put nails and fasteners to make sure it went tip over and you
have to go in there and dress it and you have to go in there and feed it and you
have to go in there and take care of it because it can't do any of those things
for itself.
right? This spirit that you're worshiping. But now you want that spirit to control the weather for you.
Right. Yeah, it's sort of it's interesting how kind of blatantly kind of in your face that is,
right? Like like look pagans, your God is just such a wimp. I mean, that's what it comes that's really what it comes down to.
And it's it's, you know, that that that theme that is repeated throughout scripture, that this is that that Yahweh is the God
is the God who can
control, you know, that everything just simply obeys him. Right? And you know, that's why the disciples
marvel when Jesus rebukes the wind and the waves on Galilee. Like, who is this that the wind and the
waves just obey him? You know, like no, no spirit can do that. You know, accept the one true God. He's
the only one who simply commands and things happen. You know, there's no struggle. There's nothing like
that and you know then the apologetic is like
Look, Pagan, look how pathetic your God is.
Just, I mean, what you say about what your God can do
and about what you need to do in order to interact with your God
is so much smaller than the way that the one true God
who created the heavens and the earth revealed himself
and said, this is how we interact with Him.
And nonsensical.
Can't clean Himself or prop Himself back up
if He tips over but can help your wife get pregnant.
Right.
Right. It makes no sense, right? Yeah. But so as mentioned, God creates an image in his
creation in order to get certain things done. And so this is sort of the other trajectory
through Genesis 1 that I mentioned before, where God in this work of creation, at the beginning
of it. I beginning of Genesis 1, there.
After God creates the heavens and the earth, there are these two problems.
In Hebrew, it's funny because it rhymes. The world is tohoo of bohoo,
which the King James Version translates as formless and void.
Formless and void. Yes. And formless means sort of chaotic disorder, right, out of order.
and void is empty. So this is the
two problems. It's this chaotic mess and it's empty. And so on the first three days of creation
God puts things in order, right? He separates the light and the darkness. He separates the sky
from the sea. He separates the dry land from the sea, and puts those things in order. And then in
the second set of three days which correspond. So on the first day he separated light and dark.
on the fourth day he fills the heavens with the sun moon and stars. Right? And a lot of the
fathers by the way have this is the point at which the angels are created. Right. Right. And then on
the fifth day, right, he had on the second day he had separated the sky in the sea. On the fifth
day he fills the skies and the seas with life. And then on the third day he
separated the dry land from the water.
On the sixth day, he fills the dry land
with life culminating in human beings.
So, three days taking care of the formless,
three days taking care of the empty.
But then once, what's been is created?
I never saw that pattern before, actually,
so that's pretty cool.
I'll give credit to my old professor Meredith Klein.
That's...
who pointed me to that, but you find it in Thomas Aquinas and even some of the fathers.
That pattern. So then when Adam is created, when man is created, he's given this command
to fill the earth and subdue it. And those two things conform to the two problems still.
Yeah, right so
Eden, this may blow some people's minds too, but Eden isn't the whole earth, right?
We're given a location of it.
Yeah, yeah.
We get geographic details.
It's a garden in a particular place.
It's not the whole earth.
And so, Adam is told to fill the earth and subdue it, right?
So filling is filling.
Subdued, the word they're translated subdued actually means to conquer, like to take a city.
conquered.
and take something, take control of it, put it in order.
And so Adam is charged to continue that work.
So expand Eden.
Yes, basically.
Yes.
To go out of Eden and take Eden with him.
Right.
And it continue to continue that act of creation of subduing the world,
putting it in order and filling it with life.
Right.
And hopefully not getting too much ahead of ourselves,
that's exactly what we're called to do at the end of the Divine Liturgy
is to take the church which is eaten and to bring that into the world and expand the church.
To churchify the whole creation.
The dismissal is arguably the most important part of the Divine Liturgy.
Right. Right. So when we do...
So stay for it. Yeah, we have to be safe for it.
I just think for everybody.
And don't...
If I may make a controversial statement here, don't send people off to Sunday school or to coffee
hour or wherever until that final amen because we're being sent out in that dismissal to expand
Eden. That's what's going on. We've participated in Eden and now we're taking Eden on the road and
and laying claim to new territory for it.
So yeah, that is pretty mind-
It's going pretty cool pretty cool and and right off the bat
We see Adam get to work on the subduing part. That's what the the whole naming the animals thing is about yes
It's not about you know, what should I call that stripey horse? I'll call him a zebra
Yeah, yeah like God saying look
I can't think of anything to call these things. So maybe Adam you can come up with something. Yeah
So what we find this is especially common in
the Hittite archaeology, the Hittites were in what's now Central Turkey, South-South-South-South.
Yes, and we're a Indo-European language group, right?
Yes.
Yeah, right, which is super rare in that area in that time.
Yeah.
And what we find is we find a lot of these sort of bar relief sculptures
that depict a new king.
sitting and holding a read and
naming a bunch of wild animals yeah
So this was an image
That was symbolic a sort of kingly authority related to this idea of subduing right because the wild animals are
sort of the wild beasts are the image of that chaos and out of control element of creation. Yes, right and
and so him sitting in
And if you look at especially very early iconography,
orthodox iconography of Adam naming the animals,
you'll see he's a lot of times sitting on a rock
and holding a reed.
He's got the reed.
Right.
And he's saving the animals.
Yeah, so the reed is kind of a scepter, right?
Is that what's going on there?
Yeah.
And of course then, when Christ is in his passion,
he's given a reed to hold in his hand
Bye.
which they, you know, the Roman soldiers don't know what they're doing, but they're basically declaring him the new atom when they do this.
This is also what's behind that weird verse in St. Mark's Gospel where in his account of Christ going out into the wilderness before his temptation, it says that he's out in the wilderness with the wild animals.
So, St. Mark is setting up this image of Christ being out there with the animal.
and then lo and behold, the devil shows up to tempt him.
Oh wow.
Just like we see in Genesis 2 and 3.
But so this dominion part is, Adam gets a start on that.
Right.
But then after he's done with that, God says,
well, it's not good for him to remain alone upon the earth,
meaning we've got this one human.
He can't fill the earth with life as one human.
Right.
And so this is the problem that results in the creation of woman in Genesis 2.
It's not that Adam is bummed out that he has anybody to talk to because God is there.
Yes.
Presumably Angelic beings are there.
Yeah.
He's lacking for conversation.
And it's not like he knew about women so he was bummed he didn't have-
one available because there's literally no one had ever conceived of a, you know, no pun intended.
Yeah.
Considerable woman.
Yeah, it's about filling the earth.
Right.
You know, about the two of them being sub-creative with God's grace and, you know, perpetuating,
not just perpetuating but expanding, you know.
and having more people than to be involved in God's sub-create.
And be involved sub creatively in God's creative acts of bringing order to the world and so forth.
So yeah.
Right. And so in the same way, well, in a more full way, because what we talked about last time with the Nephilim, with the giants, is a demonic parody of this.
them trying to have their own images.
You know, right?
People in their image and likeness,
so they are to bring their work to fruition.
Right.
Part of the purpose.
and the gift given to humanity by God is this participation in God's work in the world.
That the work God is doing in the world to bring it to completion and maturity and perfection
is work that he shares with us in this world.
Yeah. Yeah.
So, well, you know, I think that that's a good stopping point.
So, why don't we go ahead and let's go ahead and take a...
our first break. And when we get back, we're going to start taking some of your calls, and
we're also going to discuss what all of this means in terms of as the story begins to roll
down through the Old Testament. So let's go ahead and take a break.
Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung will be back in a moment to take your
calls on the next part of the Lord of Spirits. Give them a call at 855-237-2346. That's
A-F-R-E-D-O.
So here's a question for you.
What does it mean to think Orthodox?
What have the unspoken and unexplored premises and presumptions underlying what Christians
believe?
Orthodox Christianity is based on preserving the mind of the early Church.
It's phronema.
Dr. Gigi Constitito brings her more than...
40 years experience as a professor, Bible teacher, and speaker to bear in explaining what the
Orthodox Phronoma is, how it can be acquired, and how that Phronoma is expressed in true Orthodox
theology as practiced by those who are properly qualified by both training and a deeper relationship
with Christ.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits, the Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father
Stephen DeYoung.
If you have a question, call now at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF radio.
Welcome back.
This is the second part of our show and we'd like to take your calls.
can call us just as you heard the voice of Steve saying 85
5 AF radio 8552372346 and we'd love to hear voices and talk to you a little bit.
So we were just talking about subduing the earth as part of the original charge given to
Adam and how that means essentially kind of expanding Eden and bringing God's creative
works and his order and his beauty into all the world.
So that's what we're going to continue to talk about now.
And.
you know, it expands outward.
So even though Adam fails,
God continues to work in the same way.
You know, God is God.
So we see his character
in the way that he interacts with mankind
and part of it is to continue to try to get mankind
to engage in this commission of bringing his rule
and order and beauty to the whole of creation.
So let's continue the conversation.
Father. Right, so yeah, obviously things go wrong. And Adam and Eve do leave paradise, but they don't bring it with them.
Yep.
And but that doesn't then say, well, God has to scratch his head and say, well, plan a didn't work.
Yeah, what do I do now? What can I come up with? Right?
But rather, this continues to be what humanity is foreign.
called to do. And in terms of the immorality of our particular discussion, obviously there's
a lot more that could be said here, but we're eventually going to get to the Theotokos here.
So yes, right. People like we want to talk this episode about the Theotokos. We particularly
want to focus on this as we talked about how the image of Adam naming the animals and
this of doing is this kingly image.
Right.
And so we want to talk a little bit about how that then...
develops as we go deeper into the Old Testament.
And so first, you know, with sort of nascent Israel, we have, you know, the first leader
is Moses.
And then after this episode with where his father-in-law, Jethro, gives him some advice.
It says, look, Moses, you're one guy, you're wasting your time listening to people argue
about who's store, who's goat.
You need some help here to judge the people, to govern this mass of people that you've
led out of Egypt.
And so that's when the elders of Israel are sort of officially appointed.
Yes.
The Greek presbyters of Israel, the elders of Israel.
And there are 70 of them.
Yes.
or 72. Yeah, exactly. Very, very important.
all throughout the Bible. And we're not like doing numerology, magic, sorcery here. It's just like when you see the same number appear over and over again, and it links up over and over again, you have to ask yourself why that's happening.
So just taking note there's either 70 or 72 elders who help govern Israel.
Right.
And the reason that's significant, we've already talked about this some in some previous episodes.
That there were.
Uh.
70 or 72 sons of God in the divine counsel when we first talked about that idea and
They were assigned as we talked about in Deuteronomy 328 and
As it connects to Genesis 11 in the story of Tower of Babel Tower of Babel
They were assigned to shepherd the
70 nations which are listed in
Genesis 10 yep and
and...
It's also going to be not coincidental in Christ's ministry that he appoints 12 disciples,
who he says are going to sit on 12 throes and judge the 12 tribes of Israel, and then he appoints 70 apostles.
Exactly.
Right, for the 70 nations.
And he even has within the twelve he has three pillars,
as St. Paul calls them, St. Peter James.
James and John and that pillar language goes back to Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob as the pillars
of Israel.
I don't know why I didn't ever make that connection before, but there it is everybody.
So, learning something tonight.
But so these structures of leadership, I don't want to go too far down this road, but
these structures of leadership in terms of the government of Israel are carried over into
the government that Christ puts over his
his nascent church in terms of the leadership. So this doesn't just go away. But so what we see now is we have Moses and then we have these 70 or 72 elders probably 72 since there were 12 tribes and that gives you six from each tribe.
But it's rare with these 70 elders and so this is an image then already of the divine council. This is an icon
of the Divine Council, where you have the one authority,
but then also this Council,
surrounding them in leadership.
And this is also going to be picked up by the early church
in the idea of having a single Episcopost,
Bishop or Overseer, however you wanna translate that,
surrounded by pressmeners.
right, which then is as we mentioned in our
second episode, we were talking about the Divine Council and we talked about that architectural feature,
the Sin Thronon, which looks like a sort of a little mini-stadium behind the altar, thrown in the
middle, lots of seeds next to them onto the right and left, the thrown in the middle is for the
Bishop, the other seeds are for the Presbyters. And so this then, once Israel's in the land,
This is going to come into the idea of the monarchy in Israel.
later the divided monarchy in Israel and Judah where you have a king and then that king's
court, that king's council. Right. Okay, so here's a little wrinkle. You know everyone who's
read 1 Samuel 8 knows that in that chapter the people of Israel comes to the prophet Samuel and
say we want a king like the other nations and Samuel goes to God and says they've rejected me
and God's
They've not rejected you. They're rejecting me because they don't want me to rule over them
But give them a king anyway, and oh by the way, it's gonna be bad
Right, and so you you come away from that like I remember you know when I
Rhyroid that
My impression was like okay well
Monarchy's okay, but certainly definitely not really endorsed by God here
He kind of you know sort of says wow
Okay, here's your king, but
Yeah
But that's not really what's happening there, is it?
Or at least it's not looking at the details closely enough, right?
Right, right.
And I know that's how people have been taught to read that passage.
Yeah.
I mean, that's how I was taught to read.
Yeah, because American Christianity is purest and Christianity.
Yeah.
Right, first great awakening, it comes from Puritanism.
If there's one thing Puritans don't like, it's the institutional church.
But if there's two things they don't like, it's the institutional church and monarchy.
Yes, right.
So in that...
gets written then into the American Constitution where there's this idea that no church should
be established. Right, right there in the First Amendment. Yep. Right. And we're not going
to have any kings around these parts. Exha, no title, no big titles, you know, nobles.
And so that was sort of a go-to passage for them to say, hey look, there it is. Yeah,
that monarchy, no good.
We need to get rid of it and have sort of a straight
theocracy.
which is how they pictured Israel before that. Now I would point them to the book of judges and ask
them how well that went. But the point being that we have to take this text in first Samuel in the
context of previous its succeeding passages that talk about kingship. So the first place we have to
to go is to Deuteronomy 17-14-20.
which is Deuteronomy the end of the Torah,
but in the Torah, so preceding this.
And Deuteronomy is not disconnected from the books that follow.
The books that follow Deuteronomy, the historical books,
including for Samuel, are called by scholars
the Deuteronomistic history.
Because what you find when you read them
is that the theological principles in Deuteronomy
that are described there in the Torah.
Sort of play out in the historical narrative. It's not just giving what we would call modern day objective history
Right, this happened then this happened and this happened but it's written from a perspective from the perspective of
This is God's teaching his Torah. This is what should be happening and oh look. It's not happening
Yeah, or here here and there maybe it is happening a little bit
What so a Deuteronomy
It gives commandments for when you have a king
you
Right? It says when you come into the land and you want a king, don't have a foreign king,
has to be an Israelite, he's not to multiply wives to himself.
Interesting.
Yeah, so there's stuff before it saying, look, when you're going to get a king, this is what
you should do, and that's the context of the rejection of what the people are asking for.
But in some sense, then giving them what they ask for.
The king is to
The main commandant for the king there is that he is to make a copy for himself of the Torah
to copy and to study it and to learn it.
But so all these commands have already been given centuries before we get to them asking for a king to Samuel.
And also it says in Judoranami that they should wait for the king who God is going to send them.
Yeah. Right. Right.
And this is the other problem. They're not waiting.
for the king god is going to send them they're demanding one right now.
Yeah, which is essentially kind of a repeat of the problem in Eden, right, where Adam and Eve
eat of the tree of the knowledge of good and evil, but they, but it's not they were never going
to have access to it is that they weren't ready for it yet. Right. And like we talked about with
in the context of the Nephilim, right, knowledge that they were ready for. Technology, etc. Yeah.
and it's the same kind of grasping.
And what they ask for when we
read this text in Samuel in detail or in first kingdoms if you're reading the Orthodox study Bible in detail, they say we want a king like the other nations, so that's strike one.
Right? Because not coincidentally, remember the other nations had like God kings.
Yeah, and they were kind of like warlord slash high priests.
Yes. So that's strike one.
Strike two is they say that they want one of these kings like
other nations so that he will lead us out and lead us back in. Yeah. When you say, well,
military. Yeah. What you might say, what does that mean in English? But that's a military
reference. Yeah. Right. That's going out to battle. Right. And then coming back victorious.
And why do they ask for that? Well, all through Joshua, all through the period of the judges,
into Samuel is the last judge. It's God who leads them into battle.
Right in many cases
literally. Yes. Right. Like he's appearing there and fighting in the battle with them. Yes.
He's leading them into battle and they're going to be victorious when they're following his lead.
Right. Is the idea. Whether, when they're following his will, they'll be victorious because he will
fight for them. Well, they're not so happy with that. Remember what we said about idolatry?
trying to get God to do what you want. So they decided in the chapters immediately,
this demand for a king, they decided, hey, we want to go out to war. You know what? Let's take the arc of the covenant with us.
And we put it in front. Yeah, we'll put it in front. And when we march out with that in front, God will have to, yeah, we will have to come and fight for us.
And we'll use the arc to get him to do what we want.
literally idolatry. Yeah. And so God says no. And not only are they badly
defeated but the arch
gets captured and taken by the Philistines.
And then there's this whole series of stories where the Philistines try to put it in one
of their idols temples and all the idols all over and bow down to it.
Yeah.
And it's not that God abandons the Yark.
And then they get a bunch of everybody starts getting boils and plague.
And so the Philistines get the picture and say, hey, you know what, we need to get rid
of this thing.
Yeah.
And so they put it on an OX cart with no driver.
Yeah, and the oxen dutifully take the ark back to Israel
But so rather than learning from this hey, you know what? God doesn't even need us to carry the ark back
Right he doesn't need us to do anything for it. We need to get on his side and on his page
They take the opposite lesson of like well, we clearly can't trust him to lead us into battle
So we're gonna need a king
Guys
Like, we're responsible, yeah, we're responsible conclusion.
Right.
So that's why they're asking for a king.
It's the wrong kind of king, the wrong time, the wrong way.
It's not the wrong reason.
It's not the wrong way.
It's the wrong reason.
Yeah, because like if God is just simply rejecting the idea of a king,
then why would he present himself as king of kings?
Right.
That would not be the term.
Right, he presents us as a monarch.
surrounded by a council sitting on a throne. Right. So yeah, there's not a problem with that
in and of itself. And so they get Saul first and Saul is kind of a judgment on them.
We won't go through the whole story of Saul, but ultimately we come to David.
Yeah. And David is for the perspective of the Old Testament as close as you can get to the
ideal human
King. Right. Right. Right. Clearly, the scriptures are very honest about the fact that he was not ideal.
Yes. Right. Or, right. But he fulfills the law by repenting. Right. And he is, he is as close as
he would get. And so in that way, right, what we're saying when we say that is we're saying that
he, most fully of everybody who's a king in the Old Testament, is serving as this image of this
icon of God.
Right. Right. And the king is called to do that in a particular way, and that's in continuity
with what we were talking about before of this act of doing and doing. Right. Exactly.
Exactly. Establishing the justice of God, which is not who committed what crimes and what
punishments do they get, but rather about putting everything in order. Again, it's the exact same,
Right, as you're saying, it's the exact same thing we see with it.
Adam, who's been charged with expanding Eden. You know, the King God's King is charged with
making his place paradise, setting it in order, you know, making sure that it's just, you
know, all of that stuff. And David is the one who does that more than, you know, more and
better than anyone else. He's not perfect.
The ancient concept of justice, which is like
in Egyptian concept or Mishpad in Hebrew is the idea that everything is in its proper place
functioning properly fulfilling its purpose and so you have peace
right and and everything is good and at rest. And so this is this is the job of the king is
to participate in what God is doing in bringing about justice. Which means countering injustice.
And so this is what he's
to do. And so because of this, because he is serving as an icon in this way, he becomes
the icon of that king who God promised back in Deuteronomy, the king who he would send.
David isn't the king who he would send. But he is the image of that king who he would
And that's again imaging is fulfilling the the character of your father, you know
of the one whom you are imaging, participating in his works,
doing the things that he does.
It's not just a matter of looking like him or whatever.
And this episode isn't about this,
but if you think about that imaging,
how that relates to iconography,
I mean, it just, wow, that opens things up pretty significantly
in terms of how we understand iconography,
that is participation and continuation
of the thing the person that's being imaged, right?
So yeah, yeah, yeah, and so because of this this is what what's sometimes called the covenant with David
This announcement that Nathan the prophet comes and makes to David
This is the context of that of connecting
David to this king who is going to come and that this king who is going to come
Who's going to become known as the Messiah the anointed one which is one of the terms for a king because that's how you became king you were anointed anointed yeah
This, we read about this in two different places.
It's not just the Gospels where we have multiple versions of the same story.
This is also true of the Old Testament because we have
First and Second Samuel, First and Second Kings, or First through Fourth Kingdoms.
And then we have First and Second Chronicles.
Yeah.
And I'm guessing these represent various ways that the same stories have been written down.
And then they're compiled together to be what we now understand as the Old Testament scripture.
Right.
Right. And they have different perspectives. First, the fourth Kingdoms is really talking about the
justness of God's judgment, indistroing Israel and sending Judah into exile, showing the descent into
sin and madness that resulted in that. Whereas, first and second Chronicles were written later
in the exile, and they're more about this messianic hope that the line of David is going to produce this
this Messiah. But in the two different versions of that promise from Nathan to David.
One of which is in Second Samuel or Second Kingdom 716, the other one of which is in First Chronicles 17 verse 14
and the surrounding verses. There's this subtle change in language.
Right. Which is cool. This is cool.
In the Second Samuel Second Kingdom's version, the promise is that Nathan says to David,
David Yor, meaning David's house and
kingdom and throne will be established forever.
Right.
And then the second one is in his descendants.
And then in first chronicles, 1714, the language is almost the same except it says that
his descendants will be established in my meaning Yahweh's house and kingdom and throne
forever.
Right.
Yep.
So when you take those together...
You have a son of David who is going to be a king of Messiah and who is going to sit on both David's throne and Yahweh's throne.
Yeah.
And that's not David because David does not sit on the throne of God.
Right.
Yes.
And so this is both a critical point for the development of the whole idea of the Messiah.
who Jesus is going to be, spoilers, right?
But, but it's also, as we mentioned,
one of the basic building blocks,
where we talk about, you know,
we use our theological term,
calcedonian Christology.
The idea that comes out of the later church councils
that Christ is both God and man,
fully and completely, right?
again this isn't some idea
evolves over time. We're in the Old Testament. It's in the Old Testament. It's part and parcel of
this Old Testament promise. And Christ Himself tries to point the Pharisees to it, right? When
He, when He said, quotes the psalm and says, the Lord said to my Lord, sit at my right hand
till I make your enemies, your footstool at your feet. He says, how, if the Messiah is David's son,
and how does he call him Lord?
right because normally no sun would ever be called Lord by his own father. Right. It's
right. It never goes that way. But because Christ is God, he is the Lord of David as well as
being his son. His son because he's human. So this is embedded right there in that very basic
promise. So and so yeah. So Christ moves the Davidic kingship which is this sort of icon of
God.
in his divine counsel into full reality where you've got he is God in his divine counsel because
he is Yahweh, he is the Son of God.
So rather than being you know David surrounded by his counsel being this icon right now that
is combined is the divine counsel.
David's throne and God's throne are the same throne that Christ sits upon.
Yeah.
Yeah, so we've got a call actually that's coming in from Cody who is in Texas and he has a question specifically about what we were just now talking about.
So Cody, are you there?
Yeah, howdy from Texas.
All right. Nice to hear your voice, Cody. Welcome to the Lord of Spirits podcast.
So my question relates to is the typology between...
you know, the Davidi Kingdom and the Queen Mother role that we see.
What other positions are there within the Kingdom, specifically relating to Isaiah 22-22?
I hear that a lot as a proof text, specifically in Roman Catholicism when they're talking about
you know the Prime Minister and Jesus quoting that in Matthew 1618 but
not as an apologetics specifically but how does the role of the prime minister of the
Davidi kingdom is it fulfilled in the new covenant?
That's a good question.
I don't know the answer to that, but maybe Father Stephen does.
Yeah.
So, the issue with the, and I'll go in the lower, the issue with the Roman Catholic interpretation
of that is not really their interpretation.
how they restricted to St. Peter.
So there is a connection in imagery there with the keys, with the cheef steward of David having the keys to lock and unlock.
That image is picked up, but the keys aren't only given in the Gospels to St. Peter.
right. They're also given to all of the apostles and so the Orthodox
understanding of the
that connection doesn't exist.
It's that connection exists,
but that the binding and losing is a function
of the church, rather than of a single bishop
within the church.
Right.
So yeah, that steward role is there.
There are other roles.
For example, we see going forward in the narrative
of David's life that Nathan the prophet
is part of his council.
Yeah.
see that as part of...
of the role that St John the Forerunner, and I'm sure we'll do it episode on St John the Forerunner at some point,
but that he takes on in the Divine Council.
So yeah, there are these other roles, and we're going to, I think the rest of the show now is going to be about that Queen Mother role that you mentioned.
Yeah, so does that, does that answer your question, Cody?
Yeah, I think so, and I think that things don't fit, you know, between the old testament and the New Testament fulfillment,
filming it. It's not a wonder
one mask, I guess, because we have one-queen mothers,
I'll see a total.
But I guess it's a type of and not a all-analysis phase,
I guess.
Right.
OK.
Well, thank you very much, Cody, for that call.
Thank you.
Good to hear from you.
Yeah.
So all right.
Well, the one thing that I wanted
to add about what we were just talking about about Christ
fulfilling the Davidic kingship.
being, you know, sitting on both the throne of David and of Yahweh, is that, you know,
we talked about David as an icon of God.
And one of the things that I was pointed out to me years and years ago, actually, when
I was still in my undergraduate studies, I recall one of my professors actually talking
about this question of how words function.
And of course, words are essentially in a way icons of the things that they talk about.
And he made the point.
And there's only...
one word that means himself, that doesn't point to some other thing. And that's the word
of God himself, Jesus Christ, the son of God. He's, he unites, you know, both to use modern
linguistic terminology, both, you know, refer and referent, right? He is the word who
means himself. Whereas all other words means something other than themselves. Like words
don't mean the sounds that are making.
referred to a thing. If I say book, I'm referring to the object, you know, not to those sounds, right?
So I always loved that and it was one of the ways that I began to understand what it means for
Christ to be the word of God. So yeah, cool, cool stuff. Okay. Well, we actually received a
a recorded message from Ben who had a question very much related to about what we're
just about to talk about. So our engineer this evening is Matyska Trudy. So Matyska, could you please
play that recorded message for us from Ben? Hi, fathers. This is Ben Bauman calling from Grand Rapids
Michigan. My question is in regards to the phrase the Queen stood at that right hand, kind of in
general. How would an ancient Jewish person have understood this? Would they have seen this as a
relation to something within their culture. What I'm getting at is the idea that as far
as I can remember, there aren't any queens of Israel mentioned in the Old Testament.
So how did they have really seen this? The Queen's to the right hand. What would that have
been in reference to in their minds? Thank you, fathers, and love the show.
All right. Well, that is an excellent question and we are going to discuss that as soon as
we get back from our second break.
So let's go ahead and go to break.
Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung
will be back in a moment to take your calls on the next part of the Lord of
Spirits. Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF Radio.
Hi, this is Father Evan Armitas, priest at St. Spirit
Beard and Greek Orthodox Church and Christ.
and Colorado, and the host of the Ancient Faith Radio Sunday Night Call and Show,
Orthodoxy Live. I am pleased to announce today the release of my first book for Ancient Faith
Publishing, titled, Toolkit for Spiritual Growth, a practical guide to prayer fasting and arms giving.
It seeks to provide a guide to the three basic and primary disciplines of Orthodox spirituality.
Through these disciplines, Christ opened for us a path that frees us from the disordered way of
life has become normal for many.
Even though their hearts and minds...
tell them otherwise. Please join me in exploring the three-legged stool of Orthodox spiritual practice,
prayer, fasting, and nomsgiving. Books now available at store.ancientfaith.com.
And the title once again is Toolkit for Spiritual Growth. I look forward to sharing it with you. God bless.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits, the Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen
the young. If you have a question...
Call now at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF radio.
Welcome to the third half of Lord of Spirits.
And we do want to hear from you.
So call us at 855-AF radio.
And this episode turns out to be very similar pattern
to a lot of our previous ones, where we say,
we're going to be talking about this.
And then we spend the first hour talking about things
that don't seem to be about that.
but actually
As we're about to discover, lead right up to it.
So first we had to establish what it means for man to be in the image of God and his role
in paradise.
Then we had to establish exactly what it means that Israel is governed by a king.
How that continues man's role in paradise, that exact same role.
And now that we've established this idea of the kingdom of Israel, as especially the court
of David in particular and we're going to
to talk about why David in particular,
not just because he's the best example of this,
but there's something about his kingship, his line
that's really important here.
And now we're getting to the point where,
where are we actually are gonna be speaking explicitly now
about the mother of Jesus Christ.
So, all right, well we got that question from Ben.
What would an ancient Israelite, ancient Jewish person
have thought about if we'd start...
about that phrase from the Psalms, the Queen,
stood at the right hand, which of course is the title
of this particular episode.
Yeah, so now in the third half we get to our topic.
Yes, and...
But you'll see how this is necessary.
We can't just jump in.
We have to set it up because otherwise it doesn't make any sense.
So what we see in, again, this close reading of
We will test it with...
what we see in terms of Queens, I do have to say to Ben when he said he didn't know of any Queens of Israel mentioned in the Bible.
I do have to say bro do you even Jezebel?
Yes, right.
But hopefully...
Maybe not a good example.
Yeah, right.
I mean when you're reading Psalm 45 you're like oh yes that's about Jezebel.
That's not about Jezebel.
No, not about Jezebel.
But so we do see that there's this pattern and it's unique
to Judah. It's unique to the southern kingdom of Judah. Because we have to
remember that Israel gets divided into the southern kingdom of Judah and then
there's the northern kingdom that is often just called Israel and that's where
you get, for instance, the, you know, the Ahab and Jezebo stuff, right? There's
it's two different places now. It gets split up. So there's two different
kingships happening. Right. And and it's important to give a little historical
context of this because we don't think about it this way.
Okay, the amount of time that Israel was united as one political entity is about a century.
Yeah, it's about a hundred years. Right. It's before that you just have tribes. Yeah.
And then Saul sort of manages to get most of the tribes into a loose coalition.
David really starts the monarchy and then everything spins out of control with his son Solomon.
And that's 80 years between the two of them.
And then things divide again.
The Northern Kingdom of Israel only existed for another about 200 years, a little less.
And then boom.
Yeah, so there was all over.
There was a political entity called Israel for a grand total of maybe 300 years.
Yeah.
Yeah, in the Old Testament.
last a little longer than that. It lasts another 140 years, a little less, 135. And then it is taken
into exile. And so just to give that perspective. And David was actually made King of Judah before he
became King of all of Israel. He had to settle a rival claim from one of Saul's sons. So Judah and
and the rest of Israel were never welded together that strongly.
It's sort of like the American...
north and south between the founding of the country and the Civil War.
Right? That's technically they were one country but it wasn't good.
Right. So uniquely in Judah, we see beginning with Solomon, the person who is considered to be
the Queen is not the favored wife of the King because the King was...
than one wife. Well, except they also had more than one wife in the northern kingdom.
Right. And in all of Judas neighbors. Right. Right.
Polytomy is the norm, especially amongst the powerful. Right. And so that, well, that's
an easy explanation. Sometimes you'll hear that from folks who don't want to go down
the trail. We're about to go down that, well, it's just because of polygamy. Right. You
have one mother, you have lots of wives, but there's often a fevered wife.
I'm going to write this one who's Jezebel for instance, you know, right, right.
Right. The wife of the heir or the mother of the heir, right? Yeah.
And so, yeah. So they dealt with polygamy and still having a queen who was the bride of the king
quite well in every other nation in the world except Judah. Right. Right. So, but so there's this unique
institution to Judah where the queen is reckoned as the queen mother. And this starts with,
I don't know if you want to read it from first Kings or third kingdoms, it starts with Solomon.
Yeah.
Okay, so this is first Kings or Third Kingdom's chapter two versus 19.
You may remember everybody that Solomon is of course the son of David, the immediate son of David,
and his mother is Bathsheba, who had been the wife of Uriah, whom David arranged to have killed
so that he could cover up his sin of adultery with Bathsheba.
So this is first Kings 219. Bathsheba, therefore, went unto King Solomon
moment.
to speak unto him for Adonizza,
and the king rose up to meet her and bowed himself under her
and sat down on his throne and caused a seat to be set
for the king's mother, and she sat on his right hand.
So it's another throne that he's sitting directly on his right hand,
which is... remember that... I mean, that's the place of honor after the king.
That's number
to basically acting that's the highest position the highest position without being king at the right hand. Yeah, right. Yeah.
Yeah, sure. I mispronounced one of those names there.
At a Niger. I don't know.
At a Niger is the usual English for it. It's actually a Doni. Yeah.
It's been my lord is Yahweh. It's what it. Oh, yeah. There go. Yeah. Sure. Um, but, um,
So this isn't just a thing that Solomon does because he loves his mom.
Right? This isn't just Solomon's a mom.
boy. It's not because I mean this is this you know within a king within a monarchy within
a traditional monarchy the king's court is the king's government right you know the the like
we don't think of this now because like if the you know say the president of the United States is
is sitting in meeting so many in the oval office he doesn't have a throne and the person at his
right hand is not the vice president necessarily you know it says it just doesn't work that way but
in a king's court the people in the court are the ones who are running the place again right so
just you know that's what the
divine counsel is in those gods' court.
Those positions at the right and left hand are particularly important, right?
Because when the king is sitting on the throne in judgment and he's making decisions,
the people who have access to him, right, in order to influence his decisions, right?
Or for him to seek advice, right?
Are the ones sitting at his right-handed and at his left hand?
Immediately next to him.
So these are this this is where why that comes up later
with St. James and John and their mother.
Right.
Okay, can we sit at the right hand on the left and say,
if you're a king though, right?
We want the top spots.
Yeah, that's reserved.
Those are reserved.
And actually have been for centuries upon centuries.
Yeah.
But so this is the position that's given.
And it doesn't stop with Solomon.
Right.
the as you go
through and I'm going to I'm going to rattle the verses off. No one's going to have time to look these up as I rattle them off
but I'm going to do my best Jack Van Impey because no one could reverse references faster than him. The late great Jack Van Impey
as you go through as you go through all of I'm not going to give all the chronicles references this is just
first-second gigs, they're paralleled in chronicles, every single one of them.
But for first and second...
say in case your third or fourth kingdoms, what we're going to see is that every time a new
king of Judah is coronated, there's this pattern, there's this stereotypical phrase that's used,
right, where they're named, they become the big king of Judah in a certain year, and then it says,
and his mother was, so and so. And those occur in 1 Kings 14, 21, 15, 2, 15, 10, 22, 42,
second kid.
18, 8, 26, 12, 1, 14, 2, 15, 2, 15, 13, 15, 30, 15, 33, 18, 2, 21, 1, 21, 19, 22, 1, 23, 31, 23, 36, 24, 8, and 24, 18.
Boom, that's right.
If you look at stuff of people, and I did, you will see, and so and so became king and his mother was.
And so and so became king and his mother was.
This is one of those details that...
Unless you're looking for it and understand what it means, you'll probably just roll right by it.
But again, like Father said, this is only the king of Judah. It is only the kings of David's line.
Not the Northern Kingdom of Israel. You don't get this pattern there. It's only here. They always mention who his mother is, and it's because the king's mother, the queen mother, is the one who is at his right hand.
And I
recall when looking into this by the way, if I could just interrupt, you know, I recall
when looking into this, this is so sort of institutionalized, right? It's so much an
office that there's actually, that you can actually get deposed from it, right? It's not
sort of automatic. Like, it happens one time when one of the king's grandmother is occupying
the position and she falls into idolatry and so he deposes her from it. You know, that,
But it's so much of an office that you can actually get...
kicked out of it. Yeah. And it's an office with power that you can use for evil because
there is an evil one at one point. Affiliah, who is one of the daughters of Ahab, who gets
married off to the king of Judah, and then decides to try to eradicate the line of David,
them all killed off so that she could put a hat and saw a habs line in the
and kingdom also.
But because she was in this green mother position,
she had the power to try to control who was going to be
the next king and to have people assassinated.
So this was a governmental role.
Yeah.
And so in the position then consists of,
it's not just someone who gives advice or influences
the king, but also someone.
Like if you know that someone is close to someone
power.
Then you will go to that person and say, hey, would you mind talking to the king and asking
for this?
I know he'll listen to you.
And so within a special, the human context, that makes total sense that his mom should
go to him and say, hey, I think we should do this.
So there's this role of the Queen Mother receiving petitions and passing them on a totally normal
thing for the person.
standing at the right hand of any king to be doing.
Right.
And it also goes the other way, where, and this is a place
where it is kind of analogous to our president and vice
president, where the president can say to the vice president,
I'm going to put you in charge of getting this through
Congress, right?
Or a delegation happening.
You in, right.
And so it's not, it's not delegating, it's not delegation
in the sense of like, I'm going to take some of my authority
and divest myself of it and give it to you.
like we do.
already talked about with the Saints, it's, I'm going to administer XYZ through you.
Through you.
You're going to be my representative.
You let them know this comes from me.
Yeah, exactly.
And being this mother, one of my kids, like when I said one of my kids to go fetch another
one, you tell them I sent.
Right.
So yeah, so that goes, that goes both ways with this office.
And as you mentioned, you know, you can read all those verses.
rattled off. If later with this is a recorded podcast you can go back and pause. But if you go and look in between, in between, it talks about the succession of kings in Israel is mixed right in there in the northern kingdom.
Never mentions their mothers.
Yeah.
So it's not the same habit.
Yeah, the same book.
So this is this is this unique institution with the Devinic king and the Devinic line.
So
So because the king, the Davidic king in particular, as the anointed one, has this particular
iconic imaging relationship with Yahweh the God of Israel, we get these Psalms, Psalm
45, from which the title of this episode came, is not the only one, but it's one of the
major ones.
these Psalms that are sort of oath to the beauty and the glory of the King of Israel.
Right? And this has something important to teach us about veneration too. Going back to a topic we talked about a couple podcasts ago that there's didn't seem to be a problem with a Psalm praising God's king.
right that that was not seen to be taking away somehow no you're only we
shouldn't be singing Psalms to the king we should only be singing Psalms
directly and about Yahweh
That's it, right? Why? Because the king is the icon of God in his rule. So honor given to the king
Passes to the one whom the king is the icon of right this is the is is honoring God because
That's his king who he established
right
But so when we get into Psalm 45 and into the details of this praise it includes not only the king
but also the
in.
in Hebrew it's Gabby Ra, this Queen Mother role.
And I don't know if you wanna read that.
Sure. Yeah, yeah.
So this is Psalm 45 beginning with verse nine
through 11 and then skipping to 13.
The Queen stands at your right hand
in gold from Ophere.
Listen, daughter, and consider and incline your ear
and forget your own people in the house of your father
because the King will greatly desire your beauty
because he is your Lord, worship him.
All right.
glorious is the daughter of the king within the palace. Her clothing is woven with gold.
Praising the queen. Praising the queen. And notice. And touch the tour directly. But also just
just like we were talking about with Psalm 110 and the Messiah being both
David's son and his lord. Notice that the
Queen we're talking about here is both the Queen Mother and the daughter. Yes. Yeah.
Right. Which that only works if the King is God. Right. So it's you know it
that Psalm does double duty. Just as David you know with the Lord said to my Lord in Psalm 110.
cool as so and so right and so with with
and his mother, right? What we would expect, if Jesus is the Messiah, if Jesus is the Christ,
then the announcement that Jesus is the Messiah, Jesus is the King, Jesus is the Davidic King,
would be immediately followed by Mary is his mother. And she is both his mother and therefore
the Queen Mother to his King and Messiah and his daughter because he's her
create.
and savior at the same time. And so that can only, that song can only really be fulfilled in
Christ and his mother. Yeah. She, she therefore is the mother of God and the daughter of God at the
same time. Because by, she's his mother by virtue of his humanity and his daughter by virtue of his,
his godhood. Cool. Cool stuff.
I don't know, I just, you know, when you get to the point where we've led up to now, all I can kind of do is marvel.
Right, it's just so astonishingly beautiful and, you know, it's just,
it's like a great poem that just sort of stretches over thousands of years, right?
And, you know, a poem that God is composing and everything comes into place and we see then,
you know, we're leading up to, we're just a few weeks away right now from the Nativity of Christ.
And so this is a perfect episode to...
have before our Nativity episode,
you know, that there she is holding God in her arms
as a child, and she is both his mother and his daughter
at the same time.
Cool.
Yeah, and so to be right to the point, indeed,
I am saying here that when the apostles
went out and preached the gospel,
The gospel is and we'll get
more into this I'm sure in the future the gospel is the report of Christ victory that
has led to him being enthroned as king.
And so when they're announcing that Jesus is the Messiah he has won this victory over
the powers and over death and over the powers of Hades they are also announcing who
his mother is.
I'm saying the Apostles did that.
You may say, well, how can you prove that?
And I say I can prove.
that. Oh, proven for me, Father, even you can just leave me hanging there. So,
and the way I can prove that is from one of the earliest anti-Christian writings that we have.
Okay. All right. So, you listen to this show for the deep cuts everybody.
This is it. This is so pretty deep. So around 150 AD, middle of the sound.
century, 151.60. There's a fellow named Celcis or Kelsus depending on who taught
you Latin, who was a pagan and who wrote what was considered by the church
fathers to be the most scathing and pointed, pointed by point pagan attack on
Christianity and the Christian gospel.
Yeah, he was doing a takedown.
Yeah, so this was his, you know, if this was on YouTube today, it would be Kelsus destroys
Christians.
Right.
So Kelsus would totally have been a YouTuber.
Yeah.
Yeah, he wasn't an atheist.
Right.
But he's irrationally like a lot of those YouTube apologists.
Yeah, and so.
We have to remember, Kelsey's now in 151.60, he's never been to a Christian worship service.
Right.
Because they didn't allow outsiders in, and he's a pagan and an opponent.
So he's only heard rumors about that stuff.
The stuff that he knows about the Christian gospel that he's attacking is just the stuff
that's in the public proclamation.
The stuff that Christians were preaching as they evangelized, right?
It went out.
Yeah.
So, the stuff that's on the website to put it in.
Right.
Modern terms, yes.
So all the stuff he's attacking is the stuff
that's publicly known.
This is what the Christians believe.
This is what they teach.
And in this case, he's specifically attacking the gospel.
He's attacking the idea that Jesus is God
and that Jesus is the Messiah.
He's the king.
Yeah.
Right.
Those are the two particular points he's attacking.
Because those, of course, are the central points
of the gospel itself.
Right.
And so we have a number of responses to calcists
written by different fathers.
and different early Christian writers. The most famous one is the one written by origin,
uh, Contra-Celsus, or Contra-Celsum, um, appropriately enough. Um, and we don't have the whole
text. Yeah. Calcissus is original whole text, but we could reconstruct a lot of it from the
church fathers and early Christian writers who quote him to respond to him. Right? Right. I think
You've got to put back together from the quotes.
Here's what he said. And if you're interested in early interactions with paganism, a lot of this anti-celsus literature goes really in depth into some of the ancient pagan beliefs.
Right. Like origins start talking about the piffy ends and likes with these like I mean deep cuts of
Greco-Roman paganism but
but anyway one of the things
that
Calcisco
after is Mary. And we find out pretty quickly that knows a bunch of stuff about Mary. Yeah,
right. Where did he get that from? Where did he get that from? Right. Where would he have
gotten that from? Because at she, I mean, we should remember, she was not an important person
as far as the world was concerned. Right. Right. No one was writing biographies of Mary, who was like
Jewish
court official or Roman. Right. The only people talking about her are Christians. Right. And so he's
hearing these things that he knows about her in the public, public proclamation of the gospel by
Christians. So she's a part of that proclamation. Right. And he thinks that attacking her is a way
to undermine the whole thing. So it's not just that like it's some detail that he heard them talking
about. Do you think this is part in a point?
important part of the proclamation.
And so I'm gonna, I'll read this quote.
Okay.
That's, yeah.
This is what, this is some of the things,
he says a lot of things, some of them very nasty,
but this is, this is some of the things that he says
about Mary.
He says that Christ was born in a certain Jewish village
of a poor woman of the country
who gained her subsistence by spinning.
It was improbable that the God would entertain a passion for her because she was neither rich
nor of royal rank, seeing no one even of her neighbors knew her.
So how is Kelsus attacking the Christian gospel by saying this Mary person is a nobody.
She's a peasant.
Nobody ever heard of her.
own neighbors, the other people the village probably didn't even know who she was.
Right. Why how could she be the mother of his pagan perspective? How could she be the mother of a king let alone the mother of a god?
Yeah. Yeah, because because recall in the ancient world
this idea of the rags to riches story or
you know, local boy makes good
You know the underdog wins that stuff is all nonsense to an ancient pagan. Right. Oh, if you're on top of
things, if you're, you know, that's because that's the way it's supposed to be the gods
set that up.
No one makes it big, you know, coming from nothing.
Or if there was somebody who came from humble beginnings, they'd tell all these stories
about how as a child, they were already exceptional in doing amazing things.
Yes, right.
Right.
And so, so Kelsa thinks that if I just point out that this, this God that they worship,
His mom is some nobody, then that just shows our ridiculous
this Christianity thing really is.
Right. She can't possibly have been the mother of a king.
Yeah. That's how he attacks the Christian gospel, which means
the Christians were going out there as part of the gospel and
preaching. She's the mother of the king and the mother of God.
Right. Which would have been important and meaningful for
Israelites, but
not important or meaningful to a pagan, right, in the same way. Right. Yeah. Yeah. So this is,
so 150, 160 AD, we're talking less than 50 years after the Apostle John died. Right. And long
and long before the canon of the New Testament is clearly recognizable all over the world.
Right. That her identity is the Queen Mother and the Mother of God is a central enough part of the
the Christian Gospel Pro...
that calcist thinks refuting it undermines the whole thing.
And I could add on a top of that, that 20 years later,
St. Irenaeus, who's a spiritual grandson of St. John,
is writing about how the Theotokos is the second.
Eve, right?
All of these other things, basically about his grandmother.
Yeah.
Right, the theological significance.
of his grandmother in God's purposes of redemption.
So this is not something that develops later, that comes into Christianity from paganism
in the fifth century or something.
Right.
This is the opposite.
This is the early Jewish.
This comes out of the Old Testament.
It's part of the gospel in that it's part of Christ's identity as king.
Yes.
and her.
the mother of God is part of his identity as God and those things are tied together in the
idea of the Messiah by David's throne. Right. And so therefore we get hymns like we sing all the time
of the Orthodox Church more honorable than the cherubim more glorious beyond compare than the
Seraphim. That's not just a way of saying she's really, really glorious. It's talking about her
position in the divine council because, you know,
think back to our first couple of episodes everybody, remember we talked about the Throne Guardians,
that line of himnography specifically is talking about the Throne Guardians who are at God's throne,
he's enthroned upon the chair when he's surrounded by the Set-o'feeh and they are the ranks of angels
that are the closest to him, right? They are at the very top of the Divine Council in that sense
And we're saying in this hymn that she's above them. Why?
She stands at his right hand.
She stands at his right hand. She's the Queen Mother.
He's the son of David.
Therefore, she's the Queen Mother in this line of Davidic kings.
And she's his mother, but she's also his daughter,
because he's God, the thrones of David and of Yahweh are united in Christ.
And so, because of who she is,
We cannot help but proclaim her as his mother.
as we proclaim the gospel. It can't be left off because otherwise we're
we're proclaiming a gospel that doesn't that has nothing to do with God's
kingship and his throne and being the son of David and the Messiah etc etc etc etc
if that doesn't blow your mind I don't know I mean this is the podcast
where we're where you know I'm blowing my mind we're you know but I mean if
that doesn't blow your mind I mean I you know it's just it's really astonishing
like she's not this add on, you know?
And it's certainly not like an attempt to import paganism into Christianity.
And it's none of that.
It's deep, deep all the way goes back to Genesis as we were just saying.
Amazing.
Yeah.
And so you may notice in most Orthodox churches behind, you know, in a high place above
the altar there is iconography of Christ and Throne.
And he is enthroned twice in that iconography.
As man he is sitting on his mother's lap.
Yes, and if you look at what's surrounding them as God he is enthroned upon the cherubum.
Right.
Yeah, and then on the icon of almost every orthodoxy canostasis, you see Christ, his icon right next to the Holy Doors,
to his right, to his right.
his mother to his left, the prophet of God, the forerunner whom we're going to talk about.
We will.
I promise you.
Yeah, we are definitely going to have a whole episode about John the forerunner.
That's we're looking at the divine council right there in the Akena Stasis as well.
And so in this role, she has that same sort of twofold ministry as part of the divine
counsel where she intercedes, meaning she prays, right, and passes on prayers, right,
from from us, from those in the church, and the other direction, right, where where God
or son works through her in his administration of the world in the same way we...
talked about him working through angels and saints in a general sense, but in a special
way through her. And so when you look at the prayers and hemnography surrounding the
feotokos, you see these two things. You see on the one hand that idea of seeking her
intercessions and her prayers for us. And you see this idea, often of protection and those
kind of things where it's talking about Christ's work.
miracles through her and through her prayers. And so that takes place in both
directions. What we're saying about her, we're saying is what we're saying about
all the saints, but her in this special unique sense as sort of the highest of
the saints and the closest of the saints, being in that right hand position,
in the same way that we talked about ranks of angels.
right in terms of their closeness to the throne of God.
She's not a different species from us,
but the place that she holds is different.
Yeah.
Wow, wow.
Well, all right, well given everything we just said then,
let's offer some final thoughts
to wrap up this evening's episode
about our Lady of Theotokos.
You know, I just
I just want to speak from a personal point of view.
I recall when I first encountered the Orthodox Church now 23 years ago, more than 23 years ago.
I had been raised evangelical Protestant and of course as an evangelical Protestant,
we did not venerate the Virgin Mary.
Now I wasn't in a kind of anti-Mary part of Protestantism,
but it was just sort of not there.
We sort of liked her and kind of rolled her out a little bit more around Christmas.
But not really important.
And I remember, though, when I encountered the Orthodox Church,
I had Orthodox people who asked me, you know,
like, is marrying a problem for you, right?
Because there's a lot of people, a lot of Protestants,
who, when they encounter Orthodoxy,
that they just can't get over that, right?
Like, it's just kind of too much, you know?
But I remember at the time, when they asked me that question,
When they asked me that question, I thought to myself,
And I said, you know, I, no, she's not. She's not. It just sort of her place just sort of
made sense to me. Now I didn't understand everything we just been talking about, probably almost
maybe maybe 1% of it at the time, you know. But I remember that it just, it made sense to me.
And I think the reason that it made sense to me is because of this, this sense of what Orthodox
worship is right that it is entering into the the
presence of God into his throne room and offering sacrifices to him.
And so within that image of what worship is, when in that reality,
I shouldn't just say image, but when that, you know, that experience of what worship is,
if there's a king there, then it makes sense that, uh,
that those who surround him would have this very elevated place, you know,
not to be elevated above mankind to be some different kind of thing.
You know she is still
human, just as I'm human, just as you're human. But nonetheless, it made sense to me. And then
over time as I began to learn how to sort of get to know her and so forth, it became just more and
more natural to ask her for her help, right? Because she's close to the king and it makes sense to be
able to ask her for that help. But when I got to the point where I understood what we were just now
talking about and how how utterly deep the roots of her
position go into the old testament. Then there was, for me, there was this experience of,
I don't know, it was an experience of beauty, right? It was like hearing a big symphony,
and then there's that final last note, you know, where everything resolves, and all the
melodies come together, and it's just glorious, and then, you know, if you're at a concert
You stood up and you...
you know, clapping and just feel this elation, right? That's how I felt when I encountered
this understanding of the Queen Mother as shown so many places in the Old Testament and then
fulfilled in the New Testament and then preached as we noted by the Apostles. And my hope is that
whoever you are listening this evening or whenever you're listening that you might have some of
of that same experience.
That's my thoughts, Father.
Yeah, I think sometimes the things we've just been talking about,
about the Theotokos and about her, about the Virgin Mary in general,
our treatise is kind of ancillary, right?
This is sort of a thing, an issue to itself
And you know, it's not central to-
theology, we have our theology, we have our Orthodox theology and our Orthodox worship,
and then there's this sort of Mary piece and a lot of people kind of have trouble with
it, as Father Andrew was just saying.
But I want to point out that really what we've been talking about tonight and what she exemplifies
is really the core of the gospel and the Christian proclamation.
And it's a core that's gutted.
a lot of American Christianity of the materialist variety.
We have in that kind of American materialist Christianity,
a very anemic skeletal form of Christianity,
where there's sort of this partition between God
and the world, between God and humanity,
where we Christ ascended into heaven
he's gone and people die and now they're gone or they're separated from us by this partition.
There's not really a way through it. What's on the other side of it is kind of hazy, but so I
do what I need to do to get saved and then I try to be a good person for the rest of my life here
in the world and try to have confidence that when I die and I go to the other side of that
Partition.
I'll end up in the good place.
That's not the vital Christianity that's alive and that is made of fire that you find
in the scriptures and that you find the apostles preaching.
Saint Paul not only over and over again says that all of those partitions and dividing walls
have been broken down.
begins when he writes a letter to a church.
writes a letter to a church where they're experiencing some pretty horrific problems with sexual immorality,
with with heresy, with false teaching and a false gospel, and all of these things,
he starts by talking to them about the fact that they are sons of God, that they're seated in
the heavenly places, that they're like the angels, that they're part of God's divine counsel,
that they're in communion with God and with His saints.
part of God's plan and his work in the whole creation. That's where he begins and then
works from there to get down to the details of, hey, here's how you should treat your wife
and your kids. Hey, here's ways that you can and can't act in the world. And so what
we see with the feotocos is exhibit A of that. We see a human who has fully come into
You
what God created her to be and who he created her to be, who has reached the kind of maturity
and completion as a person formed into the image of God that the Scriptures are constantly
talking about as the goal of our Christian life.
And she's done that, she's crossed that non-existent partition and is still connected to us
and we can see her there in the heavenly place.
is awaiting us at the end of the journey. And the fact that the person who has most fully
done that in the Christian religion is a woman is not to be underestimated. Because the
The Christian proclamation, including who Christ's mother is, did more to change the role
and the understanding and the value and the freedom and the appreciation of women in this world
than any human ideology ever has and ever could. The transformation from the way the ancient world
looked at women is 180 degrees. And that despite all kinds of quote unquote goddess worship.
Because a goddess isn't like me or like a human woman.
A goddess is some other type of being.
But the Thetocos is like me.
She's a woman like my wife and like my mother and like my sisters.
She's one of us, who has achieved and received what we're all striving for.
striving for. And therefore as an example to all of us, a beacon to all of us, an intercessor
for all of us.
us. And that's not just some ancillary thing. That's not just some obstacle I have to climb over if
I'm not orthodox and want to join the church. That's central to what we understand salvation to be
and who we are in Christ and the value of every Christian but especially Christian women.
So those are my thoughts.
Oh man, at the end of well.
Before we finish this evening, I just want to note that, of course, we will be back in two weeks,
being the fourth Thursday of the month.
However, on the new calendar that both fathers, Steven and I are on, that is Christmas Eve.
So we're not going to be live that night.
We're going to have a pre-recorded show.
So if you want to submit questions or comments for that one, make sure you send them to us by email or
also by our SpeakPipe connection that you can find on the Ancient Faith Radio Live web.
So just please note that the December 24th episode will be a pre-recorded episode.
And so we're going to be talking about astrology.
Yeah.
Oh yeah, there you go.
And not that it's just bad.
All right, well that is our so for today.
Thank you very much for listening.
If you didn't get a chance to call in during this live broadcast, we'd love to hear from
you either via email at Lord of S-
at www.ancientfaith.com or you can message us at our Lord of
Spirits Podcast Facebook page. We read everything but we can't
respond to everything. I'm sorry I wish we could. We get so much
email. We do say what you send for possible future use in
later episodes. And join us for our live broadcast except for
next time on the second and fourth Thursdays of the month at 7
PM Eastern 4 PM Pacific. And don't forget to like our Lord of
Spirits Podcast Facebook page while you're at it. Join our
Facebook discussion.
leave a recommendation and then invite your friends.
And if you leave a review on Apple Podcasts, Facebook,
or wherever you get your podcasts,
then that raises the visibility of this show
and gets more people connected.
And finally, be sure to go to www.incscientfaith.com
slash support and help make sure we and lots of other AFR podcasters
stay on the air.
Thank you very much and may God bless you through the prayers
of His Mother and of all of His Saints.
You've been listening to the Lord of Spirits, with Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew
Stephen Damick, and Father Stephen De Young, a listener-supported presentation of ancient
faith radio.
And I beheld, and I heard the voice of many angels round about the throne, and the beasts,
and the elders, and the number of them was 10,000 times 10,000, and thousands of thousands,
with a loud voice worthy as the land that was slain to receive power.
in riches and wisdom and strength and honor and glory and blessing.
Revelation chapter 5 verses 11 through 12.