He will be a staff for the righteous with which for them to stand and not to fall.
And he will be the light of the nations and the hope of those whose hearts are troubled.
All who dwell on the earth will fall down and worship him,
and they will praise and bless and celebrate with song the Lord of Spirits.
1st denoc, chapter 48, verses 4-5.
The modern world doesn't acknowledge but is nevertheless haunted by spirits, angels, demons, and saints.
In our time.
many year into break free of the prison of a flat secular materialism to see and to
know reality as it truly is. What is this spiritual reality like? How do we
engage with it well? How do we permeate everyday life with spiritual presence?
Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen
De Young host this live Colin show focused on enchantment in creation. The
union of the scene and unseen as made by God.
and experienced by mankind throughout history.
Welcome to the Lord of Spirits.
Good evening everyone.
Welcome back to the Lord of Spirits podcast.
My co-host, Father Stephen D'Young
is with me from Lafayette, Louisiana.
And I'm Father Andrew Stephen Damick
and a Mayas, Pennsylvania.
And if you are listening to us live,
you can call in at 855-AF radio.
That's 855-237-2346.
and Materska Trudy will be taking your calls.
and I be nice to her.
We will get your calls in the second part of today's show.
So tonight our show is about Pentecost.
But in what is now classic Lord of Spirits form,
we have some groundwork to lay before we get to our full points.
We patient and you'll find that this pays off at the end.
As with any of the major feasts of the church,
there are multiple angles from which one can look at them.
With Pentecost, we could discuss the feast
as the reversal of the Tower of Babel.
What it means?
for Christians to acquire the Holy Spirit, who the Holy Spirit himself is, the gift of speaking
in foreign languages and so on, but our starting point tonight is, as with so many things on this
podcast, way back in Genesis. And the first chapter of Genesis, God takes the formless void world
and makes the heavens and the earth and all the life that is in them. And then in Genesis chapter 2,
you, the narrative backs up to the beginning again and retells the story, but with a f-
focus on a place called Eden. So, Father Stephen, what exactly is Eden? Well, Eden is the place where God is. Right. You mean it's not like some dusty town in an archaeological dig in Iraq somewhere or... No, nor is it at the bottom of the Persian Gulf.
nor is it in the last the last history channel documentary I watched where they
were trying to track down where it was said there's this
in what's now Turkey built on top of it.
Oh, there are some who say it's in Missouri.
Yes, there's that Jack's.
They're there.
Yes, yeah.
Right.
I've been there.
It's lovely.
It's quite lovely.
And there's those who say it's been paved over and put
into parking lot.
Yes.
But there's there's our first 80s music reference for the
evening.
Yeah.
80s.
OK.
I don't know.
Yeah, I have to look that up now.
Sad just
I know. Okay. Uh, he is where God is. So this is, this is right. And this is, this is what we're going to be
tracing for folks today, uh, to tell you what we're going to tell you. We're starting at the
beginning of the world and we're tracing the place where God is. Okay. Where he is at different
points in time. And so this is going to be connected to ideas of sacred space and sacred place.
Yeah, so this is a good one
to have already listened to the entire podcast up to this point in order to get.
Yeah, let's go back and listen to 30 hours.
If you find, you should still be able to follow it, but it'll be much richer if you've
listened to the sacred geography episodes, if you listen to the body episodes.
Yeah, yeah. But anyway, so here we are.
The place where God is is also the place where you would go to meet God.
Right. Right. So.
You can meet a Christian in Christian sands, you can meet the devil in Helsinki.
But if you want to meet God, you have to go to certain places.
Right. And the point being made by this is not that there's places where God isn't,
right? But rather, again, this is about human experience, right? Where you meet God, as you said.
Right, this is about where the presence of God intrudes into
the time and space that only exist as part of human experience.
Right. Right. Right. So and that's, well, yes, we as all Christians have
historically affirmed that God is everywhere within creation. Right. And always
has been. It's also very clear, just on a surface reading of the Bible that
there are places where he really really is.
Right, right, that's right.
And so it's that really really is that we're going to be focusing on tonight.
So the first of those places is Paradise which this is a little bit of review because
we've talked about this before but Paradise of course the word comes from a Wald
Garden, it's a Persian loan word.
So it is this space that is walled off, sectioned off within the cosmos that has been created.
And it is not the entire earth at the time of creation, right?
Because even though when it is planted in Genesis chapter 2,
God doesn't tell us east of where, he tells us that in the east.
He plants a garden in the east, which means it has a location.
It means there is plenty of cosmos that is not eaten at that point.
Yeah.
Right.
It's left hand.
and when he creates Adam and Genesis 2
he creates him from the dust of the earth and then places him in Eden, meaning that
that earth dirt that he's made out of came from somewhere outside.
And that wall represents this, that there's this separation.
Of course, we talked about how the intent was that Adam and Eve as they came to maturity,
or that time Adam and woman as they came to maturity.
would then leave the garden and take Eden, take the presence of God with them.
Right.
And would participate in, take part in, be given the grace by God to participate in
turning the whole cosmos into Eden, filling the whole cosmos with God's presence.
Of course, we also know from Genesis chapter 3 that that is not what happened.
Right.
right here.
And so at that point, humanity was expelled from the presence of God.
Right. Yeah. And like most icons of this, you see them walking out of Eden, kind of looking over their shoulder, and there's a chair up there with this flaming sword.
and some you get Adam sitting down and weeping over what he's lost.
But...
But the mean point is, as you said, that they're expelled from the presence of God,
whether that literally means that they walk through a hole in the walls,
and it's not necessarily that way. The point is that they're not with God anymore
in the way that they were before.
We don't know if that entailed actually leaving a place the way we would think of it now,
But that's that's the way that iconography iconographically is depicted which is
and the way it's described in the scripture.
So that's what we've got, right?
Right.
And often, I canography will even depict the wall.
Yeah, right.
Right.
And so that wall, that barrier,
rather than becoming a place that distinguishes
the holy place from the rest of creation,
it becomes a barrier between humanity
and the presence of God.
And this is often, as so many things are
in a-
the West looked at as sort of a punishment.
Right, right.
This was this nice place.
This was this wonderful place.
This blissful place being in the presence of God.
And now you've got to go out there
into the crummy world because you were bad.
Right.
Right, I'm sending you away
because you have offended me.
Right, right.
But that's not what it's about.
Instead, as we've talked about on this podcast,
before
Or when man created immortal, created to be immortal and sustained as being immortal by
God, but the problem is, if an immortal being sins, he's crystallized in his rebellion
against God.
So what happens is that God gives them mortality so that they would have the opportunity to repent
because you need mortality in order to be changeable in that particular way.
And so...
actually being sent out is a mercy. Right? It's not as God said, it's not good for man
to live forever in this state. In the state of crystallized sin. Right. Because then he would have been just
like the devil, right? Who also fell in Genesis 3. And that would also mean that the devil would have
succeeded yeah right because that was the
devil's goal, right? The devil's goal was to destroy humanity to make humanity like
himself. That's always been his goal. That's still his goal is to make human persons like
himself. So yes, God prevents that victory by expelling humanity from his presence. And
this dynamic that happens here in Genesis 3, we're going to see stretches all the way through
the Scriptures. This idea that while humanity
is sinful and while we're bearing in our bodies and our souls, our lives, the effects of our sin,
it is dangerous for us to come into the presence of God. Right. And this plays itself out in,
well we're going to talk about a bunch of the ways that it does, but like one immediate way,
for instance, as we're saying Paul talks about an unrepentant person in the Corinthian church
that has to be cast out until such time as they repent.
it's dangerous for them to be there. It's dangerous for that person to be within the presence of the
church and receiving the Holy Mysteries while they're living an unrepentant life. And I mean,
this is also the basis for a lot of our eucharistic discipline. You know, when someone's not ready to
receive the eucharist because of some grave sin, they need to be purified before they're ready to
because, again, as St. Paul says, those who receive it in that way, some get sick and some die. You know,
he says that it's dangerous.
It's dangerous to be in the presence of God when you're not purified.
Right. And so just as in paradise, man had to be prevented from eating of the tree of life.
So St. Paul has to prevent unrepentant people from trying to eat of the tree of life.
Because it would be bad for this.
Suffering, yes, it's a man suffering that, suffering that faith.
Yeah, that paid. So this is this is
an act of love by God both to protect them from his holiness and to give them then
the opportunity to potentially eventually come back. And so what then unfolds as
we as we move on in Genesis what unfolds in Genesis 4 through 6 is we see what
can happen in the worst case scenario.
Yeah, that's right.
Where God is still very present in the earth with humanity.
And humanity is becoming more, starting with Cain, is becoming more and more wicked and
more and more corrupt and is being more and more dominated by sin, by the powers of
death, by the powers of darkness, and that's building up and building up and building up.
Yeah, right?
In his face.
Yeah.
Right.
Yeah, look.
Yeah, exactly. And so this concept, and we're going to mention this much times, but this is an important concept.
This is called death by holiness. And it's basically that if you are in the presence of God and
not prepared to be, it's going to be really bad for you.
Not because he's like mad or anything like that. It's just this is death by holiness. And we see it a
bunch of times in scriptures. So now we're going to talk about it a number of those times. Right. And and the God's holiness is over and over again compared to fire.
Yeah, right. And in your best case scenario of coming into the presence of God, right?
It's like putting iron into the fire and all the impurities are burned away.
Yeah. Right. And the iron is purified. That's your best case scenario.
In the worst case scenario, the whole thing gets burned and melted away.
Right, and so Isaiah when the flaming coal is brought to his lip
to purify them. That's not a present, pleasant experience. Don't try this at home.
Right?
I think burning coal pressed to your lips, right? But that purifies him. Right? And so,
right? And this is, this is because of God's holiness and because of who he is.
And this is not that he likes going around, you know, torching people.
And this explains why then that cherub is put at the gate of the garden with the flaming sword.
It's not to protect the garden from man defiling it.
It protects human beings from entering in a place that would destroy them.
That's what it's doing there.
Right, because it would be better.
Right, remember, the chair of is there to keep them from the tree of life.
It's better for them to die physically than to eat from the tree of life and be immortal
ly dead spiritually.
Right, so it's to stop them from something worse.
So, as we see this evil and wickedness and sin and demonic activity and corruption build up in Genesis 4 through 6,
This sort of culminates
as we've said before, most famously in the Giants episode.
Right?
Yes.
This sort of culminates in Genesis 6 verses 1 through 4.
And of Genesis 6 verses 1 through 4, verse 3 is sort of the poor ignored,
doesn't all over of the whole situation that nobody ever talks about,
because everybody gets excited about the Giants.
Yes.
Right.
People do.
Which are in verses 1, 2 and 4.
Right.
Yes.
So, definitely.
Yeah, so verse three says
So the Lord said so this is right after the description of the giants coming around so the Lord said my spirit will not and then some translation says remain in
Others says contend with so my spirit will not remain in or my spirit will not contend with
human kind indefinitely since they are mortal they will remain for 120 more years
That's what that verse says
Right. So what's going on in that verse?
Right, so God's spirit, the Holy Spirit, right, is in the whole cosmos, right?
He's everywhere present and filling all things. And that means that all of this sin and wickedness
that's happening, building up to and including what the giants are up to, is happening in God's
presence. Right. And so there's this this Hebrew version.
that's used that is can mean either a Biden or a
remaining or contend with. It could have a positive or
negative connotation depending on context. And I would suggest this happens very often with Hebrew,
especially in Hebrew poetry, but in Hebrew in general. And you even get some of the new testament
riders because they're thinking with a Hebrew aromagal brain doing this and the
in the New Testament, where they will deliberately use a word that could be taken in multiple senses
and use it to kind of mean both, right? It's porque no los dos, right?
Yes, right. It's pung fully intended.
Right. It's...
Remain in, right? Meaning, remain here in humankind in the cosmos, right?
My spirit cannot long remain there.
And part of the reason for that is my spirit being there is how
to contend with. Right? It's a struggle. It's a battle. Right? Right. And now you notice he
doesn't say here that he is going to depart. Right? That's that's that's not this part. Right. He says
He says that the humans are going to depart.
Yeah, they got to remain for 120 more years and then
Right, so yeah bad things are going and so this is what
produces the flood
the flood happens
Because God's presence remains in the world and their wickedness doesn't stop
death by holiness and so
life on earth minus Noah and his family right and the life.
life in the arc of salvation is wiped out because it is in God's presence and is wicked.
I feel like in the back of my head there is an Avengers Infinity War joke just percolating
up somehow about destroying all life and it being inevitable and so forth.
This is more than 50 percent.
Yes, a little bit more than 50 percent.
99.9.
I'm not, I'm not.
Well, that's because Thanos isn't God.
Right.
He just can do that.
Yeah.
And the reason it's water, we've talked before the sea, right?
Yom, this is chaos.
Chaos, yeah.
The force is chaos.
And so what God essentially does, the way the flood actually happens and the way it's
described, it talks about the water coming up out of the ground and the water coming
down out of the sky, right?
is reversing the second and third days of creation.
So God just stops restraining. He stops protecting humanity from the chaos and evil that he's unleashing in the world.
This is how punishment works in the Bible.
Yeah, there's all the patience.
Patience God has patience for a while and then it's like, okay, time's up.
Right, when God punishes people, he's not...
actively torturing them or inflicting pain and suffering on them. Right. The way punishment works in the scriptures is
God just stops protecting people
Yeah, from their actions and from what they're doing and lets them suffer the consequences, right?
Right, and so this is what happens here. He lets chaos come back and consume the cosmos and
Then he recreates again
Yeah, takes it back.
to Tahu-Abohu, right? Then...
Yeah, that's the formless, formless envoy, right?
Right, right.
For Genesis, Genesis 1, 2.
And so then, afterwards, we have this symbol of the rainbow,
right, which is not, as some folks might think, it's not like
God tied this beautiful, shiny, colorful bow around the earth.
Right?
Is it annoying?
Yeah, it's bow like the weapon like with arrows. Yeah, right bow like bow arrows and God sets it down
Right says he places it in the clouds. He sets it down
Which is is the ancient Near East right when someone's going to war their depicted
I kind of graphically right as holding a bow Pharaoh's holding a bow the king of the series holding a bow right
So God setting his bow down says okay I'm not gonna go to war with humanity.
anymore. Right? And you will know that this promise is true because you'll be able to look up
at the sky and see my bow still sitting there that I haven't picked it up again. Right? And
so he's saying when he says he's not going to destroy the world again. Right? He's saying,
I'm not going to allow humanity to get to the point where it they destroy themselves by being in
in my presence.
And so that's why we see in Genesis 10 and 11, we see something at the same time very
similar but at very different unfold.
Yeah, yeah.
I mean, and it doesn't take long, right, for things to start to go bad again.
You know, Noah sets down and they start rebuilding, but there's wickedness with it.
I mean, we don't need to go into it, but there's wickedness within the house of Noah, not
too long after all of this.
And then eventually you get the 70 nations, they're all descended from Noah, and they
start doing bad things again, especially one particular construction project, right?
Right.
And there's some build up to that in the genealogies in Genesis 10, which again for some reason
not people's favorite part of Genesis.
the genealogies. But
There's this fella who shows up in the genealogies.
There's a couple of important things
as to those genealogies, actually.
I think we already referenced in a previous episode,
the prophecy that Noah's father,
Lammick, makes about Noah,
which is really important framing the flood.
Oh, that's actually the previous.
That's before the flood, sorry.
In this, in this, the table of nations in Genesis 10
that's laying out the 70 nations
and how they're all descended,
we run into this fella, Nimrod.
Right, which is not just a way of...
is not just an insulting thing to call somebody,
it's an actual person.
Or a super popular pendant from the 70s
to have hanging amidst your chest hair.
Oh wow.
You can look that up if you want to go back.
That's a call back then.
But.
Yes.
So who is Nimrod?
This actually came up in the Lord of Spirits Facebook group
the other day, asking, is Nimrod a giant?
Because of the way he's described as being this mighty hunter
before the Lord.
right? Yes. So Nimrod is indeed. Nimrod is the he's serving the purpose in the
narrative of being the founder of Babylon. Now there was actually another Assyrian
city named after him Nimrud.
Okay.
Which was the...
military center of the Assyrian Empire much later.
It's centuries later, but this is all part of Ah-Kh-D.
This is all part of the northern part there.
But the reason they're named after him is not that,
oh, hey, you remember that hunter guy in the Bible
in the genealogy, right?
The reason for that is that Nimrod or Nimrod
is the lexically, it's the same name as the God.
Nernerta. Yeah, so who's who's that? I think a lot of us probably have never never heard of Nernerta.
Well, have it you've been reading your tablets from the Library of Esther,
Bannerfall, the second? Well, you know, there's still there's still 90% of them have not been
translated yet. So I haven't gotten to those. Well, that's why people need to get to it. Come on.
Yeah, sleep it on these tap.
So, Nernerda is one of the primary gods of the Pantheon and one of the, was one of the main gods
of the original Babylonian Empire. Yeah, associated with farming, healing, hunting,
law, scribes, and war. So it's kind of a nice portfolio there. Right, because he was essentially
for a period of time serving the function of most high god. Yeah. So if you're someone who has that
even for a little while.
you tend to take on a big package. Right. Right. Right. And now this is the original Babylonian
empire. We have a bad gauge in our heads a lot of time of how old things are in the ancient
areas. So when we think of Babylon because of the Old Testament, we may think of like Nebuchadnezzar.
Right. Right. Maybe his dad, Navajo Pulaszor, that's the neo-Babalonean empire.
Hmm, that's the new one.
in the six and seventh centuries BC.
This is what, a couple thousand years before that?
The original one, yeah, we're talking about like 2,500 BC
and a few centuries before and after.
So we're talking about like Hamrabi.
We're talking about the Martu,
who are the biblical Amorites, right?
Who we already talked about in the Giants episode a little bit.
So this is one of the gods of Babylon
at that time.
right at that time. And so what the the text is doing in Genesis 10 is it's tying this to this particular
Nephilim fellow, right, who is the city founder figure who becomes the God,
Ninerda, he ends up his spirit ends up being worshipped by
the Babylonians. That's what's going on here.
And it's part of the
part of Genesis showing us that the whole Nephilim thing is even starting to happen again.
Yeah. Right. Just like the genealogy of Cain that we had before the flood, now we've got this genealogy
that they should said, oh, looky. Right. The whole Nephilim thing is happening again. And then we, this culminates
culminates with the tower of Bable we talked before about how the
Babylonian, Bobbi Lee means the gate of God, the gate of the gods.
And how this temple, this Ziggurat that's being built, was looked at, and how they were
trying to draw Yahweh the most high God down and sort of make him serve their purposes.
Yeah, yeah, it's it's you know being a gate right it's it's essentially rather
like trying to break into Eden, right?
You know, we'll make our own parodysaicle garden
on our own parodysaicle mountain,
and we're gonna make God come down here
and be with us and do what we want, right?
Which is, you know, that's not the way the God
set things up in Eden.
You know, it's a violent sort of aggressive,
technological kind of approach to relationship with God.
Right. And it's based on this in Genesis, that every future empire that's talked about in the
scriptures all the way up through and including Rome is described in terms of Babylon.
It's the prototypical bad civilization. Right. The starting with the city that Kane founded.
Right. This is continuing that streak and that's going to continue all the way up into Rome.
But
So if the same thing is unfolding again, God has promised that he's not going to wipe
everybody out again.
And so all the people in the world are all gathered around the zinger at.
God is trying to calm down.
He said he's not going to destroy them all again.
So then what is the other option?
The other option is for God to remove himself.
believe, right?
For God's believe.
And so this is why again, it is out of mercy. This is why God steps back at Bable. And as we read about
more in Deuteronomy chapter 32, why when he steps back, he assigns the 70 nations of Genesis 10 to
the sons of God to angelic beings. Right. So there's this buffer between him and them.
right yeah so so that they won't perish
Yeah, and it's fascinating how much of the action of what goes on in scripture.
And we're going to see this more and more as we talk. But it's fascinating to me how much of the
action of what goes on in scripture is really about this very basic dynamic of dealing with the
problem of death by holiness, of people not being ready to be in the presence of God. And so then
the things that happen as a result of that. It's fascinating how this is kind of a unifying principle
for so much of what's going on in it.
Scripture. Yeah, and and part of the reason we miss it so often is that in our contemporary
world, we've almost completely lost the idea of sacred space. Yeah, yeah, right. You know,
in fact, even even amongst Christians, they're like, well, isn't every place sacred? You
know, which which what that does is like so, so that's correct, although, you know, spoiler alert,
I will talk about that later, but what it effectively does is it makes it so that
nothing is no place is sacred.
Or just like, for instance, those who object
to having holy days in the church calendar,
like, well, every day should be like it's Christmas.
Well, when every day is Christmas,
then no day is Christmas.
You know, like you tell someone,
every day should be like your birthday, right?
Well, then the no days are your birthday.
You know, that's what tends to happen
is our sense of egalitarianism,
flattens everything out.
you know i like that's in the in-tro door shop
is is it secularism, materialism makes everything flat and you know this is part of what's going on.
Right. It doesn't it doesn't take what's lowly and broken and lifted up. No. It takes what is high
and lifted up and pulls it down. Yeah. Right. And that's why iconoclasm is such a perfect
instance of it. Right. Yeah. Is that it's pulling down and destroying. Right. Something that
that is otherwise...
beautiful and uplifting. Yeah. So, okay. So now we've got God has withdrawn himself from
the nations and assigned angels to them to govern them by proxy. And, you know, what happens
with them later is while we've talked about that before. But there's still this problem
then of God's sort of active presence in the world being withdrawn. He's not going to just
Just leave it that way.
Just let us be this
Right. Something's got to change. Right. Because the goal was, right, remember the goal of the
expulsion for paradise was so that there could be repentance, so that they wouldn't
have been eternally condemned. And so the goal of withdrawing here again is so that the people
won't perish because God doesn't want them to perish. Right. So what we get then in Genesis 12,
beginning with Abraham. And there's a monster time lapse here but
What do we get with Abraham in Genesis 12 is the beginning of salvation.
Right. And Abraham is living in the midst of or probably around the time that they're building
a big cigarette, right? Right. You know, they would have looked up and seen this thing
and lived in its shadow.
Yes, and that's where the memory of that, that he was there in the
the Ur-3 period when the Great Ziggurat of Ur-o was being built.
The memory of that is why you sometimes find in, especially in Targumic traditions,
for later Israel, there are these things connecting Abraham to the building of the Tower
of Babel.
Even though the text clearly doesn't do that, but there was this preserved oral memory
of the building of a ziggurat in Abraham's lifetime.
And those two things kind of got blended together due to their proximity in the Genesis story.
But so Abraham is the beginning then of salvation.
This is what distinguishes a lot of theories out there about what distinguishes Genesis 1 through 11 from the rest of the book of Genesis.
But sometimes genre, sometimes all kinds of things are suggested.
But what really distinguishes it is that Genesis 1 through
11 is outlining the problem. Right. How we got here. And then Genesis 12 is the beginning of the
solution. It's the beginning of salvation. And this is why when we get to the New Testament,
anytime St. Paul or someone else is talking about salvation, they start with Abraham.
Yeah. Right. That's where they go to because this is this is the beginning now of
of the recovery.
And so you have Abraham, who...
Yahweh draws near to personally, and literally he draws close to him personally.
He appears to him repeatedly.
He stands in front of him and talks to him.
But Abraham and his immediate descendants are living as nomads.
They leave or in the Abraham story notice is identified as Ur of the Caldees.
Yeah.
What's that about? Yeah, it actually isn't.
Or of the case or was in Sumeria, not a god and it and it was the Babylonian Empire.
Didn't really exist at that time and didn't control or but more than that, the term Caldien refers to the neo-Babolonian Empire.
But it's called or of the Caldees.
in the Genesis text precisely to make the case.
connection to what just happened with Nimrod of the Tower of Babel.
Oh, interesting.
Caldians are Babylonians.
Sort of more like, or like the Caldys.
Right, sort of.
Yeah.
So it's making the point that when God does come and appear
to Abraham at that point and calls him out, right?
He's calling him now out of Babylon.
he's calling him out of the city.
God had already withdrawn himself from that and now he's calling Abram out to come out with God
away from that civilization
Yeah, and so the the place where God is
Since Abraham Isaac and Jacob and Jacob sons are living nomatically
The place where God is is with them
wherever they are.
right? And so this is why all the way through up to Moses, it will be talking about Moses
more in the second half. When God identifies himself, he doesn't identify himself as the
God of a place. Right, right, which is, you know, like what most, most spirits of that time
were associated with, you know, the local God basic.
terribly local. Right. Right. He's he's a Genesis 1 through 11. He's God most
high. He's just God. Right. Right. God of gods. Right. For Genesis 12 on for a good
long while, he's the God of Abraham, Isaac and Jacob. Yeah. So it becomes local,
but not local to a place is local to these people. Right. He's with him. Yes. He is with them.
traveling around with them. Yeah and he appeared.
to all of them bodily, right? And so what we see in terms of sacred space is not a temple or
temples, right? It's not that kind of thing, but at these places where Abraham, like at Mamry or
Jacob, like at Bethel, where Ristals got there. Where they encounter Yahweh,
personally where he appears to them, where they are active, and they build an altar there.
Right. And then that is the place when they come back,
ritually, and offer sacrifice on that altar, they're making the time when they were there in the presence of God
to be that time again.
Yeah. So they basically go on pilgrimage back to those places.
And by means of offering sacrifice there, they're there again.
there's then there's then again. Right.
Put it right to take for dimensionally ritual time travel.
Yes, exactly. Yes.
They don't travel back in time, but that time becomes this time.
Right. You know, and you don't have to go 88.8 miles per hour. Right.
Right. Right. Right. You need zero gigawatts of.
So and and as a note, if you actually look at those altars in the patriarchal narratives
and the stories of the patriarchs in j...
Genesis 12 through 50, there are 12 of them. And there's one in each of the territories
that God later assigned to the 12 tribes of Israel. So if they had done what they were supposed
to do and taken the land, they were supposed to take each one of them would have had one
of those shrines within their territory. But of course they didn't.
Disappointing. Right. So I don't know if there was giggling or not. But anyway,
So, before we move to act two and get to our friend Moses, so before Moses, there's
this big time gap between the patriarchs and the beginning of Exodus.
Right, right.
It's like five to 700 years of space between them.
So basically, Jacob and Sun.
are in Egypt and then five to seven hundred years later you get the Exodus.
Right. You know what's going on? Right. You go from 70, not coincidentally, people who go down into
Egypt to what's going to become the nation of Israel. And so during that time, during that,
the centuries, right? Where is the God of Abraham Isaac and Jake?
up right because there I mean as far as anyone on earth is concerned there
did so God isn't hanging around in the cemetery right yeah so the question
did God just withdraw again for a few hundred years and then come back to
Moses right or follow them into Egypt I mean what would happen if he had
follow them into each of them would probably be out for the Egyptians.
So as it later is the what's actually in the Bible and some archaeology tell us where he is.
Yeah, and I'm just going to prep us this everybody by saying I had no idea.
I have no idea.
Yeah, yeah.
Yeah, so we're put your put your hats on so that your skulls don't explode too much here.
Alright.
So...
Uh...
the earliest mention of the name Yahweh as a God that we have outside the Bible is on a wall
at a temple at the city of Solub in Nubia so this is northern Sudan today. Right. This would have been
an Egyptian settlement, right?
Right.
It's an Egyptian-table built by-
Pharaoh Amenhotep III as a temple to Amen Ray. And so on the walls of this temple, there
are these cartouches, right? And a cartouch is sort of a way of marking off an inscription.
So you have like usually an oval shape and then the whole Olympics are within that.
I remember seeing those for the first time reading Astrix and Oblix comics when I was a kid.
We
We had the asterisk and Cleopatra comic.
Thanks to my dad who bought it in Australia, if you can believe it.
True story.
That's how I learned about cartouches.
I think I still have it actually.
So I mean worth money.
I mean, it's probably.
Yeah, I don't know.
I would have been.
So that's my first thought.
Yeah, right, right.
Yeah, I think I mean, if I do have it, I would have had it since like 1982, 1981.
I mean, it's a long time ago.
I mean...
But that's how I learned what a cartoosh is.
Right.
So these cartooshes are basically Aminhotep III, bragging about all the people who he'd beat
up on in war.
And where they were from and sometimes who their gods were and all that kind of stuff.
Like a lot of trash talk.
Right.
In the midst of this was built in the
early 14th century BC, early 14th century would be sometime between like the year 141350 BC.
As when this Cartuchus carved and it refers to one of the people who he had beaten in battle and
and taken slaves were the Shasu of the land belonging to Yahoo.
Okay, so was the common way of abbreviating Yahweh?
It still is. Benjamin Netanyahu has the name Yahweh in his last name.
So every type Jewish people say his name, they're saying Yahweh.
How about that? Some questions we occasionally get from listeners.
Yes, right.
Yeah, I mean there's a lot of there's a lot of
Jewish names that include Yahweh in them in one way or another.
Elijah, right?
Isn't it like Eliahu?
Yes.
Yeah, that's the Yahweh.
There's the Yahweh, yeah.
Yeah, the Yah.
Hallelujah.
Right.
The Yah at the, yeah.
Yeah, yeah.
Yeah, oh, oh, but Daya, right?
Isn't that?
Yeah.
Yeah, yes, exactly.
Right.
So the Shasu of Yahweh's land.
Who are these Shasu?
It's-
It's not the land of Yahoo like the name of the land was Yahoo.
It's Shasu who come from the land that belongs to the God Yahweh.
It's a possessive genitive.
And there's a similar inscription in Amara West from the 13th century BC.
So from about 100 years later.
also talks about the Shasu who are from the land belonging to Yahoo!
And you don't have to look far to find out in Egyptian records that the Shasu are
What they called the Edamites
Right, so these are
descendants of Esa the brother of Jacob right the Edamites the descendants of Esa
the settled
Members of that group were called the Edamites they were settled in the land of Edam around Mount Sair
that's the IR and then there were also the Midianites.
who you read about in the Old Testament were basically a mixed group of
edomites and ischemy lights. Okay so that's who the video lights are. So all
these people are descended from Abraham. Right because their sons are
descendants of Esau. Yeah. And it's this bunch so we actually meet one, right? I
I don't know if we meet any before him, but we meet.
one next to this, when Moses goes out into the wilderness and spends what is it 40 years
out there? Moses goes on the lamb. Yeah. Yeah. Right. Right. Right. Right. He's the law. Yeah.
So he's right. So he's out there and he meets a local girl and marries her that's Zappura
and her father is Jethro and he's a priest and he's Midianite.
and he's a priest of Yahweh.
He's a priest of the, right, the most high God.
Right. Of the most high God.
And so he's the one who then imparts, right?
Uh, uh, the knowledge of who he always to,
most it shows him where the mountain of God is, right?
And when, when God introduces himself, uh, to Moses, he says, right,
your forebear's newies El Shadai is the God of the Mountain.
But you will know me as Yahweh, right?
So what this shows us, both from, again, reading Exodus and from this archeological find,
in terms of what the ancient Egyptians of that time knew about those people, is that the
The worship of Yahweh had been continued by the rest of Abraham's descendants.
to this point who didn't go into Egypt.
Right. And it's not just this,
well hey, look, there's Jethro.
There's a bunch more about this.
There's, yes, inter-oil testaments.
Yes. Yes.
Yeah, there's multiple references.
And I'm just going to rattle off the references
so people can look these up.
Deuteronomy 2, 1 through 5, and 12.
Joshua 24-4
judges five four and then Ezekiel 35 versus one through 15 and they all reference
Mount Sarah if I'm correct as he IR once again you could actually just do a
word search on you know the Bible Gateway.com for the word Sarah and you'll
see all these references to it and like for instance the one in in judges five
four right Lord when you went out from Sarah when you marched from the region of
the earth trembled.
and the heavens dropped, yes, the clouds dropped water.
So you get God, He's in this place called Sarah.
And it is.
It is.
It is the Edom, you know.
Right.
It judges five.
They're describing Yahweh coming to lead the people of Israel into Canaan, into the Promised Land.
Yeah.
And He comes to do that from Mount Sarah.
Right.
That's where he was there being worshipped by the Edomites.
And then he comes from there to lead the people of Israel.
The Deuteronomy 2 verses that you mentioned,
first it's that when the Israelites came to the Eidom,
they were just kind of hanging around there for a while.
And God had to kind of tell,
hey Moses, come on, get it moving.
We got to get into the problem.
Yes, I'm here, but this is not the place.
Right.
but he says there he says you are not to
take literally one foot. It says the length of one foot, one human foot. You're
going to take one foot of their land because you always says he brought the
eedimites there and gave them that land. And he's giving Canaan to the
descendants of Jacob. Yeah. And isn't there a reference? Is this the one in
Deuteronomy 12, the Horites? Right. Who are in steer? Are those giant people?
Yes. Yes. So God clears out giants and brings Edom into the living.
Right. He used the Edomites to clean the giants out of line and give it to them directly
parallel to what he's about to do in the book of Joshua. Yeah. Right. And so there's this
direct parallel. God did the same thing with Edom that he's going to do with Israel. He
did it there first. Joshua 24 verse 4 that you mentioned. That's at the end of the book
Joshua where Joshua's laying out how
God had fulfilled all the promises about the land that he made to Abraham.
Attention our dispensationalist friends. The book of Joshua says that God in the conquest will
filled all the promises about the land that he made to Abraham. It literally says that. It's
but then fulfilled. Part of that fulfillment, according to Joshua 24 verse 4, is that God gave the
land of Edom to the descendants of Esau.
and brought them in there and gave it to them.
And then the last one of those references you read in Ezekiel
is the other end, it's after Judah has gone into exile.
And at the time Judah went into exile,
the Edomites sort of used that opportunity to do some pillaging and some expanding
of their territory and to sort of turn on their brothers and gloat.
And so Ezekiel is promising the Edomites
that because of their wickedness, they're going to suffer the same fate.
jute did. So there's this direct parallel between what happens to Israel and
what happens to eat them in the Old Testament. They're treated fundamentally the
same way. Cool. Well everybody now you know where exactly God was during those
five to seven hundred years and knowing He's half the battle. It G.I. Anyway, yes
it is we'll be back in just a moment as we can
continue this discussion as we head towards Pentecost,
but right now we'll take a break.
Father Andrew Stephen Daymick and Father Stephen DeYoung
will be back in a moment to take your calls
on the next part of the Lord of Spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF radio.
This is an ancient faith radio public service
The Mental Health Task Force, the Assembly of Canonical Orthodox Bishops, has recently launched
two mental health initiatives, a National Directory of Orthodox Mental Health Professionals,
and an Orthodox Mental Health Needs Assessment that are available at www.assemblyofbishops.org
slash mental-health.
The Directory of Orthodox Mental Health Professionals features licensed Orthodox Christian clinicians
across the US who are available to serve as resource.
to those seeking mental health care, substance abuse care, and or professional consultation.
While the orthodox mental health needs assessment is an anonymous survey for all orthodox jurisdictions,
clergy, and laypeople across the U.S.
The aggregate data from this survey will help the task force better understand
and address the mental health needs of orthodox faithful through the development of ministry resources.
Once again, that web address is www.asssemblyofbishops.org.
slashed mental, dash health.
This we're back now with the Lord of Spirits,
the father Andrew Stephen Damick and father Stephen DeYoung.
If you have a question, call now at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF radio.
You voice of Steve?
Always great to hear from you.
I actually had lunch with the voice of Steve last week.
just his voice.
Yeah, well, you know, I actually his body was present in all of its
So this is like this is the potentialities. This isn't like a metatron situation
Okay, yes, he's not the metatron
Or mega-tron
Yeah, so all right. Well, we do have a caller waiting
She's been patiently waiting Yvonne has a question about the tree of life. So Yvonne, are you there?
Yes, I am. Thank you for taking my call.
You're welcome. Yes, yes. Welcome to the Lord of Spirits podcast.
It's actually about the tree of knowledge and it's a quick question.
And then if it's okay, I have another quick question after that.
But everybody calls it the tree of knowledge.
But you know, how it's the tree of knowledge of good and evil?
Is that are they saying it's a tree of like judgment, like the old, you know,
the old fashioned definition of judgment, which was like discern.
I don't mean like...
I mean like discerning knowing good and evil knowing right and wrong. Is that? Is that what that means?
Yes, I'm just gonna go out and live and say yes.
Am I corrected my yes father? I just want to make sure it's stealing stealing my bit. Yeah. What can I say?
Yeah, if you go, I was gonna say if you as you go forward in the in the old testament
that phrase, knowledge of good and evil.
what it's used for in the rest of the Old Testament is sort of coming of age or maturity, right?
Like a child becomes an adult when they're able to know good and evil.
Yeah.
So the idea is it's not an evil tree.
The idea is that there would have been some point when Adam and Eve had reached a point of maturity
where God would allow them then to come to that knowledge, right?
They would have been mature enough and prepared for it, but they
Hey,
to seize it for themselves, right? Or the devil gets them to seize it for themselves, right?
By telling them, you'll be like God if you do this, right? You'll sort of leapfrog the process.
Right. Yeah. Okay. So what was your follow-up question then, Yvonne?
Well then, you were talking about, oh gosh, now it's Abraham, Abraham, right? How he was in
by the Tower of Babel, you know when it fell apart.
So was he, it doesn't even matter.
but is it true that he had the original language?
You know, like how before the languages were divided,
whatever, like, he had had the,
because it pulls at that,
when he said what benefit is there in being a Jew,
and then he goes all much in every way
because they're the keepers of the oracles of God,
does that mean like that they had the pre-the-loovian language
and would it even matter or instead of Abraham have that,
if he was by battle?
So.
Well, I mean, I would love to say that the original language was Lithuanian, of course.
Or Old English, one of the two, but not likely.
Not likely, yeah.
No, so Abraham, as we just said, Abraham was associated with the Tower of Babel in Scripture,
right?
But he's not actually there.
He's a lot later, right?
So by the time we meet Abraham, the nations of the world have already been divided up into
many, many languages.
So could he have had the first language?
Like could he have held on to it?
You know what I mean?
Because I know you said that genealogy is really boring,
but there is a lie.
He's an author and his name is Vaughn Hepner, V-A-U-G-H-N.
Hepner, and he writes these fictional books,
but I actually have like, you know,
because his books are so good.
And they're very, very easy to read.
Like he goes into the genealogy.
That's what either of Janice is.
And um, but anyway, I think he suggested it in his books that maybe when Babel was spread out that
One of the groups kept the original language, but I guess nobody did
I mean, did anybody have had the pre-delute like is there anybody that I was just wiped out?
I would I would talk about like the books of Enoch and stuff like that being from
Pre-deluvian like somebody would have to speak the language, right?
Well, but we obviously we don't have any copies from back there.
Yeah, but I think most likely it's gone.
You could you could try to do that with Sumerian, I guess,
because Sumerian is a really weird language.
It's not related to any other language in in Earth history.
It's it's weird in that regard.
But at the time Abram lived in the...
in the Earth 3 period.
I mean, there were Sumerian words that got incorporated
into other languages, but he would have been speaking
a version of a Canadian by that point.
Right, which is a Semitic language.
Right, a Semitic language, yeah.
Because they do this some genius, like if you follow
if you like, do the math,
wait until it's jammed.
What have the stuns of an oral wood
have still been alive when Abram was alive?
and they suggested in this book that um...
They could have talked to each other on that.
I guess it doesn't matter, it's all fictional.
Yeah, yeah.
The problem with that approach,
this will get people grumpy at me.
The problem with taking that approach to the genealogies
is that if you try to take any one of them literally
in the Old Testament,
you run into trouble with some of the other ones.
First off, like they don't match.
And the way ancient genealogies were written,
Thank you.
list every single generation. They just listed important figures. So especially the genealogy
of Abram, there's probably a lot being skipped and here's why. Because if you take those
numbers that you say there's no skip generations at all, then there are only 300 years between
the flood in Abram. And it seems on or not the flood in Abram.
between the Tower of Abel and Abram.
And it seems unlikely to me that you would go
from all the people in the world being in one place
to Abram being able to meet the Pharaoh of Egypt
and they have a whole civilization over there in Egypt
and then they have a whole other civilization
in Sumeria and another one in Syria.
And there are kings and they're developed
to different languages and all of that
that all of that could happen in 300 years.
Yeah, it's just not a thing.
It's just not possible.
The other thing is that, you know, just even speaking from a linguistic point of view,
language changes a lot.
And there's no, even if someone is safe living for hundreds of years, there's actually
no reason to believe that they wouldn't change the way that they speak along with everybody
else.
Right.
I mean, I've lived in different parts of the United States and I even lived on the island
of Guam for a while.
And the way that I talk has altered, right?
I do not sound like the southerner that I was born to be.
I sound now more like the Yang.
he's among whom I live.
And that's just within my few decades of life,
languages change over time.
They simply do, especially when you don't have
mass culture like television and radio and so forth
and mass literacy, everything just goes
a lot more quickly in terms of the way that it changes.
So it's just not plausible on any measure.
So, all right, well, does that answer your questions, Yvonne?
Is that...
Thank you so very much. All right. Well, thank you for calling. All right. Okay. Well now that we've
We've watched God come out of sear and come to rescue his people in in Egypt
Although we should say we see that in progress. Yeah. Let's go to another mountain, right? Another significant mountain that
Yes, yes, another mountain that is being the mountain of God and that's Sinai
Right, so
We've already seen one transition, we're a couple actually,
but we've seen this transition to God being the God of these particular human persons.
Right. Right. And being where they are. And then we saw him being at this mountain.
Now we're at Sinai, of course, we see, well, at first with Moses, right,
we see the same pattern we saw with the patriarchs in the sense that,
Yahweh, the God of Israel is with Moses. Right.
He's with Moses and Aaron when they go back to Egypt. Right.
now with them as people, but once we get to Sinai, we then get the instructions given
to build the Tabernacle.
And so this then is going to be a transition where there's going to be this place where
God is going to be, where His presence is going to be in this particular tent, which is
going to be set up at the center of the Israelite camp while they're wandering in the desert
and making their way, they're gonna pitch their tents and...
camp and another thing that people love reading their favorite part of the
Torah is the detailed instructions in the book of numbers about the order in
which the tribes march and where they set up camp in relation to each other and
to the tabernacle. I know that's like the big everybody's super excited about
that. But still a big cosplay reenactment or so. Right. So but the the tribes camped
Oh
around, right, in a circle around the tabernacle, right? Right. And that, just that way of camping,
you have God dwelling in the midst of His people, and you also have this idea starting to
develop that we're going to go into more detail here in a minute of these sort of concentric
circles leading out from where the presence of God is, right? Right. You've got the presence
of God in the tabernacle, then the next circle out, you've got the camp, and then outside
then you've got outside the camp.
So this is in a certain way a return to the way things were
in Eden or Paradise.
Yeah.
Because you had the walled garden.
And then you had the world outside of it.
And you now have the world outside the camp
and then the camp with the tabernacle at its center.
And that's why you get the Edenic imagery in the tabernacle.
Right.
So but for our purposes tonight, where we're eventually going to talk about
pinnacost, the most important part of this, and we talked before the sacred
geographies that we talked a little bit about the tabernacle there from that
other perspective. But we want to talk about what unfolds in Leviticus 8 through
10 right as the tabernacle is put into
and consecrated. Okay. So before we get to that, we actually do have a caller. So Christopher
is calling and Christopher, are you there? I am. All right. Well, Christopher, welcome to
Lord of Spirits podcast. What is your question or comment or insinuation for us this evening?
Well, I'm reading just actually just finished Father Steven's book. Oh, you have a book,
You have a book, Father Steven?
he does. Yeah. I don't know if faith still has it, but yes, I do have a book. Buy them now, everyone.
Sorry. Sorry. Go ahead, Christopher. I'm sorry.
Well, I have a question about the the angels that got assigned to govern the nations and cities.
And I wonder how all of them became corrupt and demons because I know they're talked about and
and talk it in the Lewis's, so we have faces and they have...
a mixed influence there.
Good and bad.
Right.
So how did all of them become
correct?
The gadgets choose the wrong
ones or what?
Well, it depends on what you
mean by how did.
Right.
Um, well, so it's not all of
them because they're St. Michael.
Right.
Number one, right?
So it was one at least, but
also also.
I think.
Um, I think what
why people understand this point is that I haven't effectively communicated what I'm
hopefully about to effectively communicate.
You'll have to tell me.
So it's not just a question of well okay there are these 70 individual angelic beings,
plus a Michael.
And those particular beings are assigned to these nations and each of those beings individually
goes bad.
So...
And in some cases, that's what happens, that that individual being goes bad.
But you also have cases like Nernerda that we were just talking about, where the people
of a given city begin worshipping a demonic entity.
And by doing that, that demonic entity by then becoming demonized in their worship of
him, that demonic entity becomes the power that's controlling that city.
Yeah, they're sort of dark patron
So, is that the people that are causing it by making it an idol?
Well, so what he's saying is that in some cases, you've got essentially a good patron
who goes bad by virtue of accepting worship that's being offered to him by the human beings
under his care.
But in the case, for instance, of Babylon, it's being depicted as you've got probably a giant
spirit. So we're talking about a demonized human soul who interacts with the locals and they
begin worshipping him and taking him as their patron. So he was already bad before they started
doing idolatry with him. Okay. So that's how you get bad patrons in one way or the other.
Right. And so that obviously there are now more than 70 nations. Right.
In different places in the world. Right. Right. And so a lot, but what the scriptures do tell us is
is that all the gods of the nations are...
demons. Yeah, right. Uh, and what the pagans offered sacrifice, they offered to demons.
Right. So there's there's no indication that any of them are still worshiping Yahweh.
Right. That's the key. They're not worshiping Yahweh. So if they're angel, if I'm sorry.
Go ahead. So by, uh, by Saint Paul's time, when he writes in 1 Corinthians, when he says
all the, all the gods of all the city, states, those are all demons that are all just
It's followed by that time.
Well, or they're worshiping another spirit, right?
So none of the nations of the world go on to worship unfallen angels, right?
They stop worshiping Yahweh the true God and they start worshiping other things.
So in some cases, that's the angel who was assigned to them who has now fallen and is
participating.
in that worship. In other cases, it's some other demonic spirit that they started worshiping.
Okay. That distinction helps. Yeah. Yeah. And so, but the point is that it's now the demon
who's in control, right? Through sin, the power of sin, and through death, who has now
enslaved those people. Okay. Does that make sense? It does make sense. Yes. All right.
to the end of the book.
always going to be more always going to be more questions. So yeah, all right, well,
well, thank you very much for calling, Christopher. Good to talk to you. Okay. So we were talking
about the tabernacle. And we were just about to discuss how it gets consecrated. So how
do you consecrate a tabernacle? Not that I recommend going and doing this. Yes, right.
for the rest at home.
This is not how to, is it like, hey,
got a kid?
Yeah, have fun.
Yes, because she wants you about to hear how it's done.
Yes.
So there are.
There are sort of two principal things that are done and then something happens.
So all of the elements.
So when we talk about elements here, I'm talking about the physical objects that make up the tabernacle.
So physical objects like the altar of incense, the altar of burn offering, the tent posts, the tent pegs.
the goat hair curtains, right? All the things, right? They're going to be put to get physically
put together to make the tabernacle. And the tabernacle that is going to designate the
space where it is, right, as sacred. All of those things are first purified with sacrificial
blood, right? Purified from what? Right? Well, they're taken out of the world, right? We've
talked about this before previous episode.
those are taken out of the world where they have the taint and stain of the sin and wickedness in the world on them.
Right? And it's not just a question of them being pure enough to come into the camp. This is going to be God's presence.
So it has to be completely pure. And so the sacrificial blood like in in the day of atonement cleanses these physical objects.
then they're anointed with oil right and then after that has been completed then
The Theophanec Glory Cloud, a certain group of people just got excited.
Yeah, that's going to be the name of my next band. The Theophanec Glory Cloud.
The, uh, you're inclined to do that, are you?
The, the, I got that reference.
Yeah. So the, the, the fiery cloud, which is the presence of God,
which is the Holy Spirit, really, right? The presence of God in the world,
the one who couldn't bear with man before the flood.
Right. And had to leave now comes to fill the tabernacle. Yeah, right. Comes and fills the tabernacle.
So now the question of where is God is answerable because he's in the tabernacle now. Right. Yeah.
This is this is this is where he's going to be located as the Israelites for 40 years are on their way
to the land of Canaan.
And so then in Leviticus 10 right after this happens.
the story of Nadab and Abahoo unfolds.
Right, which I feel like should be the scriptural passage that is covered in the first day of liturgics and seminary.
I can't even just be a good idea.
Just to steer everyone.
Yeah, and you're printed it, you know, right now, like the liturgic on has the commandments of St. Basil de Pris which are excellent.
There should be also a page where you just simply include this passage.
Right.
Yeah.
So the they'd have an Abahoo are two of the sons of Aaron, right?
The high priest and they're in their Levites, right? They're
They're part of the priestly bunch, right and
well the Levites
Well anyway, we don't get that. Yeah
Yeah, they're in the high water the family. They're their family exactly and
So people argue about what exactly the problem was and you get different hints and different
parts of the text.
I go for an all in approach of they did everything wrong.
Right.
So we know from the text that they were drunk.
We know from the text that they went into offer incense at the wrong time.
Right.
Maybe because they were drunk.
also know because it's called strange f-
that they offered the wrong kind of incense, right?
Because there's the whole incense recipe
and how they were supposed to offer it, right?
So they're drunk and they do everything wrong
in terms of what they were supposed to do
and their duties to go into the tabernacleist priests.
And they fall over dead.
Fire comes out for the presence of the Lord
and consumes them.
Yeah.
Right. Death by holiness.
Right.
And so this is
not only, right, we see this theme again, but this is an object lesson now to all the people in the camp.
Right. Here's what I'm saying. We need to put it on the turtap books.
That the fact that God is now dwelling in their midst is not just, oh, lovely, right?
Yeah.
Isn't that nice?
Right.
I really, I really feel like God is here tonight.
This is it. That should scare you.
Yeah.
right? Someone says that? No.
This is a serious thing, right?
A serious thing.
And so they need to conduct themselves accordingly.
And so when the day of Atomant ritual
that we've already gone through in detail
in a previous episode is given in Leviticus 16,
when it's given, it's given expressly
right at the beginning of the chapter,
it's given because of what happened to Nate Abinabahoo.
Right, that's verse one of chapter 16.
The Lord spoke to Moses after the death
the two sons of Aaron when they
the junior before the Lord and died,
and the Lord said to Moses, et cetera.
And this was a good five chapters previous.
Yeah, right.
So it's brought up again here, to our point.
This is why, right?
And so this process is put in place
for the cleansing with blood and reconsocation
once a year of the tabernacle,
the purification and reconsocation every year
of the tabernacle, so that the priest
will be able to go in safely.
come and safely into the presence of God, right?
The purification that's necessary for them.
And expanding out from that, this is what the vast majority
of the Torah is, right?
The law.
Torah not like the first five books, Torah like the law,
right?
The way we think about it.
This is what the commandments are aimed at.
The commandments are aimed at.
And this includes both what we'd call quote-unquote moral
Okay.
commandments and what we quote unquote call purity laws and all of it, right?
That distinction, by the way, was first made by a second century
in Austin. I had to throw that in. Anyway,
what the whole thing is aimed at is God is now living in our midst.
We're now in the presence of God. This is how we need to conduct ourselves to do it for that to be safe.
because if we don't, one of two things that we've already seen in
scripture in Genesis, one of two things is going to have to happen. Either God is going
to the language that's used in the Torah is God is going to break out in the camp and
people are going to die. If he stays and we are impure and wicked, or out of his love
for us, he's going to have to leave. And then he's not going to be with us anymore.
We don't want either of those things to happen. And so the Torah was laying out what had
to happen.
for that to be possible.
And then you get, because of that, this is, and I know we've talked about this before, at least briefly,
you have those concentric circles and those concentric circles, the closer you go in,
the more purity is required of you.
Right? So the Torah sets this standard for purity,
for the Israelites who are living in the camp who are living near to the presence of God.
They have to have a higher standard of holiness than the rest of the world.
Right.
So I God never tells them, you need to go and make the Syrians stop eating pork.
Yeah. No, it's. Yeah. Right? Because it's not law. It's not actually law.
Right? It's not some kind of eternal legal moral standard.
That's, it's not that. It never function is that. Yeah. It's a liturgical preparation.
And so they didn't have to force that a
else because they're not living anywhere near God. They're not drawing near to the presence of God.
So they don't need that holiness. Now if they want to, if they want to come and eat the Passover,
well then they have to be circumcised and then they have to start following the commandments.
Which safely draw close to God.
Yeah, which I mean has an obvious pastoral application in our time, which is frankly that
that the only people, I mean, however you want to slice it,
the only people are actually going to be effective.
in terms of convincing them to follow the commandments of God are those who are trying to draw near
to him. The people who are not have no reason to do that. You know, I mean, you could try to convince
them of its benefits or whatever, but really, they don't have any good reason to do that. And
if you look at the command that Christ gives the apostles, he doesn't tell them
go into all the world and tell them to do my commandments. It's go into all the world,
baptize them make them disciples and
teach them to do all that I have come like it's the whole point is is that it's entry into the church that
involves all of that right it's the other way yeah yeah yeah it's not you know it's it's not yeah
exactly I mean the call to repent is a call to draw near to God because the kingdom of heaven is
at hand that's what's going on it's precisely this exact same exact same dynamic right but so
So yes, on one hand we live in a society, so I'd rather not have to worry about my...
he the neighbors murdering me, right?
Yes, right.
There's a certain amount of restraining
that he's to go on.
Right.
But on the other hand, on the other hand,
me trying to go and get people who don't know Christ
to live a moral life has no value.
And it has no more value to them to have lived a moral life
rejecting Christ than it would for a worshipper of an anerda
that not eat pork.
Yeah.
Right.
It means nothing, it does nothing, right?
Right, so this is all about trying to close it so that the Israelites have this higher standard than the surrounding world.
The priests within Israel who are the ones who are living and working in and around the temple have a yet higher standard, right?
The regular people in Israel did not have to maintain the level of purity that the Levites have the priesthood.
And then the
High priest most of all right because the high priest had to do all the preparation for the day of atonement for that one day when he went into the the holy of holies. Yeah, and so when we get to
Solomon's Temple the first temple all of this that we see in the tabernacle which is mobile gets concretized. Right in terms of a fixed building in a fixed place.
stationary, right? And it's important to note that
This was not God's idea
Right he didn't because I mean how how many times is he saying scripture God is not dwell on temples made by hands
Right
God it's not God's idea for them to build a temple, but he agrees to it
Just as it wasn't his idea for them to have
You know a human king he agrees to it, you know
Yeah, yeah, right and and there's this
Great disparity, right? That you notice very quickly when you actually read the text, right?
You go to the last whole last half of Exodus is all of the minutia of the instructions for every element of the tabernacle being given in detail twice.
Yeah, God, it's God's blueprints, literally. Yes, and they're all laid out and then it describes them doing it in the same level of detail.
so you get it all twice.
You don't get that with the temple.
Yeah, it's literally man-design man-dead.
Yeah, and the way that the temple is described is actually almost identical to a sero-finition
temple built at the same time.
Meaning a pagan temple built at the same time.
Now, when I've said that publicly before, I've had people come to me and say, hey, there's
this one verse in first chronicles that if you read kind of sideways of squint and it
Kind of...
sounds like God gave David the plans for the temple. Okay, and my response to that is,
let's save that's what that verse really means. Do you still think that one verse with
a passing mention in First Chronicles is comparable to the whole second half of the book
of Exodus in the Torah? You don't see any difference there. Right? I just kind of love
the fact that someone is reading the Bible so closely that they come to you with that
So that's great. Yeah.
They weren't Google searching to try and yes, there's that as well. Yes, Google School of Theology, but
You see this very clearly when you when you see the dedication, right? We're talking about the dedication of the tabernacle
Well, you look at the dedication of the temple
You see this very clearly in terms of Solomon's prayer and then God's response because Solomon's prayer is very much
I mean, it's it's virtually tower of Babel kind of stuff
It's moving in that direction, right?
It's Lord, whatever anybody prays toward this temple, give it to them.
It's, you know, God do all this stuff related to this temple as object, right?
It's very close to like, we want you to come live with this object and then we're going to use
that fact to get what we want from you, right? And so then the flip of that, God responds and
and goes into great detail about how he did not ask.
for a temple and he does not live in buildings made with human hands and he's not going to
automatically do that and if they keep the commandments he will bless them and if not they're in
trouble right he lays all that out and then at the end basically says but because I know you are
human and weak and hardhearted I will condescend and I will come to dwell in this building.
Right, so then again they do the purification with blood, the anointing with oil.
And then you get once again the name of my next band the theophonic glory cloud, right comes and fills
fills the temple yeah, and so then this is the place where God is
Israel is destroyed
by the Assyrians the northern kingdom
Judah
Right God departs from the temple and
They go into exile and you see the two faiths there, right?
You see death with the northern kingdom you see exile, right?
having to remove himself with Chuda, with the Southern Kingdom. And he does that again so they won't be destroyed, like the Northern Kingdom.
Yeah, because they will be destroyed.
Because they fell into evil. Right, they go into exile just like Adam and Eve were exiled from the garden, so that they can repent and eventually return.
Yeah, so then after, I don't know, how long is it in the Babylonian exile? 70 years.
Yeah, yeah, they come back and
and they rebuild the temple under Ezra.
So you got the second temple.
Thus, this is our term, second temple Judaism, right?
And they do the consecration service, the blood,
the oil, but there's no theophonic glory cloud.
That's a big difference.
Right.
Yeah.
Does that mean it doesn't work?
that the temp that they're not actually worshiping there.
I mean, no, they're offering the sacrifices there.
Yeah, but it's sort of from a distance, like a better song.
But there is no, there is no direct experience of God happening there.
And then and Tychus, the fourth epiphanies, the Seljuk and monarch comes and
desecrates that temple and it falls into ruins.
And the Maccabee brothers get torqued off and go in.
and
stage their successful war to reclaim the temple and regain their
independence and they go and they rededicate the temple and start the
celebration of Hanukkah but no the offentic glory cloud even after that
rededication right even after all that and so this is something that in the
Second Temple period, they were keenly aware of.
Yeah, God did not...
come back. Right. Yeah. And even, and even then I can't remember, I'm the timeline is,
is not clear my head, but the when the Roman general Pompey actually, when was that in relation
to the Maccabees? That was 110 years later. The Maccabees were under the, yes. That's
right. I was, yeah. So then the Romans come in and the Roman general Pompey decides to go,
walk into the temple and go all the way into the Holy of Holies in which like if this had
been 500 years before whatever.
would have meant he would have been struck dead before he even got in but he goes back there
and he just doesn't see anything and he's like oh they must worship their God with their minds
you know like he's so impressed by that but literally but but but but God's not back there
yeah the Ark of the Covenant isn't even back there yeah this back there is literally an empty
the Cherubic Throne, right?
An empty Throne.
And so they were aware of this.
And this is part of why they understood themselves
to still be an exile, right?
It wasn't just that they were still being dominated
by the Persians and then the Greeks and then the Romans
because there was that brief period with the Maccabees,
with the Hasmoneans, when they were independent, very brief.
They made a treaty with Rome and it was a bad idea.
That's how they got annexed.
But they were aware of this fact, right?
God hasn't come back.
we're still under foreign domination.
This isn't it, right?
And so we see this language in the New Testament
of restoring the kingdom to Israel.
We see this like, and these various groups,
various Judaism's of this period relate themselves
to the temple of Jerusalem in different ways.
We tend to think that they all accepted it,
but they didn't.
So the Cumeron community that produced the Danciskroles,
their whole basis was of going out in the desert
and doing sort of reconstructed temple rituals out there
was because they were...
rejected the validity of that temple, right? They're like,
God's not there. This temple's bogus. There were the Jewish
community in Elephantina in Egypt who built their own temple
there. I did not know that. Yes. Is there anything left to
that? Is that around at all? Yeah. Yeah. You can see where
the well of souls was and stuff. You could see basically like the
floor plan of the foundation. Suddenly, I'm having Indiana Jones
flashbacks here.
Yeah.
So, right.
So.
So they were aware of this that this hadn't happened.
And that they're looking toward deliverance,
especially associated with the Messiah.
And this is part of what that deliverance is going to bring.
It's not just, you know, we're so used to history
being written in the 19th century German mode
that, you know, we thought, oh, they're all
looking for a political Messiah.
Like politics was separated from everything else at that time.
Yeah, no, they wanted God back.
in their worship center. Right. They wanted the Romans out and they also wanted God back.
And those two things were related. Right. Right. Right. So as we end this half,
right, I wanted to break down for a minute because I don't think we have this in our heads fully.
When we talk about the tabernacle or the temple being in the middle of the temple,
of the people of Israel and this kind of thing.
I think somewhere in our heads, most of us have this idea
that it's like, well, that's where they went to church,
right?
Because we're kind of reading our own experience back into,
Their experience.
Right.
And often Orthodox Christians will not entirely incorrectly say,
well, you know, our worship is like temple worship, right?
Which is not totally wrong, but it's wrong in certain key ways
right right yeah yeah so yeah so let's imagine what it would be like if a modern
you know Orthodox Church actually functions like the temple or the tabernacle
right what would that actually look like right right so we're gonna say your
local Orthodox parish right is the tabernacle or the temple your and ancient
Israelite pilgrim going there for what of the feasts right because it was
right talked about before obviously.
without fast travel, people weren't going there every week. Right? So this is a lot more like Eden,
right, which was still closed and the chair with the sword is still there, right? You're near.
You're able to draw near to God, but not go into His presence. So if you're the average person,
you would come to the narthex.
right of your local Orthodox parish. You would lead your animals to the
narthex or you would bring money because there would be people in the narthex
and in in parts of the parking lot selling sacrificial animals for people who
couldn't came from a long way away and couldn't bring animals with them.
Right. And you would get your house you would then give those animals to the
priest. The priest would go take off with the
animal take it to the place called the
He killed the animal, he butchered the animal, he skinned the animal, separate the meat
the way he was supposed to, under the law.
He would take the portions that were going to God, he would take them out into the parking
lot and burn them on a big barbecue pit out in the parking lot.
He would then hand you your wrapped up pieces of meat to take with you to eat with your
family.
And that would be it for you.
Right, you would that be your visit.
Yeah, you wouldn't go into the equivalent of the nave.
Right.
And only the priests would go there.
Yes.
And the Holy of Holies, which in modern Orthodox churches,
the sanctuary, the area where the altar is,
no one would go there except what, once a year,
the high priest would go there.
Right.
And the women and children would stay in the parking lot.
The male head of the family would go in the narthex and deal with the priest.
with the priest.
And actually make these things right.
And the priests would go for
matins and festers,
they would go into the nave and only the nave
and offer incense and prayers twice a day.
And then one day a year,
the high priest,
Kallit of the Bishop,
would go back behind the iconostos
only on that day,
with a big cloud of incense
and purify the place.
And then come out. That was worship. Right. This is this is our pre-Christian worship. If we put it into those terms. Right. So I think we need to realize just how shut out from the presence of God.
People still were in order to understand the reality of what we have now going on in church.
And with that
We're going to go ahead and take our second break.
We'll be right back.
Father Andrew Stephen Daymak and Father Steven DeYoung
will be back in a moment to take your calls
on the next part of the Lord of Spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF Radio.
No one of books these days offer us techniques
self-improvement.
But in the newest release from the ancient faith store, gratitude in life's trenches,
Robin Phillips takes a different tack.
He shows us that God made us where we are in the pain and heartache of the present moment.
Instead of looking for a way to escape from hardship, we can cultivate an attitude of gratitude,
peace, and self-acceptance that will transform our experience of suffering.
Drawing on his own experiences and his work as a consultant in the behavioral health industry,
as well.
the stories of saints and sufferers, teachings of the fathers, and recent discoveries in neuroscience.
Phillips shows us that the journey to personal well-being is one we can all travel,
regardless of the hardships we may face. To find this book and others like it, you can go to
store.enginefaith.com. Again, that is store.enginefaith.com. We're back now with the Lord of Spirits,
The father Andrew Stephen Damick and
Father Stephen DeYoung, if you have a question call now at 855-237-2346. That's 855-AF radio.
All right, welcome back and thank you for that voice of Steve. We would love to hear from you,
so do give us a ring. Okay, so we just talked about how the actual experience of a worshiper
an ancient Israel was and compared it against.
our experience now as Christians actually coming to church, coming into the
nave, men, women and children, and actually having and seeing the veil opened to
the Holy of Holies, you know, very different from ancient Israel. And so there
has to be some kind of transition between these states. So let's talk now about
about what happens in the New Testament.
There is a transition and it starts...
with a young, young girl.
What was she about?
What do they say?
She was two or three years old, I think?
Yes, yeah.
When she was old enough to be brought to the temple,
the Theotokos.
So this is a little bit pre-New Testament.
They're right.
Yes, all right.
Well, slightly pre-New Testament.
Yes.
And so we have, for folks who are listening
who aren't Orthodox, we have a feast, right?
Of the entrance of the Theotokos into the temple.
Be careful.
as has been handed down to us by Christians since this happened,
who I don't think are liars.
The Theotokos, when she was born to her parents, they were at an advanced age,
and so to give thanks to God for giving them their child, St. Mary,
they brought her to the temple to serve as one of the
a virgin there. This was an institution that already existed. It goes actually back to
the tabernacle. One of the rarely discussed offices of the old covenant was that there
were women who lived at the entryway to the tabernacle. So they couldn't go into the
courts of the tabernacle, but they lived just outside the gates and they were dedicated
to assisting the priests and the Levites in
terms of sowing cloth, preparing things,
repairing things, feeding people,
taking care of all of these sort of duties.
And so when the temple came about,
and we know for sure,
because this is recorded,
people talk about it with the second temple,
but when the temple came about,
obviously you have it now in one fixed place,
you had these women who were dedicated into,
and their referred.
as virgins because they didn't get married, right?
So rather than having children, having responsibilities to a husband and children, they dedicated their lives to taking care of these things.
And because of that, they had to maintain a higher level of purity because they're closer, right?
And then the rest of the people.
And so the Theotokos was brought to be one of these women when she was a young girl.
right which I mean and just as a
sidebar, I mean, what a what a contrast that is to what the nations were doing, right?
They also had women that were hung around their temples.
That's right.
Yeah, and shrines.
And they were the opposite of, you know, virginal pure, like it was, it was yeah, exactly.
That we could be fair and throw the Romans the Vestal Virgins, but that's a whole other discussion.
Yes, right.
But and this is also important and I won't delve into this right now, but
Sometimes we get questions from our Protestant friends about the importance of the theotokos as ever virgin
That she was always a virgin through her whole life
This is a big part of that. Yeah, cuz she's been set aside for this
It's yeah, it's a part of her dedication of her whole life and self to God. That's the focus of that not anatomy
Right, right. That's not primarily what it's about
so
So this happened and then
And what our forefathers of the faith have added down to us is that then when she came
of age because of those same purity laws she could no longer remain in those temple precincts.
And so that's when she was betrothed to Saint Joseph as her protector who was an older
widowed man who was to care for her.
And then presumably at some point in the
future, she would have, right, if she had, you know, given birth to our Lord, she would
have come back to the normal process. She would have come back to the temple to continue
serving in that capacity. This is also the role that the prophetess Anna has when Christ
has brought to the temple to be dedicated. And there's this widowed woman there who's
been living there for years since her husband died. She is also one of these women.
So in the feast, we celebrate her being brought to the temple.
And the story that's been brought down to us is that she,
in sort of a contrasting parallel to the general Pompey,
went back into the temple itself and went back even
into the Holy of Holies.
And this event is we have in iconography.
We have it in the feast, the festival celebration,
and in the hymns related to it.
But the key element of this that's being brought across to us
and that is relevant for what we're talking about tonight
is that this is the beginning of that transition.
Right, right.
And she's welcomed back there by Zachariah,
the priest who, of course, he knows,
he's, well, it happens later.
But I mean, he's the father.
the four runner like he's got this prophetic.
place, you know. And I think a lot of the hymns talk about him, you know, the Holy Spirit
comes upon him and he welcomes her, you know, to do that, which is, I mean, that's the
appropriate thing for a priest to do. A priest is there to serve as the one who connects
people to God, right? But in this case, she's coming to be, she's essentially in some ways
coming not quite to take his place but but she's there to fulfill that role.
he's there to be the temple.
Right, because he's,
God's where God is going to dwell.
Right, even though this is the second temple,
so technically that's not,
that's only kind of the place where God is.
Yeah, it's not.
So it's not.
Really a temple.
Yeah.
Her womb is going to become the place where God
will be whiz for nine months, right?
Yeah.
While, while Christ is within it.
And so this sort of hand off, right?
sort of takes place.
at this feast and at this point.
And so she is being set apart to be God's dwelling place.
And so in our tradition that we've received,
the understanding is that the Thayotokos like the Tabernacle
and like the temple was purified by the Holy Spirit for this role.
Right, and there's a couple.
different, there's a couple different views amongst the church fathers as to
exactly when that happened. Some of them, like St. John Christophe and some
others, say that it happens at the enunciation. So she's purified when the
Archangel Gabriel comes to her and then the Lord is conceived within her womb. But
then others say that she gets purified in her mother's womb, but notably
after her conception. So after she's conceived in the
unusual way by her parents, God purifies her in the womb of
Saint Anna so that she is then prepared throughout her life. So
there's variation on this point between some of the church
fathers, that's okay, it's okay, it's all right. Right.
They all agree that she was purified. Yes. And they all agree
that it happens before the conception.
of the Lord and you know it's just a question of exactly when before that right and someone
might ask why would she need to be purified in the womb right obviously she hadn't committed
any sins right in the womb right right but the response to that of course is that yeah the
goat hair flap of the tabernacle that Moses purified with blood and anointed with oil hadn't
committed any sins either.
Right.
Yeah, yeah, yeah, go back and listen to our atonement episode for a little treatment of that
It's about dealing with the residue of sin in the world right existing in the world
Yeah, right and her being set apart for this special purpose of being being purified
For this purpose and and this isn't just this this crazy
Mary thing that as orthodox folks came up with right
Um.
Yeah, yeah, there are other there are other saints that experienced this too
Right right so it in our
Traditional understanding right Saint John the four runner was
Purified and received the Holy Spirit in his mother's womb. That's why he was able in the womb to give testimony to who Christ was
When the Thaotokos came to visit Saint Elizabeth
The prophet Jeremiah says God set him apart from his mother's womb
right have to be right
to be the prophet. So this is something we see repeatedly in Scripture and in the history of
the Church that there are particular individuals who God sets aside in calls to a particular purpose.
And when he does that, he comes and he purifies them. And sometimes it's later in their life,
like St. Paul on the road to Damascus. And sometimes it's all the way back in their mothers' womb.
Yeah. And sometimes you see something like that and you might think yourself,
Like well how come I wasn't purified and my mother's
and I have to struggle against sin and whatever, whatever, whatever.
But number one, that is simply not the way that the world works.
But number two, anyone who had this,
they usually went through a whole lot of suffering
as they fulfilled God's purpose for them.
Almost all of them.
It's not necessarily something you should ask for.
If it's something that God gives, then your...
responsible to that. But it's not something that God gives to very many. There's certain
people who he has a particular purpose for them and so this is what happens.
Right. And you don't necessarily really want to drink the cup that they drank.
Right. And aren't there certain cases even where, like, if I remember correctly, we were just reading
the readings last night for the feasts of the Nativity of the Forerunner. And one of the readings
is about Samson and it doesn't say that he's you know from his mother's womb and yet that did
turn out well ultimately, you know, um, and Samson didn't turn out well. Yes, yes, I've never heard
this before. Big center, big time center, big time breaker promises. If you say, if you say,
massive other Andrew, they make murder slash suicide at the end. Yes. Yeah. So, right. And so, so,
this is the, like we said, this is the beginning of the change, right? And of course,
right with the Theotokos.
Right, the Theotokos, the great gift she was given by God is that she got to participate
in the salvation that comes through her son, most fully and completely and directly and
personally.
Right.
And so when Christ comes, we have all of this language, particularly concentrated in St.
John's Gospel, regarding Christ being the new temple.
the new temple to replace
the second temple, the new temple like the one Ezekiel prophesied about during the exile.
Right. Right. Then it wasn't that second temple that it's actually, it's actually Christ when
he's born. And so, we see that at Holy Feeophony at Christ baptism in John 1, 32 through 34,
the Holy Spirit comes and ascends upon him and then rests within him, comes to abide in him.
The presence of God comes in.
stays, almost like a Theophonic Glory Cloud.
Yeah.
And then John 1 verse 14 is part of St. John's prologue.
He says, literally in the Greek, the word became flesh and tabernacled among us.
And we saw his glory,
that he was full of grace and truth.
Right, so that's the imagery of Christ's flash.
being like the curtains of the tabernacle. Right? And God's presence, God is dwelling among us,
right, in the flesh of Christ, and he is full of glory, right, like the glory, the
Ephanic Glory Club that came and filled the tabernacle and the temple.
Yeah, and, you know, to double down on his identification as the dwelling place of God,
as being
the temple in John chapter 2 verses 19 through 21, this very famous passage where Jesus
says, Jesus answered them, destroy this temple and in three days I will raise it up and the
Jews then said it's taken 46 years to build this temple and will you raise it up in three
days. And then this amazing editorial comment from St. John, but he was speaking about the
temple of his body, you know, that his body is the temple of God in their midst.
Right.
You know.
It's not that building, it's him now.
Right, and Christ isn't just the new temple,
but he's the final and eternal temple.
Right, one that Ezekiel talked about.
And so that's why I also written by St. John in the book
of Revelation chapter 21 in the new heavens of the new earth.
There's no temple because the Lamb is there in this nest.
Right, yeah, and if you want to read that Ezekiel reference
by the way, it is literally the last nine chapters of Ezekiel.
chapters 40 through 48.
it's it's stunning stuff. Yes, really, really, really beautiful. And it's talking about Christ.
Dispensationalist friends. I don't want to pick out our dispensationalist friends too much tonight, but
well, we're talking about temples and stuff. Past to happen. Yeah. Yeah.
That happened. So, yeah. Now, oh, and so the other place where this language of a temple is used,
of course, related to the Holy Spirit is Saint Paul. Right, right? And he talks about this at
at a couple points.
and first Corinthians and first Corinthians 3, 16, and 17, and 6, 19, where he says that
our body is the temple of the Holy Spirit.
Right?
So we will spirit.
That's not just about like you eat right and don't smoke or drink.
Your body is a temple.
Oh, okay.
No, I'm more on the side of the meme that my body is a temple.
It's broken down abandoned and decrepit.
like
shall remain one another.
So,
but
Y'all's body is a temple of the Holy Spirit.
Right. Yeah. And this isn't
this sort of separate independent thing.
Right. Where, where
there's now a whole bunch of temples.
Right. Not just Christ.
Right. It is. It is.
Right. As St. Paul says in Galatians 3 verse 27,
If we've been baptized in
Christ we've put on Christ. So I say Paul says in Christ after just about everything, right?
He just adds it on to almost every sentence, right? That's we our bodies have always written in
Christ. So Christ shares his templeness or tempolitude, right? With with us, right? If we are in
Christ, then we are functioning as a member of his body.
which is the temple, where his nexus of potentialities.
Right.
And so now,
dun dun dun.
In our Petticoz episode, we're going to talk about Petticoz.
Yes.
And we're going to just a little bit of build up to that.
Right.
Yes.
We prepare to prepare to prepare.
See, our podcast really works like the Orthodox liturgical year.
You know, it's just it's a year every episode.
Yeah, yeah
I mean, it's a liturgical season.
Yeah, there's a reason for this.
And only a few people out there will know what I'm talking about.
But I had too much Yale School preaching in my background.
So that's how you end up structuring things like this.
But so yeah, be saying now we're going to talk about Pentecost was actually sort of like
let us complete our prayer into the Lord.
Like yes, we've got a little ways to go.
Right exactly.
Exactly.
Okay. Luke chapter 24.
one of my favorite chapters.
because it's about Eastern Pennsylvania? No, it's about the...
This passage, so Luke 24 towards the end, Christ meets with two disciples as they're walking along the road,
since Luke and Cleopas. We talked about this a couple of weeks ago, a few weeks ago, with the post-Resurrectional
appearances of Christ. This is Christ on the road to a mess.
Why is this important?
It's on the road to Emmaus.
Emmaus in particular, right, right exactly.
So we talked earlier about the Maccabin revolt.
So that is successful at a battle that took place at Emmaus.
So Emmaus is like a famous battlefield in this time and place.
place. So like the example that you know from
time, again, to bring it back to Pennsylvania. If someone would say, you know, they were on
the road to Gettysburg, you're like, Oh, Gettysburg, yes, yes, I remember what happened
there. And that's exactly the same thing. Like, amaze is this famous place because of
the battle that happened there. And so everyone would would see when they'd, when you would
read that, right? And looks gospel, what you're getting then is this reference to this
This battle that was fought in one there, that led to them.
the temple being rededicated after had been desecrated. So that's all part and parcel of
on the road to Emmaus. Right. So people, people miss this a lot because they say they think this is
the only place Emmaus has mentioned in the Bible. But if I go and get your 1611 King James,
turn to first Maccabees. Right. Which is in the 1611 King James. Yes, I have a replica of a here in
in my studio.
Right.
The battle of a- this is the climactic battle where the cellulocates are defeated and driven
out.
So, yes, so this is what's being conjured up here is not just the battle, but the aftermath
of the battle and the idea of the rededication of the temple.
And the proof that St. Luke has the rededication of the temple in mind is how he ends his gospel.
the last two verses.
of the St. Luke's Gospel, Luke 24 verses 52 and 53.
Right. And they worshiped him and returned to Jerusalem with great joy and were continually
in the temple blessing God. Right. And so you may notice that, you know, this is volume
one, when you go to volume two in the book of the Acts of the Apostles, they're not hanging
out in the temple. Right. When St. Luke narrates the ascension again, he doesn't just
describe them going back to the temple.
Right.
So he's not that, you know, he's making things up
one time or the other.
It's just what he's choosing to focus on.
So why does he choose to focus on the temple
here at the end of the Gospel Luke?
It's to bring out this dynamic, right?
Christ has just won this victory, right?
That's what the Gospel is.
It's the report of a victory book from Father Andrew
coming soon.
Yes.
Thank you.
It's so.
Look, I've been selling...
your book a lot. So I expect a little bit in return here.
That's anything negative about it. No, no, it's good. It's good. I feel like I've been doing a
pretty good job actually. Yeah. I think my name's in the front. So it's just my narcissism that's
causing you to push it a little bit. That's right. So, right. A report of a victory. Yes. Right.
So this victory has happened. Right. And so the victory is being compared to the victory in a
mass and then what happens?
the temple is rededicated.
So what we should be expecting is we can close the back cover on volume one
and open the front cover on volume two is,
oh, now I'm going to read about the rededication of the temple.
Great.
And that frames then what we have
at the beginning of the book of Acts.
And if you remember the atonement episode, we talked about how
price atonement purifies not just
of anybody physical space, but the whole world.
The whole world, right?
Which is illustrated then, for instance, by the fact that you've got Cornelius, this Gentile
Centurion who receives the Holy Spirit even before he's baptized, and then also the incident
where Peter is told to eat these animals that previously have been unclean, and what
God's system is don't call any
unclean that God has made clean. God has made it clean and how did it become clean
by the atonement that Christ accomplished in his passion, death and resurrection.
Right, and so Christ's blood has now purified the whole cosmos. Right, and so now when
individual humans receive the laying on of hands and or anointing, the Holy Spirit
you
The Theophanic Glory Cloud, the presence of God, comes and fills them, right?
As a temple of God.
And this starts with the apostles on the day of Pentecost, right?
When you notice how the wind and the fire come into the room in which they're sitting, right?
So St. Luke even brings in that spatial idea to where the apostles are, right?
but the spirit cubs it fills.
not that room, making that room the new temple, but fills them. Yeah, right. Yeah. That's that.
Right. And yeah, I think this might be this might be peak Lord of Spirits episode structure here,
because literally we're now finally getting to what what Pentecost is. Right. Right. This may be the
worst offencing offensive all of that that pattern but I
I think it's to get there, we had to look at all of that, right?
So the Holy Spirit descends into them.
And but there's like, there's aftermath now, right?
So just as with the presence of God
in the tabernacle and the temple,
you had to do the purification, you had to do,
everything the right way in order to prepare
to be in the presence of God or else...
could die, again, death by holiness. Now there are things that happen connected to the fact that
the apostles and the church are now effectively the holy of holies. So the classic example,
and this was one that always puzzled me when I was a kid, I was never quite sure what to make of it.
You've got, you know, in there's still in Jerusalem and all the disciples, you know, all the
the Christians are pulling their stuff so that no one has to be in want.
Right? Yes, yes.
But it's voluntary.
But they, you know, so people are selling property and they're pulling their money so that everyone can be,
no one has to go hungry. And you've got this one couple, Ananias and Safaira, who decide to sell their property
and instead of giving all of it over to the apostles.
for the help of the poor, they give only part of it,
but then they lie about giving only part, right?
So first Ananias lies directly to St. Peter
and then he dies.
And then he's taken away and then his wife comes in
not knowing that he's dead
and St. Peter asked her the same question,
Did you give it all?
She says, oh yeah, this is all of it, which is as a sidebar,
is an interesting note that she is, as a Christian woman,
she is answering for herself.
She's not simply being lumped in with whatever her husband
happens to say, like she's actually responsible for herself,
which is a very different role for women in the ancient world.
And she lies also, and then also dies.
And when I was a kid, I read that I'm like,
That seems a little extreme.
Lord, you know, like, like, I mean, not that I have any business second, second guessing,
you know, God's judgments, but, but, but understanding it in terms of this question of death by
holiness, you know, they, they, they are literally bringing an offering to God, right? But doing
it in a bad way and lying. That's why they die. And St. Peter says, you have not lied to men,
but to the Holy Spirit. But to the Holy Spirit. The Holy Spirit cannot long contend with human
wickedness it's so
So Ananiyus and Safaira are the Nadab and Abahu of the new covenant.
It follows the same pattern here at the beginning of Acts, as the dedication of the Tabernacle.
And so then what comes in terms of the Christian life, right, they serve as this kind of warning.
And so if we are members of Christ's body, and therefore our body is the temple of the Holy
Spirit, and the Holy Spirit is in our midst, and Christ is in our midst when we gather
worship, then rather than the commandments and the way that the Torah works in our life
being like the old covenant where it was about purifying this physical space, this external
physical space and maintaining its purity in these concentric circles.
Now it's gone interior.
Right.
And so that's why the Christian life becomes about repentance.
It comes about cleansing and purifying and rededicating ourselves.
Yeah.
God of space.
Right.
Yeah.
It's, I mean, it's, I don't know the right word to use.
But it's really powerful to look at what's going on in the Old Testament there with the Tabernacle
and Temple and realize that actually now applies to us as persons because we are, we fulfill
that role now.
As much as we are in Christ.
Yeah.
Alright, well, let's give some final
comments. There's, at the first place I want to start is with that final point, right,
which that, that when we undertake the fasting, the prayer, the repentance, the asceticism,
all of these things that are part of Orthodox Christian life, you know, when we undertake
these things. It's I think often we can
receive that stuff is like there's one way which is people like, oh it's just burden I have to have because I'm orthodox.
Or sometimes people take it as being like a hyper macho thing.
Like, oh look at us, we're like the Marines of Christianity, we fast, we pray, we long services.
Like, right, you know, those ways of looking at it.
But fundamentally, those are kind of almost materialist ways of understanding these spiritual practices.
you
Right, they are disciplines, but a discipline has a purpose.
It's not merely just to be disciplined.
Right.
The discipline has a purpose, and the purpose is to prepare us to be in the presence of God.
And when we don't do that, then we degrade because it's not good for us to be in the presence of God,
and sometimes...
that degradation gets so extreme and our sin becomes so extreme that we have to be removed from
communion until such time as we are prepared to return again. So it's purification so that we
can worship God, so that we can be in His presence, so that we can be within the temple. We talked
earlier about what Wood orthodox Church life.
look like, if it actually functioned like the Tabernacle on Temple and how separated we
would be from God.
Now, we have the opportunity to be right there in the place where the sacrifices offered.
We have to prepare ourselves to do that.
That's what this life is for.
It's not just sort of like self-discipline or somehow or becoming better person.
It can do those things, but that's not what it's for.
And the other side I wanted to mention in my final remarks.
is that with the descent of the Holy Spirit into the church, and we being in Christ and
being his body, being now the temple of the living God, then what that means is the task
that Adam and Eve were given back way back in paradise where we started, has now been
restored to us, and we've been given the ability to actually take it further than they
they could have.
when they were first created because of their immaturity.
And that means that our task as Christians
is not simply to become better,
but rather to take paradise into the world,
to expand the temple,
to bring, you know,
because when someone becomes a Christian,
when they are baptized into Christ,
then they are then also part of the temple of the living God.
They become pillars of the temple of the living God.
Right.
So our task is to churchify the world.
And we do that not only by the act of evangelism, although that is absolutely critical, right?
Evangelism is a message.
It's the announcement of Christ's victory.
But it's also to take on this role of, you know, be fruitful, multiply, cultivate the
the earth and that doesn't just mean make sure you have a well mode backyard.
bringing God's love and justice and compassion to the people around you, right?
This is what the task is. This is how we bring the presence of God and his, his
making things right and putting things them in order. That's how we participate in
that. So this is God's act. It's God is the one who expands Eden, but it's our
task to be the the instruments by which that happens. So there is both an
internal side to it in terms of
of our own attention to our purification, to meet God, to worship God, to commune with God.
And then there's also this external outward initiative taking, outgoing side to it as well,
where we are to serve those around us, to sacrifice ourselves for those around us, so that they too
can participate in this same life. That's its purpose. All right, what you got for the end,
and Father Stephen.
No.
So, humans...
are like tartises
Yes, they're bigger on the inside
And I want to
Focus a little on we already
brushed on this a little bit but
The Holy Spirit comes and writes the law writes the Torah in our hearts
And this is how the New Testament expresses.
and the Old Testament prophesying that it would happen.
Talks about that internalization of the law
that we were talking about right at the end.
And despite the fact that we've probably all heard
or read that a thousand times,
I don't know how much it is sunk in for us,
because we still have this focus on the outside
and on the external and on our interactions
out there with the world.
when we think about commandments, whether we're thinking about the 10 commandments of the Old Testament,
we're thinking about the commandments of Christ.
We're thinking outside.
But what this internalization means, and you see it reflected everywhere in Christ's teaching in the Gospels.
Yes, if you have yeast in your house and you don't contain it and treat it properly,
it will infect things and infest things and can poison your kids and bad things will happen.
But if you allow a little left...
into your heart and your soul and your mind, it will spread and it will infect
everything and it will destroy you. The internalizing of that commandment is
far more important than the externalizing of it. And what Christ communicates to
us in the Gospels, we read a gospel on Sunday for Petticoast where Christ says
about the coming of the Holy Spirit, that rivers of water will flow from your belly,
right, which is a weird promise to receive. Most of us try to keep that from happening.
But what he's talking about are the rivers and paradise, the rivers and Eden
that flowed out of Eden to water the whole earth, all that external stuff, what we do in the world
in terms of the...
how we relate to people, how we relate to the world around us, how we see the world and interact with it,
all of that flows out of what's going on inside.
And so if we don't keep what's inside of us clean and pure and dedicated to Christ and to a service,
then everything that flows out of us is going to be tainted by whatever's wrong inside.
get good fruit from a bad tree, rotten tree.
And so I think what we need to be reminded of maybe
is that keeping the commandments of Christ,
living the Christian life, always begins
by going back into the paradise that's inside of us,
that the Holy Spirit has put there when we received Him
within ourselves and maintaining that space
with all the...
that the Levites and the priests of the old covenant had, purifying ourselves of
sin, rooting it out, finding it, driving it out, repenting of it, repairing what's
wrong, confessing, receiving forgiveness and cleansing and purification. And
once we maintain that, all of these other things will flow out naturally. The love,
the joy, the peace, the patience, the kindness, the goodness, the faithfulness,
the channel.
the self-control, all the fruits of the Spirit will blossom forth when we've done the hard work
of getting into the mess and the brokenness and the dirt and the grime and the ugliness that's
still lingering around in different places inside of us. So we talk a lot and Father Andrew just
talked about and rightfully so, I need to go out into the world. But we also need
to not forget to go inside of ourselves and take care of the temple, care for the temple,
purify and rededicate the temple that lies within us. And so now I have a question for Father
Andrew. Oh boy, if I sing spring up oh well, will you yell the splash splash in the background?
Wow.
That is a very dim, dim memory,
in a very shriveled part of my brain.
Glad to bring it back.
Thank you.
All right, well, on that note,
that is our show for tonight.
Thank you very much, everyone, for listening.
If you didn't get a chance to call in
during the live broadcast, we'd love to hear from you.
Either via email at Lordofspiritsatationsfaith.com
or you can message us at our Lordofspirits podcast,
Facebook page.
you do read everything but we
can't respond to everything, but we do save what you send for possible use in future
episodes.
And join us for our live broadcasts on the second and fourth Thursdays of the month at 7pm
Eastern 4pm Pacific.
And if you are on Facebook, like our page, join our discussion group, leave reviews and
ratings everywhere, but most importantly, share this show with a friend whom you know is
going to love it.
Or even if you just think about love it, go ahead and share it.
And finally be sure to go to ancientfaith.com.
support and help make sure we and a lot of other AFR
podcasters stay on the air.
Thank you very much and may God bless you always.
You've been listening to the Lord of Spirits with Orthodox Christian priests, Father
Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung, a listener support.
presentation of ancient faith radio. And I beheld and I heard the voice of many angels
round about the throne and the beasts and the elders and the number of them was ten
thousand times ten thousand and thousands of thousands, saying with a loud voice,
worthy is the land that was slain to receive power and riches and wisdom and strength and
honor and glory and blessing. Revelation chapter 5 verses 11 through 12.
The Center for Family Care, a Ministry of the Greek Orthodox Archdiocese, nurtures and
and powers families.
Helping them to...
to educate the joys and challenges of life.
Its ministry focuses on equipping families
to apply the teachings and practices
of the Orthodox faith to every dimension of their lives.
This podcast will feature interviews,
reflections, book reviews, and narratives
that will encourage dialogue and strengthen families.
Welcome to Family Matters.
My name is Father Alex Gucettis,
and today we are speaking with President
Christine Chambers-Monkowski.
Our top...
that begins organ donation, family decisions.
Visited a Christine received a Bachelor of Science
from Drexel University in Philadelphia
and later completed a Master in Theological Studies
at Holy Cross Orthodox School of Theology
in Brookline, Massachusetts.
She's married to Father Paul Minkowski.
Their parish, Saints Cyril and Methodius in Lorraine, Ohio
is under the Bulgarian diocese of the OCA.
In her secular work, Christina's work at the Cleveland Clinic for 15 years.
She was a medical embodisman there for five years.
And for the last 10 years, she has served as the clinic's organ donation coordinator.
And it's part of their end of life care team.
In this role, she works as liaison to life bank, the organ procurement organization in Northeast Ohio.
Welcome, Christine.
Thanks for having me, Father.
I'd like to be
Begin by reading the pastoral guidelines of the Greek Orthodox Archdiocese of America
regarding the donation of organs.
Quote,
although nothing in the Orthodox tradition requires the faithful to donate their organs to others.
Nevertheless, this practice may be considered in act of love, and as such is encouraged.
The decision to donate a duplicate organ, such as a kidney, while the donor is living,
requires much consideration.
and should be made in consultation with medical professionals and one spiritual father.
The donation of an organ from a deceased person is also an act of love that offers the recipient
a longer, fuller life. Such donations are acceptable if the deceased donor had
willed such action, or if surviving relatives permitted, providing that it was in harmony
with the desires of the deceased.
Such actions can be a-
proved as an expression of love and the self-determination of the donor.
In all cases, respect for the body of the donor should be maintained."
Much more can be added regarding the scriptural and theological support of this position.
But our purpose here is to dialogue on a practical medical and emotional dimension of
organ donation.
And Christine is on the front lines of this process.
Can you tell us about-
how you became involved in this work?
Yes, I was, as you noted, an on-budsmine at the clinic
for a number of years.
And in that capacity, I really end up having a lot of
really pretty intense conversations with families
and also knew my way through the clinic
very well in terms of, you know, each institute
Institute and Doctors and Nurses in each institute.
So it put me in a particularly unique situation
when the position became available
for the organ donation coordinator,
a friend of mine had recommended me for the position.
And I'm really glad he did.
I think it's one of the few things
I would have wanted to do outside of being an on-budsman.
A budsman was a fabulous job,
but this is pretty incredible.
So it's really giving me a quite,
I can say more than perfect time.
I mean, it's-
a tough time to be with people at the end of life,
but it is clearly a very sacred time to be with people.
So I really, as I got more involved with the role
and really developing our end of life care team
at the clinic, it just has given me an opportunity,
really, to work very closely with families
and discuss this decision outside of the hospital
and inside the hospital.
And so I welcome the opportunity today.
Thank you.
So what's the process or the procedure of organ
donation. So as the statement you read from the church notes, father, there's living donation,
and then there's donation from a deceased donor. So what most people see in the news with
the living donation is a person is evaluated by the hospital's living donor team,
confirms that they're a match for the recipient, and then a surgery date is scheduled.
usually this is kidney or liver and that organ is recovered from the living donor and then
they immediately transplanted into the recipient.
So they both stay in the hospital to recuperate.
But today we're talking really about
deceased donor situations.
And that's a lot more complicated
than what we just described in the living donor situation.
So first of all, when we say organ donation,
we're actually talking about organ tissue and eye donation.
An organ donation can be considered
for patients at end of life who are on a ventilator.
later. So that would be patients who are in an intensive care unit in the hospital.
Tissue and eye donation can be considered for those patients in the intensive care unit
we just discussed, but also it's considered for every deceased person immediately. So immediately
following their death they can be considered for donation, whether that be in a hospital,
a hospice, or a care facility. So when we focus on donation, organ donation itself,
Hey.
I think we really have to be honest to say that most people are not familiar at all about how this miracle of donation actually works.
We see it on TV and in the movies and suddenly someone has donated an organ and the other person has received the organ and immediately following that the families are meeting and thrilled at what has happened.
That's not the reality.
It's a complex process and is designed to ensure that the gifts of the donor save as many
lives.
as possible. But I think it's important to first talk about for a minute who can
actually donate organs. So not everyone passes away in a manner where they can be
an organ donor. In fact a very small percentage of people die in a manner that
allows them to have their organs recovered for transplant. As we mentioned
I mentioned earlier the person is on a ICU. So the organs have to be continued to
received blood and they have to be viable for transplant.
The person must be on a ventilator.
So in most of these situations, the potential donor