He will be a staff for the righteous with which for them to stand and not to fall.
And he will be the light of the nations and the hope of those whose hearts are troubled.
All who dwell on the earth will fall down and worship him, and they will praise and bless,
and celebrate with song the Lord of Spirits.
1st denoc, chapter 48, verses 4-5.
The modern world doesn't acknowledge but is nevertheless haunted by spirits, angels, demons,
and saints.
You know...
time many year into break free of the prison of a flat, secular materialism to see and to know reality
as it truly is. What is this spiritual reality like? How do we engage with it well? How do we permeate
everyday life with spiritual presence? Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew Stephen
Damick and Father Stephen De Young post this live Colin show focused on enchantment in creation,
The union of the scene and unseen as made by God.
and experienced by mankind throughout history.
Welcome to the Lord of Spirits.
Good evening, everyone, and welcome to the Lord of Spirits,
podcast, I am Father Andrew Stephen Damick in Emeas, Pennsylvania.
And with me, from the almost the Gulf Coast, is Father Stephen D'Young
from Lafayette, Louisiana.
And if you're listening to us live, you can call into this program
program at 855-8-
F radio that's 8552372346.
And we're gonna get to your calls in the second part
of today's show.
So one of the historical movements
that has shaped Christian culture in the West
profoundly is the Protestant Reformation.
And one of its products was the focus on this question.
How am I saved?
Even though this question is the sort of perennial Protestant question.
It is actually affected Orthodox and Roman Catholic Christians as well.
Now, it's not an unorthodox thing to ask, to be sure, but the way that it gets asked,
and the way that has become embedded in the individualistic culture of the modern West,
has brought us to what I believe are some misleading conclusions about what salvation is.
So tonight, we're going to be talking about theoses.
And I think you'll see what I mean about this problem.
as we go. So for our Orthodox listeners, I hope that we'll be giving you a fuller picture of what
Theosius means. And you know, for our non-Orthodox listeners, well, enjoy the ride. So to start us off
this evening, let's discuss how salvation gets talked about both by all kinds of Christians and also
by Orthodox Christians in the English speaking world. I mean, do we Orthodox really have a problem in
the way that we're talking about it? And you know, especially for those who may not know this word,
Tha-o-c-s-w-
what is the sort of quick definition of what that means.
So why don't you give, you know, the elevator speech,
although you're not really known
for your elevator speech as Father Stephen,
but you could see elevator speech
on what theoses is.
Someone says, what is that word you keep using?
Yeah, well, and I think part of the problem we have
in this area is that we don't go much beyond
the elevator speech.
They're sort of like, right.
in order to ask meme about theosis, right?
which is, we'll talk about theosis.
We usually reference St. Peter's comment
that we become partakers of the divine nature.
Some times called divinization.
Someone will quote St. Athanasius saying
that God became man so that men
but become gods.
Everybody gets scared and thinks we're Mormons.
So, but part of it, part of the...
issue I think is that that hasn't really been integrated into a lot of the way we think.
We sort of tacked that on as an adjunct.
And then when we even as orthodox Christians start talking about salvation and satiriology,
which is the fancy word for talking about salvation, we sort of lapsed into a kind of amalgam
of Protestant and Roman Catholic views of salvation.
usually slightly the opposite of whoever we're talking to about it.
Right. It's a kind of a prologetic point.
And it's interesting to me, I mean,
certainly there is a difference between the way that English speaking Orthodox Christians talk about
salvation and the way that Roman Catholic or Protestant Christians talk about salvation.
We're not saying that it's kind of all the same.
But there is kind of an issue.
with at least the way that English-speaking Orthodox Christians tend to talk about salvation,
even when we talk about theoses.
Right? And part of what we're going to try to accomplish this evening is to integrate that
into what we've been discussing for our last several episodes,
and hopefully to show its connections to all parts of Orthodox tradition,
which is what this whole show is all about.
But you know, so the elevator speech version.
of theoses is that so it comes from the Greek word theos which means God. So the elevator speech
version is that we become like God, right? And that's what salvation is, is that we become like God.
And there's that line from St. Peter becoming partakers of the divine nature.
And the reason why I think that the way that we tend to talk about it is problematic is this.
As I said, you know, in the process.
Reformation there was this focus on this question. How am I saved? How do I get saved?
How do I be saved? And certainly Protestant and Catholic answers to that question are different.
But if you think about the question itself, the question itself focuses in on an individual human
person realizes he has some kind of problem and that that problem needs to be fixed, right?
And, you know, we won't get super deep into this because this is the show is not about
apologetics, this show is simply about trying to talk about the Orthodox tradition, but at
least for the sake of comparison, we should note that most Protestant and Catholic understandings
of what salvation is about is ultimately about satisfying God's divine justice, right?
Now how you satisfy God's justice varies between Protestant and Catholic presentations, and
certainly there are multiple Protestant presentations, and there's even some variation sometimes within
Roman Catholicism.
But basically that's the problem is that you know you've there is a justice problem
and you know someone is committed a crime and so that needs to be dealt with.
Now I'm simplifying so if you are a Catholic or you're Protestant, please don't think that I'm trying to summarize every single thing that you believe about this.
I'm not. I know there's way more to it. Okay. But nonetheless that's still kind of the problem is that God's divine justice needs to be satisfied.
And so then there's the focus on,
where do I stand on which side of the line am I on?
And for the Orthodox Christian,
in the English speaking world,
the way that it often gets talked about.
And again, we're not necessarily talking
about official theology,
we're certainly not talking about
what you hear in the church services.
We're talking about maybe what you hear in homilies
or the way that people talk about it on the internet.
So it's that kind of discussion level question.
is that we
He sometimes will agree that there's this problem that I need to get on the other side of
that justice line and satisfy God.
And oh, by the way, what happens when I do is that I become like God.
So Theo's is somewhere downstream of salvation in some sense.
Or that, well, we'll say yes, Theo's is salvation.
And it's a kind of personal improvement, right?
personal experience and that to me is the problem is that it's become individualized and now sometimes you'll hear people will say well
You know, we're damned alone, but but we're saved together
So they'll kind of you know make this sort of nod to ecclesiology, right that salvation is it happens
But it's kind of a group of us doing it together
But but the thing that I've come to believe is that that is not enough, you know like it's not
It's not entirely raw.
long, but it's not enough and it doesn't really, it doesn't do justice, no pun intended
to Orthodox tradition.
Right?
What do you think?
Am I getting the analysis of the problem right here, Father, from your point of view?
I think so.
And I think in large part, it stems from the fact that I think for too long we've sort
of looked at it as an-
approach or a metaphor where, you know, well, the West
takes approaches that are, you know, they use courtroom
metaphors and banking metaphors and these other kind of
metaphors. And the East tends to use more, you know,
ontological metaphors, talks more about healing and
transformation. And these are different perspectives and
these are different. Right. Right. And so when when someone
says when one of our Orthodox fathers and forefather
says that theosis is the orthodox view of salvation.
We all sort of nod our heads and we say,
oh yeah, I guess that's sort of our perspective.
We see it more that way.
And that's not what's being said by our fathers and forefathers.
They're making a claim about what the apostles taught us
that they were taught by Christ, that salvation is.
Yeah.
and that it is not and not to
but to tease as we go forward tonight,
we're gonna see that this represents
a fundamentally different way to read, for example, St. Paul.
He talks about salvation a great deal.
That this isn't just a different perspective.
This is a completely different way of understanding him.
Looking at the words and terms he uses,
and how he describes it, that I think a lot of times
A lot of times we even as Orthodox Christians.
have glossed over because we've been sucked into sort of
internecine Western debates about the materialogy.
And it's who's trying to be on.
And there's also just kind of a cultural problem.
Culturally, we're individualists.
So when I conceive of Christianity,
I can see of what is my problem and what do I need to do
to solve it.
That's the way that we tend to think about it.
So as a result, looking at salvation
as a kind of religious version of a self-help program
or of a workout program, I mean,
and I'm saying that people are trying to reduce it
or they're functioning in bad faith, right?
They're not.
I mean, maybe some are, but I don't think most are.
But the problem is that it is fundamentally individualistic,
I will write it
that if even if you read salvation as being theosias,
deification, divinization, whatever translation
you wanna give to that word,
it's still often conceived of in a kind of individual way,
like, okay, now work on your theosias.
This is my spiritual program to become more virtuous
and more peaceful and more successful.
Right.
What does it mean to become more like God?
And often then the answer is given in...
moral terms, or maybe like if you get really advanced, then you can have what we might
think of as supernatural powers, you know, because look at what some of the saints are
capable of, right? You know, it's a kind of enhancement, right? I think, you know, I think
that maybe that's one of the best ways to understand what kind of the problem is. And
again, we're not saying that orthodoxy has gotten this wrong. What we're saying is
that a lot of Orthodox people don't quite understand the full
the Orthodox tradition of what salvation is, of what the OCC is.
And so we're gonna try to deal with that.
We're not gonna claim to get it all from this,
but we're gonna talk about this particularly from the angle
that we discuss things and God willing
give a much fuller picture.
And I hope that it's gonna be a more hopeful picture actually.
You know, something that's more doable in a lot of ways.
I think it is.
You know, yeah, this...
And what's opposed to, we've been saying what it isn't, right?
What's opposed to that kind of individual view.
And what we're going to be saying, and what we're going to see tonight that the scriptures
are saying, is that this is about the purpose for which the world was created.
This is about the purpose for which human beings were created.
Right.
At the destiny of humanity.
So it's something much bigger than just, you know, am I...
going to be able to keep my patients better when I'm stuck in traffic.
Right. And it's not just that something broke and it needs to be fixed.
Yeah. This isn't playing B like God had a plan A people send. And so now here's
plan B, right? This is plan A. Right. And it runs as we're going to see tonight
from Genesis to Revelation literally in the Scriptures. Yeah. Yeah.
So let's start that there and I think that especially
Especially for those of you who haven't heard of theosis before and you're wondering,
what is this?
Is this even Christian talking about people being divinized or deified?
Because again, because Father Stephen is a biblical scholar and because as a former pastor
myself, I strongly have emphasized, and we're always from my whole life, emphasize, that
the main element of Orthodox tradition that Orthodox Christians need to know is the Bible.
We're gonna focus especially.
on the Bible. We are going to talk about some stuff from the Church Fathers as well.
We're going to especially focus on the Bible. And so we're going to begin by showing how
Theosis is right there in the Bible. And you don't even have to wait until you get to the
New Testament. It's in the Old Testament. It's right there at the beginning. So, so let's
start, especially with the the promises to Abraham. God talks to Abraham and says, this
This is what I'm going to give you.
This is what your destiny is.
So let's...
Let's talk about that.
Take us on in, Father Stephen.
Everybody in your Bibles?
So well, if hopefully folks have, and if they haven't,
hopefully they'll go back and listen to the last couple episodes
also.
The last episode we talked about the fall of the demonic
and hostile powers, all five issue of them.
And other than that, fifth issue one,
Now, other than that fifth ish one, all those are just
described within Genesis 1 through 11, the first 11 chapters, the first book of the Bible.
And then so this happens, culminating in the Tower of Babel, and then the beginning of
the response to that comes in Genesis 12 with Abraham.
And so this is really the beginning of that response.
So we talked about how, at the Tower of Babel event, that God had distanced himself from
humanity. Humanity had tried to control God and
manipulate him and God in response had stepped back and put sort of lesser spiritual powers in charge to govern the nations.
And so now when he comes to Abraham and appears to Abraham, that Abraham sees him and talks to him by the way,
he makes these promises to Abraham over, over against what's happened.
And these promises are reiterated three times
during the story of Abraham using similar
language. So the first of those is in Genesis 15 verse 5 and he that being God
brought him being Abram outside and said look toward heaven and number the
stars if you are able to number them then he said to him so shall your offspring
be. Right and probably most people when they hear that they think okay God is
saying Abram you're gonna have a lot of descendants. Look how many
stars there are. You're going to have that's going to your descendants. Right. Okay.
Right. Which is which which already I mean it's going to become more clear as we go, but already
notice he doesn't say so many shall your offspring be. Right. He's the word there that's translated
so shall your offspring be meaning your offspring are going to be like them. Now that can include
quantity, but it's not necessarily limited to
Yeah, yeah, and it actually reminds me of, you know, John 3, 16, God so loved the world, right?
Which a lot of people take is meaning God loved the world very much. But it actually means God
loved the world in this way, right? And so it's the same idea, you know, in this way your offspring
show be. You know, they're gonna be like like the stars. So...
So that's a really suggestive thing.
Let's continue on.
There's more references to stars.
So five, seven chapters later, right?
Seven chapters later, Genesis 22, 17.
This is God speaking again.
I will surely bless you, speaking to Abraham.
And I will surely multiply your offspring as the stars of heaven and as the sand that
is on the seashore, and your seed shall possess the gate of his enemies.
So this is similar.
Right.
Now there's a parallelism here that you don't necessarily see in English translations.
Okay.
That's there in the original Hebrew.
So he's saying, God is saying Abraham two things.
He's going to bless him and he's going to multiply him.
Those are two things he's going to do.
And then he says his offspring are going to be as...
the stars of heaven and is the sand of the seashore.
So, his offspring being is the stars of heaven corresponds to God blessing him,
his offspring being is the sand of the seashore corresponds to God multiplying him.
Oh, okay. So is this sort of set up grammatically in Hebrew so that this is obvious?
Yes, that's why there's a parallelism there in the structure of the phrase.
So there are going to be many, the quantity is going to be like the sand of the seashore.
And then the quality, the way it was going to be is as the stars of heaven.
And this adds this additional element of his seed possessing the gate of his enemies.
And that's an image, the gate of a city. If you have a walled city,
the gate of that city is the center of
power, both in terms of the defense of the city, obviously, but also in the social
custom of the ancient Near East and of Israel, that is where the men of the city would go,
that's where cases would be judged, the equivalent of trials would be held, that's where business
contracts would be ratified.
So this is the center power of power.
So this is talking about his seed basically taking the position, taking the position of
power.
of his enemies, which is part of them becoming like the stars of heaven.
Right. And that's interesting that you mentioned that all those things
happen at the gate. And you know, it's this kind of liminal spot between, you
know, civilization and what's out there, you know, the chaos, the wilderness
and so forth. And you know, there's a lot about authority and power that are
specifically about standing at the
that place, that border place, you know, you think about,
if you, let's say you hire a security guard for your home,
you're not gonna have him in the basement,
you're gonna have him at the door,
you're gonna have him at those, that entrance, you know.
So I think that that's a really interesting thing as well
as we kind of build this.
Okay, so we've got one more line from Genesis
That's about God.
God's promises to Abraham.
And he's the Abraham by this point, I can't remember exactly which chapter that happens
in.
By 26 he's Abraham.
Okay, all right.
So it's Abraham to Abraham.
All right.
Maybe we could talk about that some other time.
But yeah, so chapter in chapter 26, God makes, again, very similar promise to Abraham.
He says, chapter 26 verse four, I will multiply your offspring as the stars of heaven and will
give
your offspring, all these lands, and in your offspring, all the nations of the earth
shall be blessed. So you get, it's interesting. And that one you get, not only the sense of
multiplication, lots of them, but again, they're as the stars of heaven. And then also building
on the previous one, there's this notion that they're going to take the lands, right, that
the lands are going to belong to his offspring and then and in your offspring all
all the nations of the earth should be blessed.
So you've got now an additional, I mean, this is the way I'm reading anyway, that there's
this additional sense that the whole earth now is going to partake of the blessing that
is in these promises given to Abraham.
Right.
That the offspring of Abraham becoming at the seed of Abraham, becoming as the stars
of heaven is going to have this beneficial effect for the nation.
the nations who had just been scattered at Bable,
the nations who had just been assigned to these other powers.
And then also this gives us the relationship to the land
because this is a typical kind of prophetic promise
that we find in the Old Testament.
And this is important because this is a section
that's a lot of our Christian friends misinterpret
in terms of the relationship of the land
to the promises to Abraham.
When God gave promises and gave prophecies,
all
the Old Testament and even their examples in the New Testament. There was a sign attached
to that prophecy. There was some immediate fulfillment. There was something that happened
immediately in the short term that they could see and that served as the guarantee that the
greater prophecy was going to come true. So kind of down payment, so to speak.
Right. If you want a real quick example, you can see this in Luke 2 with the Shepherds. Right?
Angel comes to the shepherd.
Shepherds, it says, you know, unto you is born this day in the
Savior who is Christ the Lord, right?
So the Messiah has been born.
And then they say, this will be assigned to you.
If you go over here, you'll find this baby laying in a
food trough, right?
Which you wouldn't expect to find.
And so when you go over there and you see the baby in the
food trough, you'll know that, yeah, that's the Messiah.
Because that's an odd thing you don't expect to see.
Right, not to mention angels talking to you.
Right. So a little odd.
Well then the so the the strip of land in Palestine right canin is not the promise to Abraham
It is the sign or the down payment and so at the end of Joshua when at the end of Joshua
They're emphasizing that God had given all the land that he promised to Israel
Right, that's not the end of the Bible
Is that like okay?
promised fulfilled. Done. Good job. Good job. But it's establishing that yes God did this and so
we could be confident that the rest is going to happen. And so for example when Hebrews says that
Abraham was looking for a heavenly promised land that's not some kind of weird allegory. That's
Abraham was actually looking for that, right? And the land was...
the sign that he would truly receive it.
Yeah. Well, okay. So it's it's clear. I mean, you know, the idea that Abraham is going to have a
lot of descendants. That's pretty straightforward. The idea that he's that his descendants are going
to receive the land of Canaan as and you know, as a kind of down payment. That's pretty straightforward.
So let's talk about what it means that they're going to be as the stars. And
Unless you're brand new to this show,
you probably kind of know where we're going with this.
But for those who are brand new
and maybe for a little review for everybody else,
let's talk about what it means to be as the stars, right?
As we talked about in our second episode,
where we discussed the Angelic hierarchies.
We mentioned specifically, for instance,
that there's one of the Angelic ranks
that
called the virtues in English translation anyway, and that their task is to help God to
govern the creation, that they're kind of in everything.
And I mean, if you have to sort of, and this is not all there is to it, but if you need
an image, you can ask yourself, well, what makes the wind blow and the stars shine and
the oceans move and whatever, you know, certainly you could say well.
these gravitational forces and these, you know, those kinds of things.
But that doesn't answer the question as to why it is the creation even works the way
that it does, right?
Science can sort of observe this stuff.
But ancient people understood that there were spiritual beings who were engaged in the,
you know, the maintenance, so to speak, the working, the functioning of creation, and that
that includes the stars, includes the Sun and the Moon,
it includes...
everything. And of course, that's the reason, for instance, that ancient pagans would
associate their gods with these particular elements of creation is because they understood
that creation had spiritual beings helping to make it go. They didn't come up with spiritual
beings as an explanation for the things that they couldn't understand, which is kind of
the modern materialistic interpretation of ancient religion.
But rather they had had experience with these beings.
And eventually, of course, some of them fall and they start to worship them, which is not good.
But nonetheless, there is this sense that they have this association.
And so, when God is talking about the stars to Abraham, he doesn't mean that your descendants are going to be like big,
blazing
you know, balls of gas, right? That's not what he means. What exactly does he mean?
Well, he's... we have to remember, of course, that Abram himself comes from
Er of the Caldees. He is a Caldian. He is a Sumerian technically of the Earth,
what's called the over three period.
And so...
Abram had an understanding of the stars that's commensurate with what you were just describing.
The, we talked about the Tower of Babel and again how this is coming immediately afterwards.
And as you said, unless this is your first time listening, you've heard us refer to
Deuteronomy 32 verse 8, which talks about the Tower of Babel event when the most
Ty divided the nations, he numbered them according to the
the number of the sons of God, and we've talked about how that's another name for the angelic
beings. And then in a corresponding passage in Deuteronomy 4 verse 19, God talks about
the people are not too worship, the people of Israel are not too worship, the sun, moon,
and stars to whom God has allotted all the nations under the earth. So the sons of God
And...
the Sun Moon and stars are here sort of made equivalent as divine beings.
And this isn't just something that's an ancient Mesopotamian religion that God used as a metaphor for Abraham and then got lost to time.
This is a view, the view of the Sun Moon and stars and the divine beings related to them that existed at the time of the Apostles
and at the time of the ride.
of the New Testament. It was a constant throughout. And the fact that it existed at the time is
attested to, I don't think we should probably read this whole quote.
Yeah, I agree. I can read part of it.
We've got a big quote through our notes. We need to go to break in just a minute so we can
start taking some of your calls. But yeah, why don't you read a little bit, Father Stephen,
maybe summarize what Philo of Alexandria is talking about.
This is Philo of Alexandria.
who was a member of the Jewish community in Alexandria,
it's from a text that is called on the special laws,
and he's in this, he's commenting on that
Deuteronomy 4 verse 19 passage,
and this is his explanation.
So he says, some persons have conceived that the sun
and the moon and the other stars are independent gods,
to whom they have attributed the causes
of all things that exist.
But Moses was well aware that the world was created
and was like a f*****
large city having rulers and subjects in it. The rulers being all the bodies which are in heaven,
such as planets and fixed stars, and the subjects being all the natures beneath the moon,
hovering in the air and adjacent to the earth, but that the rulers of force said are not
independent in absolute, but are the vice-royes of one supreme being, the father of all,
in the imitation of whom they administer with propriety and success, the charge committed to their
care as he also provides
resides over all created things and strict accordance with justice and with law.
And I'll skip to sort of the end of the quote.
He talks about how these subsidiary gods with a small G, these spiritual beings who govern
the Sun, Moon, and stars are worshipped by the pagans as if they were these independent
gods themselves and independent power.
But what Philo says, rather, we must therefore look on all those bodies in the heaven, which
the outward sense regards as
gods, not as independent rulers since they are signed the work of lieutenants, being
by their intrinsic nature responsible to a higher power, but by reason of their virtue not
actually called to render in an account of their doings.
So, that transcending all visible essence by means of our reason let us press forward to
the honor of that everlasting and invisible being who can be comprehended and appreciated by
the mind alone who is not only the God of all gods, whether appreciable only by the intellect
are visible to the outward senses.
but is also the creator of them all. Right? So he says there they are, see subsidiary beings who serve,
Yahweh the God of Israel, the one God of all, and we should rather in seeing their governance of
the universe ascend beyond them to contemplate and honor and worship their creator. Right. Right. So in
In other words, when God says to Abraham that his offspring are going
to be as the stars. This is what he means, that they are going to be as these angelic beings
who govern creation, including the stars, that they're going to be like that, they're
going to function like that, they're going to serve like that. And so this is embedded
from the very, very beginning of what we could think of as being sort of the salvation story.
when God speaks to Abraham and says,
now look, come out of this.
Horrible civilization of Cain that you live in now and go to a place I'm going to show you and
This is the story that we're now telling that your offspring are going to be as the stars
So that's that's what we're going to wrap up the first part of our show this evening
And we go ahead and go to a break and when we come back, please give us a ring
We'd love to talk to you and we're going to continue telling this story
Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen
to young will be back in a moment to take your calls on the second half of the Lord of
spirits. Give them a call at 855-237-2346. That's 855-AF radio.
Hi, this is Father Evan Armitas, priest at St. Spirit on Greek Orthodox Church in Lolland
And the host of the Ancient Faith Radio Sunday Night Call and Show.
Orthodoxy live. I am pleased to announce today the release of my first book for
Ancient Faith Publishing, titled, Toolkit for Spiritual Growth, a practical guide to prayer
fasting in Am's giving. It seeks to provide a guide to the three basic and primary disciplines
of Orthodox spirituality through these disciplines Christ opened for us a path that frees us from
the disordered way of life has become normal for many, even though their hearts and minds tell them
otherwise. Please join me in exploring the three-legged stool of our
with Doc's spiritual practice, prayer, fasting, and non-sgiving.
Books now available at store.ancientfaith.com.
And the title once again is Toolkit for Spiritual Grove.
I look forward to sharing it with you.
God bless.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits,
the Father Andrew Stephen Damick,
and Father Stephen DeYoung.
If you have a question, call now at 855-237-2346.
That's 855 AF radio.
Welcome back and thank you for that voiceover Steve.
So this is the second part of our show and it's where we begin to take your calls.
You can reach us at 855 AF radio.
That's 855-237-2346.
And we would love to hear from you.
We'd love to talk to you.
We're going to continue to talk about these promises to Abraham and what exactly they mean
and a special...
as they start to play out in the New Testament.
So, all right, well, Father Stephen,
I see that you've got in our notes here
that this promise to Abraham, that his offspring
will be as the stars, that they're going to be like the stars,
gets reiterated a couple of different times at least,
maybe multiple times in the New Testament.
Many actually I'm seeing lots of times.
You wouldn't believe people how many times
this gets reiterated in the New Testament.
But you know before we kind of get in
get into that too deeply, just to try to reconnect this back to all the things that we've
been talking about for this whole show.
Now just to reiterate, so for those who've been on this journey with us the whole time,
you know probably what I'm about to say, but God's divine counsel, His hosts, His armies
of angelic beings who assist Him in creation, who obey His will, who help to govern creation,
who are not only messengers to us and help to protect us.
but also that they are these vast cosmic intelligences who do the will of God,
and surround him and are always present with him.
This is what the promises to Abraham are about.
That Abraham's offspring are going to be like that,
that they're going to function like the angels.
And, you know, this is why...
For instance, we've titled this particular episode,
Sons of God equal to the angels.
Now that is a quote from Jesus Christ himself in Luke chapter 20 verse 36,
and he says there that the Sons of the Resurrection, and that's us, right?
You know, God willing, the Sons of the Resurrection
are become sons of God and equal to the angels.
That's what's going on here.
So Jesus himself is repeating essentially what the promises to Abraham are and being very
explicit about it.
That's really explicit.
They become equal to the angels.
It's funny.
I mean, I don't think I've ever heard people talk about salvation and then mention that
verse.
It's almost like, oh yes, that's what happens kind of after salvation, maybe.
but clearly in terms of these promises given to-
Abraham becoming a son of the resurrection means becoming one of the sons of God.
If we talk about that, it's a rank of angels. And as Jesus says, equal to the angels.
Right? Equal to the angels. So what we've got a call coming in and it's not quite exactly on
what we've been talking about. But I think it's an important one because we've got a lot of questions
about the role of demons. Right? And so we have Cody who is on the line
from looks like North Carolina.
And he has a question, or he or she,
forgive me, I'm not sure what we'll find out in just a second.
Is questioning about the role of demons in mental illness.
So Cody, are you there?
How are you, it's been here for me?
Yes, I hear you.
Okay, cool.
Yes, so actually the guy that was calling in
from the first podcast where I found out
and then my wife were actually catacumants as.
same church. Oh great great and you definitely sound like you're from North Carolina by
the way I have to say I live there for I live there for 11 years and you are definitely
from North Carolina. I appreciate it. But anyways my question is I don't really I don't
really hear this guest very much. At least I don't but like demons. Do they have any like
particular parts to play in middle hill of bright.
like in schizophrenia or in even something like clinical depression.
Like I don't hear it discussed very much that I was wondering what you guys' professional
theological opinion would be on that.
Yeah, well that's a great question and I know it's something on some people's minds.
And I think one of the reasons for that is there have been many cases throughout history
where people said while this person is insane, therefore there is a demon.
And now in the modern world it's kind of like, well, we've outgrown that idea and we know that mental illnesses is just a chemical imbalance or, you know, that kind of thing.
And I think the problem with that modern approach is that it assumes that there is a kind of spiritually neutral ground. Okay.
And the other problem is, of course, that mental illness.
And I mean, I am, again, I'm not a psychologist.
I'm not a psychiatrist, I'm not a doctor of any kind.
But mental illness is a vast category that
includes a whole lot of different kinds of things.
And so it can be everything from clinical depression
to schizophrenia, which itself, schizophrenia
is a vast category that includes a whole lot of different things.
There's all kinds of things that are classified as mental illness.
And I think that to say that there is no
spiritual influence involved when someone is mentally ill.
I think is irresponsible if we believe that there are spiritual beings around us.
I think it would also be irresponsible to say, oh, I see a problem with this person,
therefore, they must be demon possessed, right?
We don't know that.
I'm not qualified to say whether someone is demon possessed, even though I believe
that demon possession is real.
I'm not qualified to say what a certain, you know,
mental illness on a person that you might see in a person, what that exactly is, even though I believe
that mental illness is real. And I would also say that I don't think that these things are necessarily
mutually exclusive, right? They're not. I mean, I feel depressed if I haven't had enough protein
today. Does that mean that my spiritual life is in no way involved? It absolutely is involved.
You know it
it always is involved. And I'm, you know, we have spiritual beings around us. So I mean,
my answer would be that it's possible and kind of it depends. And, you know, it depends a lot
on the given the particular circumstance. So I don't know, Father Stephen, is there anything you
wanted to add to that or correct or whatever? Well, I think it's important to say that
that mental illness and demonic possession
are two different things.
Okay.
Demonic possession is a different phenomenon than mental illness.
Although it might look like mental illness to people who don't believe in demonic possession, right?
Hello, oh, is that to me? Oh, I guess I'll get father Steve, are you still there? Oh
I think we lost father Stephen for just a second there.
Oh, man.
All right.
Well, yeah, I don't know what he was about to say, but Father Steven, do we have you back yet?
Well, we're going to try to get him back.
But if I had to try to finish his sentence, Demon possession, of course, is where someone
is surrendered to a demon and they kind of take control of them.
Right?
kind of occupation going.
on there. Whereas someone who's behaving who has mental illness, they're affected by
something and they may well be affected by demonic temptation, maybe because they've fallen
prey to it over and over again. So, hopefully we'll get Father Stephen back here and we
the rest of his sentence, but maybe not.
All right.
Any well, that's how you know it's
live radio everybody because anything can happen.
Yeah, definitely.
But I think the thing that we have to try to avoid is this idea of saying it's kind of
that any weird thing we say can any, you know, that any weird behavior we see in a person
must be a demon or that it must be a
you know, they're just, you know, they're just mentally ill or whatever.
So all right. Well, I hope that's helpful. I'm getting, I got to just got a note
here from Father Steven that his, his power went out. But we're going to try to reconnect with him
and, and hopefully we can, we can do that. So we have Bobby as our engineer this evening. So
Bobby, can you, can you go ahead and take us to a break and we're going to try to reconnect
with Father Stephen.
This is the general rule of this show is don't bring Bobby in.
What? And you're doing it.
I'm sorry. It's fine.
Yeah, okay, I'll take you to work.
Thank you, Bobby.
All right.
Father Andrew Stephen, Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung
will be back in a moment to take your calls
on the second half of the Lord of Spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF radio.
Now available on Ancient Faith Publishing, the shield of Selmic Prayer, reflections on
translating, interpreting, and praying the Psalter.
In this posthumous collection of poet and teacher Donald Sheehan's reflections on
Psalms and Selmic Prayer, called from his journals and teaching notes, you will find two
quite different kinds of writing working in tandem.
and personal journaling by a man.
of faith, a scholar, a linguist, and in the deepest sense a teacher. Alongside scholarly
linguistic and poetic analysis by a man steeped in poetry who thought like a poet. Here's
what Father Stephen Freeman has to say on the road.
In the spiritual life, two things are essential. What we do, and how we do it. And this wonderful
collection of the late Donald Sheen spots on the Psalms. We see...
both. He takes us into what the Psalms are in depth. That is the Word of God. But he also demonstrates
time and again how those deaths shape his life in the world in which he lives. Thus we are given two
things, the Word of God and a life in which the Word has given shape. It's a path we all should walk.
You can find this book and others like it at store.
It seems to me that in this modern life of ours everything has become so frightfully
materialistic.
There is a very great need of transfiguration of a change of our attitude, of our way of
thinking, of our way of behaving, of holding
and also everything needs a new Christianization.
It must become more aware of the Christ within us.
First published in 1981 and long out of print,
the Holy Angels by Mother Alexandra
has yet to be surpassed as a comprehensive and comprehensible
account of the nature of the angels
and their role in our salvation.
In lay person's terms, Mother Alexandra
presents the essence of everything.
The Church has to teach us about the angels, beginning with the Old Testament,
continuing through the New Testament, and concluding with the tradition of the Church
as expressed in her theology, hemnography, and iconography.
For those who long to become better acquainted with these holy servants of God and to understand
their role in our lives, this book is a great place to start.
available now at store.antianfaith.com.
Again, that is store-
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits, the Father Andrew Stephen Daymak and Father
Stephen DeYoung.
If you have a question, call now at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF Radio.
All right, we're back.
Father Stephen, are you there?
All right, I'm not hearing him yet.
So welcome back everybody. It's Father Andrew from ancient from ancient
faith radio. It may as Pennsylvania. Father Steven you there. I am here. Yay! So what happened?
There's a storm here in Louisiana. It happens all too frequently. My power went out.
But we can continue. Okay. Well, you're connecting through your tablet, right?
Yeah.
as Dakota for dropping out in the middle of my response.
Yeah. Well, you know, it's funny the other day someone said to me, and I mean, I, I,
again, I don't know what, you know, I can't read demons and angels. I'm not an expert on this,
right? We're just talking about it and trying to live it as best as we can. But someone said to me,
you know, you know, you guys talking about these things, you're inviting, you're inviting problems.
God willing, we're...
We're able to get to have an episode where we don't have a technical issue that we can't
possibly for tell coming in.
But here we are, and that's okay.
So hi everybody out there in ancient faith radio land.
It's live radio.
So Father Stephen, why don't you finish out?
Hopefully Cody is still listening.
He's not connected now.
But why don't you finish out what you were saying and correct whatever wrong thing I said
to him.
No, I wasn't, I was not correct to give you in this case.
Oh great.
for me.
I was just saying that once we distinguish between the modic possession is a phenomenon.
And on one hand, between mental illness and the other, then we need to understand that.
They are the same relationship to mental illness that they do to physical illness.
You know, there's no...
There are different forms between, you know, a disease of the liver and a disease of the brain.
Right.
It's the same kind of issues and the same kind of way we should understand and deal with it.
Yeah.
And I should probably note for our listeners that you are now connected over your data connection through a mobile tower.
Is that right?
Yeah, so there we go
All right, so just expect a little weirdness.
It's just the way it is, but we are gonna continue
to do this show.
So anyway, all right, well, Cody,
I hope that's helpful to you.
Let's continue talking about these promises
to Abraham that were given and what they exactly
they have to do with theoses.
So Father Stephen, why don't you continue us on
and talk about especially,
I mentioned that verse from Luke 20, 36.
and with the Lord says that
the resurrection becomes sons of God and equal to the angels.
And let's continue talking about this.
So these promises get reiterated.
What happens there?
Right.
Well, we're going to talk about a few different places where
they get reiterated.
Then we're going to take a deep dive into St. Paul.
There's ITs earlier because there's
They're very important to how
policies the whole
the whole pattern of salvation.
But in terms of a few places where elements
of what we've been talking about get reiterated.
So for example, in Matthew 19 verse 28,
there's a verse that gets glossed over a lot
where the disciples, soon to be apostles, ask Christ,
you know, well, what about us?
We've given up all these things.
you know, to follow you. What what promises will we receive in return and Christ
tells them that they will sit on 12 thrones and judge the 12 tribes of Israel.
Of course, judge in this context is like the Old Testament concept of a judge.
It's not sort of you're going to hear cases or it's not just about the last
judgment, but this is about sharing in Christ's reign and his rule over over the
world.
Now.
And of course the same thing gets re-interrated in Revelation chapter 20 verse 4.
It talks about the saints and the martyrs who come to life and rule and reign with Christ
for the period between their deaths and his return, which is figuratively sort of represented
there as a thousand years.
And then in terms of the element of camping in the gates and we're going to, as another
other teas, talk about this.
lot more in our Halloween special just next week, one week from today. There we go, there's a promo.
So more of this then. But one of the things that we notice in
St. John's book of Revelation is that he encounters with the heavenly hosts and the angels
who are worshipping and praising God, he encounters 24 elders, 24 human elders.
Right.
Press...
And there's a lot of different ways of understanding that number, right?
The 12 tribes of Israel, the 12 apostles, or how we do it.
But they are particularly elders.
And of course, starting with Moses in the Old Testament, there were 72 elders of Israel.
Right.
And so 24 is one third.
That's interesting.
It's just a few chapters.
later that when we read about Satan being cast down from heaven, that with him he
takes a third of the stars. So there's the stars again. This isn't about sort of an
exact number of the angels who fell or even exact proportion, but it's to give
us this sense that oh look a third of the elders are these humans who have been
glorified a third of the angelic beings.
to give us this replacement idea, this camping in the gates of the enemy, taking the position of power and authority.
So those are just some examples before we get into the deeper dive, at least on St. Paul.
Yeah. Okay, well, let's get on on the diving board and take a deep dive into St. Paul.
Oh, take a couple of bounces.
Yeah.
Yeah, thank God.
And everyone out there, please pray right now
that Father Stevens' data connection stays strong
and also pray that his power comes back on.
And as long as we're able, we're gonna keep doing this
because this is what we're supposed to be doing tonight.
So, okay.
You know what I could say, we're not dedicated.
Yeah, exactly.
I know I feel bad here in my wonderful studio
where everything is nice and the power is on,
the lights are on.
That's okay.
So and I'm here rubbing two sticks together to try and
smoke signals.
But so, so a couple of things with St. Paul.
First of all, we tend to think about as contemporary Western people to think about St.
Paul sort of the wrong way.
Okay.
We sort of picture him because he was a teacher and because he was, is Jewish, right?
We think of him as sort of like
a modern rabbi. And so pictures St. Paul sort of sitting and studying these musty scrolls
of the Torah and these other ancient Jewish traditions and he sits there and he reads them
and he thinks about them and he sort of comes up with this theology. Then the portions
of which then end up in the Bible. And that's not only not how the scriptures see St. Paul,
Well, that's not even how St. Paul sees himself.
The picture we get of St. Paul from the book of Acts and from St. Paul's own writings
For example what we normally call his conversion on the road to Damascus
Right
Is kind of a knackronistic to call it a conversion because it's not as if there was this religion Judaism and then this other
Religion Christianity and St. Paul left one and went to the other in 35 AD, right that right right that didn't happen
rather the way St Paul does
describes it himself. He actually borrows language directly from the book of Jeremiah in
Galatians when he describes it is as sort of a prophetic call. The way Isaiah had this vision
of God seated in the temple or Ezekiel had this vision of the divine throne or Jeremiah
experienced this call. So St. Paul saw himself as called to be a prophet. And that's not
the only time he sees and interacts with Christ if you read the book of Acts closely.
It's actually three times in the book of Acts.
Christ appears personally to St. Paul and they interact. And in addition to that, we have
St. Paul's description of his sort of visionary experience of going to the Third Heaven. So
St. Paul is really more like the Sears, the prophets, the mystics of the Old Testament than
like a modern Jewish rabbi slash theologian. Right. Right. And so and we could go in all kinds of
detail about his personal prayer practice.
This isn't all that, but for our purposes tonight,
this obviously affects how he viewed salvation.
This isn't just a question of theology
and how does it work and what's a good metaphor.
This is talking about his own personal experience
of salvation, his own experience with Christ.
And that's what he's writing about.
Right.
So he's having visions.
He's a mystic, he's like Moses.
He's like one of the prophets.
And it's interesting.
One of the things I've always thought was kind of cool,
serving in the Antiochian Church,
especially up here in the Northeast,
means that you're gonna bump into people of Middle Eastern
background, including ones that are actually
from the Middle East.
And so you're gonna hear people speaking Arabic.
And one of the things that's interesting to me
is that the Arabic word for profit,
which forgive me Arabic speakers if I'm mispronouncing this,
I think is al-Rassul,
is that same word is used to refer to
apostles actually. So like for instance, bulos arosul is the apostle Paul, right? So it's interesting
that in Arabic at least a kind of colloquial way of describing apostles and prophets is with the
same word interestingly enough, even though they're not, you know, it's not literally this,
like it's not the same word in Greek and I don't know if that's the word that's used in the Arabic
Bible. I don't have an Arabic speaker sitting here with me. But I thought that was kind of interesting
is that apostles are looked at as being
prophets of another kind, you know, of another time.
Every one of them saw God, whether it was Christ,
it is earthly, Christ is God.
And they speak on behalf of God, just, I mean,
that's what prophets do.
So yeah, okay, well, let's, you know, before we,
before we get too deep into Paul,
we actually got a question that came over email
from Father David, David Subu,
and forgive me father David if I'm
I'm not saying your last name, but he asked about something we talked about in the first
part, and he said this, can you talk about possessing the gates and how it connects to
the harrowing of Hades and so forth?
Is he on the right track?
I mean, it seems to me like he's suggesting that, you know, we talk about Abraham's offspring
possessing the gates.
I mean, does that apply to the gates of Hades as well?
Yes.
I'm gonna partially punt on this just because I don't want to steal our own
under next week. Okay, all right. So yes, this is going to be a major focus. So the answer is yes.
Yes. Yes. And to further tease next week, we're going to be talking about how Christ
conquers all of the enemies and then shares that victory with humanity. And that's what
becoming a saint is all about it's gonna tie on a lot of what we're talking about.
about here. So, but we need to kind of lay a little more groundwork here first, I think,
before we know. This is the show where we keep saying tune in next time. It's coming.
Yes. It's coming. Don't worry, everybody. All right. Okay. So where should we start out
here? Should we start out with this quote from Galatians chapter three? Well, let's write
before we do that. Okay, I want to call back before
all of my electrical shakhanry took place. The big themes and terms we saw in terms of the
promises to Abraham about the sons of God, the seed of Abraham, who are the heirs to the
promise, to the inheritance that he's been promised. These are the key terms related to
fiosus
as it's originally laid out way back in Genesis, right?
And then is being pursued going forward.
And so now when we have those terms in mind
and know where they come from,
when we read St. Paul talking about salvation,
it's important to see how he now is going to use those terms
in relationship to Christ.
And we're actually going to be focusing on,
we're going to be reading,
we're not going to go through the whole chapters,
But we're gonna be
talking about texts from Galatians 3 and 4 and Romans 8 and for any of our listeners who
have an awareness or connected to Protestantism, you'll know that these are some of the basic
chapters that are used to lay out sort of the Western and particularly Protestant view of salvation.
And I think we're going to see once we have these terms in mind and this understanding of what
Theosis is in mind that these
text actually means something very different that we may have been brought up or heard that
they teach because in some cases we've been focusing on the wrong terms and the wrong
words.
Yeah, which just then continues the tradition of this podcast where we try to blow everybody's
minds with things that have been staring you in the face.
So, but so here we are.
three is a complete
We kind of lost you a little bit there father, even you still there. Yeah, I think I think glacier is three that first is a good place to start
Okay, all right, so okay, so Galatians chapter three verses 26 through 29 for in Christ Jesus
You are all sons of God through faith
for his
Many of you as we're baptized into Christ have put on Christ.
There is neither Jew nor Greek.
There is neither slave nor free.
There is no male and female for you are all one in Christ Jesus.
And if you are Christ's, then you are Abraham's offspring, heirs according to promise.
So there it is.
There it is.
The promise to Abraham described as being we were sons of God.
And how does it happen?
baptism.
It comes through baptism because we put on Christ.
And of course, I mean, that line, right, for as many of you as
were baptized in Christ, have put on Christ, that is sung at the Orthodox
baptismal service. Right? And yeah.
That text has been kind of atomized. We've pulled the pieces out and quoted them
separately so much that we kind of lose the flow.
We have first made use of been baptized in Christ.
This is all because of God through faith.
Right.
And that is as many have been baptized in the Christ of put on Christ as saying that that takes place through baptism.
and that by being baptized we are therefore Christ
and in being sons of God we're also Abraham's.
see and heirs to those promises to Abraham.
Yeah.
So this is all tied together for St. Paul with baptism.
And so the receipt of those promises is not
in the larger argument of Galatians from circumcision
to be in Abraham's fostering by being
in class which happens through baptism.
Right.
OK.
So yeah, it's just amazing when you
start to look at all these things in this larger context.
and connect these parts of the scripture to each other.
So moving forward then to Galatians chapter four.
If we look at verses five through seven,
we get this from St. Paul,
so that we might receive adoption as sons.
And because you are sons,
God has sent the spirit of his son
into our hearts crying,
Abba, Father, so you are no longer a slave,
but a sun, and if a sun...
than an heir through God.
And, you know, I think that often when people see this, of course,
you know, the idea of being adopted into God's family makes sense.
But if we recall that the sons of God are this kind of angelic rank,
and we recall that what does it mean to be part of this royal family?
Well, you know, if you're in a royal family, you have a job to do.
You have something that you're supposed to be doing.
And by virtue of being close to the king and father,
Father.
You share in his authority, in his glory, in his work, in his ministry.
And this happens because God has sent his spirit into our hearts,
that we have become sons of God.
And sometimes, of course, it gets translated as children rather than sons.
But it's not that that's sort of totally wrong,
but it obscures this idea.
of the sons of God that you know this image from the Old Testament that gets
then carried forward into the New Testament, right? And I think it's really
important that we we emphasize this idea of adoption. We're adopted as sons.
And I just wanted to mention and maybe and hopefully we'll have time to talk
about this a little bit more, but I just wanted to mention especially I was
reading today a paper from my friend the late Father Matthew Baker and
and
Father Matthew and I were in seminary together and he was just a brilliant, brilliant, brilliant person, but also just a deeply Christian man.
And he died in an accident some years ago, but anyway, he wrote a paper called Deification and Sunship according to Saint Athanasius of Alexandria.
And I could just talk about this paper for hours,
but one of the things that he mentions, of course,
is that CNethanagius talks about adoption a lot
when he's talking about theoces.
And the term that's used for adoption, and this is actually an ancient Greek term.
It's not something that that ethnicists came up with, but it's long predates them.
But the term that it's used for adoption is, and I'm sure I'm going to mispronounce this, I don't know,
Rio Thesia. Did I get that right? Rio Thesia.
Close enough. Rio Thesia.
I'm not forever at work.
Yeah, okay. Rio Thesia is a sort of Rio swetch, which means sun,
you know, and the C, which means kind of a setting or placing a
not that you can always take a Greek word apart and get the meaning of it, but in this case it kind of works.
Being made a son.
Being made a son, rather than being born one, it's sort of the idea you're being made a son.
And that's part of the key thing for him in terms of theosis, and he also connects it with this term, theopeses, which means God making, being made a God.
right?
And there's that classic line from Athanasius, God became man so that we might become gods,
or might be made gods.
And all of this is tied together, that being adopted in Christ as sons of God, being made
gods, this is all together.
Theosius, it's all the same thing.
So it's really something.
So yeah, this idea, we're adopted as sons.
That's right there in Galatians chapter 4.
First five.
So did you want to add anything else to that
on this part from Singapore, Father?
No, I think we can go on to Romans eight.
All right.
And we can go through some of these quotes now,
a little more quickly because we're gonna see
a lot of the same thing.
So this is a lot of sort of piling on.
We can see how central this is to St Paul's thinking
every time he talks about salvation.
in Romans 8 verses 14 through 17.
for all who are led by the Spirit of God or sons of God,
for did you did not receive the Spirit of slavery
to fall back into fear, but you have received
the Spirit of adoption as sons by whom we cry,
Abba, Father, the Spirit himself bears witness with our
Spirit that we are children of God and of children
than heirs, heirs of God and fellow heirs with Christ,
provided we suffer with him in order that we may also
be glorified with him.
So
And you may have noticed it switches from sons to children there. That's because the Greeks switches from sons to children.
Oh, there you go.
Both the phrase sons of God and children of God occur in the scriptures in the Greek.
Unfortunately, because we want to be gender sensitive, a lot of modern translations translate both as children of God.
So you can't tell which the original says when you read in English.
But sons of God, of course, has this important weight that we've been talking about
referring to the Inchellic.
beings, whereas children of God refers to other elements of that. But we have this element
of adoption here. It's connected to being heirs again of the promises, fellow heirs
with Christ, and also with, of course, glorification. Right. Another element of the oath is coming
to share in Christ's glory, the glory of the resurrected and reigning.
Yep, yep, so there it is again over and over
Do you want to do the next one?
Yeah, okay.
Let's pile these on a little bit.
Yeah, right, right, right.
So this is continuing in Romans 8, right?
Yeah.
So Romans 8, starting with verse 19, going through 23,
for the creation waits with eager longing for the revealing
of the sons of God.
For the creation was subjected to futility, not willingly,
but because of him who subjected it,
in hope that the creation itself will be set free
from its bondage to...
corruption and obtain the freedom of the glory of the children of God. For we know that the whole
creation has been groaning together in the pains of childbirth until now, and not only the creation,
but we ourselves who have the first fruits of the Spirit groan inwardly as we wait eagerly
for adoption as sons, the redemption of our bodies. So this connects us then to this idea that
creation itself is participating in this.
Which, I mean, if we understand that these sons of God...
that these angelic beings are our governing creation and participating in the
governing creation and that our job is to do the same thing. And if we're in
Christ, we begin to do that. Then it makes sense that the creation we've bound
up in human destiny, right? And that can't be what it's supposed to be in
a sense without our participation as sons of God. This isn't humanity over
against creation. The whole
purpose of creation for Saint Paul. The reason God created everything he created,
including us, was so that he could share his divine and eternal life with us, humans.
To bring forth the sons of God. That's the purpose of everything and of all this.
And this takes place at the redemption of our bodies, notice our physicalities. So this is not
redemption from our bodies from the world.
But it's in and with the world.
So theosis is as nothing to do with nozzlesism. This is the opposite of nozzlesism.
Yeah, right.
And also notice that language that St. Paul uses fairly frequently of the first
fruits of the spirit, whereas we were talking about with a sign in a deposit,
we have received the spirit which is the sign of the truth of the promise of the redemption of our bodies,
at the resurrection.
Right, it's the sign in the beginning point.
And then just real quickly
Romans 829 to pile one more on.
This gets quoted a lot, especially by our Calvinist friends,
because it talks about predestination.
But let's just for a second, don't get
triggered by the word predestined and listen
to the rest of the verse, right?
That for those whom he for new, he also predestined
to be conformed to the image of his son
in order that he might be the first born among many brothers.
Right.
Right. So the what God and the word there that translated predestine really means to set an order in advance.
Right. So following off of what we just read about creation, God created all these things and put them in place and set them all in order
for the purpose that we would be conformed to the image of Christ. We become like Christ, another element of theosis, become like God.
so that Christ would be the first born is the begotten Son, the unique Son.
and then we become the sons of God through heaven.
Adoption, yeah.
In Christ.
So, right.
Well, we could probably talk about lots more stuff from St. Paul.
But let's go ahead and because this kind of wraps up this part of the,
our show for this evening,
let's go ahead and go to a break.
And when we come back,
we have a call that we're going to take, God willing.
and we'll continue.
continue to talk so let's go ahead and go to break.
Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung
will be back in a moment to take your calls
on the second half of spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF radio.
Hi, this is Father Evan Armitoss, priest at St. Spirit
and Greek Orthodox Church.
and Lolland Colorado, and the host of the Ancient Faith Radio Sunday Night Call and Show,
Orthodoxy Live. I am pleased to announce today the release of my first book for Ancient
Faith Publishing, titled, Toolkit for Spiritual Growth, a practical guide to prayer fasting
in arms giving. It seeks to provide a guide to the three basic and primary disciplines
of Orthodox spirituality. Through these disciplines Christ opened for us a path that frees us from
the distorted way of life has become normal for many, even though their hearts...
minds tell them otherwise. Please join me in exploring the three-legged stool of
Orthodox spiritual practice, prayer, fasting, and nomsgiving. Books now available at
store.ancientfaith.com. And the title once again is Toolkit for Spiritual
Grove. I look forward to sharing it with you. God bless.
The Ancient Faith for the Modern World.
This is Ancient Faith Radio.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits, the father Andrew Stephen Damick and father
Stephen DeYoung.
If you have a question, call now at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF radio.
Welcome to the third half of the show as we stumble along amid storms and power outages.
and father Steven
data stream. Yeah so all right well before we continue I'm sorry I'm just
laughing over here what else can you do before we could before we continue we
have a call and this is Father Christopher who is calling and he's calling
about the scriptural understanding of demons so Father Christopher are you there
Yeah.
I am here, Father.
Good to hear your voice.
Oh, it is good.
the year years too. So welcome to the Lord of Spirits Father.
Well, thank you. And actually that's a little bit quite a bit
different than than what I wanted to ask. But if I could, I
wanted to make a comment to both of you.
Comment away. And I should tell I should tell our audience, by
the way, the Father Christopher and I are old friends. And and
Father Christopher and I were in seminary together at St.
on seminaries. So um
So I'm ready for anything.
And we were texting today.
We were texting today.
And father knows I'm going to embarrass my wife
because she was a classmate of his.
And she's the brightest star in our family.
And she made a comment about when she became Orthodox.
She was a biblical studies major in college.
And she said when she became Orthodox,
it just really opened her mind to the depths
and the breadth of the scripture.
And when we were listening to your episodes last week, she said the same thing.
She said, I feel like the very similar thing, listening to this podcast and this teaching,
is just opening up my mind to the depth and the breadth of the scripture.
So I just wanted to thank you, first and foremost, for all of us who are listening to this wonderful
work that you're doing.
Thank you, Father.
Thank you very much.
Thank you.
Thank God. Thank God. Thank you.
So what's your question Father Christopher?
My question would be, you know, we see one of the authors of the book like Tolkien and
some of the other Inquins, a hints of vision of the Council of God.
I guess my question is when did we lose this teaching?
When was this lost to us?
between between them and where
We are now, did they kind of rediscover it through the love of mythology and scripture?
When do we lose this?
Yeah, that's a good question.
Father Steven, why don't you go ahead and start us off with this one?
Well, it depends on who the we is and the question.
Yeah, right.
Yeah, in one way maybe.
Yeah, I mean the part of it is that
If we is the Orthodox Church, I don't think it was lost, but I don't know that recent
generations have fully been able to appropriate it.
Because it's contained in our liturgics, it's contained in the writings of the fathers,
too many of which are still untranslated into English.
It's contained.
in texts, ancient Jewish texts that were preserved not by Jewish communities, but by Orthodox Christian communities.
If you get the two volume Old Testament, Suda Piggrafo, which is sort of the biggest repository of
Second Temple literature out there, and you read the prefaces to the books,
where the manuscripts come from, it's Marseille, it's St. Catharines, it's Mount Athos.
You know, there are...
a number of second-template Jewish texts that we only have preserved in Slavonic
because they were preserved at monastic settlements in the Slavic world. So these
have been preserved for us by the church and they were continually copied and
recopied right up into the 15th and 16th centuries and then the printing press came
along. And so I don't know so much of its loss is just that we haven't laid
We haven't fully as a generation laid hold of our inherent
inheritance. In the West, it's a lot more complicated. I think in the West, other issues
started to take precedence. No, there are Protestant Bible scholars who are trying to
reappropriate this in evangelical Protestant context. I think if they really follow it through,
be drawn in electively into the Orthodox Church.
But it's our secret weapon.
But so.
They are kind of rediscovering it over there,
but it's by going back as scholars,
going back to this literature and that kind of thing.
And as you said, I think Tolkien,
I mean, Tolkien I know was reading
the most newly translated ancient Nareastern texts
and that kind of thing that he could lay hands on.
Some of which turned out to be forgeries
and that kind of thing, but he didn't know.
Or just badly mis-translated, but he didn't know.
But he was one, and that's why he's someone
you see the
early on start to pop up in because he was deeply interested in it and kind of pursued it,
even in the West. Yeah. Yeah, and you know, I'll say, if you're interested in that particular angle
of this, so I have another podcast called Amman's Soule in which I talk about JR Tolkien from an
Orthodox Christian point of view with various guests. And Father Stephen came on that podcast for
episode 24 of-
common soul. And we specifically talked about the kind of mythic understanding of scripture and how that's
how that's represented in Tolkien's works. And he gets a lot right, interestingly enough, even though he's writing fiction,
he gets a lot, a lot right. But you know, just to sort of address this specific question of losing this sense of
the scriptural understanding of the divine counsel and so forth. I think you know
his father Steven said
like there's a lot of the fathers and it's my understanding it's the majority of the fathers have never been translated into English
like the vast majority of patricistic writings are not in English
you know that what we have is largely the bulk of it anyways comes from 19th century Protestants
who were looking for stuff to kind of use to argue against Roman Catholics in many cases
so it becomes kind of submitted to those sets of questions and then that can kind of distort the way we read it
And you know this is a perennial...
This is going to be a perennial issue on this podcast, which is, you know, why have I never heard this before?
You know, someone who's maybe raised Orthodox Christian or cataclyzed well as Orthodox Christian, they've never heard this stuff before.
And again, it's not because this stuff isn't in Scripture. It's not because it's not in the liturgical services.
It's not because it's not in the church fathers. It's just that probably whoever taught you
wasn't aware of this understanding. Now, that doesn't mean that you're not really an Orthodox Christian or that you're not capable of
of salvation, right?
because the whole point is to be faithful to Christ with whatever it is you've received.
Our task here is to try to help people be more faithful, right? But yeah, it's interesting.
I mean, I watched Father Stephen, for instance, give some talks about some of these things
to a group of clergy who were just sitting there dumbfounded. And again, they were almost all saying
why have I never heard this before? But the beautiful thing is that if you hear it and then you begin
to connect the dots of the things that you do know already, it makes a lot of
I mean, that's been my experience over and over again.
So I hope that a lot of people feel that way
about this podcast, like wait a minute.
Now it all makes sense, you know?
It's sort of like our inheritance.
It's sort of like one of those websites
where they're like, do you have money
that belongs to you in another state?
You know?
And if you go out there and you find out,
hey, I wrote 250 bucks at West Virginia, you know?
or there's a estate from my uncle in California.
That's sort of the way it is with this vast wealth of an inheritance we have from the
Orthodox Church.
There is this vast wealth of inheritance, but we have to go and look for it in each
generation.
We have to go and find it and appropriate it and collect it for ourselves in every generation.
Right.
Catechism is, I'm still being cataclyzed.
I've been Orthodox for over 20 years and I'm a priest and I teach this faith.
but I'm still being catacized and that's okay,
because Orthodox Christianity is not something
that you have in a box that you carry around
and you open up and show what a complete collection
of Orthodox that you have.
If I may say so.
Yeah, all right, so.
All right, well, we're gonna take one more call.
I hope that's helpful to you, Father Christopher,
but we're gonna take one more call
And then we're going to go ahead and
Wrap it up for tonight. We've unfortunately had some interruptions of stuff because of
Gremlins and Father Stevens power grid, but we have
We have Kathy calling from Minnesota. So Kathy, are you there?
Yes, I'm here. Oh, this is gonna be good radio
I can see I can see from the call I see as he says de Young. I'm like oh
of his relatives.
All right, Mrs. D. Young.
I feel like I have to call you Mrs. D. Young.
Yes, well, most of your fellow clergymen
just call me mom, but that's OK.
This is scared to death now, see?
No, it's not that.
I would just like you to possibly discuss this.
difference between the Protestant concept of sanctification and the Orthodox concept
of theosis.
Okay.
Because what I'm picking up, I mean I grew up Protestant.
So it was a process and it was sanctification and you grew into it.
It doesn't sound like that.
That's the same as the ocean at all
Yeah, so I would say you know
Just to give father Steven a moment or two to figure out what he's gonna say to his mother
Sorry
You know
You know the first time father Steven and I were on live radio together his sister called
I am feeling a little left out. Where are my damicks at?
I don't know.
Anyway...
know my dad listens but he probably would never call.
See I always text I text Father Steven after these sessions with questions and he always says
why don't you go in?
There it is right exactly.
So here's what I would say.
You know in most Protestant so I grew up Protestant as well I grew up as an evangelical.
And in most Protestant context sanctification is something that kind of happens so you
You've got your salvation.
you've got your ticket or whatever.
And sanctification is kind of the improvement
that happens after that.
And that can be understood as moral improvement,
especially, but from an Orthodox point of view,
now we wouldn't say that we don't believe in sanctification.
I mean, that's a word that's in scripture.
It just means becoming holy, right?
But we would say that that is
salvation, right? That becoming holy is salvation. And if you especially understand that what becoming holy means is
becoming one of the holy ones, one of the the hosts of heaven, one of the divine counsel,
then it is a much more
active and complex understanding of what it is that we have been called to do, right?
We're not called to just sort of fix our sin problem and then be
better people after that. Again, I know I'm simplifying, but what we are called to do is to become
like the stars in heaven. We are, you know, that is to say, like the heavenly hosts. We are called to
become as one of these, one of the divine counsel, one of the holy ones of God, right? And so,
so we would say that sanctification is a word that describes what that is. You know, it's something
and we grow into the fullness of the
the Statue of Christ, right?
It's not an instantaneous thing.
It is at the same time something that we have by means of baptism,
but that we also are called to grow more into,
because just because your baptism does not make you instantly,
in the full sense, a member of the heavenly host in every way.
So it's kind of all of that stuff together.
And I think the value of what we're discussing this evening
is to say, like, look, the destiny of mankind
is to stand.
alongside the angels and to do what they do.
You know, and so by virtue of being in the presence of God, we become more like him, and
we become more like him, not just sort of by standing there and absorbing his holiness,
but by participating in his works, just as of course the opposite happens.
If you participate in the works of demons, then you become like demons.
It's kind of the anti-theosis, you know, demonosis, for lack of a better term.
So that's what I would say.
say there's a difference between theosis and sanctification, I would say that theosis
is sanctification, but that the sanctification in most, not all, but most pros and models
is a much reduced kind of image.
So I don't know if that makes sense.
Father Steven, what would you say to your mother?
Well we read Romans 8.29, we didn't read 30 and 31, where a lot of this in terms of the
the Protestant view of salvation comes from.
Although sanctification.
is left out there, but there's what's called usually in Protestant theology, the
orthosolutus which is the fancy Latin for the order of salvation. So there's
an idea that there are these different moments in our salvation that represent
a sequence, right? And the main ones that usually are there's there's justification
which is held to be this one time thing that happens at the beginning when you
get saved. And then there's sanctification which is this process.
that comes afterwards and then glorification, which is what happens when you die and go
to heaven.
Right.
To really simplify things a lot, right?
But so there's, there's a, it's a temporal order.
It's a series of moments or periods in our salvation.
But when you read at the end of Romans 8, there's actually nothing in the Greek to imply
any kind of temporal order or succession that one happens after the other.
They're all in the same verb tense.
all it's
the Eurasians, which is just the simple past tense. These things all happened.
Yeah. And even in the English it just says he also, he also, he also, not he then, he then
it's all so. And so if you see, if you understand justification is being made righteous,
being put right, sanctification is being made holy, glorification is coming to share in the glory
of Christ as we saw St. Paul already talking about and we can throw in more.
Right. But these are all not sort of a temporal order, but these are all things that happen
to us as part of us being conformed to the likeness of Christ, being conformed to his
image, as St. Paul said in Romans 829 at the beginning of all that, that that's the goal.
So these are all aspects of it, but they're like facets of a gem, not these separate independent
Same.
or processes. So there are all things that are true of those who become sons of God by the grace of God in Christ.
So does that answer your question, Mrs. DeYoung?
Yes, I mostly asked it for others who have been brought up with this Protestant concept.
Sure.
Thanks.
This I-
of process and you know this step and then this step and then this step.
And I think it comes to mind and my son likes to say, well yeah, but and tell me a bunch of other stuff.
But the whole idea of, you know, he does.
I am saved. I am being saved. I will be saved. All those things are true.
at the same time that it, but yeah, they're true at the same time rather than being a process,
a one at a time step.
Thank you, Bob.
Enjoy the snow.
You're welcome.
All right.
Well, we're gonna just to wrap up.
I mean, let's each give kind of a, you know, concluding comments.
But before we do that, I want to just give a plug.
We have a special episode happening next week.
Now normally where we have shows on the second and fourth,
Thursdays of the month, but we have a special fifth Thursday,
bonus episode happening next week,
and it is our Halloween episode,
and it is called the Real Demons of Halloween.
And it's R
assertion that Halloween involves demons and that that's not a problem for us. Okay, so we're
not going to give away what we're all going to be talking about next week. But I just want to
give that plug and please, you know, find that event on Facebook, share it with your friends,
invite them, and so forth. But I, you know, so for my final comment, I just wanted to,
to read a little passage from that paper.
I mentioned earlier from Father Matthew Baker of Blessed Memory and the papers called Deification
and Sunship according to Saint Athanasius of Alexandria.
You can Google that up and you'll find it.
It's all online actually.
So he talks about, he's talking about Saint Athanasius, obviously.
He has this.
This is in one of his paragraphs.
He says this.
In his letter to the Egyptian bishops in 356, Athanasius will count.
Be with this.
again, that means adoption or sunmaking. As amongst the four instructions and gifts of grace
given us by Christ, together with prayer, power against demons, and that exceeding great and
singular grace, knowledge of the Father and the Word Himself and the gift of the Holy Ghost.
According to Athanasius, the Spirit of adoption and of freedom gives the Christian fearlessness
to confess the truth. And I just
love that paragraph in his paper and how, especially he connects that notion of, of, are being adopted
as sons of God with power against the demons. I mean, this is an angelic ministry, right, to fight
against demons. You know, knowledge of, of the Father and of Christ himself, the gift of the Holy
Spirit, you know, that, and, and also that fearlessness to confess the truth. I mean, if you become one of
of the divine council if you
become part of the heavenly hosts, then you can confess the truth because you have nothing
to be afraid of. Nothing at all. You stand with God, you stand with His angels and you're
becoming like Him and you're taking your place alongside them and it's alongside all the
saints, alongside all the saints. So that's just what I wanted to highlight at the end.
Father Steven, your final comments?
Yeah. I think it's important. The reason that this is important, what we talked about tonight
is important.
is that I think for too long we've thought too small about salvation and about God and
about his plan.
This life isn't about, you know, I did some bad stuff but I'll do what I need to do to
make sure I get to heaven anyway and get out of this crummy world.
It's not about God really.
wanting to save us, but he has this justice problem he has to get over. This is about the God who created
the universe, the eternal God who created everything, created everything so that he could become one of us
and so that he could share his eternal divine life with us forever. And we have the opportunity,
not to do that when we die if we do the right thing.
here on earth but we have been given the gift to be able to start to experience that right now
right now starting with our baptism. Until we realize that we're going to think too small and
we're going to get bogged down in a lot of mundane things in life in the world.
But as long as we keep this great destiny we've been given and we've been created for by God
in our minds, but we'll have a different perspective about the world and living in it, about
the people around us, how we view them and their struggles, and we'll come to know better
the God whom we worship and whom we're becoming every day more like.
So that's my closing comment, and hopefully next week I will not be talking to you on a
red solo cup connected to a string.
May it be blessed, you know. Pray, pray, pray for us, everybody. Please, please pray for us. I, I believe that this is important work. So thank you very much for that, Father Steven. That is our show for today. Thank you for listening.
If you didn't get a chance to call in during the live broadcast, we would still love to hear from you either via email at Lord of
Spirits at ancient faith.com or you can message us at our Lord.
of Spirit's podcast Facebook page.
We read everything, but can't respond to everything,
and we do save what you send for possible use
in future episodes.
And join us for our live broadcasts on the second
and fourth Thursdays of the month,
and on October 29th at 7 p.m. Eastern 4 p.m. Pacific.
And don't forget to like our Lord of Spirit's podcast
Facebook page while you're at it.
Leave a recommendation, join the Facebook group,
and then invite your friends.
And if you leave a review on Apple Podcasts,
Facebook.
wherever you get your podcasts and that raises the visibility of this show and gets
more people connected.
And finally, be sure to go to www.engshafethe.com slash support and help make sure we and lots
of other AFR podcasters stay on the air.
Thank you and God bless you.
You've been listening to The Lord of Spirits with Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew
Stephen Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung, a listener supported present
of ancient faith radio. And I beheld and I heard the voice of many angels round
about the throne and the beasts and the elders and the number of them was 10,000 times 10,000
than thousands of thousands, saying with a loud voice, worthy is the land that was slain
to receive power and riches and wisdom and strength and honor and glory and blessing.
Revelation chapter 5 verses 11 through 12.