for them to stand and not to falls, and the hope of those whose hearts are troubled.
All who dwell on the earth will fall down and worship him, and they will praise and bless,
and celebrate with song the Lord of Spirits, 1st denoc, chapter 48, verses 4-5.
The modern world doesn't acknowledge, but is nevertheless haunted by spirits,
angels, demons, and saints. In our time, many year into break free of the prison of a flat,
secular materialism.
to see and to know reality as it truly is.
What is this spiritual reality like?
How do we engage with it well?
How do we permeate every day life with spiritual presence?
Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew Stephen Damick
and Father Steve DeYoung
host this live Colin show focused on enchantment in creation.
The union of the scene and unseen as made by God
and experienced by mankind throughout history.
Welcome to the Lord of Spirits.
Welcome back to the Lord of Spirits podcast. I am Father Andrew Stephen Damick in a Mayus,
Pennsylvania, and with me via the magic of modern technology is my co-host, Father
Stephen D'Yan in Lafayette, Louisiana. And if you are listening to this episode live,
you can call in at 855 AF radio. That's 855-237-2346. And we will get to your calls in
in these seconds.
part of today's show. In a June 1941 letter to his son, Michael, Lord of the
Rings author and Anglo-Saxon professor J. R. R. Tolkien included this passage.
He wrote this,
There is a place called Heaven where the good here unfinished is completed and where
the stories unwritten and the hopes unfulfilled are continued.
I'm-
Remember the first time I read that passage and my heart leapt within me as I knew immediately
that it was true.
You see, even though I am a lifelong Christian, in a sense of what it is, clear.
Yes, we all want to go to heaven when we die.
But I think that for many of us, this just means that we prefer to go to the good place
rather than the bad place.
And therefore heaven is envisioned as a kind of permanent tropical vacation.
perhaps you
and in its most insipid depictions,
its scenes with glowing rings around their heads,
sitting on clouds, playing handheld harps for all eternity.
Yes, we all want to have the good end,
and not the bad one.
But is heaven really a good end?
And for many, it sounds kind of boring.
And the dubious words of the talking heads,
heaven is a place where nothing ever happens.
Well, that's Bunk.
Tonight we're going to discuss
what exactly all of this Christian life is aiming at? What does it mean to be saved
when we get to the other side of the resurrection? Will we actually have anything
to do? Last time on our Halloween special we talked about doing combat with
the forces of evil, the demons, the angels do it, the saints do it, and we are
called to do it. What about after their final defeat? And what bearing does that
have online for now.
Well, you guessed it. We're gonna start by talking about angels again. So
Like I said last time we talked about doing combat with demons, and so let's
Let's begin there. Father Stephen
Take us in. Yeah
so
Our last few episodes actually we've kind of been on this trajectory talking about
the angelic beings whom God created and with whom
He shared his dominion and his rule over creation.
We've read some quotes from ancient folks about how God has a government or a commonwealth
over his creation and that he assigned these beings to hold these different roles in his
administration over the cosmos.
We talked about how some of them at various points have a...
fallen and how humans as adopted sons of God who have received that adoption by grace
and that inheritance and have been glorified, then fill those roles, those job openings,
as we said, they're left behind by those fallen spirits.
And so we've kind of outlined this idea of the saints and glory as
being part of this sort of administration and this governance and so there's another major element
to the ministry that the Saints and glory have in this age and that we hope to share in the age to come in
God's kingdom and so it's that sort of that second role
that we are going to be talking about and
expanding on tonight
Yeah, how how those two things fit together is sort of this
twofold ministry of the sons of God of glorified humanity and of the the
elect angels as St. Paul calls them, the the angels who have remained in their
original righteousness and purity. Yeah and I think that you know occasionally we
get asked the question like okay you guys are talking about angels and demons
and next time we'll be talking about giants.
Everybody's excited.
people get excited when I talk about churnions.
There it is.
That's Father Stephen D. Young's catchphrase, everybody.
But, you know, there's this question like,
okay, well, that's all well and good,
but does it have any kind of practical side, right?
And that's one of the emphasis that we've tried to give
over and over again.
And I think that this might be one of the fuzziest spots
in a lot of Kristen's imagination.
Like, is our participation in the divine council?
Council is that?
practical, or is it just some kind of like status, or again, you know, the life of the
age to come sounds kind of boring to a lot of people. Does it have anything to it? You know?
And I remember when I was a kid and even now, you know, we read those passages in the
scripture where it talks about that the saints will reign together with Christ, right? You
know, we will reign with him. And then, you know, there's, there's this language is in
multiple places, especially in the
New Testament. And I think that when I first saw that, I thought, okay, we're going to
reign with him great. What I never really gave to my son, what exactly that means. You
know, like, okay, we're going to send a throne. So I'm going to have a crown, you know, or
you know, that kind of thing. But not much in the sense of a kind of day to day reality.
I think a lot of us have the sense of the life of the age to come being kind of static. And
not gonna be sort of work today.
So tonight that's what we're discussing is all of that. In fact, there is in the Scripture
a robust image of what it is that the saints in glory, and that's what we're called to
be, do in the kingdom of God. You know, there's actually something to do, right? So, you know,
there's this kind of twofold ministry, right, that the angels have. And last week we talked
especially.
about their position as combatants in the spiritual warfare
and then how we joined last week, sorry,
a couple of weeks ago and how we joined them in that.
But there's another side to it, like you said.
So let's talk about that a little bit this evening.
Yeah, and this is the place where we see
sort of our more active and direct relationship
with the spirits of both angelic spirits
and the spirits of the
righteous who have gone before us.
We had some questions last time about like,
well, okay, what does it mean to me?
If I live in Thessaloniki,
like what does it mean to me at about my life
that St. Demetrius is now in charge instead of Africa?
Yeah, it sounds cool.
Like yeah, I guess that's better, but right?
So this is more at the level of interaction.
right and
A lot of times I think it's diminished.
I think this is in terms of our Protestant friends who I don't want to be seen as picking
on because they are our friends.
I don't want to pick on them.
But there is a nervousness and a diminishment due to I think the history with Roman Catholicism
of wanting there to be any kind of...
relationship, right? Even even with our departed loved ones that okay well they're in heaven now so
okay we'll see them later, right? And you don't want to be talking to angels, right? You don't want to be
talking to saints that have gone before because they're now gone and there's this separation. But in
response to that what we see in the scriptures and in the traditions surrounding the scriptures
and ancient Judaism that we're going to talk about a little bit.
but is the idea that there's this very direct relationship
and that there's a role that they play,
not coming in between humans and God,
but a role that we're gonna defame
a lot tonight, right?
Right.
Interceding, which is not mediating
coming between but interceding.
And there are examples.
already, as I just mentioned in the scripture and in early Jewish traditions
from the second temple period of human beings seeking the intercession of
angelic beings. And what that means concretely is seeking their prayers,
seeking their prayers to God on their behalf. Right. And I think one of the problems
that we have is because we live in this sort of flattened secular materialist
world where we...
We generally do not have you know what we might describe as spiritual encounters or or that we don't
acknowledge that we do right or we don't know that we're we do the idea of sort of bringing in an angel or bringing in a saint
Sounds extraordinary and crazy and weird and and okay
We will acknowledge that God breaks in like this is what we talked about for the very first episode
Right, you know this idea of like okay? We're gonna put brackets around certain supernatural things
we're gonna believe in but but it
It seems a little crowded when you start bringing in angels and zanes.
But I think because it's because this is our experience of the world that we think of
it as some weird extra thing.
And like, why do you need to add that on?
Can't you just talk to God yourself?
Why do you need to get, you know, does not get in between you and God?
You know, as you said, like the sense of interfering, right?
And yet ancient peoples had a constant sense of spiritual encounter.
they may not be having visionary experiences 24 hours a day,
but they knew that that was the world they lived in,
and they were having experiences more often than we are.
And so, like, the idea of, like, well, I'm just not going to believe in that,
because that never happens.
Like, no one would say that, because it happened.
And, you know, people knew that that was just part of life, right?
That the set of evidence that we're dealing with,
which is again is mediated through our sense
and through our perception and through our interpretation
is a different set of evidence than ancient people's had,
where encounters with spiritual beings
were maybe not something that happened every second of every day,
but enough that it was kind of normal.
And I think that that's a really, really important point
to make here from the outset in terms of framing this.
For instance, if I lived,
so I'm up here in my studio right now,
the building is basically empty except for me
If that was my experience every single day and I never saw anybody else here ever, it might
become easy for me to believe that I work here by myself.
You know, that no one else works here.
If I never saw anyone else, they might be on floors that I never go to.
They might be in rooms that I never walk by.
But if I never see them, then it's easy for me not to believe that they're there and to
function like they're not even there.
And then if suddenly the room that I become aware of the, all the people working in this
building and I start to hear you know the
walking on the floor above me.
And I hear their voices and I see them in the elevator,
it might feel really deeply weird and crowded.
And what are they doing here?
This was my nice, quiet building.
That's the way that I think about this issue.
And especially for people coming into the Orthodox church
for the first time, and they walk into a church
and they see all these scenes in angels surrounding them
in the icons and constantly being referenced
in the services and so forth.
It seems a little spiritually crowded.
if
used to just me and Jesus, you know. Right. Right. And we don't, we don't sort of apply that logic
to the rest of our lives. Right. Right. Very few of us, there are some people out there, but very few
of us would say, you know, if you get sick, don't go to a doctor, just go directly to God. Right.
You don't get it. There are people out there, but not a lot. Yeah. Not a lot. And because they don't
don't last very long.
But...
And we don't say like, you know, if you have a problem, don't talk to your spouse about it.
Don't talk to your family about it.
Don't talk to your pastor about it.
Because you can just take it straight to God.
Don't talk to anyone else, right?
We all understand that God works in our lives through other people.
Right?
Right.
He doesn't have to do everything just directly for it to be from him.
And so that doesn't conflict with the fact that it's God who's doing it.
And so in the same way, we feel perfectly comfortable
asking people to pray for us.
And we see that happening in the scriptures,
for example, and this is kind of the prime example
because in the book of Job,
the book of Job, of course,
I'm not gonna go through the whole thing,
but the book of Job, we've quoted it already
the beginning part where Satan has gotten
Permission.
to sort of test Job and this testing is not testing like taking a test and you pass or you fail.
This is testing like testing metal when you're doing blacksmithing.
This is to refine and purify Job.
Job is being tested and he hasn't gotten a direct communication as to why.
From the human perspective, just all these horrible things have happened to him.
The members have been killed.
He's gotten boils all over his body.
He's lost everything.
He's sitting on the community dung heap,
using potchards on his boils to lancet them.
So thinks of God very badly for Job.
And he has all of his quote unquote friends
coming up to him and saying,
well, clearly we know what's going on.
You did something bad and God's punishing you.
Right?
And Job is saying, no, that's not it.
I don't know.
what's going on, but I know that's not it.
And then his charming wife comes and says, well, God's just dealing with you unjustly.
So curse God and die because she's a lovely person.
And Job declines that also.
It says no, right?
I'm not doing that either.
And so at one point when he's speaking with one of his friends, one of his friends says,
well, you know, if you're going to reject our answers, then you need to find out what's
going on.
So he says
to him in Job 5 verse 1, to which of the holy ones will you address your case?
And if we translated that holy ones, we've talked about this in previous episodes.
But if we translated that the way we translate the same word in the New Testament, we'd
say to which of the saints will you address your plea?
Applying, well, are you going to go to one of the people in God's administration and ask
them to intercede for you and and
and find out what's going on.
Not that, oh, we'll just go and find a God, small G,
and ask them to fix it for you,
since apparently the true God is angry at you.
Right.
And it's interesting to me looking at that verse,
Job 51, as it gets rendered in the Greek translation
of the Old Testament, right?
Which was done by Greek speaking Jews.
So these were Jews doing a translation of the Greek
according to their own understanding of their own...
scriptures, right? And the way that the Greek, if you were to translate the Greek into English,
it doesn't say the Holy Ones, it says to which of the Holy Angels will you address your case.
So it's interesting that when Jews, ancient Jews, pre-Christian Jews, hundreds of years before
Christ were translating their own scriptures into Greek, they understood that this reference
to the Holy Ones or to the saints, if you're going to translate as we do in the New Testament in
English.
is referenced to the angels.
In other words, which angels are you gonna talk to, Job?
Right, which indicates that that is a thing.
That's the thing.
They were disambiguating it to make it clear.
He's not talking about finding a holy man to pray for him.
Right?
He's talking about Angelic Intercession.
And we see this in Jewish traditional sources
outside of.
or at the periphery of with this first one, the canonical Old Testament Scriptures.
In 1st Enoch 15 verse 2, at this point in the story of the imprisoned fallen angels
who are imprisoned in the underworld, have Enoch has been taken on this tour and has
or seen them in prison there and they ask Enek to go
They say, well, God likes you, Enic. He doesn't like us so much now.
Why don't you go and pray for us and intercede for us with God and see if maybe he'll show some leniency.
Right? And let us out of this prison. Now, they're not actually repentant. They're not sorry for
anything they did. They just don't like the consequences and the punishment and want out of it.
right yeah and so unit goes
and does this and God basically gives him a message to take back to the imprisoned fallen angels
and a major portion of that message is Enic telling them on God's behalf that you were to
intercede for men not men for you. So saying why are you said part of govern and rule over them
but to intercede for them and bring their prayers.
before God. And that's imagery that's also echoed in the book of Revelation where we see the prayers
of the saints in these incense censors being brought before God's throne by the angels.
This same kind of idea. So what that's saying for us to think is that was understood to be,
they weren't just watchers and governors, as we've already described, but also were to have
this intercessory role. They were supposed to be interceding
and trying to lead human beings closer to God, closer to Christ.
And then we had one more example.
And now we've moved out another concentric circle to a text.
And as I told you earlier today, this gets really complicated.
There are dozens of books called Lives of Adam and Eve,
or life of Adam or book of Adam.
in different languages. They're all related, but scholars argue over how because you have to write a dissertation about something.
But one of them in particular, which is one of the earliest
versions of the text that comes from the first century AD.
So this is the time of Christ, is the time of the Apostles, the time when the New Testament is being written.
is being written. Okay. I've referred to as the Greek life of Adam and Eve, or sometimes the
Even though those titles do not seem to have anything in...
But that's a whole other episode right?
Yes.
Yeah, right.
Yeah, disambiguating these texts.
Yeah.
So, in this text, it's basically it's describing the repentance of Adam and Eve after they've
been exiled from Paradise.
Yeah.
And they realize that they've sinned and transgressed and now they want to repent.
And there are a lot of interesting things.
in the text, I'm sure we'll reference it at other times on the show. But for our
purposes tonight, it describes that while they're undertaking these actions of repentance,
they're doing these sort of penitential things involving prayer and fasting and vigils.
While they're doing that, the sun and the moon and the stars and the angels are said
to be praying and offering incense to God on their behalf, be sort of praying and interceding
with God for mercy for them.
while they're repenting.
Yeah.
Yeah. And of course, as we've pointed out before,
when you talk about the sun and the moon and the stars
in Scripture, you have to read that as being involved
with endelic beings.
Yeah. And just to reiterate maybe, because I think this is
important, because we just, you know, as you said, you just
quoted from first Enic, and then from the Greek life of Adam
and Eve, aka the apocalypse of Moses.
that we don't regard these books as scripture,
but like Enoch is kind of scripture adjacent
and the screech life of Adam and Eve is kind of
in the books that are being read at the time.
And the point of quoting these things is not to say,
oh well, we're reading these books
and we're drawing out doctrines from these
that you won't find anywhere else.
But rather the point is that look, see there,
These are simply witnesses to what's being believed.
at that time and the first century especially when those are being sent out by him and the New Testament is being written
You know the early church this is this is there this is in that that tradition
And so we we mentioned these texts again not to say that this is a source of doctrine
But it is a testament a witness to what is being believed and you know we already quoted from Job
So I mean, and clearly this idea of the angels praying for us and
even that you can ask them to pray for you is a thing.
In the Old Testament and definitely in the period
of the New Testament as well.
So, it's cool stuff.
It's an issue of context, right?
Because there are a lot of things in the Bible
that if we just isolate the biblical texts,
can be ambiguous where you look at it and say,
well wait, what does that mean, right?
Right, you know.
And so if we have other writings written by
faithful Jewish people at the same time, they can give us a clue to at least how
the original readers would have read it and understood it. Right. Rather than
just supplying our lives here in the 21st century as the context in which you
should read the scripture. Right. You know, like that's an important context in
certain ways for application, but but it's not the primary one because it wasn't
written now it was written then and that's that's super super important and so it's
But from there, then, we get, as you see throughout orthodox tradition, that we, seeing that
this has been a thing for a long time, we simply continue to do what had always been done
by the people of God.
And we ask the angels to intercede for us.
We ask the holy ones to intercede for us, pray for us.
But again, we don't understand that it's getting in between us in God, or like I can't talk
to God directly.
get somebody who's near him to pass this message on.
But rather that we ask them to pray alongside us
to pray for us just as in your own church,
if there's somebody who's really, really good at prayer,
who's really dedicated to prayer,
wouldn't you go to them and say, please pray for me?
And the thing is is that,
that makes it more plausible for me
to talk about that human person who's doing that thing
and say, okay, I guess maybe then angels and saints,
but actually it should be right in the other direction
that that human in my parish who
is really good at prayer is simply participating in this ministry that's always been taking place.
They're continuing to do the same thing. So of course we're going to ask them. We just, you know,
and we just, in the Orthodox Church, at least on the new calendar, we just celebrated a few days
ago, the Feast of the Archangel's, and we very explicitly over and over again ask them to pray for
us. You know, please pray for us, Michael and Gabriel and Raphael and all of them. And it's beautiful,
just really beautiful, beautiful, beautiful stuff. So yeah, and it's key to hammer on.
pray for us doesn't mean pray so that we don't have to.
Yeah, right.
They're not praying instead of us.
Like God's not going to listen to me, but he'll listen to you.
So you pray, right?
That's not it.
It's alongside it.
And that's yeah, or like I have better things to do.
So could you, you know, take, take care of the prayer part for me.
They're pleased.
Yeah.
We've, we've got mumps praying.
I can go about my business.
Yeah.
No.
But, but so we see that in that life of Adam and Eve example, right?
that Adam and Eve are very busy about repenting,
and the angels are praying alongside them.
And so going into that, this is something
that we see all through the scriptures.
In the Psalms especially, right,
praise him, all his angels, praise him, all his hosts.
Right. Right. Right.
To the O God's doors.
The Psalms and the worship of Israel
is constantly invoking the angels to join in,
and to worship it
to pray alongside and at the same time and with us.
Yeah, especially those last few Psalms
that are so explicit about that.
And I think like if I read that and I say,
oh, that's not invoking angels,
then that just means I don't take seriously
what it actually says there.
Like when it says praise him all it's angels.
That's talking to angels and saying praise God.
Like it's simply right there.
But if I approach it from the point of view of,
oh, this is not a thing we do,
And then I just have to see.
Oh, well, it's just kind of poetic and not meant to be taken seriously.
Well, and not only that with Psalm 147 through 150,
that's how we understand what it means when the psalmist asks a bunch of inanimate objects
from our perspective, the praise God.
Right.
He's not talking to rocks and.
And so and air.
Yeah, he's talking to the star beings.
Right.
He's talking to Angelic beings.
We're assigned to those.
And this is something that's run all through our
the surgical services of the Orthodox Church.
When we make an entrance, we ask the angels
to make the entrance with us.
When we pray, we ask the angels to pray with us.
When we sing, we ask the angels to sing with us.
Can't just get it.
This is a joining together, and this is part of their role.
And we see in scripture that those two things,
the things we talk about in terms of ruling and raining,
that royal part and the priesthood.
part are supposed to be joined together. Israel is supposed to be a kingdom of priests.
St. Peter says that we are in the church a royal priesthood. We have the example of Melchizedek
and Christ Melchizedek priesthood that brings priesthood and kingship back together. When
they're separated, they're separated as sort of a judgment because of a problem with sin,
then when that's overcome, they're brought back together.
And it's interesting that even in...
Even in the pagan context, they're obviously they're worshipping demons, but like the local pagan king was the guy standing in front of the altar as well.
Like he had that task.
I recall one time a conversation we had when she talked about Alexander the Great and how he deliberately, as he conquered various nations, he did the work that it took, the ritual work that it took to become the son of whoever was their most high god.
Like he became Pharaoh, for instance.
Right?
And that involved him offering sacrifices.
And but in Israel it gets divided, as you said,
because of sin, that kingship and priesthood have to get divided
because of sin.
And part of the problem with paganism is that they're sinning,
but they're not chastened by God as the way that Israel is chastened.
And so they just keep sinning and they send worse and worse.
and their worshiping team.
humans. You know? Yeah. And so when as we've been talking about in the past couple episodes,
glorified humans are glorified as sense of God that come to share in God's eternal divine life
and they take these places vacated by the fallen angels, they take on not just the royal part of
of this ministry but the priesthood.
And I've got us a good old fashioned proof text to look at.
Hey.
All right.
All right, can I read this one?
Absolutely, you can go ahead.
All right, and so I'm going to read this and then we're going to go to break shortly
after this.
But yeah, okay, so this is from Revelation chapter 20 and this is verses 4 through 6.
And this is, you know, the Apostle St. John speaking in this visionary experience he had.
And I saw thrones, the day that sat upon them and judgment was given to them.
the soul.
of those who had been beheaded because of the witness of Jesus and because of the word
of God and who did not worship the beast nor his image and did not take the mark upon
their forehead or on their hand, then they lived and reigned with Christ a thousand years.
The rest of the dead did not live again until the thousand years will be completed.
This is the first resurrection.
Blissful and a holy one is the one who has a part in the first resurrection.
these the second data
no authority, but they will be priests of God and of Christ, and they will reign with
him a thousand years. And I think it's really important to note that it starts out by saying
that it's the souls of those who have been beheaded because of the witness of Jesus. In other
words, this is human beings who have been martyred for Christ. That's what this passage is
talking about and as you said you know it talks about them raining with Christ and also
that they are priests.
And I loved the little bit of word,
notary that you put in here about to say,
well, in the new covenant, there aren't priests.
In other words, there aren't people
who are offering sacrifices on altars, right?
There's just presbyters.
And there is an argument to be made there
because the English word priest actually
comes from the word presbyter.
But in English Bibles, we tend to translate
presvideros as presbyter or elder.
and we translate it up as...
priest, right? What's interesting is that in this passage, as you said, when we
are talking about this earlier today, that the word that is talking about them as
being priests is E at F's. It actually says they're gonna be sacrificial priests
God and of Christ and they'll reign with him in that beautiful millennium. And I
know there's a lot of other popular interpretations of this passage, visa VVN
times. But just a point.
Now a couple reasons why this has to be talking about the saints in glory now.
You notice it talks about, these are the word for witness and the witness of Jesus is
martyrians.
So these are literally martyrs in the actual work.
They come to life and they reign with Christ.
And them coming to life and reigning with Christ is described as, it says literally, this
is the first resurrection.
They're seated on these thrones and raining earth Christ in the thirst for strength.
resurrection. Then it says over these, those who participate in the first
resurrection, the second death has no authority. Meaning those who aren't
participants in the first resurrection group of people who are raised from the
dead early like for a rapture, supposed to some other Christians who are raised
later. The people who are raised later are the dead who are not righteous.
dead who are not holy or the dead who are subject to the second death. So this is talking about in the
first resurrection it's talking about the the the the life of the souls of the departed of those who
are specifically the martyrs here. So this is quite literally talking about the departed saints and
what they're doing right now and that is that they are reigning with Christ and they are serving
is priests, which means they're interceding and they're offering worship.
and with that we're going to go ahead and take a break and when we get back we're going to answer a question that we just got via Facebook so we'll be right back.
Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung will be back in a moment to take your calls on the second half of the Lord of Spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237-2346. That's 855-AF radio.
Hi, this is Father Evan Armitoss, priest at St. Spirit on Greek Orthodox Church in Lolland
Colorado, and the host of the Ancient Faith Radio, Sunday Night Call and Show, Orthodoxy
Live.
I am pleased to announce today the release of my first book for Ancient Faith Publishing,
titled, Toolkit for Spiritual Growth, a Practual Guide to Prayer, Fasting and Arms Giving.
It seeks to provide a guide to the three basic and primary disciplines of Orthodox spirituality
Christ hope.
for us a path that frees us from the disordered way of life who's become normal for many,
even though their hearts and minds tell them otherwise. Please join me in exploring the three-legged
stool of Orthodox spiritual practice, prayer, fasting, and non-sgiving. Books now available
at store.ancientfaith.com and the title once again is Toolkit for Spiritual Grove.
I look forward to sharing it with you. God bless.
We're back now with the
Lord of spirits, the Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father
Stephen DeYoung.
If you have a question, call now at F Radio.
Welcome back.
So this is the second part of our show.
And it's where we begin to take your calls.
And like you just heard from the voice of Steve,
you can reach us at 855 AF Radio, which is 855-237-2346.
You can also send questions to us on social media.
And hopefully, if one of our helpers spots it,
send it to us.
And we can answer it that way, but we of course would also love to hear your voices.
So the first question that we've received this evening is from Helen, who left this comment on our Facebook stream.
And Helen said this,
do the ancients believe the planets are angels?
Are they praying to what we know as planets?
So we've kind of addressed that before but why don't you go ahead and give us a little refresh
of their fathers.
Stephen? Yeah. This is not, they're not praying to the physical object, right? But they
understood, ancient people understood that there were spirits associated with all of these
visible objects. There were invisible cigarettes associated with them involved in their governance
and otherwise associated with them.
For
ancient Israelites and for people of the second temple period, they believed that
these were angelic beings or demonic beings created by God who had been given
authority from him to exercise over these things. If we're talking about
pagans, they worshipped these spirits sort of in their own right and that was
of course the problem.
Yeah, rather than seeing them as part of the the administration of the true God the most high God
Uh, yeah, and so yeah, so that's the idea. It's not right like
We know the sun is a massive incandescent gas, right such a gigantic nuclear furnace
They didn't worship that right
Right. Right. Yeah, and it's and it's an interesting question like, okay, so if there is an angel
associated with the sun, who is obedient to God.
But then you have pagans over here
who are worshiping their sun God.
Are they attempting to worship an angel
who doesn't want their worship?
Or is there basically some demon
that's sort of saying, yeah, I'll take that worship,
excuse me, that's a different,
I mean, obviously it's hard to sort all this stuff out.
But, you know, that's kind of a connect.
Can I ask you a little bit with one question that we've gotten over and over again?
Well, probably, I think we'll explore this a lot more in a future episode, which is that
can angels still fall, right?
If people, if there's a good angel, so to speak, that's tending to the sun, could he decide,
you know what?
I'm going to go ahead and take that sun worship.
Or is it really, you know, another demon?
A demon who is accepting that?
Yeah.
And there's no reason to believe.
We always have to keep in mind a couple of things.
The first-
one is that demons are creatures of deceit and chaos and lies. So there's no reason to believe
that every spirit that showed up in the ancient world and claimed to be Apollo was the same being.
Yeah. Or if I could say I'm the sun god. Yeah. Yeah. Right. And then secondly,
and this is addressing this struggle and some others that I know people are having listening to
to the show, it's sort of processing things.
And this is something we're always going to have to come back to from the very beginning
and that's talking about the grid, right?
The Western grid we have.
And with this show, we're not coming to you with new things to fill out the fields in the
grid as opposed to the old ones that were wrong.
We're trying to get you to get rid of the grid.
And so sometimes the
confusion is going to be caused by, right, I'm sending you a word document that's got a poem in it
and you're importing it into Excel as a spreadsheet, right? It's poetry. It's not math. So it's going to come
through garble. And so if we're looking for precision, okay, exactly what Angel is doing this and
and what's his rank, and what's his name,
and where is he, and then who's this one?
And who's that you're not going to have a good time.
Yeah.
It's, it's, yeah, that's not how it, that, that sort of not how it works.
Right.
And it's interesting that that's a kind of, um, you know, correct me if I'm wrong here,
but, but, you know, ancient Nostics tended to, to, they loved their big charts, you know,
like all of this was arranged to, you know, this angel is at this, Ion and this,
you know, this Archon is over here and signed to this.
And what's amazing with how complex some of those
arrangements are is the variety of them. Like when they're attempting to get it all sorted out,
I mean no one except for maybe their little group actually buys into that particular sorting.
Yeah, so yeah. Well anyway, so with the second part of our show tonight, we want to talk about
some possible objections that people might have to what we just described in the first part.
And the first objection we want to discuss is something
that, especially that Protestants who encounter the Orthodox Church, can tend to have a big,
big problem with, and it's an understandable problem. I totally get it. I used to see things
this way myself, because I was not always Orthodox. I was raised as an evangelical Protestant.
And that's that when Orthodox Christians give veneration to angels to saints,
A lot of Protestants will look at that and say why are you
worshipping saints. Why are you worshipping angels? Isn't that idolatry? Right? And the Orthodox
person will respond by saying, I'm not I'm not worshipping them. I'm venerating them. And
the response to that might be, well, six and a half a dozen of another.
Yeah. Well, I want to be make sure we're being as charitable as possible.
Okay, and so
Even you know, yeah in one way it's objections, but I
I want to give our Protestant friends who have this issue even more credit than that.
Okay, let's say, and say that this isn't just them wanting to have an argument, although
some of them that probably is it, but they're not trying to have an argument, but that this
is a difference that they don't see.
And so the whole idea, they're good-hearted people, they love Christ, they want to worship
only the true God and since they don't see the
the whole thing makes them really queasy and nervous.
Right. It's not just an intellectual objection or something.
Right. It looks like worship to them what we do with saints and angels.
And I think that the basis for that is,
and we're going to get into this, I think, especially.
But the basis for that is that the actions that most Protestants do
in their worship.
services, right? So let's be explicit. So singing to God, you know, praying to God and telling him how awesome he is, you know, and in some cases, like if you're more affected by safer and
as the charismatic movement, they might lift up their hands.
These kinds of things are what is identified as being worship in those contexts.
right and and even if they do have especially as you get to the more of the kind of
low church side of things you know more sort of a zvingly and understanding of
for instance communion even if they have communion it's largely not described as
interestingly not described as being that that action is not described as being
worship but as rather as being a memorial like okay we're doing a stream
remember what Jesus did for us.
And so the actions that
our described as worship in many Protestant contexts,
singing, praying, praising God, and so forth.
Orthodox look at that stuff and say,
well that's just veneration, right?
So when we sing to a saint or tell him that he's awesome
or ask him to help us,
That's we don't regard that as worship we
regard that is veneration.
And we're not making this point as just pure apologetics,
right?
This is not an apologetics show.
But I think this is an important point to make,
because like you said, we're trying to get people off
of the grid, off the matrix that they're in and say,
there's a whole different world here, actually,
that we're trying to help people see and experience.
And for the orthodox, worship is focused
on the act of offering.
Right, and it's not just offering prayers, but actually offering
sacrifices and in the Orthodox Church there's essentially two
sacrifices that are offered now mean you know the the term gets metaphorically used for different since the sacrifice of praise right but
There's really two sacrifices that are being offered one is the sacrifice of the Eucharist
bread and wine being offered on the altar
Changed by God to be the body and blood of Christ and then we share that
that sacrificial meal with him because that's what sacrifice is.
is, and then also incense is sacrificed. Incense is offered. It's offered to God. But again,
we share him to smell, so to speak, but it's offered to God, and we share it with him. So,
again, it becomes a means of, of congested literally, you know, we're still bringing it into
ourselves. And so incense and the Eucharist are the things that are sacrificed, offered in
the Orthodox Church and that we understand as being the, that is what worship.
truly is. There are services where we don't offer those things, like complying, for instance,
or the hours, and we would say, well, those are prayer services. But worship and its true,
true sense is about offering sacrifices for the purpose of communing with God. And we don't
offer the Eucharist to angels. We don't offer incense to saints. We offer those things to God
alone. And so for us it's like, well, you know,
you say, well, you know, you're worshiping saints. You're like, well, no, we didn't offer
them the Eucharist. You know, it becomes really obvious when you when you understand that
that's what worship is. And then you can see this in the scripture. Okay. That's what worship
is in scripture. And the ancient world understands that. And whether you're talking about ancient
Israel or the New Testament or even pagans understood that that's what worship is. It's
sacrifices.
whether it's food sacrifices or incense sacrifice, that's what worship is. And so, you know, sometimes
again, a well-meaning Protestant might say, well, what about some, you know, uneducated orthodox
person who's bowing in front of an icon of a saint? You know, for them, is there any big difference
between worship and veneration? They may not be able to explain the difference to you, right? They
may not have the theological education to say the things that I just said, but they know
that they don't offer the Eucharist to St. George.
You know, they know they don't do that, right?
They know that when they eat and drink that bread and wine, that that's the body and
blood of Jesus Christ, not the body and blood of St. Paul, right, or of an angel.
You know, that's the really the key, key difference.
So let's kind of get deeper into some of that now.
Yeah, that's
That's made it very explicit in the words of the divine liturgy, that when we're offering
the Eucharist, we're offering the Eucharist for the people there, for the whole church,
for the whole world, and for, and after the word for, it runs through a list of the saints,
including the saints commemorated for that day, and that list culminates with, we're
offering it especially for the
Theotokos, the Virgin Mary, Christ's mother, it's offered not to her, but especially for her.
So just as the saints pray for us, we offer our worship for ourselves and for the saints in this unity.
But there's a place where in the ancient world this rubber really met the road.
Yeah, yeah, this was really, this was really interesting to me when we started exploring this
as we prepped for this. So go ahead. Yeah. So in the ancient world, we've talked about the divine
council. The divine council in a pagan context is what we today call a pantheon, right? The
group of the gods and then there's one who presides. Right. And kingship, and this goes all the way
back to Samaria. The Samarian Kings list begins with the kingship coming down out of heaven.
So they viewed the king as a God, right, as a divine figure, and he was a member of that council.
And so as the member of that council, he had a role in representing his people in the council,
Though that was often not taken very seriously.
He had a role in representing that counsel to the people
in terms of him being a God.
That was taken more seriously by pagan kings.
But while those elements are sort of adapted into the kings of Israel, where for example,
King David did pray an inter-administer God's justice on this earth to serve as sort of an
icon or image of God.
In the pagan context, the king also, as a God, received worship.
He was the object of...
worship. Yeah, sacrifices and libations were made and offered to the King as one of the
gods. And so we see that, I mean, sort of an exhibit A, just an example that probably
the vast majority of people listening, this will be familiar with, comes from the third
chapter of the book of Daniel, where Nebuchadnezzar sets up the big statue of himself and commands
that everyone must work.
ship it. Right. Right. And of course the the the three use refuse and end up getting
thrown into the fiery furnace. But this was this was prototypical in the pagan world,
not just in Babylon. As I said, this started in Sumeria. This goes on to the imperial cult
in the Roman Empire before St. Constantine, where starting with Julie.
a Caesar, they believed he ascended into the heavens and joined the Divine Council as one
of the gods. And so he was the object of the offering of incense. Thousands of Christians
were killed by the Roman State for refusing to offer incense to the spirit of Caesar. And
so this was just commonplace. And not but the answer to that when it comes to the Jewish
people and this the rubber beats
the road on this like in Daniel 3 when they're in exile, right? When they're not in their
own land. Because when they're in their own land and they have their own king, it's
kind of clear to both the king and the people, they're not supposed to worship the king
and to the king, he's not supposed to be worship. But now they're living in the land ruled
by another king, a pagan king who does demand their worship.
Yeah. And the answer to that for the faithful Judahites in Babylon is not, no year to have
nothing to do with that no good way.
could pagan king. Right? Stay separate from him. He's, you know, in our modern terms, he's
the anti Christ. Right? Yeah. Get rid of anarchy. Right? You know, opposed to the answer is, no,
you don't pray to him or worship him. You pray for him and you worship for him. Yeah. You
You offer sacrifices for him.
You offer prayers for him.
You offer incense for him to...
the true God, to the one true God, who is his creator.
Yeah, the direction that you offer your worship is really
important. It's not just, okay, you're doing this act of worship,
but to whom is it being offered? You know, there's there's an
offer offerer and a receiver, right? And, you know, there's
multiple places in the scripture where it says to pray for the
King, you know, or pray for
Like for instance, Jeremiah 29.7, seek the peace of the city where I've caused you to live in captivity.
Pray for it to Yahweh for in its peace you will have peace. Support your local community by praying for it.
And of course, we do that. And the people who dwell there and the faith who dwell there and let us praise
of the Lord. Right? It's exactly that sense that we get from that verse I just wrote.
from Jeremiah. Right? Yeah. And, and so that's a key, you know, to, to someone today, it
may seem hazy, right? Even when we talk about the difference between like tonight, intercessions,
seeking intercession and, and worshiping, right? Seeking intercession from the Spirit before
the true God versus worshiping this as a God alongside God, right? But here, what you've
got a king he's standing in front of you threatening to murder you right
That difference becomes very clear.
Yep.
Because there's something that you're called to do and then something you cannot do.
Yeah.
And it's super applicable to us today where we're in the midst of a really tense political
period, particular government official or a particular candidate for office is taken
as a kind of endorsement, right? But the scripture tells us to pray even for...
pagan kings who are actively slaughtering the people of God. Let me put a let
me put a fine point on that. Yeah, it it it first Timothy 2 verses 1 and 2. St.
Paul says therefore I exhort first of all that in treaties be made prayers
intercessions and thanks-givings the word for thanks-givings there is
literally eucharists. Yeah. On behalf of all men on behalf of kings and all those
for an authority so that we may lead a calm
peaceful life in all godliness and sanctity and that's taken over to the
prayers of liturgy. But so St Paul is saying that in the Roman Empire much of
St Paul's ministry was conducted under the reign of Caligula. Yeah who you know
Google him people if you don't know who that guy is. I know he was out of his mind
literally right yes one of the most vile he would be ever live on purpose and
and so
So if St. Paul can pray for him, if St. Paul's approach to him is, well, we need to pray for him
and hope that he will find Christ, right?
And that's what we need to all do.
Then I don't care how much you hate the current president or the previous one, you can pray
for him too, right?
That's right.
Because he's got nothing on Caligula.
I guarantee it.
Yep.
And so then even more than that, so even more than just praying for the authorities, which
which I think most...
Christians can swallow that. I go, okay, yes, I will pray for the authorities, even if I don't like them.
You know, even if they're actively trying to kill me,
the scriptures actually also tell us to honor them, to honor the authorities.
So, for instance, and like in the fourth commandment, right, honor your father and your mother, right?
That's not understood in the scripture as like if you give
honor to your father that that's taking something from God because all honor should go to God,
right? It doesn't it doesn't do that. And then in 1 Peter 2, 17, honor all men, love the
brotherhood, fear God, honor the king. Again, give human beings who are said in authority
over us. And even it says to honor all men, you know, everybody, right? And that's what
we're talking about as Orthodox Christians, we're talking about giving honor. So we honor
the king, we pray for the king.
but we do not give sacrifices to the king.
And the same is true with the angels and the saints.
We honor them.
Now, of course, we don't need to pray for them.
We ask them to pray for us.
But we also definitely do not offer sacrifice to them.
That's a worship that's due God alone.
You don't give sacrifice to anyone but to God.
Yeah.
and more than just honoring our parents.
honoring the civil authorities or honoring the saints or honoring the angelic hosts.
Not only is that does that not conflict with giving all honor and glory to God?
That is how we give honor and glory to God. And the New Testament is very clear on that.
Right? That's why it says, you know, to serve your master or your employer,
right? As you would serve Christ. Because the authority they have over you, they have
you
from Christ. In honor and obey that authority, you are respecting and honoring and obeying Christ.
If you rebel against it, you're rebelling against Christ. If you rebel against your parents,
you're rebelling against Christ. Yep. Right. Yep. And I think one of the problems, of course,
again, is looking at it from a modern point of view. So Orthodox Christians, when we say we
honor the saints, we really know what we know what that means. We bow in front of an economy,
kiss an economy, sing praises to a saint.
These are the
These are the things we do, it's a much more kind of a femoral idea.
Like, oh, I'm honored that you would choose me or I honor the sacrifice you made.
Like it's more about things that you say, more than anything else.
But we still actually do have some of those specific actions of honor.
So like some examples, for instance, when a soldier is very brave in battle and has
done something more notorious, we give him a medal.
That is an action of honor.
That is an...
action of veneration to that man or woman, right?
Again, to continue in the military image,
junior servicemen and women salute their superior officers.
That is to give honor and veneration
to that superior officer because of where that person is
in the hierarchy, right?
And you know, in public events, we stand up for the flag,
we take our hats off, we put our hands over our hearts
And
You know, we may say words of praise for someone that we're honoring.
But likewise, like to take it out of all those kinds of public things,
one of my favorite examples is if you go to a cemetery,
everyone venerates in a cemetery.
You know, you're quiet.
That's a way to show veneration honor.
You might put flowers next to a grave.
That's veneration honoring.
You might light a candle next to grave.
You might say prayers there.
You might even talk to the person who has departed.
Right, these are always...
that we show veneration and honor in various circumstances.
And so when the Orthodox say that we venerate
and honor saints and angels, that's what we mean.
That is what we mean.
And really nothing else, you know,
we're not trying to pull a fast one at anybody, right?
You know, I say, oh, you know, I'm honoring this saint,
but I'm gonna slip in a little worship
when no one's looking.
Like it's just two different actions.
it's not
the same thing. Now often veneration goes alongside worship but worship is a specific action of offering.
It's not it's not any religious looking thing you might do right. So yeah so are we gonna
are we gonna have our break before our third half and then come back with necromancy? Yes yes
it's a great time to take a break and we'll have everybody on the edge of their seats as they think
about necromancy for the third half of the Lord of
Spirit, so we'll be right back.
Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung
will be back in a moment to take your calls
on the second half of the Lord of Spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF radio.
Here is Mother Alexandra of Blessed Memory.
It seemed to me that...
There's modern life of ours, everything has become so frightfully materialistic.
There is a very great need of transfiguration of a change of our attitude, of our way of thinking,
our way of behaving, our way of hurting ourselves.
Everything needs a new Christianization.
It must become more aware of the Christ within us.
published in 1981 and long out of print.
The Holy Angels by Mother Alexandra has yet to be surpassed as a comprehensive and comprehensible
account of the nature of the angels and their role in our salvation.
In lay person's terms, Mother Alexandra presents the essence of everything the church has to
teach us about the angels, beginning with the Old Testament, continuing through the New Testament,
and concluding with the tradition of the church as expressed in her theology,
Hymnography and I can
for those who long to become better acquainted with these holy servants of God and to understand their role in our lives,
this book is a great place to start.
Available now at store.ancientfaith.com
Again, that is store.ancientfaith.com
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits, the Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung.
If you have a question call now.
855-237-2346.
Before we get into our discussion of
mechromancy, first we want to take
one of our calls and that is from
Elijah in Georgia.
Elijah, welcome to the Lord of
Spirits.
Hey, thank you very much.
Father's bless.
God bless you.
You made it through.
I did.
Thank you all so much for
doing this show.
it really beats like sitting around watching
the news or something? Yeah, this is the real news. This is this is what's actually going on.
And so what's your question Elijah? Well, honestly I have tons of questions come to
pride, but the one that I called in last night was in re, yeah, exactly, was regarding something
that was asked of Father Stephen on a previous episode.
Okay.
Somebody asked,
what is...
the relationship between mental illness and spiritual affliction and he just said, oh
probably probably the same as the relationship between physical illness and spiritual affliction.
So I was wondering if maybe you could elaborate on that a little bit.
Well you're on the spot, Father Stevens, so say more. As I recall, we experienced some of our
trademarked technical difficulties in the middle of that answer to boot.
right. Yes, that's when the power went out. So, so everybody make the sign of the cross right now.
So, hopefully, yes. So, the first part of that was I was obviously making an equation between
mental illness and physical illness. These are the same kind of thing and we tend to think about
them differently. We tend to think about
mental illness as if it's something you can think your way out of or talk your way out of or
you know just cheer up. I mean you wouldn't say that if you saw someone with a broken leg
and the bone protruding you wouldn't say, hey cheer up guy, you know, get up and walk it off,
you know, but we say that to people suffering from depression all the time, right? And it's just
is ridiculous. So I wanted to make that equation, but then...
And the other piece, and I think what you're actually wanting to know about is how that
relates to spiritual beings and that kind of thing.
And so we know from the scriptures and from Orthodox tradition that there are times
when we already talked about Job a little bit tonight.
There are times when God allows demonic spirits to afflict human beings in
different ways and sometimes that's mental, sometimes that's spiritual, sometimes that's
physical, like in the case of Job, you know, a building collapsed on his children.
So that God allows these things to happen.
And we get windows.
One of them is Job.
One of them is St. Paul talking about the thorn in his flesh where he was afflicted by the
you for one and that
the purpose that people are able to find in them. And I phrased that a very deliberate
way. Because a lot of times when things like that happen to us, then we suffer or we suffer
some catastrophe or some loss, we ask sort of why in the sense that we're looking for
some kind of answer out in the ether somewhere. Like we want to, and this is a theme in Job.
I mean, Joe really reflects on this in the ancient world, right?
We want to...
We want to go and find God and ask him or if we're feeling really salty
We want you know God to come down here and explain himself right because we're
We're angry that this that this has happened to us
And we want we want him to sort of explain well
Here's the reason why and if you just understood you know the whole cosmos and what's going on you know why
You had to break your leg or why this person you love had to pass away now instead of years from now
And that's not what we see in the screen.
and that's not what we see in our tradition in terms of how you see it.
What can make these things meaningful is how we receive these things.
So Job suffered all of these things.
That's just a reality.
It happened to him.
And he could have reacted the way his friends did and said,
oh, well, I must have done something bad and I deserve this and sort of wallowed in self-pity.
He could have done what his wife said and just gotten angry at God and
rejected God over it and this happens a lot in our modern world. That's why we have a lot of the api
s we have in our modern world, not all of them, but a lot of them. That's not how we chose to receive it.
Right? And that's not how St. Paul chose to receive the thorn in his flesh. The way that they chose to receive it
as this testing from God for the purification of their soul, the purification of their body.
and
And by trusting him that made it meaningful for them, that made it transformative for them.
And the reason why I say that made it meaningful is the days are going to come for every one
of us when we die.
That's reality.
We don't like it.
We don't want to talk about it.
We don't want to think about it, but that's reality.
And when we do, all of our stuff is going to rot and our reputation is going to vanish and
be forgotten.
But all these other things are going to disappear.
and the only thing that's going to be left is ourselves, our soul, and eventually our
resurrected body, and what we made of it.
And so if these temporal catastrophes, even the most horrible and painful of them that
I suffer, if I can receive those in a way that is beneficial to me and helps me grow
and become more like Christ, then that, right, the person who I become through them is
something that's gonna last.
into eternity. And so it's infinitely meaningful, far more meaningful than whatever it is I lost,
whether that was years of friendship or years of love, whether that was possessions,
what my sufferings that only go on for a time to the glory of God that goes on forever.
Does that help you out, Elijah?
Yeah, I believe so. Like I said, I got plenty of questions. I called that. This went on
on behalf of my wife.
and I appreciate it and I know she does too.
Excellent. Well God bless you.
Alright so before we continue on we have another question.
This comes from Lisa on Facebook.
So Lisa asks this,
if we are destined to rule with Christ
I never understood who we are ruling over.
Is it a hierarchy of unison and mutual submission?
That's a great question and I think it goes to this issue
of what exactly it means to rule and to reign, right?
On the one hand, there is a kind of ruling over that happens.
So for instance, the apostles are going to sit on 12 thrones and judge the 12 tribes
of Israel.
So that does happen in that sense.
But if you look at what the angels, for instance, are doing as we've described it, what
do they rule over?
Well, they rule over kind of making things run.
And the word that actually came to mind when I was thinking about this was a word that
is used in
the monastic context. So they have a word that's ecclesiarch. Right. Now that word
ecclesiarch is used in a lot of different ways in Orthodox Church, but in
generally a monastic context, the ecclesiarch. So if you think about that word, it
means the church ruler, if you take it apart, etymologically. But what the
ecclesiarch is generally speaking in the monastic context is the guy who
takes care of the church building. Now he may, he or she, sorry, I said guy, but
it might be unknown as well.
Here's.
She may also be in charge of, for instance, doing things a lot of chancers are using or
making sure all the supplies are where they need to go, but it may also be cleaning and
lighting lamps and all that kind of thing.
That notion of ruling or raining is not just the idea of having control over other people,
but it's really that something is in your care.
Something is in your care.
Now it might be other people but it may all-
also be, if you're an angel, it's been assigned to the stars, then you're taking care of stars.
Right.
So, I don't know, Father Steve, did you have anything you wanted to add to that?
Well, yeah, I think we need to keep in mind what Christ said about rule and authority to
his apostles, right?
He says, you know, the rulers of, and I really dislike the word Gentiles.
It's a trend.
The nations.
Yeah.
or if it's referring to people,
pagans is actually a better translation.
Because it's not talking about an ethnic concept.
That's a more modern thing.
But the rulers of the nations,
the rulers among the pagans,
they lord it over one another.
Yeah.
And so, I know there's attention,
they say, well, you're gonna rule over the world's cover,
you can be really over other people.
Does that mean that I'm gonna have a boss
in the world to come.
Right, but that's not how authority works when it's purified and holy, right?
The authority that Christ tells His apostles that they are supposed to exercise is one of communion in love.
Right, the authority He talks about between a husband and wife is love and self-sacrifice. Right? That's what authority is.
So we have to always keep that understanding of authority and
mind here. Right? That we're not going to be sort of lording it over the animals or the plants or the trees or each other.
Right? The world's a cow. It's service. I mean, when Christ wanted to show his disciples the way they were supposed to treat each other, he washed their feet.
You know? Yeah. Yeah. All right. Well, let's let's continue on and now we're going to talk about
Necromancy. Death magic and we bring that up. We bring that up because
not just because father Stephen and I both have liked role playing games in our pasts and present,
but because that is the way that some people, for instance, look at Orthodox Christian interaction
with the departed saints, that you're trying to summon the dead, that you're communicating with the
dead and you know that's what necromancy means. It means death magic right or...
or attempting especially to maybe, you know,
the traditional understanding of necromancy,
with almost all those words that end with,
with mancy is it's about trying to get knowledge
that you're not supposed to have, right?
Whether it's fortalling the future,
or you know, seeing something that's happening
in a place that you normally couldn't see.
And so in this case, it's using death magic
to make that happen.
So why, why is it not necromancy?
Right and and I've gone I've gone
through phases with this. Right? Interacting with people, people who I care about, people
I like, people who I love. Particularly again, from a Protestant background, who have this
issue. So, you know, in terms of levels, right, there's sort of the snappy answer, right?
There's our snappy orthodox apologetic answer, which is we tell them, we tell someone who
as a problem with this to go read Matthew 2232, Mark 1227.
Luke 2038, right, where Christ talking about the resurrection to the Sadducees says,
you know, God is the God of Abraham and Isaac and of Jacob. He's not the God of the dead, but of the
living. So see, they're not dead, they're alive. And so since they're alive, we can ask them to
pray for us and see, gotcha, right? That's a snappy answer, right? Check them out. They're active,
they're doing something right but
But that snappy answer doesn't really answer the concern because again, these are people
who are sincere and good-hearted and love-christ and want to worship only God and the idea of
this makes them queasy, right?
So pushing a little further, right?
The next step, pushing it a little further is, well, okay, are there examples of something
like this in the Bible. And an ancient Israelite religion.
and the religion of the second temple.
And the answer to that is yes.
We see this already beginning in Genesis,
where Genesis makes the point of telling us
where Abraham and Sarah and Isaac and Rebecca
and Jacob and Joseph and where they're buried,
where their tomes are.
And these are sites that are still known to this day.
Yeah, you can go there.
This wasn't just a matter of curiosity,
because all
already then, these were places where people would take pilgrimages, places where they
would go to pray. Right? The place where, you know, and you say, well, God's everywhere,
why does it matter where Abraham's now completely decomposed body is. Right? But this was a
place. And that has continued to be true in Judaism to this very day. I mentioned to
you last week that there was
news article I saw that a group of Israeli settlers had gone to the tomb of Abraham to
pray for the results of the United States presidential election.
And you know, that may blow some of our views of Judaism, right?
Because you'd say, well, why would they go?
Well, it's because they believe that when they go there and pray, Abraham is praying with
them.
When you read the interpretation of
of the verse that gets quoted by St. Matthew in terms of hered slaughter of the innocence
of weeping for her children.
The interpretation of that that you find all through early Jewish literature in the second
temple period is that that's talking about Rachel's spirit praying for the people as they
went into exile.
Hmm right that this isn't just figurative language that Rachel actually was we
and praying and interceding for her children.
So this was present in the ancient Israel,
it's present in Judaism all the way through
to this present day, this idea.
Amazing.
But I pushed a little deeper than that.
OK, because that's still just giving examples, right?
That's still just got to, well, Jewish people do it.
You know, press right.
Right, right.
Yeah.
And here's some Bible verse.
that point to it. And so I wanted to really get into because I was still hearing this. And even
after I would say these things, I was still hearing this for people. And they weren't people who I
could just dismiss. It's like, well, this guy isn't, you know, the sharpest tool in the drawer.
He just doesn't get it. Right. No, these are intelligent people, right, who are saying it's just,
it's necromancy. It's necromancy. Right. And so I pushed it. What is it? Right. Because it's not
a parent to me.
It wasn't apparent to me why you would even connect those two how those two things were even similar
Right how how what the witch of indoor does with Samuel is similar to
Me asking the theotokos are saying Stephen to pray for me like look like those I did their like how are these the same?
And I think when I really pushed I
Think what's happening is that for a lot of the people who I talked to who have this issue who this makes them
easy.
and disturbed. I think they're thinking of prayer in terms of communion with God.
In terms of experiencing the spiritual communion with God and talking to God
and then God talking to them, right? And so when they hear us use the language
that I don't think we should use of praying to saints, then they hear, oh,
Oh, while you're commuting with...
you're talking to him and he's talking to you and there's right like it's you're using
to eat dead. Right. Right. And that's why I say I don't think we should use that language
because that of course is not what we're doing. Yeah. It's not. And I mean, you could say,
oh, well, look, in 16th and 17th century English, which is the language that we should be
be praying and pray just me.
means ask. We see it in Shakespeare all the time. People praying quote unquote to each
other just means ask. But I mean, that's just sort of begs the point because we don't
use the word pray in 21st century English to mean something other than a religious act.
You know, I mean, I may wake up and say to my child, you know, I pray the fetch another
gallon of milk from the basement. I believe I believe that you do that. By the way,
I do talk to my kids.
That way, what sort of, and the usual dead, you know, but the fact that they would react
that way is they know that I don't normally talk that way and I'm sort of putting something
on when I do that.
And so I think you're right that that that that asking the saints to pray for us is,
you know, that we pray with saints.
We pray alongside saints.
Just as you gave that example of Israeli settlers going to the tomb of Abraham, that they understand
that Abraham praise with them when they
do that. And you know that that and yeah it makes sense to me that for people who
believe that prayer is sort of the great act of communion with God that you
wouldn't want to do that with a seat. But for us you know again we talked about
sacrifice and worship and so forth and what exactly those things really really
mean. Then, you know, neck
Comancy is again it's about control
role, right? So like, I think the people do have some of that times that sense, like,
well, the reason you're talking to a senior, you're trying to find out something secret.
Like, well, the truth is, is that most of the time when I ask, in fact, almost every single
time when I ask a senior to pray for me, I do not get some kind of voice and response
back saying, I will now reveal to you, have asked for, you know, like it doesn't, you know,
we're not the Illuminati sitting around some giant pyramid in the middle of whatever
and putting our hands on it and saying, oh, see, Nicholas, tell us the future. Like,
That's not what's going on.
And the thing about Necromancy is, it's really about control.
Right?
And I think, you know, I mentioned role-playing games.
I think people who have played those, they get this a little bit better than most.
Because what does a Necromancer do in Dungeons & Dragons?
He tries to make skeletons do his bidding.
Or he makes zombies arise and do, you know, like that's what he does.
That's what a Necromancer is.
is someone who's exerting force over...
dead bodies and stuff and trying to make them do things.
But I think another side of this also is I think of our 21st century of version to death
and to dead bodies and so forth.
Sure, we should have an aversion to death, but we've so sanitized it that any kind of
interaction with bodies, we're just not really into that.
And I think that that also is something of an...
influencer in terms of the way that people think about this.
And also, as you were getting into this,
this really brings us full circle to what we were talking about.
He sacrificed his black goats and he pours their blood into a pool so that the shades can
come and drink it, like to lure them up out of Hades so that he can inquire about it.
So this is not just communion in a general sense but this is sacrificial communion.
This is not just the understanding of
of communion that exists there.
But this is our understanding of St. Paul
as to how sacrifice and how the Eucharist work.
So do you wanna read the quote?
Yeah, sure, sure, sure.
So yeah, so in 1 Corinthians chapter 10,
which you just have to love this chapter for so many reasons.
But anyways, 1 Corinthians chapter 10 verses 16 through 21,
The cup of blessing that we bless is it not come
communion in the blood of Christ. The bread that we break, is it not communion in the body of Christ?
Because there is one bread, we who are many are one body because we all commune in the one bread.
Consider Israel according to the flesh are not those who eat the sacrifices,
communicans of the altar. What do I imply then that food offered to idols is anything or that an
idol is anything? No, I imply that what pagan sacrifice, they offer to demons and not to God.
I do not want you to commune with demons.
You cannot drink the cup of the Lord
and the cup of demons.
You cannot commune in the table of the Lord
and the table of demons.
Which I feel like there should be an,
you know, apostolic mic drop at the end.
You have to do that, right?
Boom!
And so we do not, we do not have,
we do not offer the Eucharist.
We do not offer sacrifices, right?
To the saints.
But by offering it the Eucalyptus.
for ourselves and for the saints.
We are in communion with each other
because all of us are in communion with Christ.
Yep. Yep.
All right, well, before we wrap up,
we want to take one more call.
And this is from Sherry in Washington State.
Sherry, welcome to the Lord of Spirits.
Thank you, Father.
What's your question for us this evening, Sherry?
Sorry buddy.
So I was going to ask this question last week and it pertains to what you're all talking about a little while ago about possession of oppression.
So I would like to know your thoughts on, do you feel that a baptized orthodox Christian can be possessed by demons?
Not just a pair, but actually possess.
Possessed, like T.
in control of.
Yeah.
That was brought up very briefly, and again, I think was this one of our other power problems
or something, Father Stephen, where you started talking about this?
Because yeah, this was the question about mental illness as well, about someone being
demon possessed.
And Father, you said, you know, there's a difference between mental illness and being
And so share your asking, can an Orthodox Christian actually be possessed by a demon?
Yeah, so I'm asking that because I actually in my life have seen a manifestation of that
is someone.
So I'm going to have too much detail, but I mean literally a physical manifestation, like
the color of a person's eyes changing, their countenance changing, something very dramatic.
Yeah.
And so I've wondered for years about that issue.
All right.
Well, mental health issues revolve, but something like that, you know, where you actually
We see a
physical manifestation of something, it's like, wow.
Yeah, as I often say, we can't necessarily pinpoint what's
happening in particular instances with particular people, but
Father Stephen will give us a general remark.
Right. Yeah.
Yeah, I can't wait.
Now, that's what now I will say the things you're describing are
kind of archetypal signs of where you consider demonic possession.
So the answer to this is you can't get possessed by a demon accidentally.
Right?
People aren't just walking down the street, mining their own business one day, and they get possessed by a demon.
Right.
People who get possessed, right?
Not afflicted. We talked about affliction a little bit ago.
But people who get actually possessed have invited it.
Now that doesn't sometimes that's very literal, right?
I'm here in Southern...
Louisiana. There's people here who literally invite spirits to possess them and perform
ritual sacrifices to make that happen. But sometimes it's more subtle. Sometimes it's
an invitation that's extended over a long period of time and it's like the frog in the
boiling water where it gets turned up slowly and you end up in a place that you didn't
want to when you set out on that journey. Right, so that never happens accidentally. Now,
can't happen
to an orthodox Christian obviously accidentally. My, my qualm with just saying no
that can happen to a baptized orthodox Christian is unfortunately some of our
folks think that well if I was baptized in an orthodox church I'm an orthodox
Christian even if I've never seen one since right and I'm 50 and yeah it's
being an orthodox Christian is not like being a jet when you're a jet you're a jet
life but West Side Story reference for all of you youngins out there. But you know what can
be baptized at Orthodox Christian and then proceed to live one's life in a way where you are no
longer in Orthodox Christian. And so it is possible too and there are plenty of scriptures that talk
about this in the New Testament that talk about trampling underfoot you know the blood of the
the cup.
and this and so apostasy is something that can happen and if you if you choose to
go back to Egypt you're choosing to go back to Egypt and then you're under the
authority of Egypt's gods again and you're back in slavery that's how St. Paul
talks about it a lot is going back into the slavery from which Christ delivered
you so that that can happen but there's still hope for you right that's not like
Go.
Okay, now you're done, right?
You can return, there is a service
that I think we should do more as priests
in the order that I church for,
you know, the priest's order listening.
There is a service for receiving someone back
into the church who is lapsed.
Yep.
And we don't do it a lot.
We just sort of were happy they came back.
You know, and we should be happy they came back.
But doing that service of reconciling them again
to the church of reformally receiving them back,
I think is a-
powerful service and important because these services that we do in these rituals we do aren't just
symbols or nice things or nice events or milestones in our life but they actually do something.
When that service is done they are brought back into the church and they are brought back out from
under the power of those things back into the kingdom of God and they're set free again.
So yeah that's my answer to your question.
Well, thank you. That's where we're going to enter.
appreciate it. Well, thank you very much for calling Sherry. It's good to hear from you.
And I always like it when we get follow-up questions. Like, could you say more about this?
Yeah, so all right. Thank you very much for that, Sherry. So, all right, well, we want to,
before we close tonight, we're going to give some some final thoughts. But before we do that,
I just want to give everyone the big teaser that I know that so many of our dedicated listeners
have been waiting for. And that is that our episode on Giants.
is going to be happening next.
And cheers, go up all across America and throughout the world.
No, yeah, we're gonna be talking about giants.
We've teased it over and over again,
but we're finally gonna be doing an episode on giants.
But I just want to mention that because it is falling
on American Thanksgiving, we're not gonna be in the studio
that night doing it live.
it's gonna be a-
pre-recorded show. But that doesn't mean that we're not going to be taking any of your questions
and stuff. But you're just going to have to submit them beforehand. You can send them
to us via email at LordofSpiritz at ancientfaith.com or you can also use our SpeakPipe. If you
go onto the live show part of the AncientFaith.com website, you'll find way down at the bottom
because we're the most recent live show that's happening. There is a SpeakPipe link that you
you can click there and you can
and leave us a voice message.
And if we choose that one, then we will include your voice
on that recorded episode that's happening two weeks
from today.
So like I said, we're not gonna be in the studio live doing it,
but we are gonna record that episode.
You're not gonna have to go without.
And it is gonna finally be our Giants episode.
So you're not gonna wanna miss it at all.
So all right, well, I just wanted to give
a few closing thoughts and then Father Steve
and then we'll be done for the evening. We titled this episode, His Ministers Flaming Fire,
which is the end of the clause, first in Psalm 104, 4, and it's also quoted then in Hebrews 1,7.
And we hear this a lot in the Orthodox Church pertaining to angels. He makes his angels' spirits,
his ministers of flaming fire. And this gets translated in various ways. Where does this image come from?
Well...
to dive into what I know is one of Father Stephen's favorite subjects just a
little bit in Ugaritic mythology, which is that's the Bale cycle stuff. We're
going to talk about Bale I know a lot more in the future. The God Yom who is the
God of the oceans and is the the most high God within that mythology. His
messengers appear as flaming fire in the assembly of the gods in that pagan
version of the divine council. And so what happens then is that idea
of angels being associated with fire, that image is used in the scriptures, right? His
ministers flaming fire. But this is not just a poetic image like, oh angels are scary,
and so fire is scary, and so we're going to make them look like fire. Rather, this fire
is understood as being the fire of God's presence, the fire of God's presence, and that
They become kindled by their...
participation in God by his active love for them and
especially important for our purposes this evening his sharing of his
ministry with them his governance of this world
his his
His love for the the creation that he's made and especially for us right and
that
powerful powerful image
of God's presence in his angels.
You know, it says in the scripture,
God is wondrous or wonderful in his saints.
This is one of the ways that we understand that.
The saints, the angels do not function apart from God
as they participate in the rule of this creation,
as they help to steward it, to take care of it,
to intercede for it.
They're not apart from God.
They're participating in God, right?
you know one of the conversations is the
Stephen and I had, and maybe I'm stealing a stunder here a little bit. I don't know.
You know, when a king assigns a dutchy within his kingdom to a duke, that doesn't take away from
the honor of that king. And indeed it extends it. You honor the duke and you, therefore,
honoring the king. And the duke takes care of the lands assigned to him because he's honoring
the king. And he does it in the name of the king, right? And so that's what the angels on the
scenes do there.
participating in God's own care for the creation,
his own ministry.
And so they intercede for us,
and they help to take care of us.
And it's such a beautiful, beautiful image.
When the scripture says over and over again,
they were gonna reign with Christ.
This is what it means that we are actively doing
the things that are necessary to make the kingdom go.
Go right, but it's not gonna be drudgery because
All of the imperfection of this world will have fallen away. All the sin of this world will have fallen away.
So it's not gonna be drudgery. It's gonna be
glorious, beautiful, and
super not boring.
The life the age to come is not
going to be some static
thing. It's going to be active. It's going to be creative. It's going to be the continuation of stories.
If we use JR Tolkien's images, and I mentioned the beginning, it's gonna be the
continue.
of all that is good and even more than now. So, Father Steven, why don't you give us the final word?
Sure. And I do want to say first, I was perfectly willing to do a live program on Thanksgiving. But
Bobby Maddox is going to be in a turkey coma, so he wouldn't have an end. So I'm just going to throw
him under the bus on this one. But in terms of something up what we've been talking about this
this evening.
I think the preposition with is very important.
We've, I mentioned a little bit, switching from praying to to with, right?
The sun and the moon and the stars praying with Adam and Eve for repentance.
The angels making our entrances in the church and, and, worshiping with us.
I think is crucially important.
St. John Chrysostom says that wherever Christ is, there are the saints, there are the angels,
there are all the hosts of heaven, there with him.
And I think especially now, as you know, when I was seeing some news earlier today, things
are getting locked down again, and throughout this year, I think a lot of people have felt
alone.
And I don't think that the way a lot of times we talked about taxonomy, you know, and
trying to find these structures.
And the way we think about God's heavenly administration and the saints and the angels,
where it's like, oh, well, you can't go to God directly, you have to go through these
other people in this.
I think that's especially unhelpful in a time like this because the truth that we're
talking about at its core and at its most
practical level in terms of the saints and the angels praying with us and
they're sitting for us.
Is that if I'm not allowed to leave my house and I'm stuck in my room
and I've got an icon of Christ in a candle and I light it and I pray.
I'm not alone.
I'm surrounded by saints from thousands of years of righteous people who
have loved God as I do and loved Christ as I do have struggled with what I've
struggled with.
Ben through what I've been through gone ahead of
me and are now there praying with me and for me. And the angels are there worshiping with
me and Christ is there with me. And so as Christians were never alone, that's what this is
about realizing that. And not only are we never alone, we're never going to be alone.
This communion and this fellowship and this family that we're in in this brotherhood and
sisterhood that we share with each other, with all those who have gone before us and all
those who will come ahead of us in the future.
something that's going to last forever into the world to come.
And that love and communion in faith is the substance of the rule that we're talking about
and the intercession we're talking about.
And so it's the stuff that sort of makes up what it means when we say we have this glorious
destiny to be sons of God in the world to come.
Amen.
Well, that is our show for tonight.
Thank you to all of you for listening.
listening. If you didn't get a chance to call in during the live broadcast, we
would love to hear from you either via email at Lord of Spirits at ancient
faith.com or you can message us at our Lord of Spirits podcast Facebook page or
leave us a message via SpeakPipe. And we read everything, but we can't
respond to everything. And we do save what you send for possible use in future
episodes. And join us for our live broadcasts on the
second and fourth Thursdays.
of the month at 7 p.m. Eastern 4 p.m. Pacific. And don't forget to like our Lord of
Spirits podcast Facebook page while you're at it and join our Facebook discussion
group. Leave a recommendation and then invite all your friends. And if you
leave a review on Apple podcasts, Facebook or wherever you get your podcasts
and that raises the visibility of the show and gets more people connected. And
And finally, be sure to go to ancientfaith.com.
Slash support.
and help make sure that we and lots of other AFR podcasters stay on the air.
Thank you and God bless you.
You've been listening to the Lord of Spirits with Orthodox Christian priests,
Father Andrew Stephen Damick, and Father Stephen De Young,
a listener-supported presentation of Ancient Faith Radio.
And I be held, and I heard the voice of many angels
round about the throne and the beasts and the elders,
And the number of them was 10,000 times 10,000,
and thousands of thousand...
with a loud voice worthy as the land that was slain to receive power and riches and wisdom
and strength and honor and glory and blessing.
Revelation chapter 5 verses 11 through 12.