He will be a staff for the righteous with which for them to stand and not to fall,
and he will be the light of the nations and the hope of those whose hearts are troubled.
All who dwell on the earth will fall down and worship him,
and they will praise and bless and celebrate with song the Lord of Spirits,
1st denoc, chapter 48, verses 4-5.
The modern world doesn't acknowledge but is nevertheless haunted by spirits, angels, demons, and saints.
In our time.
many year into break free of the prison of a flat secular materialism to see and to know reality
as it truly is. What is this spiritual reality like? How do we engage with it well? How do we permeate
everyday life with spiritual presence? Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew Stephen
Damick and Father Stephen De Young host this live Colin show focused on enchantment in creation.
The union of the scene and unseen as made by God.
and experienced by mankind throughout history.
Welcome to the Lord of Spirits.
Welcome back to the Lord of Spirits podcast.
I'm Father Andrew Stephen Damick in Emmaus, Pennsylvania.
And with me is my co-host, Father Stephen D'Young
in Lafayette, Louisiana.
And normally our shows are live and we take phone calls,
but this episode is pre-recorded.
So just
Despite what you hear from the voice of Steve and the voiceovers in this one, if you try
to call, you won't get anywhere.
That said, we will be incorporating messages and emails that you sent us in anticipation
of this episode.
And wow, there were a lot.
Tonight we're, of course, talking about giants, also known as the Nephilim.
And this may be among the most anticipated episodes of this podcast.
But what is it about giants?
We probably all remember the story of David and Goliath from Sunday School, but after you grow up,
are you just supposed to take that seriously?
And if you read deeper in the Bible, you start to see that Goliath is not the only giant in the Bible.
And what's more, the existence of giants is a practical problem for people in the Bible,
such as in Numbers, Chapter 30, where the Israelites spies who go into the land of
keen and see giants there and they feel like they are grasshoppers by comparison.
so they don't want to go in and fight them.
And if you read the Bible even more deeply,
you discover that the biblical origin of giants
is truly, truly bizarre.
Can modern people believe in giants?
Can modern Christians believe in giants?
Could there still be giants around today?
Buckle up because this is the giants episode.
And parents, please note,
there are some very adult themes in this episode.
and while we won't be graphic, you will want to listen to this one before you
decide whether to share it with your kids. So we're going to start our discussion
with the origin of giants in Genesis chapter six since that's the earliest
reference in the Bible. So here we go. Are you ready Father Stephen? I am prepared
that's right you were born ready. Yeah I can pretty much talk about giants at a
moments now.
And then people get excited when I talk about it.
There it is. There's the catchphrase of a fun time is had by all.
Indeed. All right. Well, so let's start with that most enigmatic passage from Genesis chapter six.
And it starts with the verse one. I'm going to read this one for us.
When man began to multiply in the face of the earth and daughters were born to them,
The sons of God saw that the daughters of
men were attractive, and they took to themselves any they chose. Then the Lord said,
my spirit shall not abide in man forever for he is flesh, his days shall be 120 years.
The Nephilim were on the earth in those days, and also afterward, when the sons of God
came into the daughters of man and they bore children to them. These were the mighty men who were
of old The Men of Renown. And there it is. And many...
conspiracy theories and careers were lost. Right? Indeed. There's a lot of crazy stuff out there about
about these four verses. Yeah, it's trying trying to do actual research on this topic, right? You can't
just go and type Nephilim into Google. Yeah. And get good and helpful and productive things on the first
say 133 pages.
Right.
But yeah, I mean, just think about the problem of just trying to research it.
If you were to type in some common, common, common word into the Google, you wouldn't get
very far because there would just be so much about that thing.
Like if you're just typing sports, you know, right?
Sports, it would just be too much.
You know, if you were to start to say, you know, the Oakland Raiders in this decade, then
you start, you would start to find a little bit more or whatever.
But what's interesting is that this...
topic, even though it is about something that, you know,
we think would be a really obscure, obscure bit of
biblical research. It's actually super interesting to people.
And so there's a lot of crack pot stuff out there. And I
think this maybe more than anything else is a topic where you and
I get, have you read so and so? Have you read so and so? What
about so and so? Have you read so and so? Right. We've had
novel recommendations.
Yes.
pop your theology, you know, weird science. Self-published books, various kinds. Yeah. Yeah.
Yeah. And there's even, I mean, as we were just discussing in the prep time,
you know, this even shows up in some Hollywood films, right? Yeah. We'll get to that, I guess,
a little bit later. But yeah. So we're going to attempt to, you know, make some some clear,
clear depictions of what this is.
based on what's in scripture, based on research into the ancient world,
based on what's in some of the books that are sort of near scripture,
like Enoch and that kind of stuff.
So, all right, so we start out with those four verses from Genesis
and a kind of, you know, I don't know, obvious reading of them
is suggesting that there are these people called the sons of God
Cool.
are having relations with human women
and that's why there are these giants.
I mean, that's what it says.
Nephilim is just the word for giants, right?
And they're these mighty men of all, the heroes, right?
So what do we do with that?
Yeah.
Well, we have to start with the word Nephilim.
Okay.
Just as a brief note,
there are some people who try really hard.
to get this to not mean giants.
Oh, right.
So, and they're trying to do some chicaneery with Hebrew
because there's a Hebrew root,
na fall, that means to fall.
Okay. So you can say,
oh, well, so they're going to try and get it to mean
the fallen ones,
which has certain residences.
You think, oh, well, that sounds good.
Yeah.
Exce-
that based on the form of the Hebrew word it would be passive. So it would mean the fallen upon.
Right. So there's some people who aren't deterred by that and so they try to argue well as we're
gonna see later in Joshua the giant clans are gonna be attacked in battles they say oh it means
fallen upon in battle. Right. Yeah. Except there's no battle in Genesis 6 and the much the much easier
way to go about this is
With Hebrew, the Hebrew scriptures are the only documents in biblical Hebrew that we have,
really.
Okay.
Right.
Almost everything else, even if you're talking about like second-templed Jewish literature and
that kind of thing, most of it's in Aramaic or Greek or later form of Hebrew.
We don't have any other samples of Hebrew as old as the Torah other than the Torah.
For example.
So what we have to do a lot in reading the Hebrew of the Bible is you have to look at
what are called cognate languages, other Semitic languages, languages that are like cousins to
to Hebrew. So it would be like if you didn't know what a Spanish word meant,
but you found an Italian word and a French word that were similar, right? It had the same
derivation from Latin. You could say, oh, well, this
Spanish word probably means something like this.
Yeah.
Right.
And you do the same thing with Hebrew.
There were words.
There's a lot of weird readings in the Old Testament of the King James version, especially
the original King James version.
Yes.
The real King James.
And that's because there are literally dozens and dozens and dozens of words that only occur
once in the Hebrew Bible.
Yeah.
There's no
The odd text clue is to what it means they literally didn't know.
And we've only discovered what they mean through like the discovery of the eukaryotic
language in the middle of the 20th century.
Yeah, and that's another Semitic language, right?
Right.
Yeah.
And so in this case, the place where we go to understand what Nephilim means is the word
Nephilim, it ends with an n instead of an m in Aramaic, which means giants.
Right.
It's very simple.
And of course it's telling that when ancient Judeans, you know, and we're translating the
Old Testament into Greek, the word that they chose to translate this word was Yigantis,
which is literally the origin of the English word giant.
Yeah, it's derived from it.
Right.
They translated this giant.
Yeah, exactly.
As a note, and we'll come back to this in the third half of the show, I think, when
And they translated this passage, a rigid-
what we call what what is properly called the Septuagint right 70
scribes in Alexandria around 250 BC when they translated this passage they translated the sons of God as the angels of God
Yeah, and they translated Nephilim as giants. Yeah, so those
third century BC Jews
Judeans that's probably another conversation for another
or another podcast.
They, uh, they
They understood the Hebrew scriptures that they were reading as talking about angels and
as talking about giants, because those are the words that they used to translate.
And you know, Greek of that period is not anywhere near as mysterious as the Hebrew of
Gentiles, the biblical Hebrew.
I mean, there's like you said, you know, reading biblical Hebrew, it's the Bible is the only
the only texts we have in that...
that period of that language, whereas with Greek, there's lots of texts, but you know, from
purtiles and piles from pretty early on. And that's why, for instance, you know, New Testament
scholarship, at least linguistically speaking, is a lot easier because there's just so much more
kind of context available. You can say, well, it may not be clear here in the Bible as to what this
means. But look at the way that pretty much everyone else in this period used this word, right?
So it's interesting.
It's great that you bring up the Septuagint translators because it shows that this was their understanding of this passage.
It's talking about angels and that the product of these unions is giants.
Right. So you have angels and human women
cohabiting and in some way. Right. Yeah. Which we'll talk about that.
Ed, right, Ed, and then they produce these progeny who are giants.
So that's what it's said.
Right, right now we have to get into what what in the world that means
Which is a second question, right?
What's we determine what it says that it's what does it mean?
Yep, and
in terms of what it means we actually have a lot of context
Not in terms of grammar and vocabulary, but in terms of other stories from the ancient world parallel stories
Uh
Most people I think know that the flood story in Genesis 6 through 9 is not sort of a unique story.
Right.
That's pretty much.
Almost every ancient culture has a flood story.
Right. It has some story of a previous advanced civilization that was destroyed in a flood and there were
some small group of survivors who were brought through it. So that's fairly well known.
that I mean everywhere in the world you find that and that
But the flood story in Genesis is not even the oldest version that we still have of the
story, right?
The epic of Gilgamesh is from a good, minimally, 500 years earlier, maybe a thousand years
earlier in terms of just the copies we have.
So people are aware of that.
less aware of the fact that there are other parts of this historical
story that are also just about universal, right?
That you also find parallel to all of these ancient cultures.
Yeah, and I think that one of the things
it's really important to note,
you know, like, you know, growing up as a Christian
in Sunday school and you get the story of no on the flood,
I think it can be easy not to think
about what exactly that event means, right?
You know, certainly it's this sort of sense of,
okay, there's a lot of wickedness out there
God is...
wiping it out by sending this flood,
and he saves Noah and his family.
But if you think about it, I mean,
this is, there is, you know,
civilization all over the world,
and it's just ended in one action from God.
And everything is wiped away, right?
And so, you know, we have this word, of course,
anti-deluvian, which means before the flood.
And then later there's this,
and we're gonna talk about this.
I know.
this fascination with the idea of lost wisdom that didn't survive the flood and how do you
get these secrets? There's this massive line in history that's drawn by the flood and there's
everything that happens before it and then everything that happens after it. I mean, now we have
of course the notion of BC and AD before Christ and then Anodomani the year of the Lord
with the advent of Christ.
And that is sort of for Christians
is the massive demon.
marketing line in history, but before this, the flood is kind of it and it's worldwide.
You know, that there was this whole flourishing, or you know, from their point of view, human
civilization, from God's point of view, was not flourishing in the right way, right?
And then it's gone.
It's all gone, right?
So I think we have to take a second and just sort of realize sort of how cataclysmic this
is it is
like the end of the world, but not quite. You know, the world is ended, but almost almost
ended, but not quite. You know, group of people is saved. So I just kind of want to emphasize
that because like I said, it's it's a cool story and everyone loves putting Noah's Ark on
their kids' walls in their bedrooms. But if you think about it, like that is that is a huge
So that's kind of what we're all cut up in that.
with this discussion of giants.
So yeah, so you said there was another aspect
that's also universal in ancient culture's stories.
Well, also another product of that is that
when ancient readers read the Torah
and read the story of Noah and the flood,
they weren't like receiving new information.
Like, oh really, there was this ancient civilization
and it was wiped out by a flood, right?
This is something they already knew about.
and the
biblical story is speaking into that.
So to give a modern example, right,
if I write a book about the American Civil War,
right, most of the people who see that book
and pick it up are not going to think,
what?
America had a Civil War in the 19th century, right?
Like they're not, that's not new information to them,
right?
Right.
But I'm going to be writing it to say,
well, I have some information about the Civil War
that you may not have yet, or I need to correct
This is a miss-
conceptions you have about the Civil War. And so that's why I'm writing this, not just
to give you new information you don't already have. So the story in Genesis, including the
flood and the other stories we're about to talk about, are not there. And that's why
these, like the mention here of the Nephilim, is so brief and sort of in passing. You
say, well, why does it, why does it Genesis go into the detail that you and I are about
to go into.
Well, because J. Assistant had to.
Right.
It's commenting on things they already know,
things that they already conceive of as part of their history.
It's commenting on them, not laying them all out and explaining them.
Yeah.
But so another aspect of this has to do with that advanced civilization.
Right.
And to DeLuvian advanced civilization.
and that part that it's an advanced
civilization is another part of the story that's sort of ubiquitous. It's everywhere.
And so the Babylonian form of this is what's called the story of the Seven Sages, a lot
of times in English translation. The word that's translated Sages there is the Babylonian
word, up-caloo. And these up-caloo are sort of divine beings. The first one is sort of
half fish half
man. And the way you see a lot of divine beings in the ancient world being conceived of as
sort of composites of human and animal forms, yeah, really, especially like the Egyptian deities
are almost always depicted as human bodies with some kind of animal head, although of course the
sphinx is the notable opposite, right? But it's yeah, it's usually human bodies with animal heads.
And that was universal.
That was true.
also in, for example, when you look at the earliest phase of Greek religion, and later they were
changed into sort of human forms and pattern after the image of Greek kings who wanted, you know,
make a statue of Zeus that looks like me, right? Because I'm a lot like him, right? But before that,
so, and you see little bits of that creeping out like in Homer, for example, where he talks about
Cow-eyed Hera.
Yeah.
having eyes like a cow was usually not conceived of as a compliment.
When trying to use that as a these take up line.
Did he have the same old guys who might be listening?
Yeah.
You have eyes like a cow.
Right.
No, that's not.
Do it.
But that's do I do.
I do.
Is DOE.
Yeah.
That would that that's that's that's the nice moderning this way.
Although I think most people probably wouldn't even know that phrase.
That's a little arcade.
But but that goes back to a period when Hera is sort of a fertility.
God is was depicted.
as a heifer, was depicted as sort of this California.
And the scriptures have that too.
You look at the descriptions of cherubim and seraphim
and angelic beings that a lot of times you've got these composites of human and animal parts.
Yeah, right.
Which we talked about that in our episode on ranks of angels.
The seraphim are kind of serpentine.
the chair of him are like lions, I guess.
little bit sphinxy. Yeah, but you have the foreheads and that kind of the
hawks and the eagle and the right. But so the first of the seven sages is
described in that way he comes up out of the river meaning the Euphrates.
Because we're talking about Babylonian story. But then what you find is these
seven sages become advisors to the Babylonian kings and Sumerian kings
before the flood.
And this is laid out, for example, the Sumerian Kings list.
You have each of these kings listed before the flood and the upkalu who was sort of their
advisor and what he taught them.
Yeah.
And taught them the mysteries of astrology or magic or some kind of technology involving
metallurgy that kind of.
And this kind of, this pattern continues, right?
Long, long, long, long at...
for the flood. So for instance, you've got in Roman imperial religion, the genius of the emperor,
right? And of course, genius is this wonderfully, is word, this wonderfully cognate with
Jeanne, or you know, Socrates talking about the Damon that speaks to him and gives him wisdom.
This idea of a spirit that accompanies someone and gives them knowledge, right? Like this,
this, this, you know, or even like even in late
Later Western European folklore, you get witches who have a familiar spirit, which often interestingly is depicted as kind of like a small animal.
You know, that teaches them things and gives them knowledge that they otherwise wouldn't have.
So this is the earliest depiction of that kind of thing that we're aware of, right?
Yeah, it's the earliest the earliest one we have but there's there's obvious parallels right in Greece the story
Prometheus who comes, it gives fire to man.
Right.
And Pandora and her jar was a jar, not a box.
I just ruined every one.
Oh, man.
I don't think so.
I thought it was an online music service, which I, you know, when Pandora first, with
that service first came, came out online.
I was like, well, that's an interesting thing to name your music service.
What are they?
Well the last thing that comes out is hope.
So, right. But of course her name, her name means all gifts. Right. So, it's, you know,
from the point of view of, and it's funny because it's depicted ironically in Greek myth.
Right. So, it's all gifts. But what is most of what comes out?
Disease and war and all this kind of horrible stuff. And then hope remains at the very end.
So even in Greek myth, you've got this irony of, you know, here's this great
from the gods, but ha ha we got you, right?
Right.
So which that's interesting because it's, it's begins this kind of critique of the gods,
which, you know, gradually flowers more and more as time goes by.
They're not just depicted as being benevolent spirits, giving all these wonderful things to man like fire, you know.
Right. Well, yeah, there's sort of an ambivalence about it because the figures who do this,
that includes the upcolour so the upcolour
the other gods get mad at them for revealing this stuff to humans and imprison them in the abyss,
which is in the depths of the waters at the bottom of the rivers in Babylonian thought.
And Prometheus, of course, gets his liver pecked out by a vulture or the rest of eternity.
And these kind of things, right? So the other gods punish them. So it's looked at as the other gods
look at it is bad yeah right look at it is bad but
Humans looked at it as good, right? And so what you find is
later generations of kings
claiming that they're the ones who have maintained this secret divine knowledge from before the flood.
Right. As part of their claim to supremacy, probably the most well-known group to do that were the
the Mardu who are the Amerites in the Old Testament.
The most famous one of them is probably Hammer.
Robbie. The Babylonian king around 2500 BC was one of the martyred. The code guy. Yeah, right. Yeah.
A lot of people probably heard of homo robberies code as being kind of, you know, an example,
the earliest example of written law, but he's also claiming to have anti-deluvian knowledge
by means of spirits talking to him.
Right. And so we see this same.
thing, the same story in the genealogy of Cain in particular in Genesis 4, the end of Genesis 4,
where Cain goes and the first part of this is often mistranslated where they have him
naming the first city after his son, Enoch. It's not that. He names the city after Enoch's son,
that's the city of Eradou which ancient people, the cement-
that ancient people thought was the first city ever.
And so, Cain goes and found the first city.
We see his later descendants invent metallurgy and music
and all these cultural, they've sort of become the culture heroes
of the world of this pre-flood civilization.
Wait, so maybe define that term culture hero
because it actually has a specific meaning?
Yeah, well, after, after um
The flood the figures who are referred to as culture heroes are going to be the flood survivors who have this knowledge. Yeah, okay, right and they sort of become the institutors of culture as it rebuilds after the destruction after the collapse and after the fall.
But so these figures in scripture, right, and are not the good guys.
the mind so this is the mind
men who are of old the men of renown, right? Right. So the Bible is saying, no, these are people
bringing wickedness into the world. And so the demonic powers, we would call demonic powers, the
beings who are giving this knowledge to humanity are not doing it to help humanity or aid humanity.
they're doing it to further mankind's destruction.
Yeah, right. I'm going to give you the ability to forge weapons of war so that you could be more efficient at killing each other. Yeah, it's like it's like giving a knife to a baby.
You know, right. Like here's the fork. Go put it in the plug socket. Yeah, right.
So yeah, so it's it's giving this giving this knowledge. That should be familiar from a chapter previous from Genesis three where what does the serpent? What does the devil do?
he says.
becomes to bring knowledge. Yeah, you eat this, you're going to become like God, you're going to know
good and evil. Right. So there's this theme then that forbidden knowledge is being offered to
mankind by by spirits who have no business doing that. And of course, this raises this question.
Right. So, you know, Keynes line doesn't just come up with weapons of war. They also come up with,
you know, mute.
music and architecture and you know it'd be it's kind of easy to sort of say well yeah weapons are bad but but what's wrong with music what's wrong with architecture what's wrong with agriculture right
and I think that that's not really agriculture it's it's it's hurting yeah yeah right there's
hurting can't do agriculture because of his curse right okay yeah yeah exactly but but yeah so you know what's what's
It's sort of wrong with those things.
And my sense is, and correct me.
wrong, but my sense is there's nothing sort of inherently wrong with them. It's just that mankind
wasn't ready for them yet. Right? Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Just like a man kind wasn't in a position to
use it responsibly. Yeah. Like my three-year-old should not be handed a knife. But my 13-year-old is
pretty responsible with it. You know, she cooks dinner. So I could use it to do good. Yeah, right.
I could use it to do good things. Yeah. Yeah. And this is, this is the same thing with the tree of
of knowledge of good and
It wasn't evil in and of itself.
It's just there would have been a time when God allowed man to eat from it, but that time wasn't yet.
And so jump the gun.
Good have
brought about his his destruction.
But so notice how the pagan versions of the story have recast this.
Yeah, right?
Who's the bad guy in the pagan versions? All of them of the story.
Yeah, it's always the other gods who punished
Prometheus
or the upkalu, right? They're the bad guy. They're the ones who don't want humans to have this knowledge, right?
And the good guys are these spirits who want to reveal the knowledge.
Yep. Yep, right. So that's why we may have said it out of the show already that some of these pagan myths,
if you understand the biblical version of the story, you can see how they're kind of pro-Devil propaganda, right?
Yes, picked him as benevolent.
Right, right, right exactly.
But it's unjustly persecuted.
Yeah, and it's interesting.
I mean, even the thing is, it's like so thinking about
Prometheus, which is probably the story that's most familiar
to our listeners.
You know, he does, he's sneaky about it.
So he has to defy the divine order in order
to bring fire to man.
And so that's interesting.
because even though...
Like so like you know as especially like as Americans we kind of love the underdog we love the whistleblower
Like right, you know, we love that kind of story like the guy rebel. Yeah, the rebel right but but you know
In the ancient world rebellion is is is super bad because the order that exists is a divine order
Right, so it's interesting that even in the story
There's still this this element of truth that Prometheus is engaging in an act of rebellion
And of course, you know, from the
context of our previous episodes where we talk about that there is this angelic rebellion that occurs.
You know, you read these stories from a biblical point of view and you can say, oh yes, well the
other gods who punish these knowledge-giving gods are actually the Lord of hosts and his angels,
you know, like the Archangel Michael, who, you know, drive out these evil spirits from the presence
of the Lord.
and send them to the abyss, you know, that this is,
this is, this is situated within this ongoing spiritual war,
you know, that these, one of the ways that these spirits rebelled,
and we talked about this in the five falls,
five ischalant of angels, one of the ways
that these spirits fall in rebel is by giving forbidden knowledge
to mankind specifically for the purpose of man destroying himself,
know and it's interesting you know
I mean, man, I think humanity understands this on some level, but we were just so tempted.
We're just so addicted to sort of knowing stuff that like, for instance, when nuclear
weapons were invented, I'm not saying that they were revealed by an opcalo, but who knows.
But there's this concern and it's a valid concern, which is like, if mankind knows how to do this,
are we going to just wipe out everything on the planet?
and that's been a question that's been being asked.
several decades and you know not entirely an unreasonable outcome you know.
Up in Heimer did quote the Bhagavad Gita. Yeah I have become deaf but it's a
rare of words. So but so we find sort of a more full version of these
traditions written down in in sort of later literature like
the book of Enoch, the book of giants at Comron, some of this other inocic and apocalyptic literature.
The reason we find it written down that late is you write things down when you're worried about losing them.
Right, so at the time the Torah is composed, this is sort of stuff that everybody knew.
Yeah, so I can just sort of sketch it out.
Right, so by the time you get to the late Persian Empire,
All right.
Some of this stuff is less secure, right?
And so that's when the sort of fuller forms of this tradition
get put down in writing to make sure they get preserved.
Yeah.
The, the, the ancient world, something being written down turned
it into a kind of monument.
Yeah, right.
And this is the subtext behind, does it always strike us
when we read the Bible?
But it is written.
Yeah.
That's why that carries so much weight.
Right.
The people didn't
have bibles in a concept of canon yet, right? But it is written. This was written down.
That means it's important. Yeah. Yeah. Right. This is like a monument left for us by our fathers.
So when we find the more full version of this written down, that's made more explicit,
you know, what these secrets were. Right? That includes things from sort of
of means of seduction to...
things evolving, witchcraft, and sorcery, and divination, different ritual things.
In addition to your sort of technological metallurgy and those kind of things.
So you can see how these are all things that are going to help lead humans into deeper
and deeper into sin.
Yeah, and how, so how like we would draw a sharp distinction between a manual of metallurgy
in a manual of push and making, right? But what ancient...
people draw that distinction? Right, no, because they don't have the materialistic
view of the world that we do. Right. So metallurgy is just a spiritual
unactivity as making a love potion. Right. It's knowledge about how the
cosmos works. Yeah. It's that's such a hard thing, I think for us, like, I'm
I believe that, right?
Like that, that these things are all in
inherently spiritual acts and so forth.
But it's really hard to just wrap your mind around it,
even if you consciously believe it.
You know, I still, I think, you know,
a manual in metallurgy to me is possibly
one of the most dull things that could exist.
I mean, I have friends who are in material science
who are like, why are you saying that?
But, you know, like to me, it's a dull technical kind of thing.
And even though I mentally can say to myself,
no, no, no, this is about elemental forces of the universe,
You know, uh...
still that looks different from a book of spells and yet for ancient people they're the same thing.
They're basically... And of course if you understand this idea of this spiritual origin of technological knowledge,
then it starts to make a lot more sense. And of course you're going to call upon Hephaestus or Vulcan or whoever your
your metallurgy God is to assist you in this work because he's probably the
one who gave you that knowledge to begin with, right?
Right, right. And so in the ancient world, there's no
difference between like chemistry and alchemy, or astronomy
and astrology. Right. Right. Right. These are like separate
things the way we've. Yeah. I heard I've one sort of said,
astronomy is just the bookkeeping of astrology. Yeah, basically,
Yeah, yeah, because we've kind of
it off this stuff and decided it's superstition. But so that sort of culminates in something,
right? All of this forbidden knowledge, all of this ritual knowledge, this knowledge of wickedness,
culminates in sort of the two great paradigmatic sins of the Israelite and Jewish and Christian
traditions are idolatry and sexual immorality. So if you smash those two things together,
there's your sort of apex of human sin.
Yeah.
And so that culmination takes the form
of sexual immorality in the context
of idolatrous pagan ritual.
Yeah.
And so in the same way that in a literary sense,
Genesis 6, 1 through 4 that we're talking about
are sort of the culmination of the material in Genesis 4
and 5 in those genealogies.
This is sort of-
the culmination point of that human sinfulness before the flood leads to what's being described
by the generation of the Nephela.
Yeah, and that's a really important point because we just read those verses out of context,
but there's a reason that they appear at that point in Genesis where they do, and it has
a lot to do with what came before it.
As you said, it's this culmination point.
It's not, it's funny because I've heard...
people treat these verses like, oh, there's this weird little detour, you know, about giants.
And okay, now back to the main story. You know, right. Yeah. But that's not who wants to read,
who wants to read genealogies? Right. Come on. We're going to get back to the later. But yes,
nobody reads genealogies. Yeah. Hobbits love you. See, this is just proof for so. And Mormon.
Yeah. And Mormon. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. This is just proof for the one guy who wrote to us in our group,
saying that
Lord of Spirits and Amman's Sula are really the same one podcast.
Yeah.
So I'm going to just throw him a bone every so often.
And we managed to get through the whole thing about the pre-flood civilization without mentioning
Numenor.
Yeah.
Right.
You had to do it.
Yeah.
There we go.
The Akala.
But so we talked about this a little in the five-ish Falls episode.
the idea that what's being described here is
is sort of ritual that actually took place.
We talked about Augs Bed, which now has its own meme as a life verse in our Lord of
Spirit's group on Facebook.
But that we, the Augs Bed, Aug is one of the giant kings and we're going to talk more about
him in a little bit.
But his bed is described in sort of this random verse and deuteronomy.
Why do we care about his-
bed and how big it is. But the reason for that, we now know archaeologically as we found
a bed of exactly those dimensions and of the same metallic construction in the Ziggurat
of Enemonanke, which is the great Ziggurat of Babylon, that was used for ritual purposes
for the sexual ritual.
Yeah, so let's talk about the dimensions, right? If I recall correctly, it would be a bed
for someone that's about 15 feet tall, right?
Right. Yeah. And end.
you know, as we talked about this in previous episodes, yeah, so funny,
and early episodes, a lot of our commentary was like, okay, we're going to get to that in a future
episode. And now we're kind of saying, well, in last time on Lord of Spirits, you know,
and show the clips. Yeah, well, right, because there were a lot of people that kind of wanted us
to talk about the subjects right off because they're just really excited about it. But it really
kind of does need a lot of this prior background. So if listener, if you haven't listened to our previous
This episode is...
I'm not going to tell you that you must pause right here and go back and listen to all that stuff, but it will make more sense. So why is this bed?
15 feet tall?
Well, that particular measurement is the way that
ancient peoples said they saw
spiritual beings appearing to them
That when a god shows up that they're about 15 feet tall
Yeah, we're gonna stop it. I'm gonna flip
it. We'll talk more about bodies and if you divine bodies in a future. But yes, one of the bodies
that a god had in the ancient world was what's now called his liturgical body and that's 15 feet tall.
Right. Pretty much uniformly across all over the world. All over the world. So, but what if you're
talking about what a video camera would see, right? If you had a tartis and you went back and took a
video camera.
right into Edamonankee, it stuck in and and videoed what was happening on the bed right on the bed.
Is that as part of the festival cycle of these cultures, the king as the high priest of the religion
would
Embought ritually embody the God who they were worshiping and how so how does that happen? I mean do they say prayers over him?
I mean, what do they do?
Yeah.
How do you get...
sacrifices, probably blood drinking and anointing, likely the wearing of a mask, and then would
go in and ritually have intercourse with a temple slave or a temple prostitute on this bed.
that would be part of bringing about fertility for the crops.
and fields consummating the relationship between the God,
they were worshipping and the people,
the demonic spirit, they were worshipping and the people.
And so if a child was conceived to said king out
of this ritual, that child would essentially
have two fathers, the king who was regarded as divine.
himself, the God, and then one human mother, the temple slave who actually gave birth to him.
Yeah. And and doesn't just put a sort of weird Paul now on that that sitcom was that in the 90s called my two
dads, which probably was not about there's a very dark, very
inversion of that shell.
But it will look comically.
And so what you find in the Babylonian sources in particular is, for example, on that same
Sumerian Kings list we mentioned that lists the Epochalo for each king before the flood.
After the flood, each of the kings is two thirds of the Epochalo, one third human.
And you say, well, how could you be two thirds one third?
Well, if you have three parents.
Right.
Then you...
can. And Gilgamesh in the epoch of Gilgamesh is two thirds divine one third human. And sometimes
in some cultures by the way, just you know, this this was reversed where it would actually be
the temple prostitute or slave or priestess who would embody a goddess and the king would.
Right. In which case you would have sort of two mothers and one father.
So you get that with Gilgamesh being an example of that and
So yeah that that happened to it, but this is this is the kind of ritual activity
So this is idolatry sexual immorality in the extreme and so it's sort of saying this is how bad
How bad it got right right before the before the flood and right and then this is the ritual that
produces
Giants.
Right. Right. And, and, you know, I think it's important to emphasize this because the, the, the passage from Genesis 6 doesn't give any of this kind of detail. It just sort of has this idea of angelic beings and human women and, you know, and so then a lot of times people read that without the historical context and they say, well, how can a demon hybridize with a human being? Right. Like they can't.
like they can't.
You know, they can't mate, right?
But that is a misunderstanding of the way
that the Nephilim ritual works.
And I know we're gonna talk a little bit more about that,
but I think it's just important to underline that
what the whole thing with Ogg and his bed
who is just one example of this ritual activity
that's happening all over the world.
What that is is actually there are two human
beings involved and one divine being, although ancient peoples would have said that one of those human
beings was effectively being divine during the activity, which is the... Well the king was divine
all the time. Yeah, right, right. But doubly so when he's yeah, embodied in... Yeah. The reason that
Genesis doesn't have to go into detail on this, right, is because the original readers knew about this,
Right Abraham lived his
Well, most of his life because he was quite old when he left in Ur, where there was a ziggurat
Right that had just been rebuilt to enormous size during his lifetime
The great ziggurat of Ur was built
Literally while he was there and alive where these kind of rituals were taking place continuously
Yeah
And he had members of his own family
where told in Scripture and it's reiterated at the beginning of Joshua.
who were involved in that idolatrous worship.
So this isn't something Abraham didn't know about.
This isn't something that people do.
They know about their versions of this.
Going out right, the Pharaoh's divine in Egypt,
he's married usually to his sister.
So the same kind of thing is good.
So they're aware of this?
So which ancient texts are describing this ritual?
Like where are we getting this from exactly?
It's not in the Bible.
explicitly. Where is this being described?
Well, it's, I mean, it's, it's all over the, but you have to read a bunch of
Egyptian ritual texts and euceritic ritual texts from Canaan and Sumerian ritual texts.
But as I mentioned to you, and then you repeated it a bunch of people doubted you.
Um, but uh, until they...
looked into it, but this basically this ritual still goes on in Japan with the Japanese emperor.
Right.
At his accession.
Yeah.
Every time, even to the present day, though, though, since World War II, it has been largely
desexualized, largely.
Right.
And that's especially interesting because that is not an Indo-European culture over
there. So and I make that point because one could say, okay, well, this particular ritual
idea existed in this one culture and then it just spread as that culture, you know, spread
itself across, you know, Europe and Asia and so forth. But the thing is that we find this,
this ritual activity happening all over the world. And as we have seen still happening
in place.
is where Christianity never really took hold.
And so,
and let's say Mesoamerica,
the Aztecs, the Toltek,
right again, not connected, right?
So, you know, that kind of,
is a big problem for the hypothesis
that just sort of spread with human culture.
Though, if you believe in the things
that we've been talking about all this time,
then it's actually much more reasonable to conclude
that the reason
why this ritual exists all over the world
is because demonic beings came to human beings
and taught them how to do it.
Just like they were teaching them all this other stuff.
So before we go to break,
then let's raise the question of why would a demon
want to do this?
What is the point?
What is the goal of this?
Other than just being perverse in general.
Yeah, right, exactly.
Yeah.
Which I mean, that's kind of a goal that they have.
Right. Why would they want to do that?
What's what we have set up for us in scripture. We have to go back again to the beginning of Genesis.
God creates man in his own image. Right. And we tend to think of that or discussions of it at least modern American Christian discussions of it at least tend to focus on the idea that the image of God is some quality that humans possess.
Right, like it's their intellect.
or language or this or that.
What separates a human from an animal, all of this kind of thing.
But the concept in Scripture is more of a verbal idea.
You image someone something.
image God, right? So Adam and Eve are
to fill the earth and subdue it, right, to go and fill the earth with life and put it in order.
And that's exactly what God did in creation leading up to his creation of them
and the giving of that commandment.
So they're created to go and do what God does.
Yeah, sub-creation.
Right, basically.
To go bring a talk to him again.
To bring the works of God and the will of God into creation, right,
as his image, as his icon.
to serve in that way. And so this goes all the way through the scriptures. I mean, when David is
king of Israel, his duty as king is to bring about God's justice in his rule. And so that's the idea.
And doing that is transformative to humanity.
Right.
Being that agent of God,
Transform
humanity. This is why the fathers taught even though in the Hebrew the words
were image and likeness are basically synonyms. But the fathers use those words to
describe how image is this capacity to do this and likeness is the fruit of
doing it. We become more like God by being the means by which God acts in the
by participating in his will and in his works.
actions in the world we become like him. Right. Right. And this is, this is of course the stuff of
fiosus that we talked about in terms of becoming sons of God. Exactly. Because this is what it means to
be a son, biblically. The son is the image of the father. Yep. Yep. Right. Adam had a son in his
own image, right? After his own like a chip off the old block, as it were. Right. And so
So we see that the devil, as the fathers tell us, falls through envy.
The reason the devil wants to destroy Adam and Eve is because he's jealous.
Because he was not created for that destiny.
The eternal son of God was not going to become an angel.
I think he was going to become incarnate to become man, to give man this destiny.
And out of jealousy he decides to destroy humanity.
And so these demonic powers we see.
following in his footsteps to try to destroy man by revealing these secrets.
Ultimately in this culmination they're trying to create their own image.
They're trying to create human beings after their image and likeness who will
bring their will and desires into the world and who will become like them.
And they can't create from the dust of the earth the way God did.
All they can do is take the human beings who God has created.
and corrupt them and twist them and lure them into, through evil, becoming like themselves.
So it's sort of an anti-theosis where these people become like demons.
And so the giants, to be a giant, is to be one of these sort of fully demonized people.
It's like the opposite of a saint. It's the opposite of someone who's achieved theosis,
this would become like Christ.
It's someone who's become like a
with all of their lusts and fury and violence and destructive capacity and
spite. Wow. Okay. Well, we are gonna go to break and when we come back, we're
gonna answer a couple of your questions. So we'll be right back. Father Andrew
Stephen Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung will be back in a moment to take your
calls on the next part of the Lord of spirits. Give them a call at 8552.
3-7-2346. That's 855 AF radio.
We're so glad you're listening to Ancient Faith Radio.
I'm a listener and an educator, and I'm grateful for the variety of resources that Ancient
Faith offers to those of us who are working to help young orthodox Christians grow in
their faith.
And faith ministries recently learned that the Renaissance Fund will match
dollar for dollar any contributions made between November 24 and December 2.
Please consider how much you can give to help ensure that ancient faith will continue to
offer new resources to the youngest members of our parishes.
Remember that any donation we make to ancient faith between November 24 and December 2 will
be matched dollar for dollar up to the $50,000 goal.
Visit ancientface.com today and click the support tab in the upper right hand corner
to...
make your donation.
On behalf of Orthodox Christian teachers
and their students, I thank you in advance
for your donation.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits,
the Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung.
If you have a question, call now at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF Radio.
And we're back.
Oh, come back.
As I said before, this is a pre-recorded episode of Lord of
Spirits. So even though the voice of Steve just told you to call,
if you call that number right now, you're not going to connect to us. We're
not there. But anyway, we wanted to talk about some of the questions that you
sent that are related to everything we just discussed. And so this first one
is an email from Deborah and Deborah wrote this.
As I was listening to your most recent podcast, when you talked about Augs' ritual bed, and the pagan king coming to commit
fornication with the Temple prostitute and thereby conceiving the next king, I thought about comparing and contrasting this with the conception of Christ.
So she makes several contrasts.
There's a Temple prostitute versus the Temple Virgin.
There's two fathers in the Nephilim ritual versus one father in Christ.
The future king is conceived, that's a parallel on both.
In the Nephilim ritual, the person is two thirds up,
Kalo and one third human.
And then in the incarnation of Christ, he is 100% divine
and 100% human.
She goes on to say, I'm wondering if the way the gospel story is written
would have been immediately recognizable as a sort of subversion, if you will,
of the pagan practices of the day.
And, you know, my immediate reaction to that is I wouldn't-
say that the gospel story is a subversion, but actually it's kind of reveals that the
Nephilim ritual is the subversion. You know, that these demons are engaging in the thing
that they're not kind of authorized to do. And of course they fail, right? They succeed
in making demonized people, but they don't actually succeed in kind of having their own
actual offspring.
in any real sense, like demons cannot reproduce, right?
They're sort of commandeering human beings
in order to make this thing happen.
Any comments on that, Father?
Yeah, I mean, there's a definite, obviously,
as you point out, there's a definite,
like direct contrast there.
And I'll throw in another one, right?
In our salvation and the incarnation,
God saves and transforms us by becoming...
coming like us by taking our humanity, right, upon himself, whereas in all of pagan religion,
and any ancient pagan would agree with this, the goal is by worshipping these beings and
performing these rituals to become like them.
Yep.
Right?
They would have absolutely agreed with that.
And that's the goal.
And Caesar or someone, one of these kings who experiences apotheosis, that's it.
When they die, they go and become like the gods they've been worshipping.
Yeah.
And any...
It kind of underlines, too, like, you know, the giants who we didn't really emphasize
this yet, but I mean, they have what we might describe of as sort of superhuman power
influence, maybe size, depending on how you read it.
They are not, from the biblical point of view, they are not nice, just, good, virtuous
people they
They are domineering destructive conquerors who are able to control lots of people.
And the thing is, outside of the people of God in the ancient world, that was seen as
positive.
You know, if you had control over a lot of people and were able to dominate them, that was
because you were in tight with the gods.
And that was a good thing for you anyway, not for the peasants that you had under your boot.
But it just shows again, like, what a difference Christ who comes.
comes in the humblest of circumstances.
And he comes in peace, he comes in humility.
He does not come with the sword, right?
His weapons are truth and meekness and righteousness, right?
And it just underlines, again, the morality of the ancient world
was so utterly different from ours that if you could control
other people and you had domination over other
people, that was an indication that the gods smiled upon you and were one with you. You
were, you had succeeded. You were it, you know.
Julius Caesar was first celebrated as being godlike because he had killed a million
gals and enslaved a million more. Right. Right. That was his slogan. That's what they
were celebrating. Right. Right. It's, it's, and so by contrast now in the 20th and 21st
century when we
say someone that say someone is like Hitler. We mean exactly the opposite, but if Hitler had lived
in the ancient world, he would have been regarded as a success as a big hero.
Well, he would have been kind of a trifler by ancient states.
Yes, by comparison. A lot more. They killed a lot more people.
Yeah. But the point stands, we look at him as we say, this is a demonic person.
And that's because we've taken on board what the Scriptures say about giants.
as opposed to how the ancient world viewed these giants.
And the word giant itself, both in the Greek and the
the Aramaic, we should say.
And this has been meme too, since apparently I've said it
a couple too many times.
But the word, they don't call someone a giant to tell you
he's a big guy.
They tell you he's a big guy to indicate to you that he's a
giant. And the word giant means
More like tyrant or thug or bully. Yeah, and it's kind of the way we in the modern world
This is the part that got me used the word strong man when we're talking about a dictator, right?
So they'll talk about Panamanian strong man Manuel Noriega. They don't mean he had an awesome bench, right?
It was just ripped
They mean he's a tyrant, right? He's a strong man. He's a bully. He's a thug, right?
That's the kind of administration has that's what the scriptures are saying
about these people, these kings, and these rulers, and these leaders, that they're this
demonically evil type of person.
Yeah.
Okay.
So we also got a recorded message from Adam who had something relevant to ask as well.
So I'm going to play that then for us.
Hello Lord of Spirits.
question is
Do we know of any literature that details how Noah built the arc?
Meaning did Noah build the arc by himself or
Did Noah have help from angels or did Noah have help from giants?
Thanks guys appreciate the show
So so what this is where you said something about that Russell Crowe movie earlier we were talking, right?
So Darren Arnowski's Noah.
Yes. Yeah. Which he adapted from his graphic novel, actually.
Interesting. I have to admit I have not seen it.
Right. I highly recommend it, but not for historical accuracy.
Right. So is Adam onto something here? I mean, you said he thinks you're pretty sure that Adam
watch this movie. Yeah, um, yeah, in the movie, um, the watchers of
of Enic and I'm sure we'll do a future episode just talking about first Enic but the watchers
are the the term that's used to refer to the angelic beings the sinful rebellious angelic beings
they as their punishment get turned into these sort of giant rock guys right I've heard of
I've heard about that and they they kind of repent and decide to help Noah it sort of help him
build the arc and edge.
off the people who are trying to be siege the arc because yeah it's sort of it's
if you take all the Noah traditions from second temple literature and from the
Bible and then you smash that together with Gladiator that's what this movie is
I have to see it now are you not doing wrestling pro including this
presence. But so I think that maybe not, but that maybe a generous question. But there
There are in those traditions, not that the rebellious angels help Noah, but there are
sort of bits and pieces and scraps of Noah traditions in some of those things that yes,
he was assisted by sort of angelic beings.
A lot of that is related to trying to present Noah as this prophet.
He's presented sometimes as an almost supernatural being himself in a lot of these traditions.
So he sort of knows
angels and hangs out with them, right? Because he has this sort of prophetic life and special capacity.
Yeah. And so there are stories where he's interacting and they're helping him build things.
And isn't there this tradition that sort of thing that Noah himself was one of the Nephilim?
There are, yeah, there are bits of that. On both sides, there are some traditions that he was.
and then other traditions.
that seemed very clear to try to indicate that he wasn't,
which means it was something that was being discussed.
Because you wouldn't make a protracted argument
that he wasn't one unless somebody thought he was.
Right.
So, but yeah, there are these stories that sort of
when he was born, he sort of came out glowing and talking
and all these other things to indicate his special status
in Genesis 5 in another one of those genealogies,
nobody reads.
Noah's father, Lamick, actually makes this prophecy.
about him that frames the whole story of the flood.
But so that's been sort of elaborated on that the reason
Lamek makes this prophecy is that he's got this glowing baby.
Who talks?
You guys are never going to read the story of knowing the art the same way ever again,
are you?
But so that based on that there's this there are these whole stories where Lamek
sort of has these doubts like am I really Noah's father because he's glowing
talking and stuff or is he one of the Nephilim and there's sort of and
Sometimes it's an angelic revelation to him. Sometimes it's Enoch actually shows up. He comes back from heaven and says
Listen, Lamic. Don't worry about it. It's really your kid. Yeah, and of course Enoch is really important to all of this stuff because
He's anti-deluvian himself
Right, it's taken up into heaven and sort of joins the divine council. Right. Yeah
right before head. But the really interesting thing about those stories is that St. Matthew
draws on them a little bit. St. Matthew's gospel actually has a lot of the innaucic literature
themes and language woven into it. But one place where he plays on that is he's when he
tells the whole story of St. Joseph the Betroth doubting what's going on with
the player Tocos.
when she becomes pregnant, sort of being worried, right,
about what's going on.
And he gets the exact opposite message.
Right?
Labic gets sort of reassured, no, this is your child.
Don't worry about it.
He's just special.
Right?
Joseph gets told, well, no, this isn't your child,
but also doesn't have a human father.
Yeah.
So say that you kind of inverts that.
That's it.
Since we're talking about biblical inverts.
Yeah.
And now you're now
read Matthew the same way ever again.
Oh, flood relief.
All right. Well, we've got one more question before we continue on.
And this one comes from Father Stephen who is an Anglican military chaplain. So Father Stephen writes this,
Genesis 6 teaches that the Nephilim are giants are the offspring of the sons of God entering the daughters of men.
This unholy offspring should all have been destroyed in the flood.
Yet, we see giants appearing later in the Scriptures.
If the giants are the result of demons
mating with humans and they were destroyed in the flood,
how did they come back?
Did the demons mate with humans again after the flood?
If so, could that happen again today?
And to that, we will simply respond,
welcome to part two of this week's episode.
So yeah.
Alright, well, he makes the point that...
There's giants after the flood.
Right?
So the point of the flood is to rid the world of giant culture, right?
And yet there are giants after the flood.
So let's start talking about giants after the flood.
And even Genesis 6, 1 through 4 alludes to that, right?
Because it says, at this time and after.
Mm.
And after.
the nephilim were in the earth.
Yeah. So, yes, even the lutes to the fact that they're going to be some later. And since
that's right before the flood, it doesn't mean before the flood. That would be at this time.
So what we see when the, we see the giants again, right, when we see the giants again later,
starting in Genesis and then especially when we get into numbers in Deuteronomy and Joshua,
It's not just sort of these isolated.
people, but there are whole sort of giant clans. There are clans, tribes,
sort of these social units that are described as being sort of made up of giants.
So it's not just, you know, there's a bunch of poor, oppressed people who have this
tyrant for their king, but they're sort of all engaging in something,
right, that they all get categorized this way.
And so this is related to how sort of identity worked in the ancient world.
Yeah, right.
And this is something that we now has modern people understand DNA, right?
We understand genetics.
We have these ideas of ethnicity and race and these kind of things in our head.
And we
read those back into the scriptures and into other ancient texts. And it really sort of
distorts what we're reading. This really makes hash of, we won't go into this today, but this
really makes hash of everything St. Paul has to say about Jews and Gentiles, if you think
that's a racial or ethnic thing. But when we go back into the ancient age.
right? You are a member of a social unit, right? Whether it be a tribe, a clan, a city,
right? There's some social unit that you belong to. It's the people you live and work and eat
and worship with. All of those things. It's all it's all encompasses. Yeah, yeah, right?
your Paul Uncomposite. Yeah. And that is primarily
manifested and made real by ritual in the ancient world.
And it still is today to a large extent,
though we're less aware of it.
And we have sort of secularized rituals, right?
I don't know if we go so far as to say,
this is what makes you an American,
but there are definite American rituals, right?
Celebrating the Fourth of July voting, right?
And if you wanna become an American,
you have to go through a ritual,
you have to go through naturalization.
which not only includes like taking a test,
which of course is one of our wonderful American rituals,
but also like you have to take an oath, right?
You have to take an oath to become an American,
which I mean, what is the point of that?
I mean, does that do something?
It's words that are understood to have a power over you.
It's a very spiritual act, frankly.
And whatever you were
before, however you identified before, now you're an America. Yeah. Because you've gone through
that initiation and now you're going to you're going to celebrate the rituals, right? We just went
through this election and had people say, Oh, the vote is sacred. Right. The ballot box is sacred.
Right. It's like, well, wait, what is that? Well, that's that's this idea intruding despite secularism.
Yeah. Yeah. Can't escape it. Yep. So in the case of ancient Israel, right? That was if you were
You were an Israelite if you were...
circumcised or the wife or daughter of a circumcised male and
You ate the Passover, right? That was sort of the the basic
Yeah, and that was and that's an important point because and this is something I I learned from reading stuff that you've written
You know when Israel
Engages in the Exodus from Egypt
There are people who are not what we would regard as ethnically
you know
descendants of Abraham, there are Egyptians, there are Canaanites that participate in the Passover,
eat the Passover, and make the Exodus, and some of them even become leaders of Israel.
Like there's so much part of Israel that they're leading Israel, and it's not an ethnic thing at all.
It has nothing to do with DNA. It has to do with ritual participation, especially in the Passover,
which is so important in that particular...
that before the event happens, you get instructions on how to commemorate it, right?
So, fascinating, you know, that you become part of this people by engaging in these participatory acts.
And two big examples are Caleb, who when he first shows up is a kenezite,
which is one of the Kenezite tribes,
and ends up being an elder of the tribe of Jude.
and Phineas, Aaron's grandson Phineas, who was ethnically a black African, who became the
high priest of Israel. So yeah, the ethnic ideas right out, they were Caleb and Phineas are
no less a son of Abraham than anybody else.
And this is underlined in the church now,
you see all this language in the
surgical texts about belonging to a
new nation, to belonging to this
phrase is even used the race of
Christians, right? And what makes
us all Christian together? It's
that we've been initiated through
baptism that we partake in the
Eucharist together, that we live
as have been commanded us by God
through Christ, you know, in
Christ and through the apostles and
prophets. It's what we do that
that makes us Christian.
It's not genetic at all.
It's this ritual participation that makes us Christians.
An ongoing ritual participation which keeps us being Christians.
Right?
Right. And that's where this is where an Orthodox canon law, right?
The bare minimum to be in Israelite is your circumcised and you celebrate Paska.
If you look at Orthodox canon law, what makes you an Orthodox Christian
is that you've been baptized and at
least on POSCA you received the Eugurist. If you don't do that you're lapsed, you're now outside
the social unit and they have to be brought back in, ritually. But so the same thing was true for
these giant clans and tribes. They weren't members of these giant clans and tribes because they just
happened to be born into it ethnically.
Right? They went through initiation rituals.
and they participated in the ritual life of this clan.
And the ritual life of this clan,
not only involved sort of the sexually immoral rituals
we've already discussed,
but we get some clues again in the sources.
I won't read the full text of this,
but if anyone wants to look up first to the next seven
versus four through six
in describing the wickedness and the lifestyle
of the giants it talks about.
not only sort of the mass slaying of animals in sacrifice,
but cannibalism in human sacrifice.
Sacrifices will do an episode on sacrifices eventually.
I know people love when we do that.
But sacrifices are in the ancient world are not killing something.
Sacrifices are meals.
And so when we're talking about human sacrifice,
in most cases it's involving cannibalism.
Yeah, minimally in the form of blood drinking sometimes worse.
Yeah, yeah.
I mean, so I don't know, maybe you know this off the top of your head.
You know, when the Catholic conquistadores came to South America and they encountered the
Aztecs who were doing human sacrifice.
Was there cannibalism involved with that?
Yes.
Yep.
Yeah.
And that was one of the motivations.
for this has to be wiped out.
Wiped out.
Right.
This, and this is going to be important, right, when we get to talking about Joshua.
Yes.
Right.
People today want to present as genocide.
They say, oh, well, this is, you know, going and murdering these people because of their
race or ethnicity.
And no, there's not a concept of race or ethnicity.
Yeah.
I mean, this is not a popular.
in the modern world either, but this is the idea of wiping out these ritual and cultural practices.
Right. And this is what has to stop. And it's not, it's not, you know, the way we tend to think of
ritual and culture now. Again, we're talking about people who are in communion with demons
and are engaging in demonic fornication rituals in order to produce demonized human beings.
who have supernatural abilities, that's what's going on.
That's being wiped out.
Mass and Slaving people, murdering those people, sacrificing them to these demons,
and drinking their blood and potentially more.
Right.
These are, this is what the Old Testament is describing as abominations
that need to be put in end to.
Right.
So you could do that in a couple of ways, right?
If someone won't stop doing these things, right?
In the ancient world, the scripture is saying that person,
if they won't stop doing this, has to be put to death, right?
If, but if someone is ritually brought into another tribe
and do another clan, abandons these things,
they're no longer part of that clan, right?
So if everyone from a giant clan has either...
dead or assimilated into another group that is not practicing those things, the clan
has been eradicated.
Yeah.
And that's really...you can't underestimate the importance of that understanding a lot
of the Old Testament history we're about to talk about.
So talking about Gigantomaki in this war against the Giants, this is really directed at
these specific plans.
And when Israel is sent to war against these specific clans, the commandments and the guidelines and the rules of warfare are different for these clans than they are for the other residents of the land.
Yeah, I think that's a really, really important detail because, you know, the book of Joshua, I think, can get kind of a bad rap in the modern world.
Um
And there are even Orthodox people who will say,
well, could God really have commanded people
to go and wipe out whole civilizations?
And I think that that reveals that the detail
that you just mentioned, that the rule
for engaging a giant clan is different than the rule
for engaging in combat with sort of an ordinary,
pagan group that somewhere else there in Canaan and Canaan because you know everybody there is
some kind of pagan except for the Israelites right so there's there's a conquest going on but
it's not just okay God has decided to give you guys this land and go ahead just wipe out everybody
right it's way more complex than that right and it's it's I mean you see this in stark relief sort of
in Deuteronomy chapter 20 where it's giving the commandments for warfare and
general. You know what it talks about how basically they aren't allowed to engage in aggressive warfare,
to take territory and spoils.
Which, that's super different in the ancient world.
Yeah, nobody believes in that.
And even when they do go into war, before they lay siege to a city, they have to offer the city peace.
It's only if they refuse all offers of peace that Israel is allowed to make war.
against the city. Does that count with giant clans as well? Well, that's it. There's, and then in the midst of all that, in
Deuteronomy 20, there's this accept, right? The invites the Jebysites, right? It lists the particular clans, the particular tribes and groups.
Right. Which if you don't know that those are giant clans, it might just look like, okay, God decided to single out these people.
for right. He doesn't like that. Right. Some reason. Yeah. But it's
It's very explicit that whenever those groups are all listed, Yahweh says, you know, number
one, he says he's the one who's judging them, he's the one who's going to defeat them,
he's the one who's going to destroy them.
Israel is sort of the instrument for that.
And he says that it's because of their idolatry and their abominations, it's because of
of these things we've been talking about, the rituals that
make them who they are that constitute that tribe,
are rituals of enslavement, tyranny, human sacrifice,
idolatry, sexual immorality.
And so there's not a difference between
those things stopping and the tribe,
ceasing to exist as a tribe,
because those are the things that constitute the tribe
as a social unit.
Yeah.
And so yeah, so they're sort of accepted.
right from those general rules which were amazing for the ancient world as you mentioned.
Yeah. Yeah. Drop out of nowhere. Yeah. Yeah. Why wouldn't you engage in wars of conquest as often as
you possibly could manage it? That's, you know, now we have this idea, well that's immoral, you
You shouldn't do that, but no one at that time had that idea except this one people that
had chosen for himself, had created this nation for himself.
Right, and the total warfare that Israel is supposed to make against these tribes,
is the kind of warfare that all of Israel's neighbors waged against everyone, all the time.
Right.
So that's not the exceptional part.
That's the more normal part.
The accepting everyone else in the world from that is the strange part about the Torah.
These are just to be treated the way you would normal treat enemies with one exception even there and that's that
To reinforce the fact that it wasn't them defeating them that it was Yahweh their God defeating them
And that this was an act of his judgment not just their military might and expansionist tendencies
They weren't allowed to take any of the spoils. Oh, that's interesting. Yeah, the the physical objects the gold the silver the
stock. All of the wealth of these tribes was considered to be tainted by what they had
done. And so it was all dedicated and considered a cursive and put under a ban and had to be destroyed.
Yeah. There was that incident about someone who took some gold. And I'm trying to remember who that was now.
Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, they can in Joshua who tried to keep some of it and
came on the camp because of it. Yeah. So the word the Hebrew word
herm there is it's actually this from the same root as as
Haram and Mount Hermann that we've talked about. You know,
forbidden. Kurt Kurt, sinful, all those things. But but the word
is used both for things that are set apart because they're
accursed and things that are set apart because they're
holy or going to be offered as a sacrifice.
Interesting.
So the
ideas that it's sort of sometimes that were dedicated, right, is used there to kind of
try and cover both meetings. These things are dedicated for destruction, right? They're
belonged to Yahweh as his spoils and he's destroying them.
Right. Which I think that, as you said, kind of underlines also just from the point of
of people who think, okay, God is commanding genocide.
If that's just sort of the bare
on.
understanding of what it is of what's happening there, then why would God, you know, put these things off limits?
It just underlines that the whole point is to blot out these practices from the face of the earth,
and Israel is his instrument.
If it was just, okay, God is giving them permission to go and wipe out these certain people and take all their stuff,
then that would be a different, different ballgame, but they're not allowed.
They're not allowed. The point is that they're going in, you know, and, and
enacting God's justice, which is to set things right.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
It really important, interesting detail, interesting detail.
Yeah, and through these tribes of their practices,
these demonic entities that stand behind them,
who are the fathers of their chieftains,
are subjecting the land, their neighboring peoples
to this demonic tyranny and injustice.
there.
slaving their neighbors and sacrificing them to their gods.
Literally.
Right.
So I mean, what about the problem?
So, you know, okay, Israel moves in.
They take one of these cities.
They kill everybody in it.
I mean, what about, I mean, are there some innocence there?
There's got to be kids, babies.
I mean, what, you know, like, how do we, what do we do with that?
If a one-year-old or a two-year-old
Horite in one of these giant clans
parishes
Without having participated in these rituals. We look at that say oh, that's a horrible thing
That's the worst thing that could happen to him this little two-year-old never got to live his life in this world, right?
Yeah, what would his life in this world have been like?
If God hadn't done anything about the Horites
He would have grown up to be initiated into these things.
At least things, right? So, to be blunt, we have to remember that the last judgment and eternal life
and eternal condemnation exist when we're reading the Bible. I know that sounds bizarre,
but, right? So the perspective of Scripture, like you read in the book of wisdom,
Right, that someone who lives a short time in
and then God takes them to himself, right?
That's a blessed person.
Right, right.
So it's basically, we should look at it as we would
an infant who dies shortly, you know,
in maybe before birth or shortly after birth
and not by any human sin, but say, let's say,
they were born with some kind of birth defect and they die.
You know, a lot of times people look at that and they'll say, why God? Why? Right? Because it seems, I mean, it's such a difficult thing to endure, especially if it's your child.
But from a Christian point of view, that person, their entire earthly existence was in innocence.
And they are in the hands of God.
And from an earthly point of view, it's the worst...
thing ever, right? You know, here's someone who had their whole life snatched from them.
And yet from a Christian point of view, what is this life but preparation for the next?
Right. The purpose of this life is repentance. Yeah. And it ends when that's either complete
or when we've rejected repentance so many times and so thoroughly that our chances have run out
in God's patience has run out. Yeah, I recall there was kind of a hard saying, I remember reading,
And I think this was in the writings of St. Piusius, the...
Newly canonized saint the elder from from Greece
He was talking to someone about
Children who die or people who die young and he essentially said
Well the reason why God took them is because he knew that if they continued in life that
They would probably become very sinful and so he took them earlier
earlier out of mercy.
And, you know, I remember reading that and I thought to myself, okay, this does make sense to me, but
I imagine that would be hard to hear like, oh, how dare you say that my kid was gonna turn out bad, you know
But here's here's St. Paceus who talks to angels who you know who has
clairvoyant insight from God saying this and while not every single thing every single saint says is
should be you know is.
is right, like all their opinions about everything.
You know, based on what we've just been talking about, if you understand the providence of God,
it does make sense.
Like there's a sense that God protects people from sin sometimes by making their lifetime
shorter than we think it should be.
And so children in a Nephilim city who, by the hand of God, working through Israel are
very moved from this
life early, it's actually a blessing because it's preventing them from becoming involved
in idolatry.
And they'll be judged much more mercifully because they never were involved in that sin.
Right?
Right.
And in our Orthodox funeral service over and over again, we refer to the person who's
passed away as the one who God has chosen and taken.
Right.
There's a delusion.
take it
to himself. Actually, they haven't suffered a misadventure. They haven't lost a battle
with an illness. They've won a battle against sin. Hopefully. They haven't, you know,
that's something bad has happened to them. Right. There's something to grieve there.
I mean, something bad has happened to us in terms of our loss and that kind of thing.
But the person from the perspective of the Christian faith has been
chosen by God and taken to himself.
And that's not a bad thing.
Yeah.
Yeah, it's hard.
I mean, it's a hard saying, but that's
because we're materialist-minded, because we function
as though this life is all there is.
That's why it's hard.
And we don't believe that God is really
using the Israelites here.
Yeah.
demathologize the text. We say what's really going on is just one tribe is killing its neighboring
tribes and calling them demons to justify it. Yeah. Right. But that's not what the text says.
Right. I mean, you could just simply say, well, I don't believe the text. But that of course,
like, well, then why why be Christian, right? You know, really? Like if you're not as important.
Yeah. Why is that all about Jannonson? Right. Why take the Bible seriously if you're not going to
to take it seriously.
Like what? Yeah, they said, why is this book important if we're not actually going to take it seriously?
And I think that that's one of the most valuable things about what we're trying to do with this show is to say, okay, look, there is some
hard, weird, difficult stuff in there. And we could either say,
well, you know, people in the ancient world thought all kinds of things, you know, or we can say, well,
this is in the text.
They were all taking it seriously.
see at the time, if I can stop assuming for a second that I'm just smarter and better
informed, then everyone who lived before me for thousands of years, then maybe there's
something there that we can come away with.
And of course, I mean, this episode is sort of the par excellence of dealing with the
weird and the difficult in the Bible.
So yeah, yeah, I appreciate the conversation about that difficult thing because it is
It is hard. It is hard. You know, yet nevertheless, I think that if we're going to work on
purging materialist thinking from our thoughts, then we need to really be willing to go all the way
in terms of trusting in the providence of God and trusting that what he says that he intends
and he's going to do is true. You know, that when he takes, for instance, a child to himself,
that that actually is good for that child.
and not just say, well, he's pulling a fast one.
So, all right.
So let's talk about some of these very specific groups then.
The book of Joshua and all of these texts,
it numbers a Deuteronomy that present this kind of Jogano,
Joganto Machi, and even laid some of the later historical books,
Neal Testament, are presenting this picture of spiritual warfare.
That's not an allegorization of what they're presenting.
That's what they're presenting.
Spirititis, war of Yahweh, the God of Israel,
against
these demonic forces who are enacting the world through these specific groups. And so when we look
at these specific groups, we see that kind of reinforced with each group, right? So we talked about
already a little bit the amyrites, as they're called in the Old Testament, who are the
the MARTU in most other ancient texts as this group.
MARTU literally means Westerners.
Interesting. That's because they came from the from the west to take over a hot and
a sumer. But yeah, they aren't west from our. Yeah, and that's the bunch that Hammer Abias from.
Yeah, Habir Abbi is the most famous one of them. And they, of course, claimed to have access
to this wisdom from before the flood that had come through these spiritual beings. Yeah.
And that's what made them powerful.
By the way, you've said the word Gigantomaki several times and I'm not sure you actually defined it.
I mean if you know a little bit of Greek you know basically it means war against giants.
That's what it is. It's war against giants. So just wanted to kind of put that out there.
Right. So the most famous, homerabi would be the most famous Amarite outside the Bible.
Probably the most well-known one inside the Bible if any of them are well-known would be Sa'hahn.
Hmm.
King of the Amorites, who, along with the guy we're about to talk about, Israel makes war against him in the transjordan
under Moses before entering into the land of Canaan. That brings us to the second guy,
Og, Og, Og, Og, King of Basin.
Yeah, and Og and Sion, Sion.
I'm not sure I pronounced it.
Are both, those defeats are both commemorated in the Psalms
that we use in the Pollyelios that we sing.
Like this morning, we're recording this on November 25th,
which is the Feast of St. Catherine on our calendar.
This morning I sang the Pollyelios and in that is this,
we've defeated Og and Sion.
It's it's sung. It's such an important
victory that it gets sung about in the Psalms.
Right. It gets mentioned again and again and again in the Old Testament, not just in those
two Psalms, but it gets mentioned again and again in Joshua, again and again in, I mean, in
second Kings, there's stuff right and sort of well why is this such a major event?
Right. We already talked about Augs bed because these are these giant kings. These are these
Tyrant Kings is to monically powerful.
kings who were unstoppable and this image of spiritual and worldly evil. Right. Right. And this
Ragtag group that had just wandered around in the desert for years with sort of makeshift farming
implements turned into weapons, defeated them through the power of Yahweh their God. And so that
that victory is symbolic of so much.
That's why it's repeated again and again.
again and again. So an August the last of the Refine which the Refine were mentioned several
times in this context. We're going to see their mentioned in terms of being giants who
were removed from the land in another place. They're also however mentioned going forward in
the book of Isaiah, when it's talking about the underworld.
the spirits of these dead kings, the shades of these dead kings. This is hidden a lot of times
in English translations where they translate it as shades or just the dead. Yeah, with the
dead arise and praise thee, right? That's in the six Psalms. Yeah, it's all 88 or 87 in the Greek
number and verse 10. That's how they're the ref aem going to praise. Well, obviously not.
That's right. So refaeem are...
I mean, does that term refer to them only after they're dead or was it used for Nephilim as their
Still on earth it's used for them still on earth. So when they come to Bashaun
Orbegin, Aug is the last of the Refaim the other ones have already been killed, but he's still a Refaim
While he's alive who are sort of these fully demonized kings are sort of exhibit a I see
And so they become these sort of ones even once they
they become these sort of demonic spirits in the underworld. So does the word
Refaim and the word Nephilim are those essentially synonyms or is there a
distinction in how they're used? No, they're not. The Refaim is a particular group of kings.
Okay. All right. A particular group of giant kings. And the term isn't original to the
the Bible. Oh. The term is what they were called by everybody. Oh, interesting. So when you look at
get you or you you got
it was a city in what's now Lebanon. That's Rush Amra. And their particular dialect of old
Canaanite is called Eugeritic. And so the Bale cycle and other things are in Eugeritic.
We have ritual texts, Eugeritic ritual texts, that for example when their king would die,
who they viewed as a god, there were a whole series of sacrifices and rights that were performed
to try to...
appease the spirits of the dead
refereeing of these ancient,
these ancient kings because they
were going to meet the now departed
king on his way to Shaol.
And to try to appease them so they'd
let him pass and not tear it.
They were sort of these, these
princes of the underworld.
Now that they were dead and their,
their tombs are these stone tombs
called Dorman.
that are in what was Bishan, what's now the Golan Heights, you can go there and see them.
Wow.
The remains of these tombs of these dead kings, that's part of why Bishan,
that whole area there in the north was considered Haram Haram.
It's right next to Mount Herman.
This was a center of this evil and corruption.
And so, yeah, these...
Parts show up there and Isaiah sort of uses refers to to that same idea that we see in the eukaryotic ritual text
He's actually talking in Isaiah 14 about the devil being cast down into the underworld and it talks about the refaim rising up to
medium and
And greet him so these are yeah, August the last one still alive
That
Then it's what he's to do but that again is why he
such a major figure. And in the Greek Old Testament tradition, a lot of the places where the Hebrew
text has Gog is in like Gog and Megag. Right. Which is so excited like how Lindsay
writes his late great planet Earth back in the 70s or 80s if I remember correctly. The kings
of the Greek. The Greek actually has AUG. It's talking about like...
the spirit of Aug, the demonic spirit of Aug as a dead referee, like coming back as a leader
of the forces of evil. So yeah, Aug's a bad dude. And that's why his defeat is such a major.
A major thing. It's like defeating, you know, it's like in, it's like in Lord of the Rings,
defeating Sauron, you know, we just defeated a basically a demon guy. Yeah, I mean, it's a major
historical event.
Yeah.
So, but this, this is an isolate, right?
These are these two kings who Israel beats on the way into the land.
Before that, they'd already had their run in with the Amalakites.
Yeah, right.
And if I remember correctly, the Amalakites aren't the ones that attack them while they're
at Sinai, is that right?
Yes, yeah.
Right.
To attempt to obliterate Israel sort of before Israel could even fully be formed and
come up.
come of age. Right. And so at Sinai there offering sacrifices to Yahweh, Moses is meeting God face to face. He's being given the law. And this giant clan comes up and interferes with this. Right. And attacks, attacks Israel. And if the tax, the way it's described is that they lay siege to the mountain, which had become the mountain of God. Right. So it's war on heaven. Right. It refers to them trying to.
lay a hand on the throne of Yahweh, right? Like they're trying to God saying they're attacking me, right?
It addition to you. So again, there's this spiritual warfare element, right? Well, so why do we say that the
the amolecites are a giant clan? Well, it's because Amolec, if you want to figure who is very clearly a giant,
But Amolec is your guy, right?
Right.
His...
Now again, for some reason, people don't spend a lot of time studying the genealogies
of Issa.
I don't know why, but Genesis 36 verse 12, which is part of that genealogy of Issa, it
talks about Issa's grandson who has wives and has children.
and that it also says he has this son, Amalek.
And it says that he has this son, Amalek, with a concubine, right, a sexual slave named Timna,
who's a horite, the horites are identified as Nephilim in Deuteronomy.
So this is someone from a giant clan who is a concubine who is in a kind of ritual sexual
slavery and who is described as being literally
the sister of Leviathan.
Yikes.
Where?
Okay.
So where is that that she describes as the sister of the
Leviathan?
Right there at Genesis 36 verse 12.
Oh man.
She's identified as the sisters of Lothan.
That's how it's rendered in English.
But Lothan in English,
Lothan is a literal rendering of what we otherwise translate as Leviathan.
It ended up being Leviathan in the early English translations for the same reason we got Jehovah.
they kind of plugged in...
incidents around the Hebrew or they plugged in vowels around the Hebrew consonants.
Yeah, so the idea that I'm just looking in Genesis 36 now and the identification of Timna
as low-tans of sister is verse 22.
Yeah, these parts that no one reads, right?
Yeah.
You know, but yeah, but it's a little bit earlier.
Yeah, and it's verse 12 where it says that she's
the one who becomes the the concubine of Esau's son, Ella Faz.
Right. Or well, the original text doesn't say it's his concubine, it just says she's
a concubine. A concubine. Oh, oh, oh, oh.
Right. So this is the potentially new king James here.
Right. He potentially a temple prostitute.
Hand. Yeah. Right. Who's who's who you sleep with?
Who's a who's a whoreye? Who's a whoreye? Who's a member of one of these giant plants?
So that and
And we're going to see that giant clan was destroyed by Esau's descendants, the Horites.
That was part of their, that was their part of the Gigantomaki, of the work of the giants,
was defeating the Horites. But Esau's grandson went over and participated with the enemy.
Yeah. And Amalek was produced out of that.
Right. I mean, is there any indication that he, that this union was
And again, parents, this is why we gave it the warning of the big.
Is there any indication that this union was him just, it elevates, you know, like, like,
he just met some girl and they, you know, or is there any indication that he actually went
over and participated in some kind of ritual act when he fornicated with her?
Right.
Oh, well, it doesn't describe it in detail.
these two pieces.
She's a horite.
Yeah, why would he do that?
He's a horite, cock you, but right.
She's a horite concubine and the sister of
low 10 of Leviathan.
Now there was now there's a place where a low 10 is listed
as one of the chiefs of the horites, but it's unclear if that's saying they
worshiped low 10.
If there was a giant chief didn't among the horites named low 10
after-
right?
Right?
A viathan?
Yeah.
This chaos monster.
But you get the idea either way of what the text is indicating.
Right.
That she's bound up with demonic, ritual sexual activity.
She's from a people who do that.
She's one of the people engaged in that.
And this guy goes and lies with her.
Right.
his other children
His legitimate children are all edomites. They're the line of the edomites.
Amalac is this other thing who starts this other tribe and this other clan.
Yikes. Man, it does get weird when you get down deep.
Read those genealogies.
Although the thing is, of course, I've read the whole Bible several times.
problems.
Sorry.
I've read this passage.
There was never any point, never any point in the past when I read it.
I thought, oh, he's, you know, he's, he's, he's, uh, he's
fornicating with, um, this demon person.
You know, it's just, you have to have, you have to have some guide, you know,
to, to know that that's what's going on here.
But of course, you know, ancient people reading this, you know,
hearing this largely for the first time, they would know all this context.
Right, yeah.
Yeah, which we do.
And when we're reading it in English too, not only do the genealogies a bunch of names,
I can't pronounce, right?
It's sort of run through them.
But also all of these it's real testament.
Start to just all blur together.
Like remembering that, oh, the horites are a giant clan.
Oh, okay.
And connecting a genealogy and genesis to a passage we're about to talk about in Deuteronomy.
Yeah.
Right.
which you, if you get to do it around me,
if you don't bail out of reading through the...
somewhere in Leviticus or Numbers, right?
Which a lot of people do.
You've probably forgotten Esau's genealogy
by the time you get to do the Ronomy, right?
Like that's not the piece you've held onto.
Yeah.
Wow.
In your mind.
Oh, man.
OK, so I remember that.
So the Amalakites, right?
So his tribe eventually does get finally defeated by Israel, right?
And by David.
Oh, by David and per.
Okay.
But there was oh, that's the final defeat, but there was an earlier victory
There's an earlier victory right with Joshua at Refidine, right with most that's why Moses holds up his hands
That's when they attacked Israel at Sinai. Okay, that was self-defense not to get wiped out by the Amalakite got you
got you right
But then because they had declared war on Yahweh and his people that's where after that battle
battle after his words at battle that's where you are waiting
fouls. This is it for them. Yep. Right. They've declared war. I mean, so there aren't going to be
amulakites. And Saul's big sin that loses him the throne of Israel is not obeying God about the
amulakites. God tells him to go and wipe out the amulakites as a giant clan. And instead he takes a
bunch of their livestock and their treasures for his own treasure. You know, do you take their
King.
and takes their king captive to parade him around
and pray about how Saul defeated him.
Don't do it, Saul.
There's this amazing moment where,
where, y'all, it says,
says the prophet Samuel to confront Saul about it, right?
And he sort of says, oh,
and did you do what God said with the Abel of Kites?
It's all like, oh yeah, yeah.
And Samuel says, you know,
I'm hearing a lot of sheep and goats bleeding
off of the distance, you know,
could it be?
Thank you!
Man!
Yeah, and which ultra is which I mean that's really this that's really interesting because
Again, right if you have a kind of a Sunday school level knowledge of the whole Saul and David story and all this
You just kind of get this idea that that Samuel picks Saul, you know at God's command and then God sort of changes his mind
It decides a David is a guy
But it's really about
That he is failure to engage in gigantumaki
You know, he's his failure to do the thing that he was supposed to do
video.
Um, um,
Yeah, I mean, it's just mind blowing
when you realize that major parts
of the Old Testament story are about making war on giants.
Yeah.
Like major parts of the central aspects.
Samuel, I mean, you know, like this is, yeah.
Welcome everybody.
Yeah, you just taken your first step into a larger world.
Right, and this is described in sort of larger terms
or programmatic terms in to-
economy chapter 2. Okay. Because the whole book of Deuteronomy really almost all
the book of Deuteronomy parts of it are historical but but most of it is about, as
Israel is now coming to prepare to enter the the land of Canaan, Moses gives
sort of his parting, his farewell address, right? His last sermon and that's why
there's so much recapitulation of things from the rest of the Torah, right?
where he's remarking.
them and putting these things together and
theologically tying these things together.
And so part of this is as they're approaching,
they're traveling through not just lands that belong to these,
like, aug and sahehan, but also the lands of sort of their cousins,
their fellow Abrahamites, right, like the Edomites,
the Ammonites, the Moabites, right, Moab and Ammon were the sons of
of lot Abraham's nephew.
So they're part of this larger Abrahamite family to whom God had promised to this whole
area of land.
It wasn't just to Israel.
He makes his promises huge sweep of land.
It's to Abraham and his descendants.
And so there are these pieces that he's already given at that point.
Israel's kind of late comers to the Gigantomaki.
The war's already going on.
is already
given portions of this promised land to the Edomites, Esau's descendants and to the Ammonites and the Moabites, lots descendants.
And when this is described, it describes how when they came to that land, God brought them there, gave them that land.
So Israel is not to take a single foot of it. That's literally what it says. Not to take the breath or length of a foot of that land from them, because God gave it to them.
but they come there, God gives it to them and they have to drive out the
giants and God drives the giants out before them. So these clans are named who have already been
destroyed and sort of the headers for them are the Anachim, the sons of Anach who cover several of
these tribes or the Refaim who we already mentioned where Augs the last one. The region Aug is the
last one is a lot of them are already gone from these other groups descended from Abraham. And so the
The Moabites have dispossessed the MIM.
Take Moabites.
Ysa has dispossessed the Horites who the tribe that concubine was from.
So this gives us another part of that picture that Ysa's descendants were brought
to the land of Edom to take it from the Horites and his grandson sort of
switches sides, right, to the enemy and engages in this.
And that's where the Amalakites come from.
But the Horites as a whole had been removed.
The Zamzumim, which is probably the best tribe name, right?
Who are said to have been part of the Refaim were dispossessed by the Ammonites.
And then the really interesting one that people gloss over is it says that the Avim were dispossessed by the Caffturim.
Okay, the people of Cafftur.
Okay, so who are they?
Cafftur is the ancient name for the island of Crete.
Okay.
And the people who were from Crete, who this is talking about are the Philistines.
Wait, but aren't, so are these one of the C-People's from the ancient worlds?
Yes.
To engage in this massive attack on...
In invasion, as the Bronze Age collapsed, human civilization collapsed at the end of the Bronze Age, the 11th century BC.
So part of that was this invasion, this mass migration from
the end of the Minoan civilization, this exodus, and one of those peoples were the Philistines,
who they were actually the Paresti originally, but Egyptians apparently turned their
arsons to elves, so they headed up becoming the Pallesti. They tried to invade Egypt,
they got repelled, and they settled along the coast.
Right, and of course that's where we get the word Palestine from as well.
All right.
Yeah.
interesting to think that there are giant clans living in what is now Palestine and Lebanon.
And the ancient Palestinians, ancient Philistines, show up from Crete and wipe them out and settle those areas.
Right. And they found these cities, Ash-Dod, Ash-Khulanghazah, Ghat, which is usually pronounced Ghat.
But you see this and
So the thing here though that's interesting is that we've got a bunch of Abrahamites, right?
People to send it from Abraham.
And then we've got these Greeks.
Right.
Who have showed up?
And they have these oaths.
Right.
And so the question is, well, wait, what are they doing here?
And it actually creates this interesting and weird thread in...
the Old Testament, the Christian Old Testament, that somehow the Greeks are descended from Abraham.
Yeah, okay. Which is bizarre, right? As an idea. And I'm not saying it's like genetically true.
Right. But if we think about descent and being someone's son, and as you said, like imaging the father,
There are less people when they end-
and Gigantomaki are acting like Israel.
Right.
And that's reflected.
There's this weird little thing.
Again, first Macabees that I know not a lot of people have read in depth.
But after the Macabee brothers have successfully staged their revolution
and gained independence for Judea from the Seljukid Greek Empire.
Right.
They are the small
independent kingdoms surrounded by much more powerful kingdoms. In fact, they're kind of on the
border of the cell you could empire and the Tala mech empire in Egypt. And so to try to not
immediately be overtaken again, they sign these treaties. One of them is with Rome, which ends up
going very badly. That's how the Romans got into Judea. Yeah. And annexed it by the time you get to
to the New Testament. They were kind of invited. The other one
with Sparta, with the Spartans. Right? And the part of the text of the treaty with Sparta
is preserved in First Macabees. And in it, the Spartans say that Jewish envoys to them,
Judean envoys to them had shown them in the Jewish sacred texts that the Spartans were descended
from Abraham.
Yeah.
had a common cause.
Yeah, with Judea.
Yeah, I'm looking at that verse now,
and it's like that we're related.
We're both of our nations descended from Abraham.
Yeah.
And the only text in the Torah that you can get that from
is this one in Deuteronomy.
Wow.
That's amazing.
So, that's where at least that tradition,
that idea that-
we had this common cause once and we could have so we should have it again. Many centuries later
is there later on in the scriptures and so once Joshua leads the people into the land
that's his goal and the book of Joshua expressly says that that's his goal. The end of the book
of Joshua says in Joshua 11, 21 and 22, right? Okay, conquest is done.
because we've wiped out all the Anachim.
We've taken care of the giants.
Right.
And it's not, it's done because we've grabbed
the piece of real estate that God has set aside for us.
Right.
Because they hadn't actually taken all of the real estate
that they were supposed to,
but they had dispossessed the giant cleanse.
There's some stragglers at the end of Wukarjashua
who it says escaped into the Philistine cities
and this is where things go bad with the Philistines.
Hmm. The Philistines become a problem.
then in the book of Judges and then for Saul and David and the early Israelite monarchy,
because they flip from being part of the Gigantomaki to sort of giving aid and comfort to the enemy by
receiving these giants that allow them to continue their ways. So does that mean that the Philistines
then did they begin to adopt the Nephilim ritual or at least sort of let people in their midst?
to are doing it. They let people in their midst who are doing it. Wow. Because even when
you get to Saul and David, they're still commanded to take out these last members of the giant
clans. Right. They have to be removed. But God never tells them they have to obliterate
the Philistines.
Interesting. So the Philistines obviously were not doing that stuff themselves. But, you know,
right, not wholesale. Yeah. Right. Yeah. I mean, they were pagans. They were just making
good gods, right? But there's this. There's this.
still this difference, right, where what these giant clans are doing is sort of over the line,
right? Their cup of iniquity is full. This can't be allowed to go on anymore. Yeah.
Right? Because of because of its consequences anywhere, right? And then it's David who ends up
finishing up the Gigantomaki, right? It's David who ends up
but Goliath being the most obvious example.
who comes from Gott from one of the cities where they took refuge, he's portrayed as one of these
refugees or the descendants of these refugees. Yeah, so it's interesting he's described as a
Philistine, but he's not actually a Philistine Philistine, he's from a sort of immigrant community.
It's sort of speaking. Right, he's one of the he's one of the Anarchy. Yeah. Right, and they're using him
as sort of this special forces troop, right? And there's lots of stuff about the way
go either
described like it's significant that all of his armor and weaponry is described as being made of bronze
because bronze technology had been largely lost at that point where at the beginning of the
Iron Age. So he's a kind of ancient warrior. Right. His armor and weaponry is this throwback to the
age where the Amorites were in power. Wow. Right. Sort of the height of Bronze Age civilization. So
So he's portrayed as the last of one of these ancient men of renown, right?
one of the last of these Nephilim, one of the last of these giants.
Yeah. And if I recall, he's described as being, I don't know, the number I grew up with was he was nine feet tall.
I remember. Well, stories about that. Numbers are tricky and all ancient text because they didn't have numerals.
Okay. So they did numbers with letters. So sometimes it gets confusing. Sometimes you can't tell if something's a number or a word because the
the consonants just happen to make up a word.
Oh.
Or they could be using the numerator.
So.
And then.
That's why when you compare like the Greek Old Testament and the Hebrew Old Testament,
the numbers are all weird.
They don't match.
Don't match, because it's a translation issue.
But so depending, if you go by the Hebrew text, he was 9 foot 9.
If you go by the Greek text, he was 6 foot 6.
But since the average person at that time in Palestine was about 5 feet tall, the average
adult male. Right.
He's still bigger than everybody else.
Yeah, either way.
Either way, he's cute.
He's like Shaquille O'Neill compared to even tall people like you and me.
Yeah.
So, so yeah, either way, he's big.
But again, that, that, his, making the point of his height is to another clue to you
along with the bronze armor and weapon, all these things to give you this picture of who he is,
that he's one of these.
He's one of the last of these.
Yeah.
and David David
goes out and defeats him explicitly. This is part of what's going on. Right. Saul
did go to war against the amulakites, but he did it. So his sin was doing it for his own glory
and his own honor. Right. As a battle leader rather than being the agent of God. And that's why
David, when he goes to face Galatias, so explicit about the fact, right. He says, you come to me with
your spear in your sword. I come to you in the name of Yahweh. Right. Yeah. Right. That it's Yahweh
who's going to defeat him, right?
David's just playing his small part, right?
Being the way that God does it.
Right.
And you get this sort of, that's a deliberate.
Underdogs kind of story.
David and Goliath.
You know, there's tiny little David
and there's big ol' Goliath.
And the only way that David is able to feed him is
because of God's help.
Right.
But that's really a misread, is my point here.
Yeah.
Because it's not about David, the underdog,
beating the bigger guy.
Yeah, yeah
way is a lot bigger than Goliath. Right. Goliath is the actual underdog. Yeah. And he gets
squished. And David is the instrument. Yeah. Yeah. Wow. So yeah. David is the actual mighty man in this
in this scheme. But then he goes on and it's narrated in second Samuel how David and his
Give it a try.
his mighty men, his commanders, take out the rest of basically Goliath's clan, right?
Those last stragglers at his defeat of the Amalakites has narrated that this is what establishes
David as king.
But this is important because, remember, David is our paradigm.
David is our icon of who the Messiah, who the Christ is going to be.
Right.
So David is the king of Israel.
defeats the giants, finally, completely totally.
And then when Jesus shows up as the and says he's the son of David and everyone calls him that
He's doing battle directly with
Spirits he's doing exorcisms. He's sending them into the same beings. Yeah, okay, so let's let's
I mean, this is this is a super deep dive episode
So yeah, so when we were doing prep
craft.
We talked about, for instance, the exorcism of Legion where the spirits are sent from Legion into the pigs and they go down the embankment and are drowned in the water.
At their request, they get their request to go into the pigs.
Rather than the abyss, the band up in the abyss anyway.
Right. Yeah. Yeah. Kind of Jesus sort of pulls a fast one on them because, you know, drowning in the water is understood as a dissent into the abyss.
the abyss.
Yeah, so I remember, so we talked about this and I realized that I was unclear on exactly
what was happening.
So my, the way that I understood, which now I understand is incorrect.
The way that I understood the Nephilim ritual and then these spirits that go into the pigs
is that you get this demonized person who comes as the fruit of the Nephilim ritual and
They've got a demon hanging around in them with them.
And then they die and then and then eventually some of those demons end up in Legion and then get sent into the pigs, but that's that's a little bit wrong, right?
Right. That's not that's not how people at the time of Christ understood it. Okay. So all right. So let's let's take the deep dive and talk about exactly what we're looking at with those those spirits.
This is an extension of what we were talking about.
about in terms of that anti-phiosis, right?
This is that come to fruition.
So demonosis.
Right.
I don't know if there's a good word for this, but that's the word I picked.
We have one of these Nephilim, one of these giants, one of these leaders chiefs, members
of this giant clan who's participating in these rituals.
That means they have this relationship of fatherhood and sunship with this demonic spirit
who is a fallen angelic being.
So they're imaging their father.
They're imaging them, they're bringing their works, you know, St. John uses this language in first, in first John, it talks about not just the sunship starting with Cain in his line in first John, but also the idea that Christ came to destroy the works of the devil.
these works are brought into the world through these people or in this relationship with these beings.
But just as in fiosus, when we become sons of God, that means our
transformation to become like God. Right? We talk about that as being divinized. Yep. Right?
We become by grace, what Christ is by nature. The same thing happens to such an unrepentant person
who has this kind of relationship with the namanic, where they become demonized. And so the
understanding was that like the refaim who we were talking about, these other, these other
Nephilim, they threw their
actions and their ritual practices and their worship are changed and transformed and become
like the demons in every way. Yeah, although there's one exception as to the way they become like
them, right? Which is that they they don't have demon bodies. Right. Right. So when their their
their soul or spirit is separated from their human body.
evil spirit. They are a demonic spirit. And so the way it was understood in the first century
AD and for a couple at least a few centuries before that,
minimally a few centuries before that is that these these unclean spirits
that the spirits we see in the synoptic gospels who are the subject of Christ's exorcism
are the spirits of these dead Nephilim.
So who have become
demonic and demonized. 90% of them are in the abyss. According to the book of Jubilee's, the other 10% are still roaming around. That's why they're unclean spirits because they're a mixture.
Yeah.
So we could call them demons, but that's actually only relatively true about them because they're not fallen angels.
These are fallen humans.
Right.
They become so fallen. They are.
are essentially demons.
And it's interesting like,
we sometimes in the Orthodox Church
talk about monastics living the angelic life.
And boy doesn't that sort of throw all this
into stark relief when you think about exactly what happens.
They functionally become angels.
They don't become angels
in kind of a terms of species genes.
Ontologically, right.
Yeah.
Jesus changing species.
As we were talking about with the saints.
Right.
this is
This is the flip side. This is the dark side of theosis. This is demonization as opposed to demonization.
So the same way that the saints in heaven are like the angels and fulfilling this angelic role,
and functioning in the role that the angelic powers had functioned in, and have functioned in.
These demonic spirits of these fully demonized people are like the demons and are functioning
in this-
monic role. Right.
And okay, so before we go to break,
we had a question that came over the speak pipe.
But before we talk about that,
I just wanted to underline that this notion of gigantomaki
is not just an ancient near eastern thing, right?
There are other cultures that talk about wars with giants.
Pretty much all of them.
Yeah, so again, just like the flood is everywhere
Everybody's got wars which the ones that I think of off right off top my head is Ragnarok
The Norse yeah, Norse story
You know where you've got gods versus giants
And now mind you obviously it gets kind of mixed up when you start trying to I you know make it into an allegory of the real the real war
It's not an allegory. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. You can't yeah, you can't say for instance that
that Odin and Thor...
for instance, on the kind of the the Quenicle Good side of that Norse war are actually angelic beings,
you know, you know, fighting against giants because, you know, as you said, it's a kind of pagan propaganda.
Like, yeah, we defeated the giants. Actually, no, you were on their side.
You know, but yeah, so what other, I mean, what other cultures have this kind of giant story,
this giant war story? Yeah. Well, in Celtic stories, you've got the Fomorians,
Okay, who are sort of these mischapen giants because they're part human part fairy. Yep. Yep ahead
Part of the party. Yep, and they're their tyrants their cannibalistic
Right, they had to be defeated right in order to take possession of of
The area and you know possibly the most famous. I mean if you look up Gigantomaki
Right on the internet you're probably going to find the Greek form of the story
Right.
which Gaia, who was the mother of the Titans,
we already talked about how the Titans in a lot of ways
are parallel to these rebellious angels
who were responsible for the Nephilim in the first place,
who get imprisoned in Tardarus, right?
In fact, St. Peter, in second Peter,
talks about the angels who sinned in the past,
having been confined to Tardarus.
He uses the word Tardarus to make that parallel.
So Gaia's mad that the Titans have been imprisoned, right?
And so to get revenge for the Titans,
she sends the giants out of the earth
to go and sort of counterattack.
And these figures play out a lot in the visions
of Daniel and then the visions of Revelation
through that.
The Giants Typhon, who's another sort of monstrous creature that gay ascends to get revenge for the Titans
A lot of the depictions about the anti-Christ that you find in Daniel and
Revelation are based on that are based on this story that it's this figure who's coming to get
quote-unquote revenge for the Titans for these angels who
who produced the Nephilim and were imprisoned.
And that continues into the patricistic period.
Saint Irenaeus, one of his proposed readings for what 666 represents is the name Titan.
Oh wow.
Man.
So yeah.
So these stories are sort of, it's not just that these are versions of the same story in different cultures.
that the ancient Israelites, the people of the Second Temple period and the early Christians,
a connection between those Greek and Roman stories, and as they played out of the actual
ritual religion and worship of the Greeks and the Romans, and the truth which they saw
as preserved in their scriptures.
Wow.
Okay.
Alright, so we got a question from Christopher who left us a message, and I'm going to play
that now and we're going to try to answer briefly before we go to break.
So here's what Christopher had for us.
Good morning. This is Christopher from Tucson and I was wondering if the depictions of St. Christopher as a giant in the West or as a dog headed person in the East had any connection with the giants in the Bible.
Thank you so much and have a very good day.
Okay, so Father Stephen and I talked about this before we were when we were preparing for the show and both of us kind of concluded we didn't really have much to say about this.
I thought it would be correct.
cool to still put it out on this episode, just kind of get it out there.
And the one thing, and I don't know whether I mean,
I can't comment on how accurate it is, but I just recommend that you check out.
There's an article by Jonathan Peugeot called understanding the dog headed
icon of Saint Christopher.
And he actually does talk about the fact that Saint Christopher is depicted in
Western iconography as a giant.
And he relates that to stuff that's in the
scripture about giants. It's a really interesting article. I don't like I said I can't comment on its accuracy whatever I
I do like a lot of the stuff that Jonathan Peugeot does so I just recommend you you check that did you want to add anything to that father Steven?
No, that punts suffices for me. All right. All right. Well, let's uh
Let's go to break
Father Andrew Stephen Daymak and father Steven DeYoung will be back in a moment to take your calls on the next part of the Lord
of
spirits. Give them a call at 855-237-2346. That's 855-AF radio.
What a year this has been for all of us. 2020 has dealt some difficult blows, but in
God's grace and providence, it's also reaped many blessings. One of the blessings is a large
matching grant from the Renaissance Fund. Up to 50,000...
$1,000 to be exact, and it's not a soft match, meaning if we don't reach our part of
the $50,000, they will give it anyway.
Nope.
It's what we call a true match.
If we fall short of the goal, even by a mile, we'll only get that same amount matched.
it could be 50,000 plus 50,000 for 100,000 or it could be 5,000 plus 5,000 for 10,000.
Would it be a shame to leave that much money on the table?
Think of what AFR could do with this additional windfall.
Can we count on you to be as generous as you can this week?
We only have until December 2nd to meet the entire goal.
We need you and ask that you consider being a part of making this work.
Go to ancientfaith.com now and look for the large banner for the Giving Tuesday Matching
gift campaign.
Thank you so much.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits,
the Father Andrew Stephen Damick,
and Father Stephen DeYoung.
If you have a question, call now at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF radio.
All right, well, welcome back for the third half of our show.
and just as a reminder, this is a pre-recorded episode.
So even though the soothing voice of Steve just suggests as you should call in, please don't call.
There will be anybody to take your call.
But this is a, like I said, it's a pre-recorded episode and we did take some of your questions and comments and stuff.
We're incorporating them into this particular episode.
All right. Well, now we're going to talk about the way that these biblical texts and traditions and understandings of what's going on in those.
of what's going on in the
biblical texts were received in the church, in especially the early years, and then look
at some of the later stuff as well. And this is probably some of the points where we're
going to have a, there's a little bit of controversy. They were going to actually highlight
I think a little bit, but it doesn't have to be controversial, I think. And honestly,
I believe that the way that we've read it makes sense of the biblical text. And as you're
about to discover actually this is the way.
that almost all of the earliest church fathers read it as well. Isn't that right?
Absolutely. And we're also going to talk about why those later fathers who didn't didn't.
Yeah, yeah. So we're going to underline the fact that there is a discrepancy between the way that
that the earlier church fathers read these texts
and the way that some later church fathers
read these texts.
And, you know, just as to kind of help frame that, we should say that the fact that some
fathers read it one way and other fathers read it another way does not mean that the
patristic tradition is bunk.
It doesn't mean that.
It means that this is one of those areas where they actually do disagree.
And so, and it's a real disagreement.
you know, you can't, you can't kind of hold both positions at the same time.
And it's okay to disagree with some fathers about certain things.
Not about everything.
And when they disagree with each other,
you kind of have to.
Right.
What else can you do?
Right?
So I'll just also say that,
even if you've listened to this point in this episode
and you're like, I do not agree with the way those do-preases
just read all that stuff.
That's not what's happening.
whatever. You know, fine. I mean, we're, that's okay. But at the same time, you know, there's,
there is space within the church to have these conversations and not to
unathmetize each other because we're reading giants differently.
I think that the reading that we've taken makes the most sense of the bookletext
and that the other one kind of does it. So, well, so anyways, let's look at, let's look at
kind of a sampling of what's going
going on in the church fathers?
Well, there's just a set out even before we do that.
Okay.
There's a methodological thing here.
How do we approach an issue like this where there's
disagreement in the church fathers and there's different
traditions, right?
And there's different understandings.
How do we interact with that?
because one very negative thing I've seen.
This may be especially prominent in internet orthodoxy.
Inter-doxy.
Yeah, which I was about to say isn't really orthodoxy, but that's not totally fair.
But is this idea that well, okay, if one father says one thing and another father says another thing, or it looks like that, then I just pick the one I like better.
Yeah, right. We're not saying that.
Right, if I could find a father who says something I want to believe, I'm okay to hold that-
as an Orthodox Christian because some father did, right?
I think, or I have a proof text, right?
I wouldn't indicate that, right?
So the methodology that we're about to use
and that I think is correct
and the way to approach this is,
with an issue like this,
we've got the witness of the Old Testament,
we've got the witness of the New Testament,
we've got the witness of the fathers.
So.
So if you're going to take a position on an issue like any issue that's like this where
there's disagreement, you need to present how your position takes into account all of the
old testament data, all of the new testament data, the patristic data that agrees with you,
and explains the patristic data that doesn't agree with you.
meaning that that explains.
these fathers who know Christ better than I do, right? Which at whatever position
you take on this one for example, you're going to have to say that some fathers who
know Christ far better than I do, know the Scriptures far better than I do are
more spiritual and more holy than I am somehow got it wrong, right? And so if
If your view can't explain that, then your view doesn't work.
Right. So if you take the view, some view and some obscure writing of one church father and say, okay, well, this is the one I agree with. You've got to be explained to me how every other church father got it wrong. Right.
Right. For 2000 years. That's why that's not a good approach. Right.
So in terms of church fathers who talk about what we were just talking about, well, before we get to the church fathers, let's talk about the New Testament.
yeah yeah which we haven't read
talk much about the New Testament.
Yeah, we already mentioned the fact that even before the New Testament in the
the Septuagint proper, the translation by the Sevedi of the Torah, they translated in Genesis 6,
through for this is being angels of God, human women, right? And giants. So...
There's that before we even get to and this is of course this is the primary way in which
Not necessarily all of the apostles were reading the scriptures
Because St. Paul was certainly plenty fluent in Hebrew
But it's the way they interact because the New Testament's in Greek
That's the text that they're quoting and that they're interacting with in the New Testament text right so our first
Witness our first you know sort of canonical if we want to put it that way
witness.
to interpreting the Hebrew Old Testament,
reasonably we could say is the Septuagint, right?
That's right.
Because it's a translation,
but it's in an interpret that passage from Genesis 6,
as we said that when we first started this,
as talking about angels,
having relations in some way,
and giants being produced as a result of that.
That's those are the words that are actually used
in the Septuagint Greek.
Yep, yep. Okay.
So when we get into the New Testament in particular we find
the stories we've just been talking about about the angels who revealed things to humanity and then
rebelled and were imprisoned in and
produced the the giant
quote-unquote offspring as their sons
is referred to
several times in
what are called the general epistles,
first and second Peter and Jude.
Okay.
So the one in first Peter,
a lot of people take in a different way.
I don't wanna,
we could spend two hours just talking about this.
But,
but I'll put it to you this way.
Restrain yourself, I'm not the Steven.
Yeah.
First Peter 3 vs 19-20.
talks about Christ's proclamation in his descent into Hades
to the spirits who were imprisoned there who sinned in the days of Noah.
Right. Okay.
So that reference to in the days of Noah
is kind of clear and unavoidable.
Yeah. And if you want really solid evidence of that,
St. Augustine, who was one of the first-
church fathers to take a view different from the one we're talking about of who
the giants were and and whether there were fallen angels involved. When he comes
to this text admits he doesn't know what it means. He says I don't know why it says
in the days of Noah. Right. Because he wants to read the text is talking about
Christ preaching the God.
in terms of giving certain people in Hades a second chance at repentance.
Yeah.
And then he's like, well, I don't know why Noah, the right why why them why not anybody else.
So he's basically admitting that he doesn't have this frame of reference.
Right. He doesn't know what to do because he's rejected consciously rejected what we've been explaining.
He doesn't know what to do with that reference to
spirits that send in the days of Noah.
Yeah.
It just, you can't fit it in.
So, second Peter, two verses four through nine, talks about angels who sinned and who
are imprisoned in chains of gloomy darkness.
That chains of gloomy darkness phrase is essentially a quote from 1st Enic, talking about the imprisonment
of the angels who created the Nephilim.
I would also...
add, I would also add that if you want to say this isn't talking about that, that this isn't
talking about Genesis 6, you're going to have to show me somewhere else in the Old Testament
where angels are said to have sinned. Angels plural.
Yeah, and it's also kind of interesting. I'm looking at some of the translation notes for
second Peter 2, 4. You know, the translation I'm reading says, if God did not spare the angels
but through them into how.
lock them up and change them under darkness. What's interesting is that the the phrase
that gets translated as through them into hell, sometimes as translated as
casting them into Tarderis, but it's actually a verb, Tarder-Tarder-Roo-O, which I
would translate as sort of Tarderized became Tarderized. Which doesn't mean they had
Charter saw it. Yeah, it became
tartarized. So that's just...
reference to imprisoning these spirits in this place where you put titans. Right. And so it's
very clear what St. Peter's talking about. Right. You could you could try and argue he's using it as
an analogy or something, but there's no clear other thing that he could be speaking about. Yeah. And
And verse five he mentions specifically Noah.
There it is.
And then the flood.
Right.
And you see the same thing, the text of second Peter, the text of St. Jude's
Epistle are very close. And again, I'm not going to spend hours going into the
different ideas of the relationship between the two, but you find the same kind of
thing in Jude versus 6 and 7.
Yeah, we're also referring to this event. And just to hammer on it one more time,
These speak about angels.
plural sinning. I know there are some folks who disagree with us about what we
presented about they're not having been this sort of fall of the devil and a
whole bunch of angels before the world was created. I won't go into that again.
But even if you hypothesize that that's the case, that's not talked about
anywhere in the Old Testament. Yeah. So then you're saying.
Well, okay, Saint Peter and Saint Judah are referring to something that's not in the Old Testament.
And so then I'll say, okay, show me that in Jewish literature from the second temple period.
And it's not there.
The only thing that's there in terms of an angelic rebellion where the rebels are imprisoned
is this tradition that you see recorded in the book of Enoch that you see alluded to in Genesis
chapters four and six, right, and the origin of the giants.
So.
We've already got a, we've at least shown that the view we're talking about.
We went through the Old Testament in some detail.
We've now talked about the New Testament.
So when you get to, for example, St. Irenaeus on the Apostolic preaching.
So on the Apostolic preaching, St. Irenaeus is summarizing the preaching of the apostles.
Okay.
What they taught.
Yes.
So we've got a quote here.
from this is from chapter 18 of On the Apostolic Preaching, St. Irenaeus. And for a very long
while wickedness extended in spread and reached and laid hold upon the whole race of mankind until
a very small seed of righteousness remained among them. And illicit unions took place upon the
earth since angels were united with the daughters of the race of mankind and they bore to them sons
who for their exceeding greatness recalled giant.
and the angels brought us presents to their wives, teachings of wickedness, and that they brought them the virtues of roots and herbs, dying in colors and cosmetics, the discovery of rare substances, love, potions, aversions, a mores,
Cucupacins, constraints of love, spells of bewitchment, and all sorcery and idolatry hateful to God,
by the entry of which things into the world evil extended and spread, while righteousness was diminished.
And in...
feeble. So pretty clearly St. Irenaeus taking exactly the view that we just described.
And he's not just saying he personally holds this view. Yeah. He's saying this is what the
Apostles taught. And he is the spiritual grandson of St. John the Evangelist. Right. Yeah.
Because his teacher, as he says, was polycarp and polycarp was the disciple of John.
So he was at a position to know at least to know that.
than me. And this is mid what mid second century early second century mid mid second century.
Yeah. So he's within 60 years of the death of the last apostle. Yeah. And this isn't isolated.
St. Justin martyr in the second century. Same thing. Even into the third century, we see the same thing.
the third century we were primarily talking about origin and tertulia and yes who are
saints and so that's why I'm not quoting them and linked about it.
Tertullian actually thought the book of Enic was canonical
and
Origin did at the beginning of his career and then
said well things are kind of swinging against it. This interesting thing happened in early church history where
in the
second and first half of the third centuries
A lot of people work sure if St. Jude...
epistle was canonical. Right. And people may know St. Jude's epistle actually quotes the book of
Enic, right, as prophecy says that Eden is a prophet and said this, right. And so people actually
argued from the book of Enic for the canonicity of St. Jude's epistle and then about halfway through
the second century. And Origin talks about this because it was happening during his lifetime.
that flipped and by
that time almost everyone had accepted Saint Jude's epistle.
And so from there on people start arguing for the book of
Enoch based on Saint Jude having quoted it.
That's cool.
Yeah.
And just so people can look up where this is,
this is in verse 14 of Jude.
Is where this is.
That equals.
You begin quoting Enoch.
Yep.
Yeah.
And these things are referenced on the plates.
So obviously the book, the book of Enoch does not end up
Be-
part of the canon unless you're Ethiopian, right? And the reason for that is that Ethiopian Christianity
at its earliest stage, they didn't, sometimes when I mentioned the Ethiopian canon people will say,
well they're non-Calcedodonians, so they don't count, right? But, you know, they didn't, they didn't
change the contents of their Bible after the Council of Calcy. Yeah. Right? This is what they always
guys that because the
Ethiopian Jews considered it authoritative.
Their Old Testament canon is the canon of Ethiopian Jews,
right, that they adopted,
so they had this continuous line of it.
And so that continues though in the church
all the way up until in the ninth century,
You have um
George and Kellos were so we're in the Byzantine period and he describes
first Enoch, the book of what we call first Enoch, the book of Enoch, as being an
apostolic apocryphon meaning, apocryphon meaning hidden, it's hidden in that we
don't read it publicly in the church. Yeah, not hidden in the sense of we keep
this locked away and evolved because no one's supposed to read this. Right, we
don't read it publicly. It's a book to be read in the
not in the churches, but apostolic because he believed it preserves part of the
apostolic preaching as St. Irenaeus had said centuries beforehand and George
St. Kellos when he writes his his his chronicle of world history talks about the
exact same thing that St. Irenaeus talked about with the angels and the humans so
he still holds this position in addition to still seeing the value of the book of
and it's
Apostolic connection. So we're about to talk about the view that sort of comes to predominance
among the church fathers, but I wanted to make it clear that the view we've been describing that's the universal view of
the first
three centuries almost four centuries of the church
doesn't just go away. It isn't that everyone rejects it. Yeah
Yeah, yeah, well, and so what do we do with this idea that some people have would say well, you know?
like there were there were kiliasts in the early church, but eventually the church kind of
you know ruled against that and now we fully you know we don't believe in kiliism right so
so could we say that the church has rejected the depiction of giants and so forth that's given
in the inachic literature that we've been given we've been you know talking about has the church
rejected it and settled on something else right and and that's that's why it's so important to point
that this view still stays
around. Yeah right. Yeah and there's not and there's not like so there's there is
consular rejection of kiliasum right by virtue of the way that those creeds are written
so forth. There is no consular rejection of this reading of the giant story right.
Right. Yeah the idea that there's a that you know the the orthodox church has very few dogmas.
The idea that one of them is a particular interpretation of Genesis 6 1 through 4 is kind of silly
on the face. Yeah, and honestly, I mean...
every posca, every posca, there's that canon that's sung, it's actually the canon of Holy
Saturday, but it gets then repeated during the midnight office or the nocturns of posca,
and which, you know, it talks about the Passover and the Exodus, and it describes Pharaoh
as being this persecuting giant of old, right?
So it's interesting that this language is in...
are liturgical texts. It's there, right? Yeah, I've said references to watchers and yeah, yeah.
Yeah. Now, I did see a transaction that text, which actually refers to the persecuting
Pharaoh of old, which I get why they use that, but it actually the word is giant. The word is
giant. That's what's in there. You know, there are some there are some recentials of it that say
tyrant but as we were saying that's a synonym right yeah
Yeah, so the other view that comes to predominance is actually the rabbinic Jewish view.
Yep.
That's where it originates.
It originates of rabbinic Judaism because, and I know we've mentioned this on the show
before, but there's this huge problem in Western theology caused by the assumption that the
quote unquote Jews of any given period of history.
are identical to the rabbinic Jews in your local synagogue.
Right. Right. Right.
And that's just not the rabbinic Judaism is something that really comes into existence
between the second and fifth centuries and is only codified in the fifth and sixth centuries
with the Talmud. Right.
And it's a reaction, the Talmud, any Talmudic scholar, go ask an Orthodox Jewish Talmudic scholar,
or they'll tell you that a lot of
the Talmud is a reaction to the Christian tradition that had emerged. Right. Right. So the particular
rabbinic interpretation of this that we're going to talk about briefly now is that the so-called
sons of God in Genesis 6 are not angels, are not angelic beings contrary to what the Septuagint
says about them, contrary to all these other stuff that we've just been mentioning, but are actually
descendants of Seth, Seth, the son of Adam and Eve. And so then the notion of him being a son of God is
more metaphorical than a different than an angelic reference. And then that's what happens is that
there's this intermarrying between descendants of Seth and descendants of Keen. And then that's
what this is about so it's not about and often it's put
It's this interpretation is put for because there's a
idea like, well, how could demons, you know,
interbreed with human beings?
And that essentially just shows ignorance
of what the Nephilim ritual actually involved,
which is that there's, you know,
from a material point of view, like if you were to sort of
videotape the thing, and again,
this is why we give this trigger warning for parents
at the beginning, if you were to videotape the ritual,
you would see two human beings engaging in fornication.
You know, you wouldn't necessarily visibly see a demon involved in this.
But, you know, saying, well, you know, demons can't hybridize with human beings is a misunderstanding
of what that ritual actually involves, because it just suggests that there's two beings
involved, a human woman and, you know, a fallen angel.
And that's because of a reading of Genesis 6 where these other details, which are not
mention there are not taken into account, but as we've mentioned...
there is all kinds of evidence that this is what was going on.
Again, that these,
they're regarded as being two thirds divine, right?
That means that there's three beings involved
in their conception.
So, all right, well, let's talk about that a little bit.
Yeah, so the non-Christian Jewish communities
ended up rejecting all of the Anachic literature,
all of the literature from their own tradition
that recorded this...
part of the tradition. Right. And they did this in the second and third centuries and we have second and third century church fathers who talk about how the the Jews had rejected, for example, the book of Enic because it was too Christian.
That's literally how they phrase it. So this is based in a repute. This is how Christians were taking it pretty much universally as we just said. And so the Jewish community said repudiated that.
and came up with what's called this
It's a thite hypothesis sometimes in the literature
that it's the line of Seth and the line of King.
This gets adopted by the first,
very first sort of church,
I mean Julius Afrocanos is not famous.
We'll put it that way.
He's, I think he's a church father,
but he's the first Christian to sort of adopt this.
And then we see it, we see it show up in Saint Ephraim,
Syrian.
the East and then St. Augustine in the West. So we're talking about like the very late, very
end of the fourth century, very beginning of the fifth century, where this first appears
in Christian writings. Right. Right. And just to help people date, so sexist, Julius
Afro-Connus, not to be confused with Julius Afro-Connus, who was an earlier person. Yeah, so this
This is a Christian, right?
The earlier one was not a Christian.
He was born the year 160 and dies in 240.
So, you know, he's writing relatively late second century, early third century.
Right.
Yeah.
He's the earliest data point we have for this view.
He's a Libyan.
Right.
And so when it starts to, when you get prominent people, St. Ephraim and St. Augustine, St. Ephraim's
at the end of the fourth and and
St. Augustine is writing at the beginning of the fifth and that's when the
View kind of goes mainstream
Because yeah because of their influence right and it comes to become the
predominant view
among the church fathers
Now that said St. Augustine as we already mentioned has certain problems like he doesn't know what to do with that reference to the days of Noah
He also has this
Weird ambivalent discussion
of the book of Enic because he says, well, okay, St. Jude says Enic is a prophet and he wrote this and it's a quote from the book of Enic, so Enic wrote something.
Right? And at least some of what's in the book of Enic must be that.
And so he tries to argue that, well, you know, the book of Enic then is so old, it comes from before the flood.
and you get people like Saint Jerome who say to Gus its contempor-
giving protracted arguments about how the book of Enic would have survived the flood.
Like, well, Noah must have had a copy.
Yeah.
Not the arc by Ed which is copy from there.
Right.
Which still seems like extreme special pleading, but for the fathers, this was, you know,
so say to us and say this must represent this text we have now, must represent Enics work,
but he says, look, that makes it so old.
You know, we can't verify what in this text we have now.
actually comes from Enic and what doesn't. And then he makes this circular
argument where he says, you know, you can't trust this story about the watchers
about these sinful angels in the book of Enic, right? Because not everything in
the book of Enic is true and goes back to Enic. And so you say to him, well, what's
an example of something that's not true and doesn't go back to Enic? And he says,
well, the watcher's story. Yeah. Right. Right. It's untrustworthy because it has
stuff like this story in it so you can't believe this
right? This is a circuit argument. So he has some, he has some problems even getting this view for it. But there are more basic problems with this view.
For example, it doesn't make sense of the Old Testament data because, okay, before the flood, the line of Seth and the line of Cain, intermingle, somehow that makes giants.
Yeah, right. Who are who are
impressive enough in some way that when the people of Israel show up to
Canaan that despise.
There's even there yet.
Yeah, right.
Before the flood still.
Yeah, okay.
Yeah.
But yeah, right.
Exactly.
Before the flood.
Yeah.
But I mean, the point is is that when people see giants in the Old Testament,
they're freaked out by them.
Right.
That this has some kind of impressive element.
I don't know why marrying your sort of distant cousin from a different child of
Adam would do anything like that.
Yeah, right.
Right.
Then you also have the rules.
You know, you have the problem after the flood of, okay, so did the line of cane and the
line of Seth survive the flood independently somehow and then mingle again.
So you get more giants to make the Nephilim after the flood.
Yeah.
Right?
Like, well, then how does that work?
Right.
So Old Testament wise, it doesn't make a lot of sense.
Yeah.
I remember reading that, um...
there is some passage that and I think we should spend a moment or two on this because I know
you did some research about this. There is some passage in St. John Chrysostom where he takes the
Sethite view. Is he actually is that actually his view? Yeah well there's it's hard to know for
sure. Okay so why is it hard to know that? If he does take that view right he's taking that view
around 412413.
So relatively late so compared to so this is after this post St. Ephraim post St Augustine right so
It's reasonable. It's reasonable that he would have taken that view
Then he would have taken that view right the place where he really takes that view and spells it out
um
Is in a set of homilies where
There are a lot of theories because he he's got two sets of
of families on Genesis.
And scholars disagree about how those relate to each other.
A lot of people argue that he gave both and tried to make one the earlier set and one the later set.
So it's sort of a revision or they'll say one represents notes taken by a different person on the same homilies.
The dating in the early fifth century is secured.
But there are also a significant number of people and these people include
St. Phodius the Great is notes on the library at Constantinople who think that what are now considered
to be the later homilies weren't St. John Chrysostom or at least reflect another hand that someone else
came and revised them. So it's very possible St. John Chrysostom held this view. I'm not arguing that he
didn't. It's also very possible that
We don't know what view he held and this was sort of expanded upon by a later editor of his homilies.
And certainly you go later in the fifth century, sixth century.
There are plenty of people who held the Seth Eid hypothesis who could have done that.
Right.
But so it's not a slam dunk to you.
So the point being that it's not a slam dunk to use this text from Chris Osamie say,
well, that's what Chris Osamie view was and that's it.
Yeah, and therefore that's right.
right? Yeah, absolutely. Yeah, yeah, against all the other, all the other, that's a methodological
problem on top of everything else. Yeah. So in addition to, to this view not working with
the Old Testament, view doesn't work with the New Testament, right? Those passages we just
read in 1st and 2nd Peter and Jude, as we already talked about a little, who are these
angels then? Yeah. Right. Why were they after strange flesh? Right. It just kind of creates
these
sort of dangling bits that then aren't integrated into the rest of the Old Testament narrative
that has then commented on in the New Testament.
Right. So then the last piece as we talked about is, okay, well, so then either side has to
explain why the other group of fathers got it wrong. Right. In other words, all the, yeah, like why,
okay, if they did get it wrong, then at least let's understand how they could have possibly gotten
that wrong because
You can't just sort of leave it leave it there, you know, right? Yeah, right. We're not gonna say any of the fathers
Didn't know what they were talking about. We're not gonna say that any of the fathers were dumb
Yeah, right right. Yeah, right. Yeah, so
I will leave it to someone who holds to the Seth I'd hypothesis to explain to me how all of the earliest church fathers most closely connected
The Apostles got it wrong. That's up to them. I don't know how you would do that
But right I won't I won't straw
and them by making an argument and defeating it.
I'll let them put that forward.
But I will put forward that it's very clear how the later
fathers beginning at the end of the fourth and
beginning of the fifth century and onward would have not
understood what was going on.
Because what we find, first of all is the fathers who start
We start moving to the satellite hypothesis are all approach
the other view as being an angel appears to a human woman has intercourse with her, she gets pregnant
and has a baby that's half angel half human. Right. And they're saying that's not possible because
angels don't have bodies that could reproduce with human bodies. That could reproduce. So in other
words, the thing that they're rejecting is not even what the ancient tradition is. Right. Right.
They're rejecting that.
They miss someone to propose that.
Yeah.
Right.
And we did the child warning, so I'll go ahead and say it.
Their issue was not about the sexuality,
their issue was about the reproduction,
because St. Augustine, for example,
demonstrably believed in incubi and succubi.
Right.
And so that was at the part they thought was impossible.
It was the reproduction part.
But so that's not what the tradition was claiming.
So first of all, they're rejecting that.
Now, why wouldn't they know what the tradition was actually
claiming Saint John Caching, who's one
of the people in the fifth century who takes the Seth Adhypothesis gives us a really good
clue.
Say, John Cashin, who's a saint who's very important to me and who I respect a great deal,
but disagree with about this.
When he's talking about how you know the Seth Adhypothesis is right and the other isn't,
because he's writing in the early fifth century there's this, the pre-proposomative view is
the one he's not taking at the time he's writing.
He says, well, if this is what happened, why isn't it still happening now?
Right, right. That's his question. And we've gotten a lot of questions.
A lot of what we talk about this about, well, could this happen now? Right, right.
So he's asking the same question, but he's saying, look, this doesn't seem to be happening now.
if that's what happened before why isn't it?
And the answer to St. John.
is well, yeah, it wasn't happening in the province where he lived, right? It wasn't happening
in Marseille where his monastery of Saint Victor was. It was happening in Mesoamerica and
in China and Japan and in so so mayor empire. He didn't see it happening. So that yeah, so
He was looking at a fundamentally different set of data.
than what the earliest church fathers were.
And because they're living in different times,
and John Cassian lives in a time in which Christianity
has conquered a lot of the world,
whereas the earliest fathers are living in times.
Like, for instance, Justin Martyr writes these apologies
to the emperor to try to explain Christianity,
at least partly to try to convince the emperor
kill so many Christians.
because that's his way. He's living in a pagan world in which Christianity is a little minority.
So he's surrounded by pagans doing pagan things, including probably the Nefelim ritual.
Right. These rituals, mystery cults, they're offering sacrifices to the emperor as a God king.
Right. This is all, this is, this is very real to him. He sees this all happening. Right. And so
he has it under saying what this is talking about.
out.
St. John Cash and had never seen an animal sacra.
take place, right? And so that changes your perspective. Paganism, Paganism really started
dying at the beginning of the second century AD, or the beginning of the third century,
I'm sorry, the beginning of the third century, beginning of the two hundred AD. And that
was for two reasons, number one, Christianity was just clearly ascendant in the Roman Empire.
And in.
the old pagan rights weren't fulfilling.
And so what you see is paganism
start trying to Christianize itself to compete.
So you see this in neo-platonism?
Right.
It's just trying to Christianize plate-nism.
Yeah.
Or Julian the Apostate wishing that pagans
were basically moral in the way the Christians are moral?
Yeah, in the fourth century.
He's the last gasp of trying to turn the clock back.
Yeah.
But you see this in all these nost-
sex that arise are just attempts to Christianize mystery religions and different
cultic ritual aspects of pagan religion. Sort of put a Christian peneer on them to
try to get that audience. Someone in our Facebook group posted some quotes
from Hermes Travis Justice from the Hermetic literature from the third century
from the same period which is very clearly adopting all of these Christian
language and Christian ideas, did this kind of quasi-nostic frame.
work they're trying to compete. And part of that was by the middle of about the
third century, animal sacrifice starts dropping off. So, uh, St. Constantine
apparently, even before converting to Christianity was not a big fan of
animal sacrifice. He just thought it was kind of gross and repugnant. Interesting.
And sort of sort of sub moral. And so when he became Christian, he instantly sort
of did away with it in terms of the military and the imperial part of the
religion.
So that he wouldn't have to do it anymore.
And we should emphasize that it's these rituals that are what make paganism go.
Like this is the engine that drives it and not just in a sense of like, you know,
this is social bonds or whatever, although it's that too. But, but,
but when people stop interacting with demons in the way that is the most effective,
then it weakens the demons influence over them.
Right. Yep. Right. They're not worshiping them anymore.
Now they're sort of opining.
they're trying to draw moral lessons that are moral along the line of Christian morality
than pagan morality from Homer, for example, which is a fundamentally different thing than
classical paganism.
And so in the fourth century, paganism is fighting its last gasps.
St. John Crisostom's rhetoric teacher was literally a member of the last pagan gem,
generation in the Roman Empire.
And they basically give it up hope.
They were just kind of sticking to their guns and being
contrairions about not wanting to embrace Christianity.
Yeah.
So there's this parallel development.
On the one hand, you have the death of paganism going on.
And pretty much in parallel with that,
then this rise of misunderstanding where Nephilim come from.
and therefore rejecting that.
misunderstanding that we see reflected in some of the church fathers.
Right. And they're trying to address it at a metaphysical level of like how could you have
interspecies reproduction, right? Rather than in this ritual and religious context.
Yeah. All right. Okay. So we just wanted to, before we finish, and I know this has been a
Mando long episode, but you love it. All of you listeners.
There's a slipper side. This is been the one you've been waiting for. I know.
But before we close, I don't...
wanted to take a couple of questions that were sent to us. So this first one is a
message that was left for us by Father Fotius. So I'm going to go ahead and play
this one now. Hi, this is Father Fotius Avant from St. Sava, Orthodox Church in
Allen, Texas, and I have a few questions. Are giants recognizable only by their
size or is it more by their violent and terrible deeds? Also are giants by
virtue of their.
demonic parentage and or intimate influence beyond the scope of redemption.
And finally, are there giants amongst today?
And if so, how do we deal with them?
Okay.
Well, we've kind of addressed most of what Father Fautius says, but the one, the two,
maybe that are kind of left dangling a little bit are, can giants repent?
And then also, are they potentially around today?
What do we do about that?
So, all right, so let's take them into that,
or can giants repent?
Is that possible?
Well, we talked about how, you know,
if you leave the giant clan,
you're no longer a member of the giant clan.
Yeah.
Right, so it's a kind of a citizenship almost.
If you're, if you're ritually admitted
to another community that's constituted by another ritual,
right, so the sort of answer is yes.
If there's a giant clan somewhere right now
that's doing these rituals, right?
Someone who's a person of that is not-
like irredeemable, right? They're still alive and they're still human no matter how far gone,
how far down that road they may be. They could be baptized into Christ, they could come and receive
the Eucharist, they can be Christian and experience theosis, right? In terms of are there giants
today and how should we deal with them.
So if we take that
Seriously, in terms of what we've been talking about,
we'd be talking about a human being who's not just
like they're demonically possessed,
but a human being who has become demonic,
who has become demonized like fully, right?
And so we'd be talking about,
I don't wanna be graphic.
I've met someone like this in a prison setting.
someone who is not even really human anymore, who's committed acts, the kind of things we're talking
about involving the killing of children, the torture of cannibalism. So if we're talking about
someone like this, and this is a person who has no interest in anything related to the gospel,
right? Then as controversial as what I'm about to say may be...
This is why civilizations still have the death penalty.
Right, and when someone like that receives the death penalty,
I mean when the Orthodox Church talks about the death penalty,
if you read for example the social statement
of the Russian Church, it is a good thing
to not make use of the death penalty in that it can sometimes
give a longer opportunity for repentance to someone and so that makes that
element a good thing. But the Orthodox Church has never declared the death penalty
as such unjust. Because to allow that kind of person to continue with that
kind of evil is unjust in and of itself. Yeah. To produce more victims and bring
more horror into the world.
Okay. Okay, so we got a question over email from Ian in Charleston, West Virginia.
And Ian wrote this, presupposing the existence of giants based on the literary evidence in
the Holy Scriptures, is there likewise physical evidence to further prove their existence
beyond the Scriptures? I remember in a previous episode that you mentioned the archaeological
find of a large metal bed used in pagan rituals that was used by a giant king, but do fossil
records or even
more interestingly DNA evidence exist. Furthermore, do giants constitute a different species from mankind,
or from a very materialistic point of view, are still human, but are the result of a variant
allele to a gene, like in the case of a conjo plaziam, I have to look it up, through the interaction
of demons. I think in works in the medical field, if I remember correctly.
Yeah, and we actually got a number of questions that are like this and I really
We call that there was in one of our earliest episodes, we actually had someone call in
that unfortunately did not get through who wanted to ask about, you know, gigantic fossils
being found.
So this is kind of related to that as well.
Now, I mean, we talked about how giants are not necessarily large, physically large human
beings.
So that kind of answers some of this.
Do they have a different DNA?
Um, well, let me first say before I answer that briefly.
Oh, yeah.
I want to heartily endorse Ian from Charleston, West Virginia.
Very good.
I'll read you.
He is a great, great guy.
Also shout out to Ian.
There you go.
Yeah.
And, uh, you know, Father Stephen and I both
served at that church there in Charleston, West Virginia,
although,
although Ian, I think you were still the kid when I was there,
but it's been a long time since I left.
Yeah.
Um,
but, uh, yeah, I mean, the answer,
we wouldn't expect to see a DNA difference.
Right.
necessarily because it's too human beings involved. Right. Right. Now, I mean if we're talking about giant
clans and you know with any social unit of people who are primarily marrying and reproducing
with each other, right, there would be common genetic factors but those genetic factors as we've
said aren't the basis for who's in and who's out of the clan. Right. Right. It's just something that
that would naturally happen over time.
Right.
So to give that a...
full and answers possible. So if you're looking for fossils that's kind of looking in the wrong place.
Yeah, you're digging in the wrong place.
Literally. Yeah. So yeah, I would say I don't have an explanation for for giant fossils.
Other than maybe they had like Marfan syndrome or I don't know, something like that.
We don't really have fossilized remains from the period we're talking to. Human skeletal remains
don't last that long.
So there we go.
So I hope that helps Ian.
And everyone, thank you very much everyone who sent in questions and comments,
whether you emailed it to us or sent it in via our SpeakPipe recording service.
I hope that this has been a interesting.
I know it's definitely been interesting for me discussion.
So let's just let's give some some closing remarks.
And I think I'll I'll go first.
You know, I entered into this discussion of giants.
I mean, not today necessarily, but when I first started trying to understand it,
kind of along the lines when Father Steven says people get excited when I talk about giants,
because it is kind of exciting. It's really just a fascinating
element in scripture, especially when you decide to actually take it seriously.
But on the other hand, I think that the personal journey that I went through and trying to
understand this subject.
I went from starting out thinking, okay, here's a really weird obscure thing.
Let's figure out what it means.
You know, so at least I can make an account for it.
To, you know, understanding gradually that we're actually talking about a major overarching
theme of the scriptures that actually have to do with, you know, David and the Lord Jesus
Christ.
And, you know, it's huge.
It's just, it's a big, big arc within Scripture.
And...
And that alone should make it something that we tried to understand.
The other thing that's been very valuable for me was dealing with the fact that church
fathers didn't have the same views on this and understanding what that means and how
to account for that and what to do about it, which just as kind of a meta issue, helps
us to understand the way to read the church fathers.
We can't.
treat them as a kind of set of proof texts or a closed canon kind of in and of themselves.
And I find that to be very valuable as well because there are sometimes some Orthodox people
who treat the church fathers the way that Soluscript or Appartisans treat the Bible. And that's not
the correct way to read the church fathers. So I just wanted to say that for me personally that
that this discussion, not just
in this episode, but the discussion that I've been having now for a few years trying to understand
this has been a really valuable one for me of personal growth and understanding the Holy
Scriptures and in understanding the rest of Orthodox tradition and I'm just very, very grateful
for it on a personal level. Father Stephen? Yeah, I think, you know, uh,
But nerdery aside, and I clearly am one because I consider reading, you know, Eugury the
ritual tap.
and picking through Esau's genealogy to be fun and exciting ways to spend an afternoon.
But beyond that, Nurtury, why is this important at all?
Why is this important to the orthodox faith or theology?
Other than just, hey, it's interesting and fun and neat.
I think this actually goes to the core, what we've been talking about today.
goes to the core of what salvation is.
And
But here's how I think that is.
My father used to tell me about my grandfather that at one point my father was watching the
Nuremberg trials on television which were the trials of Nazi war criminals.
sort of the most demonically evil humans, you know, of our era.
And...
My father asked my grandfather what he thought about, what had happened and these trials.
And my grandfather's response was there but for the grace of God, go I.
And usually when we say that, we say that about some misfortune someone has suffered.
Someone has ended up homeless, someone has ended up bankrupt.
Someone has died at a young age.
We say, oh, there for the grace of God, go I, it's God's grace that I have, the things
I have.
But my grandfather was saying that about becoming a Nazi war criminal.
He was saying that about becoming this sort of immoral monster who would murder other people
and mass and do these other things.
And this is how the scriptures present the demonic and our sin as participation in the demonic.
Adam and Eve have disobeyed, God says it's not good that man should live forever.
Because if we had, if we'd live forever in that state, we would have been just like the demons,
immortal and immoral, immortal and evil.
And so God gives us this life in this world and our mortality and our repentance
to prevent us from suffering that fate.
A lot of time
are Western Christian friends, present salvation as, well, God has these laws. We've broken those laws.
So he's angry at us or he's compelled by his attribute of justice. He has to punish those
violations of the law. And so Christ comes to save us from that. So God has to save us from
himself or save us from one of his attributes.
save us from his own justice.
Well, that's what the Scriptures say.
The Scriptures say that Christ came to save us from our sins
because our sins are destroying us.
Our sins are turning us into these demonic monsters
if we keep going down that path.
So the truth we have here when we look at these giants
who are the far end of where that road leads
who represent someone not become like God
God but become like the demons.
dehumanized and inhuman. We see where the path of sin leads and it shows us that in reality
Christ came to save us from ourselves. And it gives us a clarity of exactly what that means.
So I think this is important beyond all the history and the tying things together in the Old Testament
and understanding some of the hymns of the church.
That's the core.
That's the
core that despite our sin and wickedness which is deliberate despite our throwing in our lot
with these demonic spirits who rebel against and hate God Christ still loved us enough
to come and die and rescue us redeem us and buy us back so that we could become sons of God as we've
talked about in previous episodes this shows us the other side we talked about past episodes what
but received.
to what we're saved for.
This is what we're saved from.
Oh man.
Well, that is our show for tonight.
Thank you for listening.
If you didn't get a chance to call in
during one of our live broadcasts,
we'd still love to hear from you,
either via email at LordofSpiritsatEachAndFate.com
or you can message us at our LordofSpirits Podcast
Facebook page or you can leave a message for us
at our SpeakPie page.
We read everything, listen to everything,
but can't respond to everything.
I'm sorry about that.
In volume.
So we do save what you send for possibly use in future episodes.
And join us for our live broadcasts on the second and fourth Thursdays of the month at
7pm Eastern 4pm Pacific.
And don't forget to like our Lord of Spirits podcast, Facebook page while you're at it.
Join our Facebook discussion group, leave a recommendation, and invite all your friends.
And if you leave a review on Apple Podcasts, Facebook or wherever you get your podcasts,
then that raises the visibility of the show and gets more people connected.
Finally, be sure to go to ancient faith.
Thank you very much and God bless.
thousand and thousands of thousands, saying with a loud voice, worthy is the land that was
slain to receive power and riches and wisdom and strength and honor and glory and blessing.
Revelation chapter 5 verses 11 through 12.