He will be a staff for the righteous with which for them to stand and not to fall.
And he will be the light of the nations and the hope of those whose hearts are troubled.
All who dwell on the earth will fall down and worship him,
and they will praise and bless and celebrate with song the Lord of Spirits,
1st denoc, chapter 48, verses 4-5.
The modern world doesn't acknowledge but is nevertheless haunted by spirits, angels,
demons, and saints.
In our time.
many year into break free of the prison of a flat secular materialism to see and to
know reality as it truly is. What is this spiritual reality like? How do we
engage with it well? How do we permeate everyday life with spiritual presence?
Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung
host this live Colin show focused on enchantment in creation. The union of the
seen and unseen as made by God.
and experienced by mankind throughout history. Welcome to the Lord of Spirits.
Thank you, Voice of Steve. Well, it's goat week on the Lord of Spirits podcast.
I'm Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Emmaus Pennsylvania and joining me tonight is my co-host, Father
Stephen D'Young from Lafayette, Louisiana. And if you're listening to us live, you can call in at 855-8F radio.
that's 8552372346
and we will get to your calls in the second part of today's show. Well, like I said, it is goat week.
And here at goat week, we've got you covered. And the rest of the show will be explaining that joke.
So tonight we're wrapping up this three-part series on sacrifice by talking about atonement.
It's a word that is core to our understanding of Christianity, and yet there are about as many theories of atonement as there are Christian groups.
groups but where did this word come from? What does it mean? What is being a
toned for? Do Orthodox Christians have any teaching on a tonement? Well, again, we've got you covered.
And no, I will not get tired of that joke. But first, and this is where the English language nerd in me comes
leaping out. Let's talk about this English word, a tonement. Okay. So, Father Stephen, where is that word from?
Name that word? It's it's made up. Yeah. It's not just in the way that all words are made up. Right.
It's very deliberately made up.
Very deliberately invented to describe something that there wasn't really another good word in the English language for.
Yeah, it was created for English Bibles to translate a couple of words, one from Hebrew, one from Greek.
And what's fun about it is it actually
is so sometimes it gets explained as at one mint.
And that is correct.
Like that is not a false etymology.
Although usually etymologies that go like that are,
like they're just nonsense.
But you mean that butterflies aren't hurled dairy products?
They are not.
Okay.
And most people who have breakfast
are not breaking a fast.
But right, so atonement at one mint,
I look this up so I
have on my desk a gigantic dictionary called the Oxford English Dictionary for
those of you who know that what that is, you know who you are. And I looked
this up, what is the earliest use of this word? And it turns out that before
it ever got into the Bible, there was occasionally this contraction of the word
at and the word one. So you get at one, you know, or however, but would have
and pronounced back in like the 14th century.
And then.
So Wycliffe who translates the very earliest English Bible, well, I should say the
The very earliest complete English Bible
because you know
Tip of the hat to offer the great for transiting portions of the Gospels into Old English
But he he does his completed English Bible and he
uses that
phrase to one or one meant and then even one point he uses at one
right and then
it was in the 16th century in the Tindale Bible in 1526 that I actually standardizes
this word to create this new word atone for both as both a verb and also a noun.
So you get that at one meant atone comes into being as an English word specifically for translation of the Bible.
And so that's the idea that they meant at the time was, you know...
putting man and God together at one. That was the intention. So now we're going to talk about how
number one, they actually didn't quite get it right. But what is the concept that that word
is attempting to point to? What are the actual original words? So in the Orthodox Church, Greek is
kind of our base language for theology and liturgy and so forth. So where does that word?
the word, the Greek word that's translated by a tone or a tone meant, and where does that actually
first show up? Yeah, so this gets sort of double interesting because not only do we have the
made up English word, right? That is primarily reflecting, as you just described in English concept,
more than it is, trying to reflect an original word. The reason for that is that the Greek word
Elystereo.
doesn't occur anywhere that we still possess until Jewish folks start using it,
meaning the Greek Old Testament and then works like Philo, Josephus, etc.
They're sort of a handful, I think, four or five uses of it in the first century AD
and later, and like half of those are by Plutarch by one author.
But all of it
The earliest usages are of that word in this context having anything to do with this are
Jewish writers using it to translate the Hebrew concept, which partially explains why
when the English translators got to the Greek word they didn't really know what to do with
it, right?
Yeah, yeah, right.
So they just kind of perpetuated what had...
been done before like, well, there is no context for this.
What do we think this means in context?
Right.
And through theology that had developed in Latin,
they had an idea of what that was supposed to mean,
or what it had come to mean, theologically.
And so they were really translating that.
So you have to go back past the Greek a little bit.
by the way those those handful of
later Greek usages seem to be based on the Jewish use of it, meaning it's used in contexts
where someone is making some kind of offering to a supernatural being, to a spiritual being.
And I say spiritual being because it includes in a couple cases its gods and in a couple cases
its dead people.
Yeah, right.
It's of deceased people where there has been some issue between them and a living person
and so some sort of offering is made.
to mend a peace offering.
Right, to mend that relationship.
But so if we go back then to the Semitic root
that's behind all this,
it you end up with what are called kefir verbs.
Semitic words, Semitic lexemes have
what are called trilateral roots,
meaning they're based on three consonants.
Right.
And you give the verb meaning or the noun meaning by the way it's inflected, meaning literally
the way it's pronounced because they did write the vowels at all.
Yeah, and I mean, most Semitic languages work this way.
So if any of our listeners are Arabic speakers, which I know some are, it's again, those three
consonants make up pretty much everywhere in Arabic.
Right.
And then you can add prefixes and suffixes and that kind of thing.
you have a root that is three letters.
And so the kefir roots usually transliterated as KFR
is a group of words that primarily means to cover the verb forms.
So it's not like the Slavic word that has to do with
a gross tasting bubbling beverage. No, it has nothing to do with it.
Nothing. Nothing to do. Nothing to do. As far as I know.
Yeah, we
We actually we looked this up and we could find no link but who knows you know Richard Rowland
I'm gonna give you this job. So look this up Richard. He's our our staff philologist
So maybe it was once used to cover something I don't know
Covered the taste of bad food. I don't know
but
Nothing against you Kevver drinkers. Sorry, no no enjoy what you like some people like new coke you know
So, bridge.
Now it turns out was all a conspiracy, but I won't be here.
It was.
That was so wild.
We're really dating ourselves with that reference.
Yeah.
So the sort of subsidiary meanings of cover then, if definition number one of Geffer Verbs
is cover, then your secondary ones would be like wipe or smear if you're covering something
with something else, right?
Yeah.
to cover your roof with pitch or what have you.
right, you would wipe it or smear it in order to cover it,
cover it all with paint, right?
And so then logically enough,
when you find this in its noun form, right,
these same roots are used for both verbs and nouns
and also for adjectives.
When it's a noun, it means a cover or a covering.
Like a lid, right, yeah.
Yeah, it's the top, yeah.
which brings it to, you know.
I give and I take away and I gave you your OED
Thank you.
And now I'm gonna take away your KJV.
Oh, brutal.
So, yes.
I think that's a debt loss to you, frankly.
Yeah, I do.
I will say I acknowledge the King James Bible
has some errors in it, you know,
translation errors.
And we just lost all of our KJV only listeners,
Yes.
the one just bathed us across the South have just you know to retune their car radios away
from AFR.
And are this like that?
Yeah right.
Right.
That used to come through on my microphone.
Yeah.
So right.
So here's the thing right that the King James Bible translate translates this word.
When it's used for in the now form right when it's used for the thing that is on the top
the arc of-
the covenant as mercy seat. Yes. Which is lovely, you know, like it's lovely. It's a very nice idea.
Yeah. But completely wrong. And you see it in, you'll see it in even Orthodox translations because
a lot of our early Orthodox translations were either utilizing or aping the King James version.
Language. And so you could kind of see how you get there. Like if you go from a very developed
the
theological idea right where you don't really know what the Hebrew word means and so you're thinking well, okay
God is enthroned behind the Ark of the Covenant right between the Cherubim and the Ark of the Covenant is his footstool
So there's like a throne involved there and
We're thinking of a tone man is at one man and peace and mercy
see so you come up with this mercy seat thing.
But the much simpler way to read it is just it means cover. So it's about the cover the lid of the art of the covenant that has the
Cherubin. Alas.
Another another fun thing from Sonny's school ruined by Steven D'Young. So that was kind of over translated right?
That was a lot of more advanced theological concepts were packed back into the word
cut.
In light of this though, I would like to propose that from now on we refer to cover bands.
There we go.
Like brass against and cybertronic spray, we refer to cover bands as atonement bands.
Yes.
I'm Ian.
Or even Mercy seat bands if we have to be really old school.
You could just call your band Mercy seat and like, well, we'll recover band just like
the title says.
That would be like an inception.
Yeah.
Okay.
Uh.
So, yeah, so that's the word itself.
Yeah, it's important to cover that because reading a lot of things back into that word did
not stop with the King James translators doing their best and sort of didn't know any better.
It is very common for all kinds of...
Shall we say?
advanced theological ideas that have come into being over time through a long history of development,
to all be read back into usually the Greek word in the New Testament.
In the Stedion.
Because of this sort of schism in the way we bizarrely separate scholarship of the New Testament
from the Old Testament.
So Greek words in the New Testament are treated as the sort of independent
entities without reference to what they're there translating.
And then that allows you to pack a whole bunch of things in.
But we'll see more of that as we go on.
But as we go to reiterate here that, that this is not in its biblical usage,
any kind of specialized technical theological term.
Right. Right.
This is just a Hebrew, especially it's just...
the word that means what it says, that, you know,
it needs cover.
And the Greek word that's being used is being used
to pick up that meaning within a ritual context.
Got you, right.
So, all right, so speaking of that ritual context,
then the rest of what we're gonna be talking about
is the ritual of atonement, the day of atonement.
So in Hebrew that's Yom Kippur, right?
which is this
annual commemoration that's made by the people of God in ancient Israel.
It's an addition to the regular sin offerings that are being done every day.
Why does this need to be added on? Don't the daily offerings cover it? Sorry, I will not get tired.
I will not. Yeah, don't the daily offerings current. Yeah, so why why what do you what do we?
need this for, right? If, I mean, we're doing daily offerings, you know, for sin in the
NH and Israel, what's the date? What's the deal with this super big day of offering, you
know? Right. And, and as a quick note, because you said it quickly, Yom Kapoor, the Kapoor
comes from Kepher. Yeah, you go. The day that's the cover. Yeah. When, when, when a pay gets
double that gets pronounced like a P instead of an F. Oh God, that's what you're usually written with two
Peace.
So yeah, it's literally the day of covering.
Right.
And if you read a lot of recent Old Testament scholarship because of how low did the word
atonement has become, they try to call it something else.
It's never going to catch on.
Like, no one's going to call it the day of pergation.
Right?
Like, it just doesn't ever ring to it.
So it's always here to stay.
Yeah, so we have, we talk, as we talk about last time.
The sin offerings that are being offered every day are not transactional.
Right. Right. Right.
It's not like the priests are sitting there waiting, you know, like I get to the end of
Espers and sit and wait to see if anybody's going to come to confession.
They weren't like that, right? They were sitting there with the knife and, you know,
keep the fire going in the burn offering altar because somebody might show up with them.
Yeah, someone comes in. So what did you do, pal? Yeah. Yeah. Yeah.
pigeon, a lamb, and...
which is not the way confession works either by the way in case anyone's
speaking that like wait what yeah no it doesn't know in fact there's a
wonderful parallel actually in some ways between these things yeah right and
you especially don't need to bring any livestock to the church let's be clear
on that yes please in fact it's canonically forbidden to bring livestock
into the church yep yep so this is a transactional so it's not an issue of like
Oh well, maybe there are
some sins that got missed during the year. So we're going to do the sort of catch all
day of atonement like to pick up those ones that were missed. Those were being done perpetually
to cover all of the sinning that was going on, that everyone knew was going on in Israel.
So when we look at the day of atonement, we have to start with the fact that it is doing something
different than the syn offerings are doing. Yeah, right, because there is not just
the problem of the sins of the people, right? There's the effect that those sins have on not just
the people, right? And I think this is, and this is a great thing for us to mention, especially here,
because our next couple of episodes are going to be on sacred geography. So we're going to be talking
about space in particular. There's an effect on the space on the place. Sin messes up the place
please worry
you are. Right? So that's what this is about, right?
And it briefly since you brought up the next two episodes about geography, I
know maps is going to be end up on the playlist. So let's make sure it's the
yeah, yeah, yeah, as and not maroon five. Special request. You know,
so right, so it has to do with when the ritual is described in Leviticus 16,
I know everyone knew that off the top of their head because...
Yeah, I mean people just keep reading Leviticus right that's like everyone's evening devotional reading right there on the tip of everyone's tongue at all times is
The structure of Leviticus but it's in Leviticus 16 and the purpose of it
We often think of it in terms of well, this is a toning for people or for Israel
And the bad stuff they did right but
but the ritual is explicitly
stated to be atoning for the altar of incense,
atoning for the ark of the covenant,
atoning for the space within the tabernacle.
Yeah, which makes no sense if you think atone
means like make up for or pay off or whatever,
or kind of some kind of satisfaction theology.
Like what did the altar do that it has to atone?
You know, what did the 10th?
Yeah, yeah, right.
The altar has to be reconciled to God.
you know, like it makes no sense.
But if we understand it as covering
and you know, which is the perfect word
because we're about to talk about what this actually does.
But the concept is based on this idea
that there is sacred space that has been set aside
and for the holiness of God to be present there
with the people.
but the
that the people sins interfere with that, right?
That they actually stain the place.
And then sin leaves a taint.
Yeah, yeah, just mark us.
We've talked about that there's kind of an anti-phiosis
right that happens.
Demonosis.
Through our sin, that actually changes us.
And it not only leaves that residue in that taint within us,
but within the people around us and in the the the
physical creation itself. And so when the tabernacle is first consecrated, all of those objects are
built. So they're taken out of the world, right? It's not like magic wood that they went and found in
the enchanted forest, right? It's not, oh man. That would have been a great quest line. Sorry. It's not,
And it's not, you know, some kind of sacred gold mine from the Holy Mountain.
It's just reg-
I mean the the tent covering of the tabernacle was made from goat hair. Okay, these weren't special
magic goats
So it's just these common things that they had in the camp, but then they're taken and they're
Consecrated and they're set aside
Yeah, by being sprinkled with blood and then
Through the sinning that's going on around them and even within them
They develop this.
where they're made common again.
Yeah, and there's this distinction then that is made...
I mean, this comes into the creation, right?
Where you've got the whole sort of world of chaos
versus the ordered space that God sets up.
Right, so, you know, at the beginning that's eaten or paradise
but then everything outside of it, or in comparison.
Right, and then you just said the camp
the camp.
And then there's the wilderness out there, right?
But then when eventually Israel makes its way to the promised land,
it's Israel and then the nations are out there.
So there's this orderly, beautiful, purified sacred space where God dwells with His people,
and then chaos is what's on the outside.
And so sin brings the chaos in.
Or it or you could say it it it turns what has been made orderly and beautiful.
chaotic again, you know, it sort of spiritual entropy, so to speak, you know.
So this is about that.
And it's not just sort of chaos in the sense of disorder.
Yeah.
Right.
This corruption and evil.
And this corruption means and brings these things under the power of the hostile power,
hostile powers that dwell.
out in the wilderness or they rule over the nations.
That are at work outside, they cover that power in the same way that our sin brings us under the power,
brings us into bondage of, under those, those hostile powers.
And so it intrudes right into, into the camp or into Israel or into sort of a renewed,
Good.
anti-typal Eden.
And so, that space, we talked last time when we were talking about the other offerings about
this idea that they are sort of concentric circles.
And the closer you get to where God is dwelling, so God is dwelling in the holy of Holies
and the Tabernacle.
So that is the place where the threat of this corruption is most...
dire. And then as you go out to the holy place and then to where the Levites are dwelling,
the Levites and the priests have to maintain this higher level of discipline and holiness,
and then you get to the Israelites who have to do this even higher level or this higher level than
the nations. So the place works the most threat inside the sanctuary. That's the place that the
The day of atonement is concerned and focused on pure f-
and cleansing from this taint. That is the place where it is most key that this happens within the
sanctuary. Right. All right. So, so then what does the actual ritual itself look like? How does that begin?
Right. So, it's an annual thing, so it must be a really big deal. Right. So, that we have, we have
again in Leviticus 16, a fair amount of detail.
describing exactly what's going on.
So it starts with, as we talked about last time,
the idea of sin offerings.
It starts with a sin offering by the high priest
and his immediate sons who are going to be serving with him.
The high priest and only the high priest
and only on this day, who is going to actually
go into what we now call the Holy of Holies
or the Sanctum St. Torum.
to your doctor strange fan.
to actually go in there to purify that space.
And so to prepare for that, he has to offer a special sin offering for himself because he needs to be,
because he's going to go all the way in.
He has to be at this state of purity and holiness that is unsurpassed.
And people may have heard of that the
the mostly later tradition where they'd tie a rope to the person, to the high priest. In case
he wasn't so pure and he'd drop dead and they had to go out. Which that's not in there, right?
Right. Yeah, that's not actually in there. I know. That was another thing that I was disappointed
to discover was actually not in the Bible. I'm like, the rope thing is awesome. Why is that?
Yeah, awww.
So, yeah, it's disillusioning.
It makes you wonder if that was a-
practicality like if a high priest dropped dead at some point and everybody was kind of like well, what do we do?
And how do we prevent this from happening in the future, right? Yeah, I mean fish fish him out. Yeah
But so he does this in offering and then sort of the day of atonement ritual proper
begins and
So the first covering that happens is the reason this is done on this day
As we mentioned in one of the previous episodes is that this is the day that Yahweh chose to appear
Visibly in the Holy of Holies
Yeah
And so all of this is being done on this day because of his appearance. That's why this is the day when everything has to be purified
That's why it's a response. He's coming
We have to we have to get ready right we have to have it perfect
Because he's going to a
And if he appears and it's imperfect, then this is going to get bad for Israel.
Not because God's going to get angry.
Right.
It's not like I said no green M&Ms.
It's because of his holiness and his purity that is dangerous to sinful people, to sinful
humanity.
and he God does not want his people.
when he comes to visit them to be destroyed with their sins.
He wants them to repent of those sins and to be purified by his coming.
So the first thing the High Priest has to do is he has to,
in order to prepare to enter the space, he has to offer a whole ton of incense.
Not a little, not one scoop, right?
Doesn't matter if someone in the back was complaining.
It doesn't matter about fake coughing. He had to do a lot of incense because the incense was covering
Right there you go making this cloud so that he wouldn't actually see Yahweh when he appeared
Yeah, there's this veiling that happens right because if he saw him directly he'd die and again
This is all about not dying
Yeah
So that that's sort of the first covering that takes place is
is through that.
and then he said, it's offering.
Yeah, yeah.
And then, and here's the part everyone's waiting for,
the goats.
The goats.
Yeah, so you have two goats.
I heard, you know, I was like,
I suddenly remember that joke,
you know, that goes around on Facebook,
you know, you have two cows,
and that it has all this list of economic systems.
I'm like, oh, it's, you have two goats.
See, yeah, and now there's gonna be all these rumors,
like see they're claiming some kind of, you know,
economic theory.
you have a tomb in here. Yeah, no. So there's two goats, right? I mean, is a good good
goat and a bad goat? Is it right? Three Billy goes gruff. Yeah. Oh, yeah, no, they've
got to both be great. They have to be the best goats, both of the best goats. They have
to be goat goats. They have to be the greatest goats of all time. Yeah. So yeah. So yeah,
both of them have
to be perfect in a blemish because they're going to be used for two different purposes,
but which one is used for which purpose is decided by a lot.
Yeah, which means it's just a random toss basically.
Yeah, they're going to cast lots and one's going to go for one purpose, one's going to go
for the other.
So that means the one that's going to be used for the more positive and holy purpose,
has to be pure unblemished, no broken bones, not a runt, etc.
since it could be either they both have to be.
that. Yeah, right. And so when the lots are cast, one of these two goats is designated
as the goat for Yahweh. Okay. And the other goat is designated as the goat for a
zeal. Here we go. There's like cheering going up across the country now as we mentioned
a zeal. But we're going to talk about the goat for Yahweh first. Yes. Right. But this
This is the biblical actual Azazel.
So Denzel Washington and John Goodman cannot help you
So that's a reference you probably didn't get but you laughed anyway. I suspect. Yeah, yeah, right. Yeah, okay
So I thank you for the courtesy laugh for the golf clap of laughter. I'm looking it up right now
So we'll start with the good goat.
Yes, I just just just just
case.
anyone wonders I have not seen the film fallen okay all right so it's really
creepy you wouldn't like it no I've done not into that kind of thing at all yeah okay so the
good for the go for Yahweh has to be perfect blame you know right without blemish pure no broken
bones what do you do with it right basically you extract its blood right so the
You
The whole thing is burned.
The whole goat is burned after the blood is extracted.
So this is not a sacrifice in the meal sense that we've been talking about.
Right.
And take it outside the camp.
Yeah.
Right.
Now, a couple of notes, right?
There is literally no information.
Now this ritual, when you read the bit of 16, there's a lot of detail here.
We've already started with some of it.
We're going to have more detail as we go, but exactly.
what's to be done. There is no detail on how this goat is to be killed. Yep. The killing
of this goat is not ritualized in any way. And when we're talking back to Beanna T-shirt.
Like we've said, how many times we've said now, the killing is not ritualized in any way.
it anyway. Yeah, sounds like we're FBI profilers. So we don't know how.
was killed. We don't know that there were any prayers said when it was killed. No sins
are put on this goat that is being killed. We'll talk about that more in a minute. Right?
The important thing is just you have to get the blood out of it. And one way or another,
that's going to kill the goat. So the blood is drained. The body is burnt. Let me let
me a couple of other things. The goat is not caused to suffer. Yeah. The goat is not this
is not punished or abused.
didn't anyway. This go, we don't know nothing, and when a ritual, if something is not ritualized,
when you have a detailed ritual, right, and it says, before the ritual wash your hands, for example,
right, and it doesn't say, here's the prayer when you wash your hands, here's the, that means the
hand washing isn't ritualized, and it means it doesn't mean anything. Yeah, yeah, it's just a practical
thing. Right, like you know when we're serving letters
we turn the page in the book. Someone could stay, stand there and say he's turning the page,
what does that mean when he turns three pages? Oh man, what's happening here? You know,
I just need to read this word, sorry. Yeah, it's a practicality, right? Yeah. So, right. So,
the death of the goat for yawai has no theological meaning. Yeah. Yeah. And probably some people
Some people out there probably like why am I emphasizing this and and the reason is that
a lot of reformation theology kind of hangs on the idea that the goat is being punished.
The goat does have, but again, look at what it says.
Look, just read the passage, and you can see that stuff is just simply not there.
So what's important here is just we need this blood from this pure and blabeless goat,
right?
because we're going to use the blood to do something.
The blood is used, the blood is smeared, wiped, used to cover the altar, the arc of the
covenant, the other fixtures of the tabernacle in order to purify them, in order to remove
that taint that's been left there, that's gathered there because of the sins of the people,
because of the sins of the community over the course of the year, to purify it again.
It was dedicated with blood.
Now it's purified again and made holy again with blood.
So okay, so a question that suddenly occurs to me is I mean there's a kind of a general now
Maybe I'm wrong about this but I thought there was kind of a general rule of you know
Don't touch the arc of the covenant and of course. I've seen Raiders of the Lost Ark. I know what happens if you open it
But is this like the one time you can touch it when when this ritual is being performed or is it actually sprinkled from a far or it was it was sprinkled with the finger so
the
The high priest would have a bowl in which the blood was collected
Okay.
And he smears it with his finger on pretty much everything but the arc.
And the arc you would dip his like his index finger in and then sort of whip it in order to sprinkle the blood.
There you go.
On to the, on to the arc itself.
Got you.
Yeah.
And without going down the whole rabbit trail of when you can and can't touch the arc because that's a whole separate.
Maybe we'll do it with the Ark of the Covenant.
Future episode.
Yeah, so do it Ark of the Covenant episode just about that.
And all the Ethiopians will rejoice because they'll be like, we've got it.
Yeah.
They've got that covered.
So that is what is done with the goat for Yahweh in the rich.
Right.
That is that part of the ritual.
The blood of that goat is used to purify the sanctuary, to purify sacred space.
Yeah.
But we have two goats.
Right.
Right, so the other code is for a Zazel.
We'll say what gets done with it first, then we'll talk a little bit about Azazel.
Has nothing to do with Denzel Washington, probably.
John Goodman.
But yeah, so the goat for Azazel actually has Sins placed upon it in contrast with the
goat for Yahweh.
How do you do that?
How do you put Sins on a goat?
The high priest would place his hands on the goat.
on his head to designated it for this purpose and he would
It's what it says is he would recite the sins of Israel now this doesn't mean like he was Santa keeping a list
All year like the high priest was going out spying on people like see all the stuff they did and writing it down
So that would be a long long list right right so it was
Covering all of the commandments that had been broken which was pretty much all of them right
Yeah, just list off all the commandments.
You could pretty, yeah, you could pretty safely
use the same list every year because all of that
had happened again.
But those were then publicly pronounced over that goat.
And now that the goat has these sins on it,
has the ontological taint from the people.
It's sort of absorbed by this goat.
That goat can't be sacrificed and can't be brought anywhere near the tabernacle.
Yeah.
Because now it's totally unclean.
Right.
Yeah, another super important point, that the goat that gets the sins is not killed and
cannot be killed as a sacrifice.
Right.
only sacrificial ritual of any kind.
Torah in which sins are placed on an animal.
Yeah.
The only time it happens is this, and that animal is not sacrificed.
Right.
I have people who don't believe me about that, but you can look it up.
Read it.
You can read for yourself.
I know.
It's funny, you know, sometimes we get people will ask us questions like,
which Bible scholar says this?
I'm like, well, why don't we start with what does the Bible say?
just read, I mean, yeah.
sometimes some passages are very difficult require a lot of interpretation, but when the question is what is richly done with a goat
You could just open up a little bit of kiss and read it, you know, it's not yeah
It's not a mystery
Yeah, I mean you have to deal with this mercy seat stuff, but now you know how that works. So you're all set
So instead now this goat is complete.
corrupt goat has to go outside the camp, the city, right, outside, back out into the
bad place. And it's going to a zeal.
Yes, right. So the idea is to take this and the people and get them out of the place
where sin does not belong. Send it out. Get that goat out here. Right. And so, right.
And this goat is so unclean by the way that the goat would be
led out by a designated person and tied to a bush or a shrub out in the wilderness. And the
person who did that was rendered unclean by it from just like being around that goat, the sin
goat. And so he had to do some kind of ritual purification. He had to purify himself before he could
come back into the into the cave. Yeah. Okay, but I haven't I heard that the goat actually got thrown
off a cliff.
Right, that was later. That's one of those things like the rope.
That
Happened later and the reason they pushed him off a cliff or a crag
Was that a very practical problem of well, what do you do if the goat gets loose and wanders back into town?
Yeah, it's the sin goat
Yeah, like oh
Our sins came back to us, right?
so
Right, so ominous very ominous
easy way to prevent
that right push them off a cliff dump them in a hole right yeah not so great for the goat but
keeps that keeps that from happening yeah okay so the good is awkward moment yeah go to
sense to a zeal right now okay a couple of key things there one is that he's not sacrifice to a
zeal he's not sacrifice to anybody right because again what what is sacrifice it's sharing a meal with
your God. They are not sitting down and have
more derives with a zazel. Right. So he's not sacrificed to a zazel. There are also some folks who
want to suggest that a zazel isn't a being. Yeah, because doesn't the name like literally mean
to have something to do with goats? Oz is a goat. Okay. So some people will try to, we'll want to
translate a zazel instead of seeing it as a name, as a proper name. We'll want to translate it as
something like the goat who goes
away. Yeah, right. This is where scapegoat comes from. Yeah. Okay.
Escape, right? Like escape, right? Escape is go away. The goat that goes away.
So in fact, you'll see some, I'm trying to remember if the King James does this.
A lot of older English biblical translations, instead of saying they'll
choose a goat for a zeal, says it's one for Yahweh and one for a scapegoat.
And this is what they're doing.
Yeah, which...
translating it rather than taking it as a name.
Yeah, yeah, right exactly.
And when we were talking about this,
you mentioned that in terms of the actual construction
of the language there, it's a parallel construction,
that Yahweh and Azazel are being used in parallel.
And so if you were to translate Azazel
as the goat that goes away, then the other one becomes
the goat that is who he is, then comes, makes things
coming to being like it doesn't.
Yeah.
The go-to exists or the go-to creates?
Yeah, right. Yeah, it just doesn't, doesn't work. Yeah. And, and this is was very clearly understood
by the earliest readers because every extra biblical source we have from the Jewish world
treats as a as a spiritual being. A demon. A demon, right. What we would call a demon who
is the one who has power out there.
in the wilderness, right? Is this this desert spirit? And supporting that within within the Bible is also in Leviticus 17
verse 7, which is the very next
chapter and remember the chapter breaks weren't there originally, so this is just a
couple paragraphs later after the end of the ritual
for the day of atonement. There's the commandment that
that is real lights are
not to continue worshiping the goat spirits of the wilderness.
Right. So it seems to be that you know where Azazel is most likely one of those.
Yeah. Right. And it probably should be noted that that doesn't contradict what came before.
Like when there's when when when God says don't worship the goat spirits. He's not saying now
don't do the ritual I just gave you to do.
Right.
That's not worshiping the goat spirits.
He's clarifying.
He's making it abundantly clear.
This is not a sacrifice to a zeal.
You're not sacrificing a goat to Yahweh,
and then sacrificing another goat to a zeal.
In case you misconstrued everything I just said,
you're not worshiping a zeal.
Repeat after me.
Because I-
There's one thing that God does not want you to do.
It's worship anything else.
I mean, that is just a overarching commandment of the whole scripture.
Right.
No idolatry.
And so we're going to talk about this more in the second half, but Azazel, the spirit
is seen as sort of the source of the sin and corruption that has come into the camp.
And so it's basically being sent back to him.
Back to where it belongs.
But we don't want any.
Right? Yeah, where you came from, you take it back.
Let's see, we'll go home.
This goat spirit of the wilderness is then picked up in a lot of later imagery, probably
the most famous being Baffamette, this sort of Satan figure or devil figure.
Yeah, with the goat head and big leathery wings.
Yeah, yeah.
And he's often associated with other symbols,
like the caduceus of enlightenment and that kind of thing.
But we'll talk about that more here in the second half.
Yeah.
All right.
So we've covered the basics of the Day of Atonement ritual
and the two goats here on Goat Week on the Lord of Spirits.
And we're going to get back in just a moment,
but first we're going to take a short break.
So we'll be back back.
Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen D.
We'll be back in a moment to take your calls on the next part of the Lord of
Spirits. Give them a call at 855-237-2346. That's 855-AF Radio.
Are you struggling in your walk with Christ? Do you want to rediscover your
reason for living? The person you were created to be. Renewing you, a priest, a
a psychologist and a plan.
Give us your keys to unlock areas of your life that hold you back from fully experiencing
the renewal and transformation God has in mind for you.
Co-author by a priest and a psychologist, Father Nicholas and Dr. Roxanne Lowe, renewing
you combines principles of spiritual growth with psychological tools to help you become
your best self, fully connected with God's purpose for you.
To purchase this book, please go to store.AncientFaith.com
at store.enginefaith.com.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits, the Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father
Stephen DeYoung.
If you have a question, call now at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF radio.
All right, welcome to the second half of the show here on Goat Week at the Lord of Spirits
podcast. So we just walked through
the day of atonement ritual, the goat for Yahweh, the goat for Azazel and what those things mean.
And now we're going to turn towards the New Testament. But before we get there, a couple of things we
have to say at the very outset. All references to the atonement in the New Testament are explicitly about
the day of atonement ritual. That's just a good guiding principle here. Super, super important
make
all these references to Atomina and the New Testament make a lot more sense.
So I'm just going to say that at the outset. It's not about some abstract concept or mechanism of
salvation. It's about the ritual that everyone, you know, that the people who are receiving this
gospel would have known, right? Or if they were coming in from, you know, the nations, they would have
been told about this as part it was part of their inheritance now because they're becoming part of
Israel, but Israel knows the day of Atonement ritual. It's a huge
huge deal. Super, super important. Okay. But before we get to the new testament, let me,
let me, let me throw you one quick correction here. Okay. Go for it. I know you really want
goat week to be a thing. I do. But due to the frequency of the show, is it not actually
goat fortnight? That is true. But it's not like you can't have the parallel with shark
week then. You know what I'm saying? Right. And then that opens up fortnight sub references.
True, a whole new world.
I mean, I love that word. It's just a good, good word for one thing.
But yeah, yeah, I hear you. I hear you.
But we did just have, you know,
what we're going to talk about, Matthew, Matthew chapter 25 in a second year.
We had the Sunday of the last judgment, so we've had goats on our minds.
You know, but we'll get to that. Okay, but before we get to the actual New Testament,
there's some stuff surprise surprise Lord of Spear to listeners.
There's other literature that surrounds the New Testament that informs what's going on in the New Testament.
So we're going to talk about some Second Temple literature, right?
Like that mentions a Zazel, doesn't it?
Yeah. Yeah.
And a solid 80% of kidding aside, the point you made about it being references to the day of Atonement is again important.
I know we've said this several times already, right?
But when a tone mint is talked about at the new test,
It's not referring to some abstract theological idea of atonement.
It's referring to what happened on the day of atonement and comparing
specifically as we're going to see what Christ does to that.
Yeah, okay. Well related to that, actually, we have a caller.
We have Dan from New York,
and he has a question specifically about the day of atonement ritual.
ritual. So, Dan, are you there?
Oh yeah, I'm here.
Hey Dan, welcome. Welcome to the Lord of Spirits podcast.
All right. What's your question?
All right. So, so I have two questions if that's okay.
I don't think they're so such long questions.
So the first question, I mean, I'll start by saying I haven't read the book of Leviticus.
So that's so that excuse my ignorance on this.
But I have read, you know, actually after hearing the last podcast you guys did,
guys did. I was doing a little bit of reading.
And I read that the priests would lay hands on both goats,
like on the goat for a Yahweh, as well as that,
for first, is that true?
Or would they not lay hands on the goat for Yahweh?
And if they did, what was that signifying
when they laid hands on it?
Because I know the Protestants like to interpret that as,
you know, putting, placing, shifting their sins onto the animals
so that it works with their like penal substitution.
Model.
Right.
Well, we can't hang that on all Protestants.
you know like
But yeah, sometimes, no, I know what you're saying.
I know what you're saying.
Sometimes, yeah, that's interpreted.
At any time someone puts their hands on an animal,
that's interpreted as meaning that they're putting sins on it.
Right.
And I mean, there are basic problems with that.
For example, that's how people are ordained
in the New Testament is by the laying on their hands.
So I don't think they were putting their sins on like
Presbyters.
But when hands were laid in sacrificial rituals, right, it's the goat for a
zazel where it says he lays hands on it and then pronounces the sins. Other
sacrificial rituals where you see the laying on his hands, that's to
designate the animal as a sacrifice. The laying hands on someone or
something is setting them apart, right, which means making them wholly
sanctifying them for a purpose.
So we've got, I go out
to my sheep, right? I've got all these sheep. One of them I'm going to sacrifice. So that
one we go and we lay hands on it to say, this is the sheep that we're going to offer to
God. Okay. And so it's the same thing in terms of ordination. There's a lot of people standing
around. This is the person who we're setting apart for this purpose. Yeah. And if you look,
if you look at Leviticus, I mean, you know, you don't have to read the whole book of Leviticus,
But if you look at the Viticus 16, which is the chapter that
has this ritual in it. You can just read it, you know, and it shows, like I'm looking at it right now.
And it says, Aaron must then present the goat, which has been designated by Lot for the Lord, and he's to make it a sin offering,
but the goat, which has been designated by Lot for a zeal is bestowed alive.
And then later on, it makes the reference to him putting his hands on the goat for a zeal and sends it out.
but there's not unless I'm missing it.
doesn't actually say anything about putting his hands on the other go.
I mean, obviously he has to touch it.
But there's not this ritualized laying on of hands that's going on that I'm seeing here,
unless I'm just missing it, Father.
I don't know.
There's there's a tendency and this is not an indictment of anybody because I mean,
I've heard scholars who I greatly respect publicly talk about when they're talking about
Sacrifices of evil testament say oh yeah the priest would
Put the sins on the animal and then kill it and I'm like that's it's it's just not there but
people have sort of
Inbibed this idea and so they sort of
Yeah, yeah, and I mean people do that all the time like they say there's three wise men well
Text doesn't actually say how many there were there were three gifts
Right, so there's a whole bunch of things like that where we've just we've picked it up
and we assume it's there at the time.
did it actually isn't? You know, when you go check.
Okay. So does that, does that help you Dan?
Yeah, yeah, yeah. That's really helpful. That makes perfect sense.
Did you have, you had a second question?
Yeah, the second question was like what, what was it about?
The understanding of the goat's blood that was understood to have like a
clinging or sanctifying effect.
You know, over the, you know, over the, the various parts of the, of the holy
the police in the temple that you guys discussed.
Yeah, what is it about that blood that actually has that purifying effect?
Is it because it's being offered to God?
What's going on there?
Yeah, so I don't want to get too great about this because there's actually, when you get
into literature about this, I did my dissertation related to this, so I read all the literature
on this.
And there's actually, I mean, people debate exactly how the blood dealt with the taint,
Right, like did it absorb it?
Did it eradicate it? Right? I mean, so you could get super
through the weeds, right? But the basic idea is that as Leviticus says elsewhere,
that blood is life. The blood of an animal is its life. And so,
right, sin, right? This taint of sin and corruption is death. It's sort of like death stuff.
right and so you use life stuff
to purify from death stuff. There you go. Okay. All right. That makes, you know, that makes, that makes total sense. All right. Thank you. Thank you.
Thank you. Appreciate it. Thank you very much for calling in Dan. We appreciate hearing from you. All right. Okay. So that's good. It's good. We, we talked a little bit about that. All right. So
Azazel and Second Temple Literature.
What does that stuff say about it?
Right, so as I mentioned all of our earliest sort of interpreters within the Jewish world
who talk about Azazel have him as this being, actual demonic being.
And the most prominent places where he's discussed in terms of what Second Temple literature
we're focusing on our first enich, what's called second enich or slavonic enich.
and the apocalypse of Abraham.
Okay.
And just to finish it, the latter two of those are preserved for us in Slavonic.
We don't have them in the original language or even in Greek.
They're preserved for us in Slavonic.
And we're being copied in monasteries in the Orthodox world
right up into the 16th century when the printing...
press was invented. So there would be deliberately preserved for us within the church, not just
accidentally we found them in the desert somewhere. And I was going to say I want to give a shout
out the scholar on Slavonic Suda Piggrafa. So if you want to get into Slavonic Suda Piggrafa
and who doesn't?
Is Audrey Orlov?
And he's written...
and a lot of it's available for free on the internet
if you want to read scholarly journal articles.
There you go.
And now I've preempted the,
where could I read more about this message is we get
a third base episode.
I know.
So it runs you.
We understand your hunger and your thirst to know more
and we appreciate and love that.
It is good.
Yes, so allow me to feed that a little bit.
There you go.
So he's seen
In first inek when, or the book of Inek, when Zazel appears, Zazel is sort of the leader
of the bad guys, the leader of the rebellious watchers who are responsible for corrupting the line of
of Cain and leading them to destruction that results in the flood. So he's sort of the main
main motivator of that.
And when the Book of Enoch lists what the different rebellious angelic beings taught to humans,
what Azazel is listed as having taught is are the same things that Tubulcanin Genesis
forverse to.
Because if there's anything people love more than Slavonic Suda Piggarafa, it's genealogies.
Where it describes what Tuble K created.
So he's being directly connected.
Yeah.
All those technological advancements.
Yes, yes, evolving metallurgy for weapons of war and those kind of things.
And so, of course, as we've mentioned before in a previous episode, this is over against
the Opcaloo myth and others.
similar stories, Prometheus, in the Greek tradition.
Where that stuff is depicted as being good.
Like this spirit came and gave us this wonderful,
beautiful knowledge.
And the Bible is saying, no, that was bad for you.
Right?
So yeah, yeah.
And so Zazel is caught up in all this.
Right.
And that enlightenment imagery, like the caduceus
and those kind of things that are attached to Baphomet
is the same kind of thing.
There you go.
this idea of hey baby.
the serpent and Eden was telling the truth, right? Maybe he was, you know. So that's that
Pro-Devil propaganda stuff again. Indeed. So, and what this results in in all three of those
texts I mentioned, the Book of Enix, Slavonic Enix, and the Apocalypse of Abraham, is that there's
going to be this eschatological day of atonement, meaning we've got this annual day of atonement
that we do every year.
that's sort of managing things, right?
Because every year we go and we sin a bunch more
and then we have to do it again, right?
Right.
This vicious cycle of purifying this limited sacred space.
And so sort of prophetically, it's
that there's going to be this eschatological day
of atonement that's going to take care of a zeal
and take care of this sin in corruption
and take care of sacred space sort of once and for all.
Yeah.
Yeah, yeah, so this is really cool and it's a really,
I mean, this is a major kind of transitional thing
happening here, right?
Where, you know, as you've mentioned a number of times
that the sacrificial system, the old testament is basically
kind of a management system, managing sin,
managing corruption, managing taint and death.
And yet, and so that what we get in this second
The couple literature is, as you said, once and for all,
that there's going to be...
to be a great day of atonement to end them all, so to speak, you know, the ultimate,
the fulfillment of all of them.
Now the thing that has been but done in part now is being done totally and full.
And I think this is really important to note this because we say that Christ is the fulfillment
of all things in the Old Testament.
And here you have the second temple.
literature, a lot of it preceding some of it kind of being at the same time as
the New Testament, essentially pointing to this there's this big eschatological
version of this that's going to be happening, right? And you know, there's the
figure of the angel of the Lord as the one who's going to do this. He's going to
be the high priest, right? Right. The there's built in an understanding
beforehand. This isn't just Christians kind of coming up with Alex.
goreical ways to read the Old Testament, to read Jesus into it. This is before Christ's birth,
an awareness that, you know, we're managing the problem, we're dealing with the problem,
but we're not solving the problem. And so the Torah and its rituals, including the Day of Atonement,
can't be like an end in themselves. They don't lead to salvation. And so, yes, there's this,
the figure especially
Actually the apocalypse of Abraham, he's named Yeh-o-l.
This angel of the Lord figure who serves as the high priest for this eschatological day
of atonement.
And what's interesting there is, you know, people may know that these angelic names that
end in L, L is God, right?
So Gabriel is Gibur El, the mighty man of God, Michael is Mikael who is like God.
And Yahoo, the Yahoo is Yahweh.
So it's Yahweh is God.
The name of this angel is Yahweh.
No, Yahweh, God.
Yahweh, God.
There you go.
Because of how it's conjugate.
So that's why we say this is an angel of the Lord figure in the technical sense of the Old Testament.
The Son of Man, the angel of the Lord, this second person of Yahweh.
that this is going to be the person who does this.
as catological day of Atomah. And then the whole idea, not just in general terms, but in its specifics, is picked up wholesale by St. John the Evangelist in the Johanian literature.
Yeah, this is so cool. I'm getting a little giddy here because like when we were going over this in our preparation, I mean it was just stunning to me.
once you have clarity about especially what the old
Testament says there's all kinds of bits of the New Testament that just light up, left
and right.
So that's what we're going to do now, right?
So let's talk about what St. John says about this.
So he picks up this idea of the eschatological day of atonement and he says it's Christ.
Christ is the high priest who does this final day of atonement, the one that ends them
and he takes that over from the second
simple literature, right?
Yeah, and St. John's gonna say this has happened, right?
And, yeah, yeah.
When we say that you're handing literature,
we're talking about St. John's gospel,
but also first, second, and third John,
and the apocalypse, the book of Revelation.
And it's found all this.
Now, most people, when they think of a tone
made in the New Testament, right?
If I came to someone at random and said,
Hey, where would I go in the new test?
to read about a tonement.
Yeah.
They would probably not immediately say first John.
Yeah, right.
I think sometimes, you know, I think sometimes people take
first, second and third John as being like these little bonus bits
towards the end of the New Testament before we get to the big
crazy dream vision at the end.
You know, like, oh, it's nice that he wrote some letters.
Right?
But the church read these out loud in liturgy
in liturgy
and preserved them and theologized on the basis of them.
And this is from the beloved apostle who leaned on Christ's
breast at the last supper.
So actually, there is really important theology and teaching
and doctrine that's in these three letters.
And historically, especially with first John,
it's important to note that the general epistles,
which is all those letters that St. Paul didn't write.
Right? Yeah. The general or Catholic epistles, the ones written by other people, out of all of those,
all of those in the very early history of the church were being utilized by some churches and not others.
And so this is sometimes expressed as there were arguments about them. And reality was just
some communities had them and used them and some other ones didn't have them and therefore didn't.
But the one that everyone agreed on out of all of the general epistles or Catholic epistles
first John. Yep. They would all say the gospel of John and the epistle. A lot of them who didn't
even know second and third John existed except in first John. So it had this prominence beyond those
those other books. But first John is actually the book of the New Testament that uses the actual word
illisteria on Atomit most frequently. So there are other than certainly Hebrews
has a very detailed and we're going to pay Hebrews is going to be peppered throughout this half of the show.
I don't know.
But it has a very detailed description and connection between Christ and the day of Atonement ritual, as we're going to see.
But in terms of using the term and talking about it as a concept, right?
First John is the place.
And he is picking up from this, basically, anachic literature.
Second Temple literature, a certain understanding of the cosmic aspects of the day of atonement and of this
Eschatological day of atonement. Yeah, yeah, so we have in our notes
Because everyone loves it when we read from Enochic literature
First Enoch 108
It says and the whole earth has been corrupted by the teaching of the works of a zeal to him a scribe all sin
That's the indictment. It's sort of read over Azazel before he had at this eschatological day of atonement. That's his indictment. That's the charge against him.
And St. John picks up pieces of this verse, elements of this idea, form part of the structure of the book of 1 John.
So you see for example the teaching of the
works of a zeal. Right? So there's this idea that the worst of these will be
taught and handed down. Well, who would have been doing this as we talk about
this would be Keynes line? The Ken, yeah, exactly, exactly. And we don't normally
we don't think about Ken a lot. But when we do, we think about the story of
Ken and Abel and oh yeah, he was a murderer. He's a bad guy. But he was
particularly significant in the understanding of both.
Judaism of the second temple period and early Christianity as not only the first sinner as
we've already talked about a little bit, but also as a teacher of sin.
He is regarded as by Josephus for example as the first heretic.
Yeah, that's interesting.
Which is funny because like you wouldn't think of like at what point do we see Keen teaching
something?
And you know, as like, you know, I have this crazy new doctrine of God I want everyone to
follow me on.
But yeah, there's this reference.
first John 312, which makes reference of Cain being of the wicked one, who murders his
brother, right? And if he's of Azazel, this one who's teaching this forbidden knowledge,
then he's doing the works of his father, so to speak, right? He's imaging Azazel. Yeah,
which we talked about before a few episodes back.
And the next...
First in 1 John, verse 13 says that the reason he killed Abel is that Abel's works were good and Cain's works were evil.
So that works is brought in there that he's doing the works of his father, the evil one.
You also find in 1 John 5.19 the whole world lies under the power of the evil one.
Yeah, so there's that sense of the domination of demons in the world, especially Azazel.
the corruption of the earth of the whole world.
And freedom being given by Christ from that.
Right. And the way he said to do that in 1 John 3,
8 is that Christ appears to destroy the works of the devil.
Yeah, which I love that verse because if you ask people sometimes,
why did Jesus come to earth?
There's all kinds of things that they might say,
some true and some not so much.
But I love that he comes to destroy the works of the-
Like he comes specifically to do combat with the evil one
Right, and these these things that the evil one has wrought in the world are here in the world and need to be purged out
Yeah need to be purified need to be a tone for in that sense need to be removed wiped away glotted out
Cut. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah, I don't
And and so what what you see after that indictment is read
in...
First, the Enoch and in Selvanikinic and in the Apocalypse of Abraham, the same thing happens
to Azazel and all of them. Azazel gets bound and chained up and thrown into a hole in
the ground, and imprisoned there until the end of days, until the day of the Lord, at
which point he will be released briefly and then thrown into the lake of fire.
Yep, that might sound familiar.
This is a folks who have read the Book of Revelation, right?
Because this is exactly what happens to the dragon.
He's seized by an angel he's bound, he's thrown into a pit, he's kept there, and then on
the last day he's released briefly and then thrown into the lake of fire.
The lake of fire that gets mentioned in St. Matthew's Gospel and in the Book of Revelation.
has no Old Testament precedent. But the lake of fire prepared for the devil and
his angels as St. Matthew's gospel says is taken directly from the
Anarchic literature. It's a direct
direct bronze. And so this element of the eschatological day of atonement that
Azazel is finally defeated. It's not just sending him back his
while he continues to control the rest of the world out there, but he's done away with and
disposed of is, as we said, Hebrews is going to be peppered all through here. And Hebrews 214
says, it is much than is the children have partaken of flesh and blood. He himself likewise shared
in the same. Right. So this is talking about why Christ became incarnate again. Why did Christ
become incarnate. That so that through death he might destroy him who had the power of
death, that is the devil, namely the devil, right? Destroy the devil. Yeah. And so that's
one significant element of this eschatological day of atonement. And this is the one that's
particularly, it's all in Hebrews, but this is particularly emphasized in the the Johanian
literature.
Awesome. All right. Okay. Well, let's talk about St. Matthew and for those of us in the
Byzantine right of the Orthodox Church, which is most Orthodox Christians, this
Sunday was the Sunday of the last judgment in which we heard Matthew chapter 25,
where we heard that sheep go to heaven and goats go to hell.
And this is why we eat ceremonial cakes on me for Sunday.
Exactly.
Yeah, but okay, okay, so it doesn't quite map, right?
You know, with the day of Atonement, Rich Older's two goats, a goat for Yahweh and a
go for that sent off to a zeal.
But I thought in Matthew chapter 25 it said that goats go to hell.
Yeah, not all goats are the same in every reference in Scripture, right?
But what happens in is in sort of the symbolic mind,
Hi Jonathan. Of the Jewish people.
sheep and lambs become associated with Passover.
Yeah.
And as we talked about last time at a fair amount of length,
Passover represented this manu mission,
this freedom from slavery, slavery to sin,
freedom from slavery to the apostle power.
So this is sort of has positive connotations, right?
And then, so the Israelites are referred to as sheep,
sort of all through the Old Testament.
and their leaders as as shepherds because they're these sheep who are now set free from Egypt and brought out into this new pasture all of that symbolism and then
Goats get associated with the day of atonement which means associated with sin
blood death right a
Zazole right so yeah, so there is some over there is some overlap there
But but yeah, it's not it's not a perfect total categorical overlap
We have to learn to think some b-
Yeah, yeah, you have to pay royalties now that you said that. Yeah, I don't I don't think so but okay, okay, but yeah
But yes, hello all you all of you Jonathan and Pejo fans out there
We understand there's a kind of a pipeline from there to here. We welcome you. We are happy to have you
Yeah, yeah, okay, so say same Matthew he talks about
Christ as being the goat that gets sent off to his
right? Right. Right. We're gonna see to tip our hats, spoilers, then in the New Testament Christ
is both goats. You know how to say that? In the New Testament in particular we see a lot of this
connection to Christ as the scapegoat. Right? And one of the places where we really see that is,
that this requires you reading some...
outside the New Testament literature, but the epistle of Barnabas gives
a little bit more detailed description of
how the Day of Atonement ritual was being performed, sort of in some of the small details that had accrued over time
in the first century AD.
Okay.
That's where... So, their accommodations have been made. They're not out in the wilderness, right?
I said I did camping intense, right?
you've got Jerusalem instead of established city.
So he gives some of these details.
And so some of the details we get from that are a scarlet
cord being tied around the goat's head.
And that when they, after the sins had been placed on the goat,
the people would sort of gather in the streets
and they would get reeds and they'd strike the goat
and hit it to sort of drive it out.
Yeah, and while they were driving the goat out, they would sort of mock the goat and spit at the goat as
Assign them rejecting their sins, right? Right, right. I know people are being moved to sympathy for the goat.
Right. The poor goat. But yeah, okay, but but these three things, right, wrapped around with a scarlet cord,
being beaten with a read to drive it out.
mocked and spit upon. Does that sound like anything to anybody?
Yeah, so St. Matthew uses this
this language
to describe I mean
It to describe exactly what happens to Christ at the crucifixion right and he's wrapped about whether at the end of his trial
He says he's a he they wrap a scarlet robe
about him, which is kind of a weird way to describe
putting a robot. Yeah, right. I don't say I got up this morning and wrapped my clothes around me.
Yeah, so it's an interesting point because because what is St. Matthew doing? Is he just saying,
okay, I'm going to come into this. I'm going to describe this. I have all these details from the
day of Atonement ritual and I'm just going to describe that to what's happening with Christ. I'm just
going to make it look like that. No, what he's doing is he's describing what actually happens to Christ,
But he's using language.
that should remind you of the day of Atonement ritual in order for you to make that connection, the connection that actually does exist.
You know, but he's appropriately describing it to help you make that connection because
what are the gospels? They are not just unnerdive, they're narrative theology.
Like it's, you know, they are teaching you and giving you the proclamation of Christ.
They're not just saying, and this is what happened next.
you know, it includes that, but the way that they tell the story is designed to teach you how
Christ, in this case, is the fulfillment of what was given in the old covenant.
Awesome stuff. And this doesn't mean it's not historical, right?
No. Because any historian has to choose details to include in details to omit,
and we'll write about things and describe things in certain ways. That doesn't make it not
Not historians, St. John himself.
you can't write down every single thing Jesus ever did it said there's not enough
picks in the world. So they're choosing how to describe things and what
details to include in order to convey this right. So using the color scarlet,
using this wrapped around language, he says that they put a read in his hand,
it's the exact same word for read, and that they took the read from him and
and struck him with it.
have used a word for stick. Or he's driven outside of the city. Right. And the people,
and they mock him and they spit on him. Yeah. Right. And this is very important because in our
modern era, a lot of people will take these descriptions of what happens at Christ's death
and the hymns about them that we're going to sing in Holy Week in a few weeks and label them as
anti-semitic.
Yeah, which is which we're actually about to show you how it's the opposite
It's the opposite. It's not anti-semitic right so okay perfect example. This is probably the classic example
Matthew chapter 27 verse 25 where
The people say in response to pilot
His blood be upon us and upon our children
now
Given everything we just said
about the blood of
the goat and given everything you should know if you're Christian about what the
blood of Christ does. If his blood is upon you, that's actually good. Right? I
mean, Saint Matthew is himself a Jew. I mean, he's not gonna write anti-Semitic.
I mean, he's writing the most Jewish of the Gospels, right? You know, the most
hebrae eyes of the gospels when he says that Christ's blood is...
going to be upon them and upon their children. That's a blessing. That's absolutely a blessing.
Right. And in what St. Matthew conveys there with his blood beyond us and upon our children,
in narrative theology, right? Hebrews just comes out and says in Hebrews 9, 18 through 22 that says,
they were sprinkled with the blood. They had their children were sprinkled with the blood
at these
beginning of the old covenant and now we have been sprinkled and purified with the blood of Christ.
Right? So that's the non-narrative theology way to say it. But so yes, this is St. Matthew
is deliberately subverting a potential anti-Semitic reading of this. Right? This is, this is like Joseph
and Genesis. They meant it to him for evil, but he meant it for good. Right? They're cursing him,
he's taking away their sins. Father forgive them.
Yeah, and note note that it's not just Jews who are doing these day of atonement things
It's also the Roman soldiers who are doing these day of atonement things. It's a Matthews gospel
They're now participating in the eschatological day of atonement right. It's everybody says
This is so cool and then and then as Hebrews again sort of makes plain in Hebrews
and then 12 Christ dies outside the camp.
Outside the camp.
Yeah.
So Christ is both goats.
We're about to talk now about how he's also the goat for Yahweh.
But I just wanted to link these two things together,
actually from a very familiar bit of himnography
for Orthodox Christians.
And that's from the doxology.
Whether the little doxology, the great doxology,
if I remember correctly, this line is in both,
where we're seeing O Lord God, Lamb of God,
some of the father who...
take us away the sin of the world, have mercy on us, oh, thou who take us away the sins of the world.
Okay. So he takes away the sin of the world and the sins of the world. This is not just
redundancy and you just happen to pluralize the word the next time. Taking away the sin of the world
is to remove the taint, the corruption, the impurity of the whole world, right? Which is what the
the goat for a zeal does is he takes the impurity out out of the out of the
camp and
out into the wilderness, although in this case it's the whole world.
The whole world becomes the camp now.
And then he also takes away the sins of the world,
meaning the sins that the people commit,
he takes away their sins, right?
And he purifies even them, right?
So it's, I don't know, it's cool.
Christ is both goats.
So all right, well, let's talk about St. Luke's gospel,
and of course, X, which I mean these two kind of form.
single narrative together, you know, with just the, you know, in the former
treatise with theophilus at the beginning of, and I think that's the King James
version, at the beginning of, of acts. So okay, so how does, so, say Luke uses the
David's home imagery to describe Christ as being the goat that is sent to Yahweh,
right? Right, the goat, the goat for Yahweh, which, remember, the, things, the blood of
this code is used to
verify
sacred space, and so
start with a verse near and dear to my heart because I spent a chunk of my life with it
And that's first John 2 verse 2
and first John 2 verse 1 talks about
First first John 2 1 and 2 is talking about the day of atonement first John 2 verse 1 talks about Christ as the high priest who intercedes in
in prayer and then 2 verse 2 says that Christ is
the atonement, not only for our sins, but also for the whole world. And what he's doing
here is he's taking this idea of the purification of sacred space. So if we imagine, right,
that there's sort of this layer of darkness over the whole world, and then there's sort
of this dome. It's like dome of light over Israel over the camp, and the wilderness, or
over Israel.
as a nation over Judah, Judea, and that's being purified sort of under the dome, right?
It's being cleansed and purified, being kept pure.
Now that dome is expanded to encompass the whole world because Christ not only does he
not just send the stuff back to his asal, he gets rid of his asal, he then has broken
Azazels hold over the world and so now the whole cosmos.
the whole creation can become sacred space.
It can be purified in come sacred.
So not only for our sins, right, which are taken away,
but for the whole world, which is now purified,
it made holy and sacred.
It first in potency, right?
First, as with everything, it's got a logical, right?
This is happening in real time,
like we talked about in our Halloween episode.
But this will ultimately come to fruition than in the new heavens and the new earth.
Just as right now, the evil one is bound in a hole, and he'll be chucked in the lake
of fire then at that latter point.
Yeah.
Okay.
Now we get to talk about one of my favorite places.
Emeas, although not Pennsylvania, but the Emeas...
that my amazes named after. So in Luke chapter 24 you get Christ on the road to amazes.
And then there's this weird and then it's at the end of Luke, they worshiped him,
returned to Jerusalem with great joy and were continually in the temple praising and blessing God
Amen. We're just kind of a weird way to end the gospel. Like, you know, why is that?
Why is that mentioned?
Well, okay.
So there's a little bit of backstory here.
And again, Luke using this detail about Christ being on the road to Emmaus.
He's actually on the road to Emmaus, but everyone knows what Emmaus is famous for.
You guys know, right?
Emmaus does it everyone as they well should.
So there's the Battle of Emmaus.
And again, not Emmaus Pennsylvania.
Yeah, so.
So, okay, to give a little bit of background here, to make it bring in home for Pennsylvanians,
it'd be like saying, I was on the road to Gettysburg. Well, Gettysburg is a town and it has
like a Lutheran seminary there, but that's not what everyone remembers Gettysburg for. It's
remembered as being the decisive battle of the American late unpleasantness. That's for all of
all of my southern friends out there. You know, it has this sort of importance as a major
battle site. Well in for for for century
Judeans, that is the place of the Battle of Emmaus.
And that is related to the Maccabees, right?
There's this battle.
Right.
The Battle of Emmaus talks about the Battle of Emmaus.
Yeah.
Exactly.
That's the crucial battle where the Judean Army led by the
Maccabee brothers defeated the Greek forces.
Was at the Battle of Emmaus.
This is, and again, this isn't just
a random connection.
Amazes isn't mentioned anywhere else in the Bible.
Yeah, right.
Except first Maccabees and St. Luke's Gospel right here.
Yeah, yeah.
So, you know, the reason why this battle is so important
is because the temple had been desecrated
by an anti, it wasn't an anti-Casopiphanies, right?
Yeah.
who then tackles the fourth, the Piffinicia.
Yeah, so he goes in and he doesn't see an idol in there and is like, well, what the heck? You know?
You know, he actually busts his way into the Holy of Holies.
And so the temple has to be reconsecrated.
Well, he actually, I think you're mixing in with Pompey, the Roman general.
I'm actually in you in real time.
That's fine.
Both in blaspheming pagans.
Yeah.
And Tyakus the epiphanies was not his last name.
Yes.
The epiphanies.
And
Antiochie. Antiochus was obviously as a family name of the cell you could
Dynasty and they all took these titles. So one of them was
Antiochus, I believe it was the third was so so tear the savior. The savior. Yes. Yes. And so as if and
Tychus before the pifides epiphanies meant he was the manifestation of a god.
Yes.
Right that's what he did himself and he actually went into the temple
in Jerusalem and sacrificed pigs on the altar to Zeus.
Yeah.
So, yeah, you don't get much worse than that.
So, that's what's described, as in Daniel,
as the abomination of desolation.
Right. Right. Right.
Because it rendered, yeah, they couldn't use the temple anymore after that.
It fell into disrepair. Yeah.
Yeah, so the temple has to be re-consecrated.
It has to be purified.
It has to be made holy set apart again
again for the
use of God alone. What happens next? They're continually in the temple,
praising and blessing God on men. And then what happens next? Acts, the book of
Acts, you've got the coming of the Holy Spirit, feeling the creation on the
de Appentecost and the de Appentecost. It's, you know, the the feast of the giving
of the law. But isn't also there's a isn't there a consecration of the temple
associated with that as well? Or am I mixing stuff up? Well, this is, this is
So Hanukkah is the rededication of the temple. That's where the feast comes from. Right, the feast, the feast of light.
So they rededicate the temple and although it didn't happen that time when the tabernacle was dedicated when the temple was dedicated
by Solomon
after everything is dedicated after the blood is used to purify everything and consecrate everything then the presence of God
and her's in as this plot is fiery clown.
Yes, yes, yes.
And so you see the same dynamic, the end.
Luke ends with a mess and then they're in the temple and then you pick up acts and they're not hanging around in the temple for some reason
because St. Louis uses this imagery now re-dedication of the temple being the whole creation and then now that it's been re-dedicated the presence of God
the Holy Spirit can come and dwell in Sun's Daughters Everyone because of this purification that has happened.
Don't you know
that YAHL's body is the temple of the Holy Spirit.
Right.
And so this then plays out through the early chapters of the book of Acts.
Yeah.
The idea that everything is now being cloned.
So it's say Peter is called to go see Cornelius, this Eccurian who's a Roman, who's a Gentile,
who's from one of the pagan nations.
He sees this vision of the animals, the formerly unclean animals being lowered in this cloth.
that is it told don't call unclean what I've creed.
created, or don't call on clean what I tell you is clean, but do not call on clean what I have made clean purification
has happened. Right. So this purification has happened. So those animals are no longer unclean from outside the camp.
And therefore not metaphorically, but literally cordonelius this Roman is now also clean, just as clean as any Judean.
and therefore able to receive the Holy Spirit as he does after St. Peter
which is the
gospel to him and then this triggers everything,
this triggers St. Paul's mission now out to the nations
to go and sort of retake them.
Yeah, okay.
And so cool.
This the concept.
The great them is a sacred space.
Yeah.
Okay, all right.
Well then again, we'll dip back into Hebrews,
which references all of this, right?
So Hebrews chapter nine,
likewise he sprinkled both the tent and all the vessels
using the worship with
the blood, indeed, under the law. Almost everything is purified with blood, and without the
shutting of blood there's no forgiveness of sins. That last part, of course, often gets
quoted out of context. The context is the purification of the space.
That's happening.
Yes, a material objects and physical space.
It's stuck.
Yeah, by the blood.
Good blood.
Right, right. Yeah, and then again, you know, Hebrews 10, how much worse punishment do
you think will be deserved by the one who's trampled underfoot the sun of
God and here's the important part here for our purposes, and it's profaned the blood
of the covenant by which he was sanctified and has outraged the spirit of grace.
So again, the blood of the covenant does this sanctification.
This is Christ as being the goat for Yahweh.
The blood comes and purifies, and then the Holy Spirit comes to dwell there.
Look at that.
And the pivot point when we go from the end of St. Luke's Gospel to the beginning of
the story he tells twice.
and that's Christ's ascension into heaven, which he tells at the end of his gospel
and then again at the beginning of Acts he narrates Christ's ascension again.
And what Hebrews 9 verses 11 through 14 says that the key event that made this
transition between the purification of just this small sacred space to the whole
creation is when Christ...
enters into the heavenly sanctuary as high priest, right, which is describing his ascension
into heaven.
So Luke is doing this narratively.
And Hebrews is just giving it to us, theologically explaining it to us.
Awesome.
All right.
Well, before we go to break, we actually do have a call.
And this is our friend, Father Fautius in Texas.
So Father Fautius, are you there?
I am.
Can you hear me? I can hear you. Can you hear us?
Praise God. Yes, sir. All right.
Father, Father, welcome to the Lord of Spirits podcast.
Can you hear me? Was your...
Can you hear me? Was your one question for tonight, unfortunately.
So it was good talking with you.
Good night.
Yeah.
I will again.
This has just not been my day. What can I say?
Yeah, yes. I do.
have a question and it pertains to first on chapter 2 verse 2, Father Stephen, I know how
do you do this to you, I read your dissertation and it's magnificent.
Now, everyone's going to want to read it.
Don't mention that.
Yeah, you're rubbing it into a bunch of people.
I'm sorry, just so you all know it's really good.
I'm sorry, I'm sorry.
Yeah, so I can, I'll cast the hate for that one.
That's okay.
It says that Christ is the atonement or the perpetuation for our sins, not for ours only,
but also for the whole world.
what matter is the atoning work of Christ mediated to the world.
or could we say that it is mediated to the world by the church?
Yeah, here's where I have to say that's a mis-translation.
Yes, sir. Okay, by all means.
Right. So, yeah, how granular do I want to go?
It's okay.
This is like 25 pages of dissertation. I could just refer you back there.
No.
But there's literally a text.
This is how granular this gets. There's a text variant there as to whether it says monone or monone.
But that's how granular we get.
So the only is an adverb, not an adjective.
What they're translating is hours should actually be translated as hour sins.
There's a whole bunch of lexical stuff about that.
So the correct translation is not only for
our sins but for the whole world. The words those of do not occur.
I don't know. Yeah, yeah.
So yeah. So yeah.
But that understanding of it is responsible for a lot of Western Christianity.
Yes.
That's because exactly the question you just asked.
If it read that way, then you're asking the natural question, which is,
what mediates between, right?
Because obviously if you interpret it purely as related to sins
and the forgiveness of sins,
then not everyone in the world has their sins forgiven.
But, and so you have to,
and that's where Peter Lombard in the 11th century
comes up with the idea of sufficiency and efficiency
that Christ sacrifices sufficiency
for the world, but not efficient for the world, right?
And on and on and on.
Um, but
Yeah, that's all based on a mis-translation.
The only other place where the phrase for the whole world,
the phrase the whole world to Olu Kozmu,
occurs in 1st John, is in chapter 5,
the verse we read, the whole world lies
under the power of the evil one.
So if you want to interpret the whole world in 1st John 2,
2 as referring to the
the people in the world.
Then St. John is saying that all the people in the world lie
under the power of the evil one, which would include himself
and church.
Yeah.
And that makes no sense in the context of the epistle, where
he's clearly distinguishing between two groups of people.
So yeah, I'm actually not answering your question.
I'm just pointing out that you asked a perfectly logical
question based on a bad translation.
Nah, nah, nah.
It's quite all right.
All right.
Thank you so much.
Well, thank you for calling, Father.
Okay, we're going to go ahead and take our second break and we'll be back with the third
half of the Lord of Spirits.
Father Andrew Stephen Daymak and Father Stephen DeYoung will be back in a moment to take your
calls on the next part of the Lord of Spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
A-F Radio.
to the three basic and primary disciplines of Orthodox spirituality. Through these disciplines,
Christ opened for us a path that frees us from the disordered way of life who has become normal
for many, even though their hearts and minds tell them otherwise. Please join me in exploring the
three-legged stool of Orthodox spiritual practice, prayer, fasting, and non-sgiving.
Books now available at store.ancientfaith.com. And the title once again is Toolkit for Spiritual
I look forward to sharing it with you. God bless.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits, the Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father
Stephen DeYoung.
If you have a question, call now at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF radio.
All right, well welcome back to the third half of the Lord of Spirits.
We're talking about atonement.
and we've just taken a real-
whirlwind trip through the New Testament. Just I don't know, astonishingly beautiful stuff,
looking at how Christ is both goats in the day of Atonement ritual. He's also the high priest who
is performing the eschatological day of Atonement. All right, well let's, you know, we're just kind of
a mop up now, right?
We've got a few things that we need to mention.
And...
And it's interesting actually one of the first thing it's not our list which is in our notes was something actually someone sent to me
Saying hey you guys gonna mention this and that's the image of what's called the suffering servant in Isaiah chapter 53
So okay, so how is that related to what we've been talking about
Right if at all now if at all right, yeah, where is this when this subject of atonement comes up?
up in most ways.
Western theological circles, this is where they go, right?
It's to Isaiah, specifically Isaiah 53 verses four and five,
which has those famous lines about,
he was wounded for our transgressions by his stripes,
we are healed all of that language.
He took our infirmities upon himself.
That is, you could imagine that's been taken
in a certain...
direction. Yeah, yeah. Here's the thing though, we have a text in the New Testament that says that those
very verses were fulfilled. Yes, right. Okay. Matthew chapter eight. I mean, it's amazing. This is from an
apostle, letting us know how to interpret that Isaiah passage. Matthew chapter eight verses 14
through 17 just to summarize, this is where Christ heals
the mother-in-law of Peter, and then also after that lots of people are brought to him who are
demon-possessed and sick people, and he heals them, he drives out the spirits, he says a cast
amount of the word. And then chapter, verse 17, that it might be fulfilled, which was spoken by Isaiah
the prophet, saying he himself took our infirmities and bore our sicknesses. So Matthew is saying,
This is now fulfilled. What was the suffering-servant passage of Isaiah?
by Jesus' healing ministry of sickness and demon possession. Right? It doesn't say
that it was fulfilled by Jesus absorbing their diseases and becoming sick, or
absorbing their demons and becoming possessed himself. He doesn't take it on
himself in that way. He heals them and that's where that's how Matthew
interprets that passage from Isaiah chapter 4.
53 and you know when an apostle interprets the new Old Testament for you
We go by that. Yeah, but but but we're not just we're not just playing the nope card, right?
Right no no, right there's there's more yeah, there's more to it right because because
That kind of response kind of begs the question
Where it's sort of like well, okay?
What is Saint Matthew talking about right?
It's like how how does him he
diseases fulfill that. Right. And to get it that, we get some help from some of the church
fathers who get what St. Matthew is doing here. Right. And not only do they get what St. Matthew
is doing here, but they talk about this in terms of atonement. Right. They see this as a kind
or type of atonement.
It does end up being germane to our topic this evening.
So probably the most famous church father
to talk about this in terms of Atomin explicitly
is St. Athanasius.
St. Athanasius, the great St. Athanasius of Alexandria
in his work on the incarnation.
Yeah, his single most popular and famous work.
Yes, well, his most well-known work.
and
And it's interesting, I recently heard a certain, he identifies as a Protestant, but most
Protestants would not identify him as a Protestant.
Biblical scholar, talking about atonement and who tried to read Sadie Fadacious's on
the Incarnation and he just said, I can't tell what he's doing.
In terms of this quote, I tried to address it in terms of atonement theory, right?
Yeah, wait.
And from that perspective, it just doesn't make sense. But what he's on to is what
St Matthew is talking about so in short, because our first two halves were already more than half of our times this evening
So we're not gonna go through the whole work. St. Athodacus talks about in tone atonement as happening through the incarnation
that that
by God becoming man
He by virtue of
His holiness as God, that same holiness that they couldn't see and live,
on the day of atonement, the Old Testament.
By becoming man, he purifies humanity.
Not just in terms of, we tend to think of this in quasi-spatial terms.
Almost like the human body seen as a physical thing.
We might go a little further if we understand that the body is this nexus of,
of uh
powers or potentialities to say, well, all of the human powers and all of the human capacities,
but for St. Athanasius and St. Earnayas to something very similar before him by a couple of centuries,
he means spatio temporally, that Christ not only sanctifies humanity in its parts and in its powers,
but the moments of a human life.
Hmm. Birth, childhood, young adulthood, adulthood, up to and including a human death.
Yeah. And by living through those, not just again spatially, but temporarily, those things
are sanctified and purified by the union of Christ's divinity and humanity in his person.
Yeah, that perfect union thereby sanctifies makes holes
purifies humanity in our basic composition. Right? And so he's using atonement in this biblical sense we've been talking about of purification.
Yeah.
But Christ does it by living it. And so this is what Saint Matthew is seeing too in the prophet Isaiah, that by Christ becoming man and living in this world and suffering and experiencing human weakness voluntarily.
of all Ontario
et cetera, et cetera, by doing that, he is healing our humanity.
Yeah, that's cool.
And that just sort of beautifully anticipates St. Gregory the theologian, where, and now he's
speaking in the context of Christology, although, I mean, if you understand Christology in this
full sense, it really just lights up.
Where St. Gregory says, what is not assumed is not healed.
Now he's talking about...
Christ has to be fully human. But within this context of Atonement that Christ assumes the
whole human experience and therefore heals it all. He purifies and attones covers it by virtue of
being here, by virtue of becoming human and going, I don't know, that's really cool.
That's really really cool. I've said that about 20 times tonight, but this is I
I know I love it when this the fundamental unity between the old and new covenants is shown
Yeah, it's you know the
The unity of of it all and including also the teaching the church fathers and what's in the divine services so forth
It's it's so impossibly unified. It's so impossibly won right
But of course what is impossible for man as possible for God yeah
I love it when a plan comes together
Indeed.
The 18.
All right.
Yeah.
OK.
So there, but there was something else also
a connection from John 17, right?
John 17, 18 and 19 also talks about the same idea.
Where Christ, this is in the context,
This is part of the long reading on Holy Thursday evening.
where Christ is, this is sometimes referred to as Christ's high priestly prayer appropriately enough.
And Christ says in verses 18 and 19,
as you sent me into the world, I also have sent them into the world,
and for their sakes I sanctify myself that they also may be sanctified by the truth.
And of course the truth in St. John's Gospel is Christ himself.
when Christ as He sent.
himself. It's not as if he was unholy before and he's doing some action. Yeah. Right. That him sanctifying
himself is talking about his incarnation, his earthly life and his coming, his coming death
in which he has sanctified himself, his person, in order to that, in order that his disciples
and all ages would be sanctified, would be made holy.
Yeah.
That's cool. All right, well, the third half is going to be the shortest half.
But yeah, okay, so to wrap up then, just some final thoughts, you know, I mean,
the nature of this podcast is not the purpose of it, I should say, is not to be
apologetic. Like we're not, you know, we're not here to say, this is why Catholics and Protestants
and various other kinds of religious people are wrong, right?
But in this particular case, even though this episode is not primarily apological, as the whole podcast is not,
there is a disconnect that happens for people when they read the scriptures.
And as we've seen, bring a lot of assumptions into the scriptures.
They think that sins are put on animals and then the animal sacrifice to God.
That never happens in the scripture anywhere.
And so I
I think it's really critical that we understand that a tone meant as the scripture depicts it
is not some kind of system, right?
Where like this is how you get saved and it works like this.
Sins get, for instance, in one version,
Sins get transferred from you to Christ,
and he has to suffer now and be killed and sacrificed.
You know, like that's not what the scripture actually is.
depicts. And here's the problem. Here's the problem with that. Not only is that, I think just
incorrect, but it also makes it so that all the other ways that, as we've now seen, so many of them,
that the ritual of the day of atonement is expressed in the New Testament and in the work of
Christ, you miss a lot of that because it's been reduced to a system.
And our purpose is, as St. John's purpose, these are written that you may believe that Jesus
is the Christ and that believing you may have life in His name.
That's the purpose of this podcast, right?
So I mention all that because as we read Scripture more and as we live the Christian life more,
We
understand what it is that Christ is doing and how the Scripture tells us what he's doing,
then that gives meaning to so much of our lives. If you go through something, for instance,
and you experience it as a kind of harrowing, a purification, a cleansing, a cleaning out,
as we're now, we're about to enter into Great Lent. It is a process of purification. That is what
a great among other things.
That is what Great Len is. But if we understand purification just in this kind of reduced sense,
without all of this atonement imagery from the atonement day of atonement ritual,
and then the eschatological day of atonement, right, then we can tend to look at Christian life as
a kind of self-help program. Okay, I'm just trying to get better, like I'm doing a diet, a spiritual diet.
you know.
And that can lead to a lot of despair.
I mean, if you're a pastor and you're hearing confessions
and you hear people struggle with all the disciplines
of the church that are intended,
for instance, to purify us to help us participate
in purification, then there's a lot of discouragement
that can come from that.
And I think a lot of that comes because
of a kind of reduced vision of what this is about.
Right?
And the other problem with seeing a tonement
is a kind of system is that...
But it actually, it disconnects it from the actual Christian life.
It becomes this mechanism that I sort of get benefited, you know, that benefits me,
rather than something that I ritually participate in.
Right?
You know, one of the big questions that Father Stephen often asks is not as what does this
mean, but what does this do?
Right?
And that is the most important question to it.
ask when you're looking at ritual in scripture. And then of course, as ritual gets repeated
and reused and, you know, all of this kind of stuff in the rest of scripture and in the church
fathers and the divine services and so forth, what does this actually do? Well, we've looked at
this one particular ritual and we now we know what it does. And it does the same thing in us for us
around us throughout the whole cosmos.
And that is so so heart-rendingly beautiful, right?
And it should inspire us to cry out to the Lord for mercy and with gratitude and thankfulness for all that he is done, right?
And then that we then would enter into that and to participate in it ourselves.
So,
Those are some of my takeaways from our conversation this evening.
Father Steven.
Yeah, we've covered a lot and a lot of big stuff.
So this one is kind of the hardest button to button.
But the, the problem and we already talked about this a little bit
with Father Fodius.
A lot of the problems we run into,
theologically and then that end up directly affecting
our life in Christ come from not giving the wrong answers per se, but from asking the wrong
questions. And I think we've seen tonight how a lot of discussions of atonement are based
on reading backwards. So you start with a developed theological idea, read it back into the
New Testament and then from there back into the Old Testament instead of what we hopefully
did with reasonable success tonight which is started the Old Testament.
and read forward and see how things unfold.
But also that there's a fundamental question that gets asked in the West and it comes under
the banner of atonement.
Despite the fact that there's not a whiff of it in what we've seen in our survey tonight.
And that's not just how to salvation work.
how does salvation work from God?
ends. It's not a question of how to salvation work in the sense of what must I do to be
saved, which is a salutary question, pardon the pun. But it is how does it work from God's
end? How does God see it working? How does God make it happen? And a very well-known biblical
scholar at a very good biblical scholar so I'm in Gather Cool.
wrote the magisterial material on the gospel of Thomas,
for example, amongst many other great things.
Did a book a few years ago on atonement,
trying to defend the particular, quote unquote,
atonement theory of penal substitute sharing atonement.
You get these atonement theories
that are then theories of how it works from God's end,
how God does it.
Then he argued, one of his most prominent arguments
you're repeated again and again.
was that
People some situation atonement is the only theory of how it works that has a mechanism for how it works. That's his word
The idea there's a presupposition there that it's somehow mechanical
That that God saving us is like an elaborate rub Goldberg
Machine in an okay-go video or something
Where he puts things in motion and at the end somebody gets saved
It's saved.
And not only is that a bizarre assumption that there's no reason to believe is true,
even if it were true, there's no reason to believe that we as humans could understand how it works from God's side.
But the dangerous thing is, again, not just being wrong, but how this affects our life in Christ.
I am the biggest nerd anyone will ever meet. I am an Omni nerd. I can describe to you the
inner workings of countless fictional universes.
Right? I can tell you all about Iraqis, the desert planet.
I can tell you all about Gala Frey.
I can tell you all about Nimbus V, the planet of Galactic Peace.
I can understand all that, and that's fun.
Figuring out all the details, the systems, all the lore.
This kind of thing is fun.
And it can become very easy when exposed to theology,
especially theology of this kind,
trying to explain how everything works.
and everything fits together and see things from God's perspective to approach our Christian life
from that perspective. That it's about me figuring things out. It's about me piecing things together.
It's about this sort of intellectual construct that I want to form in my mind where I have the
perfect theology and I understand everything. Strictly speaking, that's not Christianity, it's
narcissism. The reality is more...
more like what we were talking about tonight that we see unfold in the scriptures with
atonement and everything else.
That there are these cosmic realities of spiritual warfare, of Christ defeating the powers
of evil, of Christ setting us free and purifying us, making us holy and setting us apart and
bringing us into his kingdom.
That are cosmic realities that each of us has been given the gift of being able to participate
in time.
For moment to moment day to day, we come to experience these realities ever more fully.
We experience them in worship. We experience them in our interactions with other people when we
show the love of God to them. We experience them in the peace we receive from God. In the actual
forgiveness and healing we receive for our actual sins on a day to day basis. This isn't just an
intellectual maneuver. This is something we can experience and participate in in real time.
and that's what Lenton
we can Pascar are going to be all about. So it's not about me or me and
Father Andrew or the Orthodox Church or anyone else coming and just bashing on
Western churches and saying, ha ha you guys are all wrong you guys are
asking the wrong questions. It's about the reality of when the rubber meets
the road and how each of us approaches our Christian life. What we want is not
just to understand salvation.
to experience salvation. And understanding the cosmic realities and how we come to participate
them, ritually and every other way, is the way that that experience becomes real to us.
So I think that's the hopefully the important takeaway beyond all the fun stuff and interesting
Bible tidbits. That this isn't just about knowing the right interpretation.
thinking the right thing, but it's about experiencing the reality of Christ.
Amen. Well, that is our show for today. Thank you very much for listening everybody.
On our next episode, we're going to be starting a two-part series on sacred geography.
If you didn't get a chance to call in during the live broadcast, we'd love to hear from you,
either via email at LordofspiritsatEngineFate.com
you can message us at our Lord of Spirits Podcast.
Facebook page, we read everything but can't respond to everything you send so much.
We do say what you send for possible use in future episodes.
And join us for our live broadcasts on the second and fourth Thursdays of the month at
7pm Eastern 4pm Pacific.
If you have a Facebook account, you should probably delete it.
But if you can't like our Facebook page and join our Facebook discussion group or we'll
be your oasis amongst the evils of social media.
reviews and ratings but most importantly share this show with a friend.
whom you know is going to love it.
And finally, be sure to go to www.AxiaFaith.com.
Stroke Support and help make sure we and lots of other AFR podcasters stay on the air.
Thank you very much and God bless you all.
You've been listening to the Lord of Spirits with Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew
Stephen Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung, a listener supported presentation.
ancient faith radio. And I beheld and I heard the voice of many angels round about the throne
and the beasts and the elders and the number of them was 10,000 times 10,000 than thousands of
thousands, saying with a loud voice worthy as the land that was slain to receive power and riches
and wisdom and strength and honor and glory and blessing. Revelation chapter 5 verses 11 through 12.