He will be a staff for the righteous with which for them to stand and not to fall.
And he will be the light of the nations and the hope of those whose hearts are troubled.
All who dwell on the earth will fall down and worship him,
and they will praise and bless and celebrate with song the Lord of Spirits.
1st denoc, chapter 48, verses 4-5.
The modern world doesn't acknowledge but is nevertheless haunted by spirits,
Angels, demons and saints in our
time many year into break free of the prison of a flat secular materialism to see
and to know reality as it truly is. What is this spiritual reality like? How do
we engage with it well? How do we permeate everyday life with spiritual
presence? Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father
Stephen De Young post this live Colin show focused on enchantment in creation.
The union of the scene and unseen as made by God
and experienced by mankind throughout history.
Welcome to The Lord of Spirits.
Welcome back to The Lord of Spirits Podcast.
I'm Father Andrew Stephen Damick,
and with me is my co-host Father Stephen De Young.
And if you are listening to us live,
you can call in at 855 AF Radio.
That's 855-237-2346.
and we
will get to your calls in the second part of today's show. Now this is a very content
heavy show. I think they're all going to be that way probably. And we want to balance
that with your calls. So don't feel bad if you don't get through this time. Just, you
know, reconnect, try next time. And God willing, we'll get to talk to you. So last time we
introduced this brand new program by talking about divine plurality in the scriptures.
is the idea that there are multiple kinds of divine beings.
for whom the Bible uses the word gods, angels, demons, and even dead humans. And we also
work clear that there's no one among these gods who is like Yahweh, the God of gods and Lord
of lords, the Father, Son, and Holy Spirit. And then we got to talking a bit about angels and
demons. But there is so very much more to discuss on this. And of course, we'll probably be talking
about angels and demons pretty much as long as this program is around. So we wanted to continue today,
They are convers-
on these divine beings by beginning with the divine council,
the divine council, and that's an image that is given in scripture.
And of course, also depicted in the writings of the Church Fathers in Orthodox iconography
in Orthodox Church architecture and in the liturgical texts of the Church.
So to get us into this, I just want you to picture the icon of all saints.
So if you don't know what that looks like, you can actually go to our Facebook page,
Lord of Spirits podcast, Facebook page.
And you'll see that today we shared some images
of the All Saints icon, also icons of the synoxies
that's the gathering of the Archangels.
And if you look at that icon,
you'll see it as Christ in the center
and he's typically enthroned, sometimes he's enthroned
on Angelic beings.
And he's surrounded by his angels and his saints.
So that's the image that I want you to keep in your mind
especially as we talk about the Divine Council.
So, you know, Father Stephen, we've got our Bibles open.
It's almost like, now this isn't your Bible study podcast, the whole Council of God,
which I super recommend everybody.
But I do think you probably will generally want to bring your Bible to listen to this
show.
I've got two Bibles next to me, and hopefully that's enough.
But yeah, Father Stephen, why don't you lead us into this discussion about the Divine
Council, and we're going to begin with the Holy Scripture.
Uh, uh, uh...
Absolutely. So what we're talking about when we talk about the divine council is the fact that
that God, in this case Yahweh, the God of Israel, our God, is God most high. You may be familiar with
that phrase from the early parts of Genesis, but that phrase the most high, you may have
have noticed is also what demons call God.
For example, in the exorcism stories in the Gospels, they referred to Christ as son of the most high.
And this is because of a relationship that was understood by pretty much everyone in the Incensate world.
That
there was not sort of we talked last time about how
monotheism wasn't a category in the Incensate world that people used.
so no one thought that there was this one God
who they worship to stood all by himself in the heavens.
And that's not the picture we're given by the scriptures.
But in what we find in the ancient culture surrounding
Israel is they had what we've mostly been taught
if we've studied mythology in the modern world
as a quote unquote pantheon, that there's
sort of this group of gods who are in charge of things.
But that's not really how it worked in the ancient world.
Right. Right. Right. Right. The way it worked in the ancient world is that individual cities and places
and regions and nations had a God, a spirit whom they worshiped, who they saw as sort of their
patron in the heavens. And then when you have larger units developed like Sumeria or Assyria
or Ahad or Syria.
the Phoenicians, etc., all of those gods get put together into sort of a group.
And generally whichever city or region had ascendancy, their God is seen as sort of the
king of the gods.
And it's not just a question of there being one God who's sort of on top at any given
time.
uniformly in all of these cultures there is a divine
father who is seen as the most high God and then a divine son who is actually the primary
God who receives worship, who is the one who presides in the counsel of the gods.
So you have L and Bale with the Canaanites, you have Aya and Marduk with the Babylonians,
You have crotos and Zeus with the Greeks and the key difference here in the conception.
when we get to Israel is that they see Yahweh as filling sort of both of those roles.
There is a Yahweh that divine Father and a Yahweh the Son, and this isn't something that
Christians come up with. This is something that's in the Torah.
Right, right. And they're both, and they're both most high God, which I think it's, I think it's
really important to emphasize that title for a second because not that we want to dive back
into
what we talked about too much in our previous episode,
I think there's gonna be a lot of overlap
between all of our episodes.
But you know, you don't say most high God
if there aren't other divine beings, right?
You know, and yet that title,
the most high is used over and over again in scripture.
So clearly there is this sense
that he is God over other divine beings.
And like you said that in the case of ancient Israel,
that the most high God is
both the father and the son, whereas in most other stories, the son is overthrowing his father
typically, right? Isn't that right? Or the son is overthrowing a previous most high god
at least. There's what's called the succession myth, the succession story, where there's
this transition. And when we get to talking about the devil, we'll talk about how the way he's
Please present.
that it in scripture is sort of mirroring those stories
but pointing out that that story actually
had a different result.
Yeah, and he fails.
Right, the propaganda that the bail worshippers
and the Marduk worshippers, et cetera,
the Zeus worshippers would have you believe.
But it's important also here to recognize,
along with the difference that there is Yahweh,
the Father and Yahweh, the Son,
and that
There is no succession, those being two key differences.
The rest of that picture, the picture that there is this council, this divine council,
over which Yahweh presides is very much incontinuity between Israel and the surrounding nations.
So the language that was used particularly by the Canaanites, the Canaanites.
It's referred to the counsel of God as the sons of L,
because L was their most high God.
And so that sons of L, that sons of God language
is taken over directly into the Old Testament
to refer to angelic beings who are not God's in and of themselves,
but are members of this counsel through whom God's will
God's will is expressed.
in the same way that a king on earth has, you know, vice-royers in regions and
advisors and other people around him through whom he administers his kingdom.
Yahweh the God of Israel is depicted as having these angelic beings through whom
he administers his kingdom which is of course all of creation. Yeah and it's
interesting that they're called sons of God, right? And I think you know, like
That shouldn't be hard for us to grow.
because you mentioned earthly kingdoms. I mean your average earthly king tends to put his sons and his brothers and you know that it's members of the family.
He puts in charge of elements of the government and you know for human beings that's not always necessarily a good idea just because you remember the royal family doesn't mean you're good at it.
but we're not talking about human family here.
We're talking about God and His Son, our Lord Jesus Christ.
and then these ranks of angels that are referred to as sons of God.
So, and like that title appears in a number of places in the scripture, doesn't it?
Sons of God.
Yes, I mean, sons of God, famously, a Genesis 6, which is a whole separate
discussion that we'll have here in coming weeks.
Yes, it turns your heads for that one, everybody.
Yeah, but but all through the solbs it's used every and this is this is one of the reasons.
reasons why in the New Testament why the Greek word Manonianese, I know people are used
to that being translated only begotten, but I have bad news for you.
That's not what it means.
The begotteness of Christ is reflected in, for example, Proverbs, there are biblical
texts from which the fathers derived that idea.
It was not just from the word mononis.
Mono Unis really just sort of means unique.
So it's saying Christ is the Unicent.
One of a kind.
To distinguish his sonship.
Right. His sonship is different
because he's begotten from the Father.
His sonship is different from anyone else
who gets the title son of God,
including of course believers.
St. Paul at the beginning of Romans 8, for example,
talks about us becoming sons of God.
and sometimes that gets occluded by our modern train
translations that want to be more gender neutral and they say children of God and so you lose the sons of God language
And so you sort of lose St. Paul's point that it's not just a family metaphor, but it's referring to
This role of sons of God in the in the divine council. Yeah, well, it doesn't even doesn't even Christ use that term
In Luke or am I misremembering that
When he talks about becoming sons of the resurrection
Maybe I'm misremembering exactly.
I don't think he uses terms, sons, sons of God there,
but I may be misremembering too.
Yeah.
I'm going to look this up while we're talking here.
Yeah, no, Luke, so Luke 2036.
Now, I'm not looking at the Greek, but in the Eastern,
the New King James, it says they are equal to the angels
and are sons of God being sons of the resurrection.
That's OK.
Yeah, OK.
Well, there you go.
So that language is actually used by Christ himself.
at least I'm looking at this translation.
I can grab my Greek and make it up here for a break.
Just to make sure I'm looking at this,
I don't wanna miss anybody here.
But yeah, this is a really important phrase
that appears at a lot of times in the Bible.
Yeah, and this idea is so central
that it's part of how we understand the place,
quote unquote, right?
because of course the place where God is.
is not a physical place as if he's somewhere and not other places.
But the place where God dwells the place where he is is described in terms of his being
surrounded by the angelic beings in the council.
And this is part of why, as you mentioned in iconography, you see Christ enthroned upon
angelic beings, right?
We talk about God sitting upon the chair of him.
Right?
We're going to talk about probably later on.
in the show, some angels whose names reflect the fact that they're parts of God's throne.
But beyond that, the place where God dwells is referred to as the mountain of assembly,
it's Harmohade in Hebrew. And that's, you know, this is again something that's held
in common with pretty much every other culture in the ancient world who believed that God's
lived in sort of a combination of two places. Number one, because there was so much desert
in the ancient Near East, the place where God dwells must be sort of luxurious and verdant,
so it must be some kind of garden. And then it must be some place where mortals
fear to tread. Right, and don't go. And so it's on a mountain.
And so you get course method of assembly idea.
Yeah, and of course for, I mean, like I'm thinking about the mythology that I remember
reading when I was a kid, and the one that comes to mind, of course, is Mount Olympus.
You know, and I remember seeing those movies from the 1960s, right?
I loved all those Greek mythology movies where you got, you know, the camera pans up
the mountain and you go through some clouds.
And there's Zeus and Hera, you know, you're usually like next to some kind of fountain or
something like that.
And but then they're all surrounded by all these gods, right?
So there's this common notion that all ancient people
have of the most high god is up on a mountain somewhere and he's surrounded by all of these other
divine beings, right? And that's in the Bible too. Yeah, that's, and that's as one of our
colors last week brought up for for bail. That was mountains of phone, the mountain of the north.
And that then becomes not one but several mountains over the course of the scriptures.
I mean the famous obvious example.
Pills are Mount Sinai and Mount Zion become the place where God dwells become the mountain of God.
And then of course when you get to the New Testament Mount Tabour at the event of the Transfiguration.
And what we see in all those cases is not just, oh well this is the place where God is temporarily, but there are specific mentions in all of those cases of this angelic counsel
So
rounding him at those places. Right? The law comes through angels, according to the
say Paul. Right. On
sign on the law comes serangles. Yeah, it's interesting. You know, I think about, you know,
it so much of this like to look at these things in scripture closely is rewriting the images
in my mind that I grew up with. So I mean, I grew up evangelical products and I grew up reading
the Bible. But also like, I wonder sometimes how much people's sense of, for instance,
what happens in
Exodus is formed by Charlton Heston. Right? You know, that movie, The Ten Commandments.
I think about that scene where Moses receives the Ten Commandments, where he receives the law.
And he's on this mountain by himself. He's all alone. And then, you know, these letters appear
on the side of the mountain. You're there being burned to the side of the mountain as God gives
each one of the Ten Commandments. And then they kind of burn out of the mountain and he's got
got these two tablets underneath.
takes them down. And it's funny, like that was the image in my head of Moses receiving the law from God.
But that's not what the Bible actually depicts. It actually talks about angels being involved,
that he's surrounded by the heavenly hosts, that Moses goes to meet God, and there is the divine
counsel surrounding him. Right? Yeah, if you follow all of the data, it's in the whole of the
the scriptures.
What happens is Moses, after his 40 days of purification, ascends the mountain, comes into
the Garden of God at the top of the mountain, enters into the tent in which God dwells with
the divine counsel, where he's surrounded by the angelic beings.
There speaks to him face to face.
He gives the covenant on the tablets written with his own hands.
right, which is which is then delivered to him. And then he descends and he creates the tabernacle.
This is according to St. Paul's epistle to the Hebrews. He creates the tabernacle as a replica
of the place he went and what he saw when he was on top of the mountain. Yeah.
Right. It's interesting. You know, when when you read the Bible as a whole,
then some of these pictures be
become clearer, whereas if you just pick out, you know, maybe the main narrative, then
some of it is kind of sometimes is left out and you only get it from other parts, right?
Like that reference to the law being received through angels is not, I don't think it's
there in Exodus, as it doesn't say that explicitly, there are no such as.
But, but, but clearly, clearly, first century Jews believed this.
So it's this tradition that's included in witness
to another parts of scripture. But it's hard, you know, sometimes it's hard to connect
the dots. You don't know, like, I'm sure I read that line about the law being received
through angels when I was a kid and didn't think, Oh, wait, I need to rewrite my picture
of what happens on Sinai with Moses. This is not like with Charlton Houston, you know,
as much as I'm not going to be. It's a great movie.
It's a Paul Inglations what he's talking about that fact goes so far as
to make the point that the person who Moses was speaking to face to face was Christ.
Right.
Yep.
That's the Yahweh who he saw is God the Son who was incarnate in these latter days.
And that's Keda.
I don't want to go into that now, but that's Keda.
the arguments St. Paul is making in Galatians
in not repudiating the Torah.
He's ultimately arguing the Torah came from the same Christ who now has fulfilled it.
But so yeah, so the picture, part of it is that in the ancient Near East, as I said,
these ideas were so common and so well known that reading the text of Exodus, for centuries
the heirs of the text, because they weren't actually reading it themselves, but the heirs
of the text understood this whole picture from the text.
Yeah, yeah, because they knew where God's live and how that works and
Right, right. They didn't they didn't need all those details written in there
So well, we've got about eight minutes until we're gonna go to break so let's um let's try to look at some specific
Bible passages that just you know give a little bit of the evidence of what we're talking about so we want to think
Oh, they're just making that stuff up
Let's let's actually dig in a little bit to that
before we go to break here and
just about eight minutes. So I see you haven't noticed you've got Psalm 82, which probably
you're going to be hearing about Psalm 82 a lot in this show.
Yeah, well let's go on there. Let me do one text first and I don't, oh yeah, they don't
get to Psalm 82. Okay. And this, this what I don't want to go into to super deep because
we're getting to it more again when we talk about the devil in particular, but yeah, in
Isaiah, Isaiah 14, 13.
And sort of the accusation against the being who we know as the devil.
God says to him, you said in your heart, I will ascend to heaven.
Above the stars of God, I will set my throne on high.
I will sit on the Mount of Assembly in the remote parts of Zafon.
Again, Mount Zafon because the devil's here being connected to bail.
But there's that language.
of his rebellion being attempting to sit on the throne,
he can assembly to overthrow God as King
and take his place in his rule over creation
and the beings whom he has created.
So it's Psalm 82 that we talked about last time.
The, that begins with God has taken his place
in the case.
Council of the Gods in the midst of the gods,
he holds judgment.
So there's this place for God who presides.
And then he judges those other gods
and in verses six and seven,
it's I said,
you are God's sons of the most high, all of you.
Nevertheless, like men you shall die
and fall like any prince.
So that language of sons of the most high,
You see them?
being called gods. And based on the way Christ quotes this in St. John's Gospel, he is identifying
himself as the God of Psalm 82 verse 1. He says that these gods who are condemned here are the ones
to whom the word of God came. Right. Logos the U is in St. John's Gospel does not refer to the Bible.
Yeah, no, that's him.
He's the word of God.
He is the word made flesh, right?
So he is that one that divine son who presides
over the council and renders judgment.
I think we also talked briefly about Psalm 89
verses five through seven last time,
but just read that again quickly.
At the heavens praise your wonders O Yahweh,
your faithfulness in the assembly of the holy ones
for who in this guy
can be compared to Yahweh. Who among the sons of God is like Yahweh, a God greatly to be feared
in the counsel of the holy ones and awesome above all who are around him. So you very clearly have
that idea of him being surrounded by this, this counsel. Right, and I think it's important, especially
there to see that comparative language, right, like who is like you, right? Because, because,
because we got a little bit of pushback.
Just a little bit of pushback on social media from a couple of people kind of suggesting
based on our last episode like are you guys polytheists?
Like really should you be talking about gods and the plural and so forth.
But the thing is that
the scripture not only uses this language of God being the most high god which means there are other
gods but also the language of other gods but also makes this comparative point.
Who is like, who is like Yahweh?
Well answered no one.
No one is a-
So just because we use the word God to refer both to the Father, Son and Holy Spirit and even to demons or to angels or to
departed human beings, doesn't mean that we mean that they're the same kind of being.
You know, that the point is that he's incomparable.
Nothing compares to the one true God.
Right? So I think I just wanted to kind of underland that point again.
and this notion that...
you know, that there are no other gods who are like the one true God. He's he's
God in a way that they're not. But we still use the word God to refer to all of them. So yeah.
Right. And the same way that we say, you know, Christ is man, but he's not just a man.
Because we say that. Right. Right. Right. Right. So we could say Christ is man with a capital
the same way we capitalize the G in God. Yeah, he's the man.
not to be a little too, he's the man.
But, I mean, like Psalm 1, right, blessed is the man,
who is the man who walks out in the council of the ungodly?
He's the one.
Yeah.
Yep, yep.
So I won't read the text of these,
but people can look in in Job chapter 1, 6 through 12,
and Job 2, verses 1 through 6,
which both describe this probably familiar to people
heavenly scene of the council sort of being convened
and the Satan.
Satan is not a name and job. It's an office that somewhat holds. Yeah, the end of the
adversary. But so he comes, he then comes into the council. And the one that I want
to read on in this will probably bring us to the end of our first half, once we
talk about it a little is this is probably the most controversial example, too, in
terms of weird Old Testament texts that people don't like talking about.
At least for tonight.
First Kings 22 versus 19 through 23,
which is third kingdoms,
if you're using the Orthodox study Bible
or something else based on the Greek text.
And so what's happening here is,
Ahab has finally kind of reached his limit of wickedness
and so now is going to be subject to judgment.
And so...
Yahweh, the God of Israel is decided, now's the time. Right, I'm going to put it into Ahab. And so
we now have this scene unfolds and Makiah, the prophet, is now describing this scene. So,
starting in verse 19, and Makiah said, therefore, here the word of Yahweh, I saw Yahweh sitting on
his throne and all the host of heaven standing beside him on his right hand and on his left.
And you always said who will entit-
ae have that he may go up and fall at Raymeth Gillian and one said one thing and
another said another. Then a spirit came forward and stood before Yahweh saying,
I will entice him and Yahweh said to him by what means and he said, I will go out
and will be a lying spirit in the mouth of all his prophets and he said, you are
to entice him and you shall succeed go out and do so. Now therefore behold,
Yahweh has put a line spirit in the mouth of all these your prophets.
Yahweh has declared disaster for you.
Well, uh, so yeah, that's interesting.
Like, okay, the God basically says, I'm going to take a have down, you know, do have any volunteers.
Right. Right.
And I mean, the scripture, the scripture basically says that he's different spirit step forward and say,
well, I've got an idea. I've got an idea.
And then one says, I'll do this.
And God picks that one.
Yeah, God sends that spirit to go and basically to go to
into all of the prophets who A.
have listens to, which aren't the good ones.
There'd be the prophets of Bale at this point.
And tell him that, yeah, if he goes into battle,
he's going to win.
It's going to be a route.
It's going to be an incredible victory.
When, in fact, he's going to be defeated and killed.
And so this bothers many people because it sure
sounds like God has this evil lying spirit working for him.
who he says to go trick Ahab.
So the first thing I would point out is,
notice though that after this scene unfolds,
God sends his own prophet to Ahab to warn him.
Yeah, right.
That's what Makai is doing.
Makai basically comes to Ahab and says,
look, this is what's happening.
Yahweh, the God of Israel has sent a spirit
to all those prophets you're listening to.
They're lying to you.
If you go into battle you're gonna die.
Yeah, right and so they have has to choose who to believe yeah, you have to look at the whole picture
The whole story all at once you can't just pick a moment in and say well, I don't like what God is doing right here
You know
Yeah, yeah, and I see you I'm sorry go ahead
I was gonna ask if you wanted to read this from say Gregory the Deologist
Yeah, yeah, yeah, so I thought this would be a good way to end up this segment
with a chord from one of the
Holy Father is talking specifically about this passage that we just read.
So this is what St. Gregory, the deologist, also called Gregory the Great in the Western
tradition.
This is what he says.
And this is from his text called the Moralia in Job chapter 2.
What is the throne of the Lord unless we understand it as the endelic powers?
He is enthroned on high in their minds and thus he controls everything below.
That is the host of heaven unless it means the many ministries.
angels. Then why does it say that the host of heaven stands on his right hand and on his left?
Since God exists in everything and is also outside everything, he is not limited by right and left
hands. But the right hand of God is the elect part of the angels, and the left hand of God means the
fallen part of the angels. Not just the good serve God by the help that give us, but the wicked
also serve him by the trials they inflict on us. Not just the ones who lift up anyone who turns back
from sin but also the weak
who pushed down anyone who refuses to turn back. So the angel of coast stands on the right hand
and on the left hand of God, the will of the elect spirits harmonizes with the divine mercy
and the minds of the fallen ones when they serve their own evil ends obey the judgment of God's
stern decrees. So we're going to talk a little bit more about what he says about
evil spirit serving him in the third part of our show today. But why don't we
Go ahead and go to a break and we'll be back and we will start taking your calls in
the second part of the Lord of Spirits.
Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung will be back in a moment to take your
calls on the second half of the Lord of Spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF radio.
Hi, this is-
This Father Evan Armitas, priest at St. Spirit on Greek Orthodox Church in Lulang, Colorado,
and the host of the Ancient Faith Radio, Sunday Night Call and Show, Orthodoxy Live.
I am pleased to announce today the release of my first book for Ancient Faith Publishing,
titled, Toolkit for Spiritual Growth, a Practual Guide to Prayer, Fasting and Arms Giving.
It seeks to provide a guide to the three basic and primary disciplines of Orthodox spirituality.
these disciplines Christ opened for us a path that frees us from the
This sort of way of life has become normal for many, even though their hearts and minds
tell them otherwise.
Please join me in exploring the three-legged stool of Orthodox spiritual practice, prayer,
fasting, and nomsgiving.
Books now available at store.ancientfaith.com.
And the title once again is Toolkit for Spiritual Grove.
I look forward to sharing it with you.
God bless.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits, the Father and
and father Steven DeYoung.
If you have a question, call now at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF radio.
Welcome back.
This is the second part of our show
and it's where we begin to take your calls.
So you can call us at 855-AF radio.
That's 855-237-2346.
You can also send questions to chatroom,
But we were especially.
love to hear your voices. And just to kind of wrap up our conversation from the first part
of the show, I just wanted to remind you of those images that we talked about at the beginning,
the icon of all saints, the icon of the synoxys of the bodyless powers of the Archangels. And you
can look at our Facebook page, the Lord of Spirit's Facebook page, and you can see lots and lots of
images of that. And the other thing I wanted to mention is an element from church architecture,
And that is something called the sin thrown on.
Now, in most orthodox,
now, the synthronon is actually very sort of reduced in its form, but you'll see
behind the altar table in the eastern part of the church in what is that area
called the apps. You'll see a throne there in many churches if there's space for
it, and that is the Bishop's throne, and then sometimes you'll see chairs next to
it. Well, again, if you look at our Facebook page, you'll see we posted pictures
from ancient churches of what is called the synthronon, and you'll see that it
almost looks like a miniature...
So there's kind of one throne in the middle and then these rows of like bleachers almost next to it
and so what's going on there? That's actually the fuller ancient form of the scene thrown on and that is the place where the bishop sits at certain parts of the divine liturgy, not the whole thing.
And his presbyter is sitting next to him again at certain parts of the divine liturgy in the hierarchical divine liturgy of the church.
And that image is exactly an image of what we've been talking about the divine count.
So the bishop is the icon of Christ and any surrounded by his presbyters.
You can see both at just the general sense of the divine council
but also the idea that this is Christ with the apostles next to him ready to render judgment at
At the Potosia at his second manifestation. So those are just some images to have in your mind and
But anyways, we want to get to some of your calls and we promise by the way that on this show that no question
No question is too weird.
And I don't know how many of you are old enough to remember the TV show Frazier from the 1990s, but I've always wanted to have a colon show where I said, I'm listening.
So we are listening and we're going to get to your calls in just a second. And we want to talk now about specific angelic beings. So we're going to get now into some details of the angelic beings.
but so so you know father again let's let's bring us in we're gonna talk about
St. Denise
The area of a guy, a lot of people think about him when you're talking about ranks of angels and the types of angels.
But of course, the various kinds of angels, the ranks of angels are all described in scripture.
They're described in the anaphora of the divine liturgy, right?
I think both Christostom's liturgy and basals, if I remember correctly, I don't know if I'm misremembering there.
But you know, you hear about principalities, powers, dominions, thrones, etc., etc., right?
So lots of different kinds of angels.
And one of the questions we've gotten sometimes is...
are these like different species? Like why do some angels look like wheels with wings and eyes on
them and others look like human beings with wings? So what's going on there? Like why do angels
look so different in various icons? Right, well that's yeah, that species issue is important
in terms of myth busting a little. And that tends to be how we look at it. You know, we look at it
like sort of like fantasy races, right?
like there's dwarves and elves and gnomes and, right?
And so we've got these different types of angels
or angelic species that look different ways.
But of course, angels don't reproduce.
Right.
These are jelly beings.
Yeah.
They're not supposed to, Genesis 6 again,
but we'll get to that another.
That'll be another episode.
At the point.
But yeah.
But they, you know, they don't reproduce.
So there are.
isn't like a species that has a certain appearance, right?
Based on that.
And so angelic beings are really sort of cosmic intelligences.
And the descriptions we generally see of them are more human beings struggling to describe
what they're seeing.
You know?
And so you get wheels with eyes and sometimes sort of crazy sounding things.
these different...
ranks of angels that we talk about are exactly that.
They're ranks. These titles are really jobs.
And part of the problem with how we talk about them is that
because we don't want to say the word gods.
Right.
We end up calling them angels or angelic beings so that we don't
trigger anybody.
But angel is actually one of those jobs.
it's messenger.
So that's one of the jobs, not all of these ranks obviously have that job.
So, right.
And calling them angels is technically accurate, right?
Yeah, it's, it's, it's, it'll be like saying the whole army is made up of privates, you
know, of corperals or whatever, targets.
Yeah.
Right.
So, okay.
So, so we before we get into some specific ranks of them, we want to take one of your
calls and we have Ashley calling
from Minnesota and Ashley is calling.
She says that she used to be a polytheist
who was told to worship Yahweh.
So Ashley, are you there?
Yeah, so a long time listener, first time caller.
Ha, ha, ha.
Um, we've been listening for two weeks.
Good job.
Well, we've heard the first episode, right?
So, um, that is not just me.
So I put this for a few times.
I'm gonna give you the exit.
experience of a friend of mine. But I've heard this story several times.
Friend of mine, very smart, I mean, incredibly intelligent person,
quite literally worships Zeus and the Greek God. And then his devotional one day was told
basically you've been a good and faithful servant, but now you need to serve the God we serve.
And I could this story from other X-pagans and I'm sure
So let me get this straight that you're basically saying that your friend, so this is a story that was told to you, but from multiple people, that worship pagan gods was told by someone in a spiritual experience that they need to worship the God that those gods serve. Is that what you're saying?
Is that what you're saying?
Yes, yes. I had a similar sense of mind's not nearly.
quote-founding. Okay, yeah, so what's going on there? Father Stephen, I mean I have some thoughts,
but Father Stephen, I don't know, I want to hear what you have to say about this first. Sure, well
as we read in that quote from St. Gregory, even the what we would call the demonic powers serve
the true God despite themselves. Right?
And this is why even though it may brush past us,
we're told that ultimately,
every knee will bow and every tongue will confess
that Jesus Christ is Lord,
both in heaven and on earth and under the earth,
meaning the underworld, right?
Sheol, Hades.
And we see, for example, during Christ's ministry,
whenever Christ actually approaches someone
whose demon possessed the demon.
and is sort of compelled by his presence to confess his identity, right?
Sort of against his will, you know, because they know exactly who Christ is.
And so we're going to end up talking about the Tower of Babel again in a future episode.
But originally, when these powers and principalities were assigned by God to administer places and
nations and cities and people.
people's, they were assigned as angels and it was to lead those people to God most high,
to Yahweh, the God of Israel. And despite the fact that they've been worshiped as an
ends in themselves, that many of them would become fallen and become the powers and principalities
that St. Paul says we're at war with.
In Acts 17, when St. Paul is...
is talking to them in Athens about the unknown God, about the most high God who's now calling them
back to him through the gospel. He tells them that he was never that far off, right, that it was
still possible for them despite the intervening issues of paganism to find their way back to God,
to reach out and touch him in Romans.
St. Paul says that the truth of this is...
written in the stars, he meant that literally, like the Magi coming to
Christ's birth, this had been there for these these pagans still to see. He doesn't
say that it's impossible. And so from my perspective what you're talking about
is just a modern actual occurrence of what St. Paul was saying was possible.
Yeah, and you know the thing that I would
I was just saying the thing that I would add also is that number one, it's certainly possible
that these demonic spirits that people are interacting with can be, you know, will serve
the one true God if it's his will for him to do that.
But also that, you know, that one of the non-rebellious spirits, you know, one of the unfallen
God's so to speak that write the angelic powers.
breaking through into that person's experience and saying,
come on, it's time to worship the only God now,
the only God worthy of worship.
So it's hard to tell, right?
Like we're not, Father Stephen and I are not demonologists,
we're not exorcists except in our task as priests.
We don't have expertise in specific experience
with angels and spirits and so forth.
but never the le-
you know, when you're talking about demonic spirits, they're not going to be dealing with someone in a straightforward way.
I mean, these are, these are big liars, right? They're extremely deceitful. And so they're going to present themselves to people in all kinds of different ways.
And so there's just so many possibilities, right? In a particular instance, but does that make sense to you, Ashley? What we're saying?
Absolutely. It's very interesting and again.
We love the show. Hope it keeps going for a long time. Thank you very much for calling Ashley good to hear from you
Okay, so let's talk now. Oh, sorry. Go ahead father
I was just to say you know that the the triparian of the Nativity says that
Those who worship the stars were taught by a star to a door the son of righteousness
Right. Yep exactly exactly. Yeah, so let's start talking about some of these very specific ranks, right? So
So, you know, the Seraphim thrones diminu-
and I'd like to actually cover all of them.
There's nine ranks, traditionally, right?
Nine ranks of angels.
And then a number of them are grouped together.
There's pairs.
I'm seeing a couple of pairs here in this list.
Let's start talking about so.
Yeah.
Let's start.
So we've got Sarah Fomen-Cheribim are up at the top.
And those are the ones that typically are depicted
in really weird shapes.
Shapes among others. I mean there's various there
But Sarifim and Cheribim are kinds of angels that maybe people have heard those terms more likely.
And they're depicted often as like animals, aren't they?
They usually look like animals.
Well, maybe not in our modern art.
But Cheribs in particular are usually fat babies with little ones.
Yeah, right.
In your reticence.
No fat babies with wings on this podcast.
Ha ha ha.
little harp playing. But in fact,
Caruve, which is where we get Caruveem is the plural.
Caruve literally means a living creature.
And so when you see like the living creatures in Revelation, those are those are Caruveem.
But in particular what they looked like if you've seen we could probably post
pictures of this after the show online.
But if you've ever seen probably the most famous ones
are at the gates of Nineveh,
which are now in the British Museum.
It looks sort of like a Babylonian's finks.
It's got sort of wings and a lion body in the head of a man
with sort of the ringlet beard.
Oh yeah, right, right.
You can see it in Babylonian depictions.
Those are caravhing.
Now I'm thinking...
What about like Gryffins?
Are Gryffins essentially just another kind of expression
of the same being?
Am I getting my head on my stuff here?
Yeah, well, yeah.
Well, no, it's okay.
There's sort of a later evolution of it
because Gryffins fulfilled some of that same role.
They're generally associated with royalty.
Okay.
Right.
The role of the Caribbean was that they were throne guardians,
Okay, they protected the thrones of kings.
and gods. Right. And of course, then they should neary those were kind of the same thing
most of the time. They're believed at least. Right. Right. So we read about, of course, all
through the Old Testament, God is described as being enthroned on the caravine, seated upon
the caravine. And of course, there were the gigantic caravine in the temple. There are
the carav-
on the Ark of the Covenant that was in the Tabernacle, there are also caravim woven into the
as tapestries in the Tabernacle. And then there were giant caravim in the most holy place in
the temple. They were representing there the throne of God.
And this I mean, were these even statues or really for icon statues? We're talking great big
big stage.
in giant statues.
Yeah.
After, yeah, in the ones that were in the temple in Jerusalem,
after Titus destroyed the temple in 70 AD or 80 70.
So, they were taken to Antioch because after Jerusalem was destroyed,
Antioch had the largest Jewish population in the world.
And they were put on display in the Jewish quarter of Antioch,
it's sort of a warning against uprisings there.
Uh, wow.
must have been demoralizing. That was sort of the moment.
That was the idea. Yeah, display of power there. But so those were
representation of the throne of God being there. And that the Ark of the
Covenant and then the altar were the footstool of God's throne. So those
were thrown guardians. And we talk about Christ being seated upon the
care of you.
for that reason. The the Syrahim, which are often when these are listed in order of rank
or often ranked higher, they're often seen as sort of surrounding the throne of God, but
they had a similar role. They were also throne guardians, but rather than the Babylonian
tradition that the Caravim are related to and that imagery, they're related to Egyptian
imagery. The Seraf is
is the Egyptian word for a serpent.
Yeah, in fact, I mean, I'm not a linguist,
but I'm just gonna throw out a guess here
and say that's set off and serpent are cognates
just looking at the two words that strongly suggests.
Yeah, yeah, yeah, I'll have to go look that one up.
So, I mean, just to pause here for a second.
So we're talking about imagery from Egyptian tradition,
from the Babylonian tradition.
I mean, is the Bible, I mean,
because these are in the Bible, is it being sacred?
Are they incorporating Egyptian paganism and Babylonian paganism?
I mean, my answer to that obviously would be, no, it's not syncretistic.
They're just, what's happening is, is that Israel and these other cultures are looking at the same reality
and the way that it's being depicted as being borrowed perhaps.
Is that, am I right on this?
Well, all right, the syncretism assumes it's not true.
not true. Yeah right.
Right. Right. It's not true. So you're taking some pagan stuff that you're taking concepts.
You know that somebody is writing these things down and is just sort of grabbing concepts from
the local culture and making something up. Right. If we believe these beings actually exist,
right, then they would be encountered by all kinds of ancient people. And if ancient people are
actually encountering them, we should expect the descriptions to be somewhat the same or similar.
Yeah, yeah, yeah, so
Yeah, it makes perfect sense if this is true.
Right.
Yeah.
Okay.
So, so let's move on.
Let's move on to the next rank here, which is,
well, let me, let me say one more thing.
It's our go-hack there.
Yeah. Yeah.
Yeah.
Right.
Because, because this, this,
this serpent connection, a lot of people, doctors and this has obvious
implications for what's going on when we talk about the devil again and we
talk about Genesis three.
but also you may have noticed if you're familiar with
King Tutts tomb, you know, in the sort of the Gold Barrio mask.
He has, you'll see the cobra, right?
Right.
Sort of perched there.
That's the, that's the Sarah who's protecting the king and the Pharaoh himself, that sort
of Pharaoh headgear we all have in our heads for the whole Brenner in the Ten Credits.
Right?
He's supposed to look like a cobra's hood.
Yeah.
what it's supposed to do.
look it's supposed to be presenting the Pharaoh as one of these divine beings. Yep. Yep.
All right. Can we talk about that now and wheels? All right. Let's move on. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah.
I want to get through these ranks because it's just interesting to talk about each one of them.
So we've got thrones and sometimes presented as wheels and that's an image from Ezekiel in
particular right you've got the
the sort of chariot, the sort of God, you know, that sense of the wheel.
Is it the wheel in the sky? I always think of that journey song.
Yes. The wheel this guy that keeps on turning. Yeah. Right.
Right.
Right. The wheel is thinking about his EQ.
And they're also called thrones in other places. And you say, well, what's the
connection between a throne and a wheel? And this is what is made very clear.
is the Ezekiel, sort of the clearest place where this is described.
The Throne of God.
is known as the the Merkabah in Hebrew, which which is based on the word for
chariot. Yeah God's throne isn't chariot because it's mobile and Ezekiel
describes as it moves in all directions. This is important for Ezekiel because
he's an exile in Babylon. Yeah. And the temple's been destroyed. Yeah so so this
in icons we sometimes see if you know correct me if I'm getting this wrong.
Sometimes see around the feet of Jesus.
Right. These circles, these red circles typically, and they have wings and eyes. Is that what we're talking about here?
Yes.
Got it.
Yep. Yep.
Okay.
And so this is the rank sort of a view that you've got the seraphim who are sort of around God and thrown.
You have the the caravim on whom he is and thrown.
And then you have the thrones or the wheels who are sort of beneath the throne responsible.
some way mobility is the image that we're given.
That's why the wheels have eyes.
It's sort of about God's omnipresence and omniscience,
not just of him, not just of God himself,
but of his, because it's part of the throne,
his reign and his kingdom being omniscient and omnipresent.
Right.
Okay, so the next rank then that we've all heard of,
I hope is Dominions, which is kind of a curious name.
But I mean, if you think about Dominion,
It's about...
There's a sense of rulership there, right?
But it's not just that.
Like there's something a little bit more specific than that.
So yeah, in our notes, which I will, I mean, everyone can probably tell that Father Steven
Kapalmo is these notes for us, which is thank you.
But he says that Dominions are angels in charge of judging and of restraining other spiritual
powers.
Right?
So you think about in human government.
We have a justice system, right?
Where you've got not only, you know,
for instance, the police who are there
to restrain evil doers, ideally,
but you also have judges who render judgment
on those who have done committed crimes.
So is this analogous to that?
I mean, obviously we're talking about spiritual realities
that are not exactly the same as human justice,
but there's just gotta be a similarity here, right?
Right.
Because we have, as we mentioned, you know, St. Gregory mentioned, you've got those on the
left hand and those on the right hand.
You have elect angels, St. Paul uses that phrase, and you have angels that we would describe
as fallen.
And so the task, the role of some of those elect angels is to restrain and combat and
ultimately to judge those fallen spirits and to sort of supervise
and limit their actions within God's creation
to prevent them from bringing about
utter wickedness and utter destruction.
Yeah.
If they have their brothers.
All right, so why don't you tell us about the next
rank that we're looking at?
This one is probably the one that interests me the most.
In a lot of ways.
I mean, they're all fasted.
The stuff is, I hope everybody,
I hope your minds are just being below and left and right.
You're gonna have to relisten to this on the podcast.
But yeah, anyway, the next one is to...
me one of the most interesting. Right, so the it's usually translated in English as virtues,
because this is one of those cases where we have sort of Greek words, several Greek words
that mean very similar things. The word is very similar to powers, but powers is something
else that we're going to talk about in a minute. So virtues is usually used for this, even
though the word virtue in English doesn't really correspond to what they do. But these are
spirits who God has decided. Remember the role of this council is...
God is the king of his creation, and so he administers his kingdom through
these other spirits and the virtues spirits that are called virtues in English are those who preside over the different
What we would call material elements of creation. So the Sun the Moon the stars the four winds
And we see these referred to in scripture, you know that the
The angels of the four winds prophetically. This is not just imagery
This is the idea that all of these things are administered and supervised and God's reign over them is
through these angelic spirits.
Yeah, so they're like moving around the heavenly bodies. They're moving around the
the winds and the waves and you know that it's what brings life to what seems like you know
and inanimate stuff.
right yet yet nonetheless has has this motion to it and it affects us you know
and and you know this association of divine beings with these elements of
creation and so here's the reason why it's interesting to me there's two reasons
of several reasons really but I'll give you to main two so one of course is
that this is part of and we're gonna talk about this a lot in the next episode
but this is part of paganism.
so that people begin to worship beings
who are associated with these elements of creation.
But also the thing that really fascinates me
is that this is a kind of, to use a Tolkienian term,
a sub-creative rank of angels, right?
They're there to express God's creativity in this creation
and to, you know, beautify it and so forth.
And of course, you know, I mentioned Tolkien
and he depicts this very, very memorably and beautifully
in the summer.
in which is kind of like his sort of fictional Old Testament kind of text with these beings called
the Valar, who are angelic beings, who help participate in creation and rule over it, and are associated
with particular elements. There's certain associated with the ocean, another with the skies, and so on
so forth. So yeah, I'm fascinated by this particular rank of angels, and it's really, really interesting
So the next one on the list is powers and principalities and probably remember.
that when when see Paul talks about for we wrestle not against flesh and blood but against
and usually people remember the line powers and principalities. So who are the powers and
the principalities exactly? Another really interesting rank of angels here. Yeah. Well, one last
brief little note on the virtues and then I'll know you're sure. To give you an idea of how fully
elaborated that was at the time that the New Testament was written. On Rocha Shana the
New Year.
There was the ceremonial blowing of trumpets.
And there was actually a prayer that was said
before the trumpets were ceremonially and ritually blown
to begin the new year, prayer that was said
to the angels of the trumpet blast.
Oh, interesting.
So like you're saying that there was angels
specifically associated with the sound
coming out of the trumpets.
Right, not with the physical trumpet,
but with the sound of the trumpet.
to bear that sound into heaven.
So this is how it's sort of fully elaborated
into the whole created order,
the original order.
This angelic involvement was at that time.
But so the powers and principalities
that St. Paul groups together, right?
As though with whom were at war,
we'll talk about how he ended up at war.
the future.
but the powers of principalities are angelic beings who were assigned to preside over nations and
regions and peoples. And when they were assigned, they were assigned to shepherd and guide
that shepherding language becomes very important in the world. Right. So these are the regional gods
that you talked a lot about when we were talking to Ashley earlier.
Right. Right. Right. And things happened. Right. But that was their original task. And so
there again, there, there this interface with the created order, but rather than being
assigned to the material creation, they're assigned to these, what we would call political
units, but yeah, groups, tribes and nations and peoples and families. Yeah. Yeah.
Yeah. Yeah. Okay. Before we move to the next one, do you have anything else to say about
powers and principalities I want to...
I don't wanna overlap again.
No, that's okay.
All right, so okay, good.
So the next add something.
Yeah, of course, right.
Yeah, so we've also got Archangels.
So now, again, this is a rank
that most a lot of people are familiar with.
And typically there's seven Archangels
who are in Christian tradition.
Now if you look at the canonical scriptures
of the Orthodox Church,
there's only three mentioned by name.
Am I right?
Michael Gabriel
and Rafael, are there any others that are actually named?
Three and a half.
No, three to half.
It depends on how you count for Ezra.
Oh, right.
Yeah.
Is it canonical or not, right?
If you're, yeah, if you're from the Slavic tradition,
then there's kind of four because you have Yuriel.
Right.
And if you're not, then technically, you only have three,
Although the entire
Orthodox tradition, it braces your ill as one of the sets.
Yes, right.
And even so even though they're not all named in canonical scripture whether you've got
three or four or three and a half, the others are named in the rest of Orthodox tradition
and exist in Jewish traditions, right?
Right, preceding that.
Preceding exactly, exactly.
So the seven archangels are, my sense is it means it's not just the
there's only seven, right? There's not only seven. Right. This is one of the areas where this gets a little confusing.
Yeah. So there's, there's like many archangels on the one hand, so Chiefs of Angels, but then there are these specific seven that kind of stand
directly at the throne of God. And then some of the icons of the, the synoxies of the, the archangels, you'll see only seven, right?
Although other icons, you'll see lots and lots of them. And then sometimes you get a kind of a hybrid of those two images,
where you get seven that are right next to...
the throne and then there's many more around it, right? But we don't, you know, we have
names for those seven. And they vary a little bit between different Christian traditions.
I was just reading about this the other day, you know, so like in the Coptic Church, the
names vary a little bit from, for instance, the ones that that we're used to and the, you
know, the sort of the Byzantine Orthodox tradition, right? So yeah, and, you know, what else would
do we want to say about the arc angels in particular?
Well, yeah, and this
to try and help disambiguate this because I'm sure it's confused.
Because we've been sort of working out from the throne of God.
Right, concentric circles.
Right, and we're working out, and all of a sudden we're like,
well, there's these seven archagels who stand before the throne of God.
We've sort of jumped back from creation back to the throne.
And that's because, and I know this is going to sound crazy at first,
but the seven archangels are not from the rank of archangels.
All right.
So yes, so sometimes yes, so that's the promise that we've got terminology that overlaps or that gets reused
Right, and I think yeah, there's a rank of our there's a rank of archangels and there are as the liturgy says thousands of them
Right right within that rank
The seven archangels the word archangel is like arch priest. Yeah
Yeah.
Right.
It means chief or first or right.
It's a-
So the seven archangels are called archangels in light of that.
They're actually higher ranked.
Yeah, those seven.
Right.
So are there, are there, are there for ten ranks of angels?
Is that or a sand?
Well, no, because those seven are not a rank unto themselves.
Oh, I got you.
Right.
Those seven are sort of special.
Okay.
So for example, Saint Michael, who's one of them, right?
problem.
He had said Gabriel there was well known ones, but St. Michael, who's one of them, in terms
of his role, because we talked about these ranks of roles, right?
He has several of these roles.
He's the chief of the Dominions in the sense that of being in charge of judging, right?
He's the one who casts down the Satan, right?
He's the one in charge of judging the rebellious spiritual powers.
He also, however, was the angel assigned as sort of the heavenly patron.
of the nation of Israel, which is the role of a of a principality, right? So the seven
arch-eachels are sort of their own thing and each of them fulfills more than one of these
roles whereas the rank of arch-angels are the step up, the eighth rank, the step up from
just angels.
Yeah, yeah.
Yeah.
So we've got one more rank to talk about.
And then we have.
recorded message that we received and we'll talk about that rank and then
recorded message and then after that we're gonna go to break and go to the
third half of our show that's a joke for all of you Car Talk listeners out
there so yeah so the final rank is the one that's just called angels and
that means just plain angels yeah just plain old angels and that's and that
means messenger and that's the job right their job is to come and deliver
messages and to speak on God's behalf to His creation although again just a
Copic.
things we see one of the seven archangels Gabriel fulfilling that role but there's a number of
unnamed angels in scripture as well who do the same thing like who's the I don't know maybe you
can tell me is the angel who appears in the Holy Sepulchre and speaks to the merbarrers is he named
or I mean he's not named in the in the gospels but is there a tradition as to him being named
And no, these are angels from the class of angels.
Yeah, drinking a mess.
message. And the angel who comes and let's say Peter out of at a jail. Yeah. So and these
are beings who carry, yeah, messages from the throne to to the creation. Yep. Yep.
All right. Well, we have a recorded message that we received from cadmen, which is actually
related to all this stuff. He left it. He recorded this message earlier this week. So Bobby
is our engineer tonight. Bobby wants you to go ahead.
play that message for us. How much does the hierarchy of angels inform us of hierarchies on earth,
such as those in our governments and in the clergy of the church, are all of these related
and is creation as a whole hierarchical by nature? Where does this stem from?
That's a great question and it helps to underline one of the points I think that we want to really
make, which is that these various ranks of angels are ranks and not different species of angel,
even though they, for instance, appear.
to us in visual form as different, right?
They're gonna be some wildly different shapes, for instance, right?
But, so St. Denis the area of apagogued in his text,
there's one called the celestial hierarchies
and then one called the ecclesiastical hierarchies.
And so he relates it directly to the hierarchy of the church.
You know, he compares these celestial hierarchies
to the hierarchy of the church,
which is one of the ways that we
know that we're not talking about different species, right? So an example that I know that,
you know, you father's saving, I've used a number of times. For instance, is that the bishop
is a different rank than the priest, but he's not a different species for both human beings,
but he is of a higher rank for sure. And he has a different role than the priest.
And you know, so you've got within the church you have these various ecclesiastical ranks.
And also you know you mentioned
Admin about the government on Earth, and for sure, that human governments, what we think
of as political governments, do have this, it's not a direct analogy, but it is somewhat
analogous to these hierarchies.
I think that hierarchy is written into creation itself.
Some things are higher, some things are on other levels, and that doesn't mean that
we look at the king or the president as being
God's chosen anointed prophet on earth, although there have been a handful of cases in human history where that was true.
King David, for instance, prophet, anointed by God, so on and so forth.
But nonetheless, there is still that hierarchy in both civil government and church government that connects with the angelic hierarchy.
Father Stevens, you want to add anything to that or correct? I'm always ready for a correction.
Well, actually, you know, or anything else.
I haven't had to do that.
Have it.
Great.
Because I've just been sticking to notes really closely.
But no, I, I, I, a couple of, a couple of points.
One thing that's very important in terms of st. Dionysius's work is he does parallel
those things.
And in addition to there being this hierarchy and not different species, it's important
that for him that the higher ranks receive proportionately greater participation.
in the grace of God, in conformity with their role
in their rank, right?
They participate in the grace of God
and able to perform those functions.
And he held that to be true both
in the ecclesiastical hierarchies
and in the celestial hierarchies.
And that's important when we're eventually here,
we're gonna talk about tonight.
But eventually here we're gonna talk about theosis
and that will become sort of important.
The other thing is in terms of human governments,
The ideal human government as far as Scripture lays it out is the Davidic kingship, right?
Because that of course is, you know, Christ is the Messiah, he's the Davidic King.
But quite literally, since we're talking about the divine counsel, the Davidic King with
his mother and throne, his queen, and his right hand, with the prophet of God on his left
hand and surround.
by his royal court is in the Old Testament the icon of the Divine Council of God and
Throne in the heavens. And that is not just a status, but it's also a calling, right? It's
David's calling then to establish God's justice on earth, right? To accurately be an image
an icon of the V rule of God on Earth.
And then of course...
Christ being the son of David and the son of God
Collapses those two and makes them one
Yeah
So the heavenly council is now the Davidic King
With his mother and thrown his queen at his right hand with his prophet on his left hand and surrounded by
By his heavenly council
So there is a direct relationship there and so all government
whether it's civil
government or whether it's ecclesiastical government, right? The bishop is also the icon of Christ
and that's both a status and a calling for him to accurately, right, reflect Christ in his
administration of the church and for the Byzantine Emperor, that was to establish justice. So that
continues even up till today though with our modern democracies, it becomes very difficult to see.
It does.
Alright, well with that, we're going to go ahead and go to...
break and it will be back with the third half of our show right up to that.
Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung will be back in a moment to take your
calls on the second half of the Lord of Spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF radio.
is Mother Alexandra of Blessed Memory.
It seemed to me that in this modern life of ours everything has become so frightfully
materialistic.
There is a very great need of transfiguration of a change of our attitude, our way of thinking,
our way of behaving, our way of holding ourselves.
Everything needs a new Christianization.
We must become more aware of the Christ within us.
public.
in 1981 and long out of print.
The Holy Angels by Mother Alexandra
has yet to be surpassed as a comprehensive
and comprehensible account of the nature
of the angels and their role in our salvation.
In lay person's terms, Mother Alexandra
presents the essence of everything
the church has to teach us about the angels,
beginning with the Old Testament,
continuing through the New Testament,
and concluding with the tradition of the church
as expressed in her f-
And for those who long to become better acquainted with these holy servants of God and to understand their role in our lives, this book is a great place to start.
Available now at store.ancientfaith.com
Again, that is store.ancientfaith.com
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits, the Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung.
If you have a question, call now at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF radio.
Welcome back for the third half of Lord of Spirits.
Again, we want to hear from you and we're going to take a couple more calls.
And we're going to talk now in this part about demons in particular.
but Father Stephen was noting during our break that he wanted something else he wanted to draw.
in here before we dive into the dark, dark world of demons.
So Father Steven, what you got?
So I just wanted to add one more,
because we've been talking about,
I've talked about the similarities,
we've talked about both last week
and this week sort of the similarities
between what we find in Israelite religion
and other cultures and then some of these distinctions.
And this species issue is actually
one of the important distinctions.
because of course, what you find in all these other cultures
is that the gods are genetically related to each other.
Right?
You have male and female spirits who mate and produce children.
Yeah.
And so the fact that angelic beings in the Israelite tradition
Israelite tradition do not have gender.
and do not reproduce is really a key and major difference here.
In fact, all of the ancient Near Eastern languages, all kind of, are offshoots of the
Canadian, but in particular, Eucharitic, Aramaic, Hebrew, all branch off around the 11th
their 10th century BC from Old Canaanite. And every single one of those languages...
has a word for goddess except Hebrew. The Hebrew language literally does not have a word for goddess.
When they refer to Asherah or Artemis or some other god that's depicted as female,
they just use the masculine form, you know, Elohim, the masculine form of the word.
as they don't have a goddess word.
Yeah, as if to say...
they're actually all kind of, I mean, if we have to use a gender term neuter, you know,
they're all, they don't reproduce, right? They're not doing that. Yeah, that's really, that's
really fascinating to draw that distinction. So all right, we're going to talk now in
the final segment of our show about demons. And we're not going to get too deep into
The particular kinds of demons or names of demons.
partly because we're kind of getting to the point we're running out of time.
But we did want to talk in general about demons, right?
And we don't worry listeners,
we're going to come back to a lot of this stuff over and over again and do with it over and over
and hopefully not in a repetitive way, but rather getting into more details and so forth,
so you can have a better understanding.
But so what are demons? Okay, so let's start off with that question.
are exactly the same kind of being that we've just been talking about, right?
They're they are angelic beings. They are, you know, these these same kinds of
beings. They're they are gods. They are divine beings. They are spirits. That's what
they are. But the distinction, the single distinction that is the most important
here is that they are in rebellion. They are in rebellion. That they have turned
against the God of God.
They've turned against the Lord of-
of Lorezic turn against the Lord of Spirits.
And they don't desire to serve him,
even though they sometimes do kind of against their will.
Or as it says in scripture,
an amendment for evil, but God for good,
I mean the same can be true of demonic beings as well,
that they mean something for evil,
and God uses it for good.
So let's talk about that a bit.
You know, they're in rebellion.
Did this...
did this big demonic rebellion happen sometime before the creation of everything? And so that's why there's
demons on the scene when Adam and Eve are walking around in the garden. What's going on there?
Yeah, the short answer to that is no. Right. Yes. How many times will we blow people's minds in this
episode? Like it's not, it's not the image you probably have in your mind of some big division of
between angels and
demons before the creation of the world is not in the Bible. It's not in the church.
Father's comes from a fellow named John Milton whom I studied as an when I majored in English
in college. You know, he's a purest. He's a purest. He's a Protestant. Yeah.
Very nice last and so he very dramatic
compellingly composed this narrative of this pre-literally prehistoric,
pre-creation of the world, sort of battle in heaven, where not coincidentally
because he's a Puritan, he thought, oh well, the devil wanted to be a king,
because that's what all bad people do, is want to be kings if you're a Puritan.
especially if you-
English spirit. But that is nowhere. And probably the simplest quote to
disprove that is St. Andrew of Cesaria in talking about Revelation chapter 12,
which is where people usually go when they try to push back on me about this,
is Revelation chapter 12. In St. Andrew's commentary on it,
He says all of the
fathers have taught. So he's in the sixth century. So all of the fathers up to that point,
according to him, as he summarizes taught, that after the creation of the world, the devil
fell through envy. So that's about as straightforward and clear as you can get. That there was not
this, this for him, for St Andrew, the problem with Revelation 12 is that Revelation 12 depicts
this fall of the dragon.
after the birth of Christ.
Yeah.
And so that's the problem he's tried to resolve.
So he's saying, well, the devil fell in Genesis 3
according to all the fathers,
but Revelation 12 seems to say that he fell
during the ministry of Christ.
And so that's the problem he's tried to resolve there.
He doesn't have an inkling
that there's anyone claiming this happened before creation.
In fact, many of the fathers
and their discussions of the creation days
have the angels being created on
one of the creation things.
No, interestingly, either the first or fourth.
So that kind of makes that whole thing
completely impossible.
Yeah.
Right.
And what we mean, sometimes people will say,
well, demons are fallen angels,
but of course as we said,
angel is a job description and a rank, right?
not a species really.
And so what's more accurate is to say that these are beings who are created to fulfill
one of these nine roles we just discussed and who did not fulfill it.
They were belled by refusing to fulfill that role as they were created and called to do
it.
And so they fell in much the same sense that human beings fall.
was created by God to perform a specific function in roles.
to be a certain thing and failed.
Yeah, there's a kind of cosmic shirking, you know,
which it's interesting to think about,
you know, we're gonna talk about demons and temptation
and all that kind of thing, but it's interesting
to think about the kinds of temptations
to sin that we tend to have, right?
You know, like, I can't tell you how many times
in hearing confessions people,
And how many times I am in giving a confession?
mentioned failing to pray regularly, for instance, or failing to love my neighbor, failing to love my wife and children.
You know, like it's really is this failure to do the thing that I was made to do, the thing that I was given to do.
Right? And so that's a demonic act, frankly. And we participate with them when we engage in that kind of shirking of what it is that we're supposed to be doing.
So yeah, just to underline this, you know, that there's not only
is there the lack of a sort of a prehistoric fall
of the angelic beings, but there's,
it's not even just one, right?
And I know we're gonna talk about this
in more detail in the future.
Yeah, I mean, we have a bunch of stuff in our notes
that we're just not gonna be able to get to tonight,
unfortunately, but that's okay,
cause we're gonna keep coming back every couple weeks.
But, you know, that,
and, uh uh, uh, you know, demon.
are real and they're here and they are these, you know, to use the language we were interviewed
by Jonathan Pajot yesterday and it just appeared on his channel today. Vast cosmic intelligences,
wasn't that the phrase that you used for these things? I think so. Yeah, and so, you know,
imagine a vast cosmic intelligence not doing the task that God gave it to, what kind of damage
is going to be done when it turns away from that. That's frightening. I mean, you know, we're a bit
mean we can even bring it down to our level right a father and a family when he
doesn't do his job look at the damage that does to the people in his family
right so it scales you know it scales up it scales down and you know so so
here's you know we're gonna talk about multiple falls a lot in detail in the
future I think so we're gonna have to probably save that because it's really
really interesting we could go on and on about it but but there is this
since there are no-
I was in-
say there are at least at least five angelic falls. Yep. So that would be a teaser for the future.
Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. So but okay. So here's the big question. And we don't have to get into
the whole story here. But why and we've maybe answered this a little bit already. Why are demons
still around? Why does God permit them? Why doesn't He just tell them if I may put it so to go to hell?
you know, send them to the abyss. Why are they
still here. I mean, we've somewhat
entered this already, right? We're
talking about God's right hand and
God's left hand. Right. And St.
Gregory, what he's expressing there is
what he's received from the tradition
that goes all the way back before
the writing of the New Testament. One of
the places where you really see this
clearly is in the book of Jubiles,
which is canonical of your Ethiopian,
but otherwise not so much.
But the book of Jubiles, this is kind
Dove.
dramatized where the the demonic spirits and we won't get it well when the giants
all get killed their spirits come out and become demons we'll just tease that
there without out there so and so that they sort of plead they plead with God
not to cast them all into the abyss they don't actually repent they just
So
don't want the past. And so 90% of them end up getting sent to the abyss in the book of Jubilee's.
But 10% of them, God kind of makes a deal with them and says, okay, I'll allow you to remain as
these sort of bodyless demonic spirits in the world. Allow you to remain until the end of days,
until the last day.
and that he will use them to afflict the wicked,
not as a punishment,
but in order to drive them to repentance.
Right.
And this is what St. Gregory's getting at
with those evil spirits that God sort of uses them.
Now they're malicious, they're just trying to harm people,
but God uses them to bring people to repentance.
And we see this idea, even though the book of Jubilee's
isn't in our canonical scriptures,
This idea is clearly...
reflected in the synoptic gospels when Christ is going to cast out one of these demons and they say,
have you come to trouble us before the time? Right. Right.
Or the doubt to be cast to the abyss. Yeah, the very famous swine gospel that we get three times a
year, right? Which, you know, it used to, I have to admit, so I'm going to make a little confession
here. You know, as a priest preaching every Sunday, I was like, oh man, the pigs again.
You know, but that's how I used to feel. And then I realized what was really going on.
I was like, oh man, the pigs...
again. Let's talk demons. Let's talk the abyss. You know, and, and, and boy, it's just, it's,
it's absolutely fascinating, absolutely fascinating. And so demons are around and they are afflicting us
and they had their own agenda, but God has his agenda. And he's, he's making use of them
for his agenda, which is to bring us to repentance. So I wanted to take, I wanted to take a call that
that we've got and this call comes from Martin who is here in Pennsylvania and I have a
strong suspicion that I know him. So Martin, are you there?
Yes, Father, I am here and Father, bless.
God bless you. So Martin, what's your what's your
question or comment for us this evening?
Yeah. Considering the reality of angels, demons, spirits, all
these things, can either of you tell me about your take on
Paranormal experiences I've had some myself.
growing up as a kid, which is why I went on my, my,
they think of and then finally, thank God, found myself at the Orthodox Church.
But yeah, just want to hear any kind of information that you may have on that kind of thing.
Yeah, yeah. Well, so I'll respond first and
say that as human beings we encounter spirits all the time, right? They're everywhere,
all the time. Good ones, evil ones. And a lot of what we're doing in the church is precisely
navigating that, right? So we're calling upon God's willing servants.
to assist us in our repentance, to assist us in the path of salvation, to protect us from evil.
And we're engaging in prayer and the priesthood especially is engaging in
exorcistic acts to drive off those who would harm us. And it's not just, for instance,
Father Stephen mentioned the extricism, you know, like in a house, right?
But also there's exorcism that's done at the beginning of a baptism, but the truth is that
kind of all the prayers of the church are exorcistic acts. You know, even the offering for instance of incense and
and you know and
it is an exorcistic act, right, because it's an offering to God and
it ascends in his sight and it is prayer. It is a sort of spiritual fumigation, right?
right.
So I don't know, Father, you want to see more about that.
You know, I made mention that you talked about exercising a house,
but I think that may have been on our interview with Jonathan Pazzo
on the symbolic world.
But we might as well talk about it now.
So let's talk about our actual direct encounter with demons.
I mean, what do we do?
What's happening?
Yeah, well, one of the things I mentioned there is that we've had the luxury,
Those of us who are old timers of living most of
our life in the tail end of Christendom, right? Where the rule of Christ was something that
in the West for centuries was enacted sort of in all of our societal structures. Whether
people actually believed it or not, whether people actually followed it morally or not,
it was enacted, it was there in the structure. And so we didn't see the kind of spiritual
phenomenon.
in the West that you would see in Africa, in Southeast Asia, in other places of the world,
where the kind of things that we read about in the scriptures and in the Gospels that
in Acts are still going on on a very active basis. Exorcism is a very live ministry in parts
of Africa and Southeast Asia and South America. And we haven't seen as much of it here, but as
This Christendom here is crumbling.
It's starting to happen more.
People are deliberately opening themselves up to the spiritual world, but they're doing
it in ways that aren't based in Christ and His kingdom and His rule, and therefore they're
doing it in ways that aren't under His protection.
This is everything from weegee boards to Kundalini yoga techniques to psychedelic drugs.
to dabbling in Hinduism and Buddhism.
All of these things are ways that not just claimed to,
but legitimately open you up to the spiritual world,
meaning to the world of spirits.
But that's not something you want to do outside of Christ.
Yeah.
Because the spirits you're opening yourself up to are not spirits
not spirits that have your best interest at heart.
their spirits who are out to destroy you.
This is their whole motivation as being of chaos.
There is no demonic hierarchy like the celestial hierarchy we were just talking about.
Hierarchy in order are good things.
The demons are beings of chaos and destruction and that's what they're out to do to destroy God's creation
in general and human persons in particular.
And so when you open yourself up to that, you're opening your
yourself up to that. And so, yeah, that's a very dangerous thing. And so, yes, people who go and
start using weechy boards, strange things are going to start happening in their house. And that's not
weird, right? That's normal. That's normal. Yeah. And just to talk about, for instance, how
what we might think of as kind of the ordinary church life, I mean, church life is not ordinary,
right but but the ordinary church life and how it's actually in
in this battle. I'll just give you one example from my own experience. A number of years ago,
I became aware that someone that I knew had tried to take their own life. And you know,
when someone does that, of course, there's all kinds of things going on, right? And it's just
horrifyingly bad. And I found this out literally I think an hour or two before
I was going to celebrate the divine liturgy
for the feast of the elevation of the cross.
And, like I said, there was all kinds of complications
and dark things going on surrounding this person
and their life.
And I found out right before we're going to do liturgy
and I didn't serve the liturgy in any unusual way.
I said what I was supposed to say.
sang when I was supposed to sing, did what I was supposed to do. But I had this very strong
sense the whole time of engaging in a kind of forceful battle. It felt like pushing the
whole time that we were celebrating the liturgy. And then towards the end, there was this kind
of feeling of relief for release. And I still remember it very, very clearly. And I mean,
It wasn't like I saw things.
or heard something weird or whatever, but there was just a strong sense of engaging in a kind of a wrestling match, you know, a struggle.
And, you know, so this stuff is absolutely part of what it is that we do. And we don't have to, we don't have to live life in utter anxiety and fear because we're in Christ.
Christ. We can call upon Christ and we have His angels and His saints to assist us.
You know, His divine count.
So our present with us and we begin when we engage in prayer, we move, we are present there
with them.
You know, we we we become part of that just temporarily here in this life, but God willing,
you know, as we remain in Christ permanently in the life of the age to come.
So I don't know.
Does that answer your question, Martin?
Absolutely.
Thank you so much, Father.
Awesome.
Thank you very much for calling.
So...
Well, we have piles and piles and more stuff in our notes,
but it's gonna have to wait until a future episode.
But don't worry everybody.
We are never going to run out of things to talk about
on this podcast.
So Father Steven, did you have any final thoughts
you wanted to give before we wrap up?
I think just one last note in that last call.
And that's it.
I think probably a lot of people who are interested
in this
podcast, this show, and these topics are wanting to open themselves and their lives more
to the spiritual world, but it obviously in a positive sense, not the negative sense
we were just talking about.
And the Orthodox Church gives us safe, constructive ways to do this, right, through the Jesus
prayer through spiritual discipline.
of prayer and fasting through the liturgies of the church.
There are ways for us to do this that are healthy, good,
that will draw us closer to Christ,
that will make us more like Christ,
that allows us to participate more in the grace of God.
And I want to make sure that we also always keep focused on that.
And even though people are fascinated by the negative side
and the dark side and that kind of thing,
It's the positive side that we're really all about here.
Yep, absolutely, absolutely.
Well, thank you very much, everyone, for listening and for calling in.
That is our show for today.
If you didn't get a chance to call in during the live broadcast,
we would love to hear from you either via email at Lordofspirits.
at ancientfaith.com or you can message us at our Lordofspirits podcast Facebook page.
We read everything but can't respond to everything.
but we do save what you send for possible
use in future episodes. Join us for our live broadcast on the second and fourth Thursdays of the
month. It's 7 p.m. Eastern 4 p.m. Pacific and don't forget to like our Lord of Spirits podcast
Facebook page while you're at it. Leave a recommendation and then invite your friends.
And if you leave a review on Apple Podcasts Facebook or wherever you get your podcasts and that
raises the visibility of this show and gets more people connected. And finally, be sure to go to
AncientFaith.com slash support.
and help make sure we and lots of other AFR
podcasters stay on the air.
Thank you very much and may God bless you always.
You've been listening to the Lord of Spirits
with Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew Steven
Damick and Father Steven DeYoung,
a listener-supported presentation of ancient faith radio.
And I be held, and I heard the voice of many angels
around about the throne and the beast.
and the elders, and the number of them was 10,000 times 10,000, and thousands of thousands,
saying with a loud voice, worthy as the land that was slain to receive power and riches
and wisdom and strength and honor and glory and blessing.
Revelation chapter 5 verses 11 through 12.