of serving through reaching out and grasping other people and helping in the midst of their
need. For some of us it may be through art, it may be through music. There are all
manner of ways in which we can execute our diagonal ministry in this life. And all of them
together form a kind of complex that makes up the Church of Christ in this time and in this place
and by which we can find further
further ways to serve in this world. Yeah, the violet bear it away. That is to say, those of us
who dig deeply into our passion know that the kingdom of God breaks into every age as a strange
and alien work. The age does not want it because it always involves the reversal of values.
from those of the
the culture around about us, which are always given over to lust and to materialism and
things of that nature.
And so we're called to a different kind of violence, we're called to a different kind
of energy, if you will, of strength on the basis of our whatever it is that we are capable
of serving in the world.
The name of the Father and of the Son and of the Holy Spirit Christ is in our midst.
He is never shown.
You have been listening to musings from the High Desert with Father Gabriel Rachele.
Contemplations on Orthodox Christianity from Lost Cruces, New Mexico.
This has been a listener-supported presentation of Ancient Faith Radio on the web at ancientfath.com.
He will be a staff for the righteous with which for them to stand and not to fall.
And he will be the light of the nations and the hope of those whose hearts are troubled.
All who dwell on the earth will fall down and worship him, and they will praise and bless,
and celebrate with song the Lord of Spirits, 1st denoc, chapter 48, verses 4-5.
The modern world doesn't acknowledge but is nevertheless haunted by spirits, angels, demons, and saints.
in our time.
many year into break free of the prison of a flat secular materialism to see and to
know reality as it truly is. What is this spiritual reality like? How do we
engage with it well? How do we permeate everyday life with spiritual presence?
Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen
De Young host this live Colin show, focused on enchantment in creation. The union
of the scene and unseen as made by God.
and experienced by mankind throughout history.
Welcome to the Lord of Spirits.
Good evening, everyone.
Welcome back to the Lord of Spirits podcast.
It is Monster Month.
My co-host, Father Stephen D'Young,
is with me from Lafayette, Louisiana,
on his hot new fiber optic connection.
And I'm Father Andrew Stephen Damick in Emmaus, Pennsylvania.
And if you are listening to us live,
you can call in just like the voice of Steve said,
855 AF radio that's 855-237-237
3, 4, 6. Montesca Trudy will be taking your calls tonight, which we will get to in the
second part of our show. So, on the Western Christian calendar, all Hallows Eve is approaching,
and if you listened to our Halloween special from last year, you know that the Christian
rituals traditionally associated with this liturgical celebration are about mocking demons
and participating in the destruction of pagan worship of them. As such, people do tend
to think about demon.
and other monsters around this time of year.
And since that is part of what we address on this podcast,
we're gonna talk, take a walk this evening
through a variety of monsters that you find in the Bible
and in adjacent traditions, vampires,
werewolves, lamea, lilyth, and yes, unicorns, yes,
sorry kids, unicorns are monsters.
But before we begin, just a note for parents.
While we're not gonna get graphic or gruesome,
some of the stuff from history and the scriptures
Make sure it's at work.
going to be looking at in this episode is pretty horrifying if you contemplate it.
So we recommend that you listen to this one before you let younger kids listen with you.
And I see that as a parent of younger kids myself.
So in the first part of this episode, we're going to be talking about straight-up demons
in the classic sense.
And the first one is Lilith, which is not just the name of Frazier Crane's wife on
cheers.
So Father Stephen, who or what is Lilith?
It's a fair you go to to hear Sarah Mc...
and Fiona. Oh man, that takes me back to my stage hand days. I worked a little
affair back in 1997 for stopping Raleigh, North Carolina. Did you have in
scare quotes delicious vegan treats? I don't think so. Okay, probably.
So yeah, as you mentioned, we try to make this a family-friendly show.
Although the priest of
bail do not cooperate in that regard at all. But yeah, tonight some of this stuff is
kind of scary. So be advised and send all your complete emails to someone other than us because we
warned you. So we're going to be talking about the actual Lilith, after whom the fare was named,
And after we're done talking about it, you'll...
definitely wonder how that works. But so this this figure of Lilith that we're going to be
talking about has been around pretty much as long as we have written literature.
Yeah, she's one of the oldest scary things ever. Yeah, so we're going to be in a minute here
when we talk about her sort of first literary appearance, it's going to be sort of one of the first
written things we have. But the name...
Lilith is sort of the normal, anglicized version of the name that you typically see.
And that is sort of a transliteration of what is in Hebrew, Lelite, in Akkadian, Lili-Too,
in Sumerian, Liel. And sometimes you will see folks who want to connect the name,
especially in Hebrew.
the elite to the Hebrew word Lila or Laila, which means night, like at the end of the day,
night falls, night, not like on horses. So that is not related. So as we just sort of laid out,
this is a proper name that comes out of Sumerian, mostly intact, right? At least the central
syllable. Now this is a demon who does stuff at night after dark. Yeah.
Yeah. Demons are want to do when they tend to do things. But and so you'll
sometimes see things related to evening and night surrounding descriptions
of Lilla. But they're not directly related. And the reason I bring this up
at all is that sometimes even in trends.
translations, there's sort of as we've noted many times on this show, a sort of materialist
bias in translations where anything that they could interpret as not being the name of
a demon, they interpret as not being the name of a demon, right? They try to translate it
some other way.
Yeah, and we're going to look at some of the fun stuff in that regard, especially looking
at biblical translations actually.
Right, so they'll do that with Lilla too, they'll try and translate it as Nye to...
evening or, you know, darkness or something, rather than seeing it as a proper name. But this is a
proper name going all the way back to its initial appearances. And the first of those appearances
is in a poem, an epic poem called Gilgamesh and Kido in the Netherworld, which should not be
confused with the epic of Gilgamesh because it turns out that there's actually it.
a number of Gilgamesh stories that are
extant. And I mean, but these are like hundreds and hundreds of years apart, right?
Compared to Epic of Gilgamesh, yeah. Right. The Epic of Gilgamesh is we now know it today
is the Akkadian version of that Epic, which was written some time, took the form we have it in
And now, sometime between 1,500 and 1,000 BC, whereas the poem we're about to talk about.
Gilgamesh and Kido in the Nether World was written during our old friend the Ur-3 period,
sort of Ur-3 Tokyo Drift. But this is, so this is, if you want a biblical marker, so the poem
we're about to talk about was written during Abraham's time. And the epic of Gilgamesh as we have it
today was written more like in Moses and Joshua's time. And I mean, is this, you know, these are on
like Clay Tabits with Cuneiform? Yes.
Yeah, yeah, so the Gilgamesh and Kiyu in the Nether World this poem we're talking about is
In Sumerian
So we have these there are actually five
Sort of epic poems about Gilgamesh that we have in Sumerian from this period and
Because journal articles and dissertations have to be written
You can find a lively literature about whether these five things are five
different traditions or whether the five of them together constitute an early Gilgamesh
epic and all kinds of things like that. But for our purposes, we just want to talk about
this one, which is Gilgamesh and Kido in the Netherlands. And if you're familiar with
the epic of Gilgamesh, you know that spoilers and Kido dies.
Hey man, I mean, I don't give spoilers. I've only been around for 3,500 years and right
after that snitch.
double door. Anyway, I tell you it was going to be scary for kids. Yeah, so, so,
Aikido dies. And so this poem, this particular poem, is not so much focused on Aikido's death,
but focused on Aikido dies, and then so Gilgamesh sort of makes the rounds to several of the gods,
the Serenian gods to try to get them to help him
to get his friend back out of the Nether World.
So his bestest bud has died and he wants him back.
And in order to try to persuade them to help him,
he gets sent on these side quests to go and do this or that,
to try to help or impress the God in question
in order to try to convince that God or God has to help him out
out with the whole
Yeah, underworld thing.
Yeah, I mean, in some ways this trope is sort of echoed
in like the Greek myth of Orpheus and Eurydice
where Orpheus goes down to get his wife
out of the underworld.
I mean, you see this kind of story
in a lot of mythology, the idea of, you know,
rescuing someone from the underworld.
And often there are like things that you have to do
in order to make this possible.
So yeah, it's really common in mythology.
I like to thank you, column side quests.
I mean,
Yeah, it's true. I mean, it really is true. Yeah. So the particular, yeah, the particular
side quest that in Nana, who's also known as Ishtar, who's a goddess, sends Gilgamesh to go do,
is she needs some help with her Hulu Putri. And what is a Hulu Putri? Well, it's this particular
tree. It's not like a species of tree. It's a particular tree.
The Halu Poo tree.
The Halu Poo tree. Yeah.
And so this is a tree that Inana had planted and she had intended once this
This sort of magical tree grew to sort of full size that she was going to use the wood from it
To make herself a throne and a bed
And right which basically says she's building a temple right right so these are the temples have
You know for sacrifices
That's what you got the throne therefore and for
are not fully making.
That's what the bed's there for.
Yeah, right.
Right.
And so this is her plan.
And so she's cultivated this special tree to do that.
And she's got a bunch of squatters who have taken up residence in said tree.
And that is Anzu, who's sort of a giant bird creature who's living up in the branches
of the tree.
And then there's a serpent living in the roots of the tree down underneath, who's burrowed
in there.
And
There is a demon named Kiseki Lilu.
Say that five times fast.
Yeah.
Um, yeah.
And I said it kind of fast,
but the central syllable of that,
and remember,
Kadeiform, Sumerian and everything else that's written
in Kadeiform,
Kadeiform is a syllabic alphabet.
Right. So each character is a syllable.
So the third of the four syllable.
in Kiseki Lili is Lill. So this is our first appearance of Lillith. She is this demon who is living in the trunk of the tree.
Okay. And so because there's these demons and monsters and creatures and stuff living in and around the tree,
the tree and Nana can't go use it so she sends Gilgamesh to go take care of her
problem so she can use her tree.
Gilgamesh goes and he gets in a fight with and he kills the serpent that's in the roots and
When they see that he killed the serpent
Leo and Anzu take off
Right, so to say cheese it. We're out of here
They take off so they don't get killed by Gilgamesh also
And so when he goes and turns in the side quest and Anas still doesn't help him with the Enki-duu problem
she sort of tricks him into taking care of her issue, which is interesting because it kind of
illustrates, it does illustrate that in pagan mythology that there are monsters that even the gods
can't handle, because, and I mean, I think this is, I mean, this is sort of a side point, but it's
a really important point I think for us to underline every so often, which is that no God in any
Any ancient pagan mythology even makes the claim to be all powerful.
that they can command anything and it has to obey.
That is something that only the God of Israel actually even says about himself.
The rest is a world of stronger and weaker creatures that are competing with each other in many cases for dominance.
So even if you've got this goddess in an Ishtar, there's demons in her tree and she can't do anything about that.
that she needs to bring in Gilgamesh who by the
way as a giant, right? Right. To deal with it. Yeah. She can't just cast them out, right?
And this is part of what's in the background when Christ comes and starts doing exorcisms
why everybody freaks out. Yeah, because no one else can do that. Because he could just tell
a demon to split and the demon splits, right? Yeah. No battle required. Yeah. So, so this is sort of
our first appearance of this.
this demon. In later, Akkadian texts, you get sort of little myths, like this is like a category
of sort of female demonic spirits. And so there's three of them that are named in Akkadian texts are
Lili Lili Tu and Ardot or Wardot Lili. And you can see that same syllable in all of those.
of the central. Yeah, these are the same sort of type of
of being. And these are related to words for the Southwest wind. And so that gives there's this idea that this is this is a a demonic creature that sort of flies.
You'd say, well, what else would it do? Well, like we talked about in Genesis 4 with sin, you know, there were a cadian demons who sort of crawled up through cracks in the ground. So some of them crawled and slithered in that kind of thing.
but this is more one that flies
and sort of is associated with coming into homes through windows the way the wind does.
And in particular the Liliths did two main bad demonic things. The first was they would
enter the homes of men and sort of seduce them and mate with them and then kill and eat them.
Yeah, sort of a succubus.
a cannibalistic succubus sort of yeah yeah yeah or like a brain man just a black widow yeah right
and the other nasty demonic thing that little us would do is they would come and rather than breastfeeding
an infant with milk they would breastfeed an infant with poison yeah yeah
Yes, we told you we told you guys. Yes. Yes. It's it's not going to get prettier from here. Um, so
The way this is talked about is there's this phrase associated with one of these Lila spirits that this is a woman that a man does not lay with as he lays with his wife
life. And that's a way of associating what she does.
with non-procreative sexual activity.
Yeah, so I mean the whole image that you get then is this kind of, she's an anti-fertility,
you know, demon, right? Like, yeah, yeah.
Yeah, so yeah. And sort of in both ways, both of those demonic things she does.
And interestingly to us nerds, this idea of the li...
the spirit sort of demon traveling around and sort of looking for men, particularly young
men, to do this too. There's also this imagery is also applied in a Canadian text to Ishtar.
The goddess we were just talking about is also one who goes around looking around and looking
in windows looking for a young man, but she was seen as being a fertility goddess.
So it sort of sets up within these Akkadian texts, this idea of sort of Lilith as Ishtar's
evil twin, right?
Like the other sort of the other side of the coin.
The Mirror universe ishtar.
Yeah.
That comes in with a, you know, a van Gogh team and a wreath sash.
So yeah, and so this I
This demonic spirit has a lot of staying power.
So there is a similar sort of spirit in Babylonian traditions called Lamash too
and those two get kind of assimilated to each other.
Lamash too and Lilith.
Which that often happens as these kinds of mythology sort of clash into each other
there is demons and gods and goddesses.
strongly associated and then often said that they're the same thing.
Yeah, or type two hypostasis of the same thing.
If you've lost your way.
Yeah, right.
Some episodes.
Yeah.
Yep.
So but the imagery that comes in, the imagery that comes into Lila
through Lamashtu that's important is that Lamashtu has said
to have the ears and teeth of a donkey.
Like why?
I mean, that's just the answer.
So random.
Yeah.
Now you...
That's the same in Pinocchio.
But suddenly, wow, this is going to ruin.
This ruins Pinocchio for me forever.
Yeah.
So yeah, the ears and or would be riding on a donkey.
And so one of Lillis titles comes to be the donkey rider.
This is going to be important in a minute.
Yeah.
So from there, from the Babylonian tradition.
It comes over into Syrian and Aramaic traditions.
The primary place where we see Lamash too in those is in these sort of magical texts,
like some of the curse bulls and plantation bulls we talked about last time, and on amulets
and that kind of thing because of course they're trying to ward her off, right?
You don't want her around.
So being that these are pagan Syrians and Arameans.
they didn't have sort of, it's not like they prayed to their main god to kind of keep them safe, right?
Because as we were just talking about with Gilgamesh and Kido and the other underworld,
that these guys are kind of all at the same power level, right? So the way that these Syrian and
aeromac magical texts generally approach trying to ward off Lamashtu.
is actually by invoking another demon who didn't like Lamash too.
So they had this idea from their stories that this other demon, Pazuzu, who was a demon of famine and drought,
and Lamash too hated each other.
And so they would invoke this one demon of famine and drought to try to ward off the demoness of
sexual infertility. Yeah. Like to try to get them to fight. Yeah, I mean, I mean, how, I don't know,
it's just it's interesting, you know, like, and you kind of wonder if the cure is worse than the
disease in some ways. You know, because it's both about both of these demons are about
destroying the things that are at the very heart of community, whether it's, you know, having children
or feeding people, but there you go, I guess.
Right, and so...
Um, oh, just for the record, Pazuzu, if anybody didn't immediately jump on that.
This is the ancient Babylonian demon and Syrian demon that stars in the exorcist.
There you go, exorcist fans.
Yes.
So there you go.
How you william Peter Blattie fans.
Um, it is Halloween coming up.
I mean, come on.
Yeah.
Um, yeah.
I've never seen that film.
I was raised basically Baptist.
I'm shocked that you know aren't you, aren't you shocked?
Yeah.
The person for whom Dr. Who is too creepy has not seen the exorcist?
What?
It's true.
I know.
Yeah.
So this then we talked about assimilation with Lamashtu.
Lilith also ends up showing up through Lamashtu in Greek stories and through Greek and even
in Latin stories.
And there the Greek name and the Latin name just transliterates it is Lamyah.
Yeah, so it's instead of Lammash too, you get, they kind of cut the end off and sort of give it a Greek or Latin ending.
Right.
Lammash.
Right, because Greek actually written Greek actually grew out of linear B.
And linear B is a phonetic language like Kuneiform languages.
It has a banana galfa bat.
So with very old words, you have that same syllabic kind of thing where you have a syllable
that gets picked up with and then based on the language development, you get different
endings put after it.
So Alamia in the Greek stories in the Greek traditions is one of the many lucky ladies
who Zeus set his eyes upon.
Yeah, I mean again showing how their most high God is super duper creative
Yeah, super duper evil. Yeah, yeah, so he went and will politely say seduced her. Yeah, right.
And then after he had done this, they had some children together and when Hera, Zeus's wife, the goddess Hera,
realized that once again Zeus was cheating on her and it had kids, decided to curse Lamiya.
Yeah, and she she does that kind of I mean, you know if you read Greek mythology
You know that this is a thing that happens over and over again. Hara is always going after Zeus's paramores
Yeah, yeah, his victims frankly is the way really we should put it, but yeah, yeah, yeah blame the woman. Thank you, Hara. Yeah
so
toxic femininity anyone yeah, right so
She puts a curse on lamia and turns her into a serpent woman
sort of waist down snake, waist up human, and forced her to eat her own children
and cursed her so that she could never sleep. Yeah, which kind of connects to that whole
sort of nighttime idea. Right. So she's out and around at night. In the Greek stories, Zeus
decided, you know, he felt a little bad after all this happened.
And so the way he decided to help Lamy out was he made it possible for her to remove her eyes.
Because that'll help us sleep.
I'm sure.
Yeah.
Geez.
Because eye strain, I don't know.
But I thought all religions were the same father, Stephen.
And paganism is beautiful.
Yeah.
So but Lamy due to having all of this befall her, proceeded to operate very much the
same way that that Lilith did and Losh do did and that's prowl around it night
looking for young man mating with them killing them eating them yeah so all
that said is background and now we get to the Bible yes all that ancient
very stern languages. Lillith makes an appearance in Isaiah 34 verse 14. Right.
And you collected a cavalcade of interesting English translations for the word lilylyt in Hebrew.
Yeah, so I mean, and we could probably double this list, but this I think gives you a sense of the scope here.
Okay, so the ESV, the English standard version translates it as nightbird, nightbird.
The King James, which is my favorite in terms of the way that it sounds, is Trans-Six.
It's a screech owl screech owl.
The new King James has night creature night creature.
It's it sounds like it should be some kind of a TV show.
Tonight on night creature.
And then the RSV gets us a little bit closer and has night hagg.
So that's pretty good.
Now wait, we have to we have to pause before this last one.
I know I know because this is there's going to be a couple first and only's on this
one of them you're gonna
have to wait for the third half. But what of a year about to get where this is the only
time we're going to say something positive about something ever? Here it comes. So there
is a quote unquote Bible translation called the message. I'm sorry, it's just hard to
not be a little bit sarcastic about that thing. It's most, I mean, just open it up people.
You'll see what I mean. But, but as I was doing my little survey of the way that this
This work is translated in English versions.
The message has it as the night demon Lilith, which is, I think, the best of any English translation
I found.
I couldn't, I could not believe it.
These proverbial stopped clock.
Yes, right, exactly.
I know.
And it's so fun that it's right about this.
You know, how weird is that?
But yeah, but you know, the nostalgia or the prettiness.
Yeah.
But yes, they knew.
So...
hats off to you for this one word message people whoever exactly you are
yeah the night demon lileth that's what the message translates it as so yes
so lileth shows up in Isaiah chapter 34 I mean what's she doing there you know
well she along with some other demonic critters is haunting the wasteland of
item as destroyed as one does. So this is this is part of an oracle against
Adam
where Isaiah is pronouncing that, you know,
Adam because of wickedness is going to be destroyed
and it's going to be so destroyed that all that's going to be left of the great cities
is going to be sort of rubble with sort of demons and wild animals prowling around in the ruins.
So that's the idea of why she appears here.
She being one of those night demons who's going to be out there
lingering around in the rubble.
Yeah, she's just sort of listed. It's not it doesn't really treat treat of her
She just sort of mentioned but but she is mentioned very explicitly right there in the Hebrew right and so
When we get to the old Greek
This is this is going to solve what may have been for many of you
It was for me for a while what are the great mysteries about the Orthodox study Bible
And it's translation of Isaiah in particular.
So in the
The Old Greek translation of Isaiah, which is sort of the first layer of Greek translations
of the Old Testament, they translated this word, Ono-Kentavaros, which since I just said
it in modern Greek pronunciation, you may not see, but the middle part of that, if you
You can see it written out is Ken Tower.
Yes, center.
Yes.
Yeah.
Yeah, exactly.
And Onos is a donkey.
So right, donkey's centaur.
And so the Orthodox study Bible faithfully translated that donkey centaur.
Centaur.
It's a very little.
So yeah, in the roots of Edom, there would be a donkey centaur wandering around.
So what was actually happening here was that you think about when the old Greek was translated.
Right.
following the b-
Babylonian exile and the time that Judy had spent in Persia
LaMache 2 is what the donkey rider? Yeah, right, right, right, right? So that was the idea they were trying to convey
But then a demonic donkey rider so it because the donkey rider this is LaMache 2, right? That's what they're trying to say and other
Jewish translators understood that that's what was going on so Aquila
when a quilla does hit.
recension he translates it as Lilith. Just transliterates it into into Greek. So I mean so these
other these these later Greek translations, I mean I say later but it's I don't know how much
later but are they just sort of editing the old Greek? Is that what's going on? Mostly they're
They're mostly trying to correct it.
So they just transliterated Lilith.
because he understood it as a proper name.
In Hebrew, right?
Yeah.
And then, Semakis, who is another one of the early translators, translated it as Lamiya,
right?
He just turned it into the Greek version of the creature, right?
The Greek version of the demon, Lamiya.
And so Saint Jerome, when he translated the Latin, uh, Vogueit, also went with Lamiya.
fifth century AD so
some centuries after all this. Right. He went with Lamia because Latin had maintained the same name
for that demon and
he
a lot of people don't necessarily know this but in addition to doing the actual translation
Saint Jerome wrote introductions to all the books of the Bible and wrote commentaries on most of them.
So basically Saint Jerome made his own study Bible? Yeah. Yeah
So
So when at this point when he puts Lamya, he says that the Hebrews held Lamya to be one
of the arenis, the Furies.
So if you know a little bit about Greek myth and stories and traditions, then the Furies
are these sort of demonic beings from the underworld that come and usually tear apart and drag
out the Hades. People who have done...
sort of horrible evil deeds.
Yeah, right.
Right. So, like you kill your father, you know, you do some terrible deed and the furies
come after you.
Right.
Yeah.
You sort of see that kind of image.
I suddenly thought of that movie ghost, you know, with Patrick Swayze and Demi, is it
more?
Yeah.
where you know really bad
like murderers get dragged off by these dark, horrifying, screeching, demonic black, you know,
black, black, black figures. It's sort of that kind of thing. Yeah, that idea manifests itself
all the time in popular culture. That's really the origin of Slasher movies. Slasher movies are
really Greek tragedies, right? Because what's going on in your classic Slasher movies is that you're
your Freddy Krueger
or your Jason Voorhees or your Michael Myers or whoever,
they always come after some group of usually teenagers
and people in their 20s.
And everyone who isn't virtuous,
everyone who isn't established as being virtuous
all gets massacred, right?
They sort of wreak this horrible vengeance
on everyone for their sins.
And there's usually only one person who survives at the end.
It's almost always a female person.
and they're pretty...
much always sort of portrayed as
original and pure and chased.
And that's why they survive.
Right. And so I'll take your word for it.
Yeah.
I yeah, no, no, no, no, it's the same kind of idea.
The narrative is serving that kind of same function that Greek
tragedy used to do.
Right. It's more more realistic.
Right.
Be good or else horrible things will do terrible things to you.
Re-enforcing this whole idea of justice and telling kids not to
Mess around.
before marriage. Right. Yeah. So, but yeah, so this is how St. Jerome understands
Lamea Lilith as being that sort of demonic spirit, right? Who sort of comes and he doesn't see it as
like goes around victimizing innocent men. Right. Yeah. He sees it as this demon is out there and
and God allows this demon to sort of punish sex.
immoral men, for their lack of chastity and faithfulness.
So this isn't sort of the end though, we just talked about St. Jerome, who's obviously
5th century Christian, but Lilith also then has this sort of afterlife in rabbinic
Jewish material.
So when you get into the Talmud, for example,
There's a whole
Statement in one of the track dates of the Babylonian Talmud about how men should never sleep in their house alone
Because if they do little it might come in the window
Yeah, so this is rabbinic Judaism basically warning against suck you by yeah, right right this can happen to you
So never sleep alone in a house men
and
There's another track date that
that says that she is the daughter of Aramon.
And which is kind of a weird,
I don't know, is this from like Judaism in Persia
because like Aramon is the shadow of a Hura Mazda
who's sort of the most high God in this sort of...
Oh, sort of, he's the God.
He's the only God.
Yeah, it's sort of in Zoroastrianism anyway.
Yeah.
but yeah, so they were sort of connecting.
or to that, then you get into the stuff that gets us to the lily affair.
Yeah. Sort of late medieval Jewish legends. Yeah. Yeah.
The one that everyone's probably heard of is the idea that she was Adam's first wife.
You know, and then they, I guess, got a divorce and he marries Eve later.
Where she's sort of this jilted her wronged woman, sort of like Lamiya.
Right, and so now she's been like done wrong by a man
and she's out for revenge, right?
Kind of idea.
There are also medieval Jewish legends
where she's one of Solomon's wives.
Yeah, that's because I'm trying to think like,
how does that work?
And maybe it's just sort of the idea
that Solomon married so many
and of course did a lot of frankly sinful things
that he picked up some real porifying people
along the way for his herm.
Well, no, this is, she was one of his first wives.
So there's a jilted thing again.
Yeah, he goes and buries all these other women
and she's jealous and...
and goes glen close and yeah.
So, yeah, and but she is sort of always associated with it and a worn against in terms of infertile
marital sexual activity.
activity that is not reproductive or potentially reproductive in nature.
Right.
Um, is, is something that sort of attracts this, this kind of thing.
Um, but my personal favorite, as I pointed out to you, or, yes, is this comes from the
medieval, this is the one that I actually, this is the one I kind of love.
Yes.
Yeah.
In the medieval Christian West, they talk about Lilla, actually still in the same kind
of vein that Saint Jerome talked about her.
but somewhere along the line and we're not sure exactly where amongst her
epithets. She picks up the title, the devil's grandmother. Yeah, I'm not sure how that works.
Exactly. Exactly. Exactly. Exactly. Exactly. Exactly. Exactly.
Like daughter or granddaughter, maybe, but I don't get how you go up the chain.
I don't know. I don't know. And who was who's the devil's parents then?
I don't know. Yeah, I mean, I don't know. Maybe it's feeding into this idea that she's a super
ancient demon that even precedes the big demon. I don't know. It's...
But fun. Yeah, we have a lot of fun. Yeah, right. Yeah. Okay. So that's one of the monsters
that we see in the Bible. And then in Christian tradition, as you know, later Christian
tradition as well and Jewish tradition. But then, you know, like I said in the introduction,
unicorns are monsters too. Sorry everybody.
explained the donkey centaurs.
Right, we come now to...
unicorns unicorns yeah and unicorns are not so much in the original of the Bible as they are in the King James
fruition yeah man yeah you're taking a beat in today okay it's all right it's all right and you
had to say nice things about the message that's gonna stick in your crawl bad things about the King James
That'll be great for like, you know, party anecdotes.
So, you know, like, you know, the one good thing I can say about the message.
Yeah.
So, and this, I'm just going to list them real quickly.
We're not going to go through each one, but the places in the King James version where
they mention unicorns are numbers 23, 22 and 24 versus 8, Deuteronomy 33 versus 17, Job
39, 9 and 10, Psalm 22, verse 21, Psalm 29, verse 6, Psalm 92, verse
verse 10 and Isaiah 34 verse 7.
And you may notice that 34 verse 7 is not totally far removed
from where Lula shows up.
Yeah, just seven verses away.
So there's a reason for that.
But those are the places where Unicorn shows up.
And again, we did a brief survey of some English translations.
Yes.
OK.
So the King James does translate this word.
whatever it is, which we're about to tell you as unicorn, the dewey reams, which has a
lot to recommend in some ways, translates it as rhinoceros, and a lot of modern translations
render it either as wild ox or orox, a-u-r-o-c-h-s, which an orox is a kind of ancient cattle breed,
breed of sorts. Yeah, yeah, yeah, that was especially
like in Eastern Europe and the steps of Central Asia and that kind of thing of old and would have
been known to ancient people. Yeah. So the Hebrew word that's behind all this is Re'en,
which basically refers to an Uru's which is like an Aurex. It's a sort of wild bowl, right? It's a
type of cattle that was an ancestor.
of our current domesticated cattle but was not domesticated. Right. And so they were sort of like
water buffalo or wild dogs, I kind of think. So those modern translations are kind of closer to
to what's going on in the Hebrew with Ram. The Greek translates it as monoceros, which literally
means one horned. One horn, yeah.
Like, and yeah, and you know, those who know a little Greek would recognize that Keros is
being related towards like, you know, keratin and that kind of thing has to do with horns.
Yeah.
And is the seris in rhinoceros, which is where the dewey reams is thinking.
So this gets when St. Jerome comes to it, he's not sure what this is talking about.
And so he just changes it in the...
Latin and put uniqueornists.
One horned thing, right?
Right.
And then the King James translators got to it.
They didn't know what that was.
So they just transliterated it into English as unicorn.
Right.
So basically what we're saying, then,
if I'm following this correctly, is that the word unicorn
is the result of biblical translation.
Yes.
Yeah.
That the word is.
I mean, obviously we're talking about a...
concept that is behind it, but the word unicorn comes from biblical translation, basically
because translators weren't entirely sure what to do with this Hebrew word.
Right.
And so the trend you see though in all those English translations, once people start trying
to figure out what it is, even the Dewey Reams, is they're trying to associate it with a
real world animal, sort of like we saw last time with Leviathan and Behemoth.
Well this has to just be some zoological creeps.
feature. Yeah. We need to associate this with. And there's some, I'm not going to go down
this alley, but hey, if you've got a lot of time on your hands and an internet connection,
you can go down a whole rabbit trail with our KJV only friends trying to explain what a
unicorn is because they take the King James as being authoritative and it says unicorn.
So this includes an argument of how it could be a
a narwhal on one website.
Wow.
So, wow.
And Kitchie don't remember what a narwhal is, kids.
It's a sea creature that in fact does have one big horn.
Yes.
That's true.
But it's hanging around the ruins of a city.
Apparently, narwhals.
That's so great.
Swimming in the ocean causes a commotion.
So, what's really going on here is we talked about last time is
This is calling upon the whole
bull imagery of behemoth, bay of evil, the bulls of Bashan, the bull bale, the apis bulls
of Egypt, the bull of heaven, that's what this is drawing on.
So this is another demonic creature.
And so when you put these together, like in Isaiah 34, this is an idea that is common in
the Old Testament and another.
ancient Jewish sources that when a civilization collapses or a city is destroyed or collapses,
and already at the time that the Old Testament is being written, right? We talked about
the or three period, right? There are cities that are already thousands of years old. So
whole cities, whole empires have risen and fallen by the time the Old Testament starts
being written. So there's ruins around that people actually are noticing. Yeah, of these
previous civilizations. And so...
They believe that when those civilizations collapsed,
the gods of those cities and nations and empires,
the spirits of their dead kings,
who they believed were divine,
all kinds of demons would make their home in those ruins,
right?
Ruins, graveyards, haunting, ancient tombs would have these,
these are the only things that would live there,
would be these sort of demonic creatures and evil spirits.
Yeah, which is where
this association that, you know, it's pretty much universal in human culture of, you know,
like you said, hauntings of ruins and of course, you know, cemeteries. I mean, and all that
kind of stuff is that these are places of the dead, the damned, the demonic, other things
to start with, D, devils, demons. Yeah. And then, you know, there's, then this shows
up with this idea that we have now of where you get.
this modern Egyptology where mummy's haunting tombs and all that kind of stuff.
Or howard Carter comes and opens King Tutankhamens tomb and X number of people all died
mysteriously from the expedition shortly thereafter because there were these sort of
ancient Egyptian spirits down there in the tomb that you interacted with.
going there. Yes. Yeah. Who disturbs my rest? Yeah.
right? Yeah, I mean, well, you know, and you know, you get a whole film genre, Indiana Jones,
you know, this is sort of all based on this kind of idea. So thanks. And so Isaiah, that's why this
shows up at this Oracle and Isaiah is that, you know, right now, as Isaiah is making this proclamation,
Eden is this prosperous civilization, they're conducting commerce. There's all kinds of life
going on in their cities. And not only is that going to be gone, but the place where that was
there's gonna be
with death and evil and destruction. Right. That's the prophecy is that it's going to go the other way.
Yep. Yep. All right. Well, that is the first half of our show. We've talked about
lamia slash lila slash donkey centares and unicorn slash rhinoceros is slash
bulls hanging around in the ruins of once great civilizations. So we're going to go ahead and
go to our first break and we'll be right back with more monsters.
Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung will be back in a moment to take your
calls on the next part of the Lord of Spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF Radio.
St. Ignatius, first century bishop of Antioch, called the Godbearer, is one of the earliest
witnesses to the
truth of Christ and the nature of the Christian life.
Tradition tells us that as a small child, Ignatius was singled out by Jesus himself as an
example of the childlike faith all Christians must possess.
In bearing God, Father Andrew Damoc recounts the life of this great pastor, martyr, and
saint, and interprets for the modern reader five major themes in the pastoral letters
he wrote.
them. Salvation in Christ. The Bishop, the unity of...
of the church and the Eucharist.
For Ignatius martyrdom is really the fullness of Christ
in a sense, which that can be challenging for us,
because number one, he doesn't seem
to have any reticence at all about going to martyrdom.
Like there's no sense of, well, this boy have to do,
you know, I wish I didn't have to,
but this was God's will for me.
He is going to it joyfully, gladly.
To find this book and others like it,
you can go to store.enginefaith.com.
Again, that is store.in...
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits, the Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen
DeYoung.
We'll be back in a moment to take your calls on the next part of the Lord of Spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF Radio.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits, the Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen
If you-
So have a question.
Call now at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF radio.
All right, welcome back.
Well, it sounds like the voice of Steve
got a little confused there for a second.
But we are back.
I think actually, I think we're being nice.
I think he really needed some extra residuals.
That's true.
So we're just really sending shoppings around the corner.
That's right.
Everybody tip your local Steve.
So we are back. This is the second half of the show. And like Steve said, you can call
us at 855 AF radio. And we are going to take a couple calls. But first, I just wanted
to give Father Steven the opportunity to talk, not that he can't, but to give the opportunity
to talk because he has a brand new book that literally just came out last week. So it's
It's called God as a Man of War.
You can get it from store.inchantfaith.com.
Father Steven, what is that book all about?
Violence and death.
Yeah, that's pretty much true.
Yeah, the subtitle is the problem of violence in the Old Testament.
So there are a lot of passages in the Old Testament.
People probably have some that immediately come to mind
that as modern people are deeply troubling to us
because they don't just to pick sort of violent new.
horrible things, though they do.
But sometimes it seems like God is kind of telling people
to do those violent and awful things,
or he's okay with it, at least.
And so these are really troubling to a lot of people.
We also have a lot of our young people
who have these things thrown in their faces
by schoolmates, by coworkers, et cetera,
your local atheist.
They don't necessarily know what to do with them themselves so they don't have sort of a good answer prepared.
And so I know some people are a little sketched out by the title, God is a man of war, but that is a verse from the book of Exodus.
Yeah, I mean, it's a Bible quote.
Yeah.
And so the book is about passages of the Old Testament that are troubling and the title is a verse from the Old Testament that is troubling.
So it kind of does
what it says on the tin. And I'm hoping it will be helpful to people in that way, to kind
of both for people who sort of struggle with what to do with this. Like how is this beneficial
to my life to read these horrible things. And also to people who have had this stuff thrown
at them and sort of don't know what to do with it to kind of prepare you to be able to give
some kind of answer to somebody who shows up and wants to throw those things
that's it.
Yeah, I'm about 40 or so pages into my copy and I'm loving it so far so I do recommend it to everybody
So this is a second part and we already take some calls so we have
Alexander who is calling and this is what it says on the call board from Transylvania Romania
Actually calling from Transylvania so Alexander are you there?
Hello, yes
Welcome, welcome to the Lord of Sp-
We are glad to have you. What is your comment to your question for us tonight?
I was thinking of sharing some information about some local creatures we have here and see what you think
about. Sure. Yeah, sure. What's up? So for example, there is this thing called pre-college,
which I guess is kind of like where we're worth. But the thing with them is that it's seen kind of
as sort of...
thing you are born with and usually it happens if you are the first generation or
more born out of well- luck and when you are born there's like a sign on your
body so people know and the thing is that sometimes you can turn into a dog but
you don't know so for example their story is like a woman is attacked by a dog
Ganty Ritz for sure and later she
with her husband and tells her what happened but a part of her Richard was in his teeth. So she knew
it was him turned into a dog and she broke up with him. That's one kind of creature and there's also
this wind spirit that lifts people up in the air and after that you can become crazy or stuff
And I read about spirits that do the same thing in Japan.
So it seems to be common.
So, that's another thing and the strangest one is being called Mark Solya, which you
put translate as big Tuesday and this demon that doesn't want like Tuesday is his day.
So if women work on his day or her day, she's offended.
And usually she comes as the woman and helps them
work but harms them at the end. So like if they are boiling cloth, she pushes them in the water
in the boiling water or stuff like that. And this story is up to very recently and people have like,
it's not like long, long, long ago type of story. It's like I know someone or even myself,
of what has happened to me.
The first thing I'll say is with regards to the first two kinds of creatures you mentioned,
we are actually, that is literally, so we're going to be talking about, among other things,
werewolves, during this part of the episode. So just stay tuned for that.
And then this idea of demons that make you go insane, that is in fact what we're going to be talking
about in the third part. But I wanted to mention this thing about Tuesdays, which seems so
sort of random and weird, but the thing that occurred
to me is, and this is the association in my head when you said this. I don't know if
father Stephen knows something else that I don't, probably. But I do know that the idea
that Tuesday is considered to be a sort of unlucky or cursed day. It exists in the Balkans.
I know that some Greeks at least connect this to the fall of Constantine Opal to the Ottoman Turks
back in 14-
on May 29th of that year because it happened on a Tuesday.
And so there's this idea that that's an unlucky or a curse today.
And so you don't want to especially like start anything on that day.
Any new venture that would be a bad day has started.
So I mean, I that's what I'm kind of aware of.
I don't know, Father Steven, are you aware of other stuff in regards to this?
Yeah, as you mentioned, we're about to talk about Rico Lug.
and all that kind of stuff. But anyway, the second two, in terms of an aerial type spirit and
and sort of a demon who has claimed over a day, right, these are things that
in the ancient past remember we've talked about how there were spirits that were assigned to
to sort of be over and help administer for God
the different elements of creation.
Right and how many of them became demonic right so the devil himself at one point is called the prince in power of the air
Right because he was in some way associated with with the air and aerial spirits are sort of a general
category and
so part of what happens
as the world is
Christianized is that
that as we talked about, particularly in our Halloween special last year, is that these
demonic spirits...
at who had control of these things are displaced and saints and angels sort of take their place
in helping Christ and minister his kingdom and his dominion.
But there's sort of this constant tension, right, where the advantage, quote unquote,
that pagans thought that they had was you can't manipulate Christ, right?
There's nothing you could offer.
for Christ. You can't give Christ a sacrifice and get him to do it. You want Christ isn't
going to give you a love potion to make the person you like, like you back. Right. That's
not going to work because he doesn't need anything from you. Right. But these sort of lesser
pagan demonic spirits, you could try and sort of bargain with and make deals with. Right.
And so if when as paganism is displaced, right. And so the days of the week, like in their
English names are
related to pagan gods.
Oh yes, right.
It's Wotens Day and Thor's Day.
And right, these are these pagan spirits,
who that was their day, right?
There's this tendency to say,
well, I want to have a good day tomorrow,
or I really need X, Y, or Z to happen.
And what we're called to do as Christians
is to be diligent followers of Christ,
to pray, to commit it to God,
that Christ is with us no matter what happens, right?
But if you have...
someone who used to be a pagan or maybe still is a pagan whispering in your ear and saying,
yeah, but if you wear this amulet or use this charm or say this or
you know write this word on a pile of leaves or
whatever right. Well, the that'll kind of make the spirit of that day do what you want.
Right. Or that'll keep it at bay if we're talking about one of these demonic spirits. That'll keep
keep it away. Right? There's this.
great temptation to sort of not trust Christ, right? Not trust God. We see that the
exude Israelites do this over and over and over again, right? Rather than just
trusting in their God and being obedient and faithful, they also want to go on
the side and, well, I really need fertile crops. So I'm going to also sacrifice
to bail. And so I think that's where a lot of these traditions and stuff come
from. So the answer is not, the answer a lot of modern materialist Christians give
Oh, that's all nonsense.
and fairy tales, don't worry about that, come on. That's not the correct answer. The correct answer
is there are demons who used to be associated with days of the week in the pagan past. There are
demons who are were spirit aerial spirits, right? And if you're not resting in Christ, then yes,
those demonic spirits can pray upon you. Christ is the protection from those spirits. And so the
the protection from those spirits is not...
to perform some kind of ritual or wear some kind of charm or you know paint something on a wall or do something like that.
The answer is to trust in Christ and be faithful to Him because Christ is more powerful and command the demons not only to stay away from you but can drive them out entirely and throw them in the abyss.
Yep.
Yep. Does that help Alexander?
Yes, thank you very much. Can I have a refund before I leave?
Sure, a fun fact.
Yeah, I have a friend who interviewed a lot of villagers like 30 years ago.
And not only did they have a lot of stories about giants, but they knew where they are supposed
to be buried and tried to convince him to organize digging and stuff.
And one of the villagers is actually named after a giant stuff.
So amazing.
If people want to dig, they can come.
All right, we'll connect them with you.
I think you're our very first caller from Romania.
So welcome.
We're really glad to have you with us tonight.
Thank you.
All right.
Okay.
Thank you, Alexander.
We're going to take one more call and we have James calling
from Washington State.
James, are you there?
Hey there.
Good evening.
Welcome to the Lord of Spirits podcast.
What's in your mind, James?
Thank you.
After I get correction, my phone number is from Washington,
but I just moved to North Dakota.
well, all right, well, somewhere on the Northern border anyway.
You weren't cold enough.
All right.
Well, welcome, James, from North Dakota.
So, thank you so much.
As a writer and a reader and lover of stories,
and particularly fantasy and horror genres.
I've observed a trend in the nature and role that certain kinds of monsters take in the
stories as it's changed over the years.
And I never really thought too much of it until I started listening to the word of spirit
and thinking about the reality of things and wondering there's actually might be a deeper
implication to how we started interacting with them and framing them.
And the observation that I made it particularly is a note with like witches and vampires in particular.
where in the older story.
which is something you became or something you did, right?
You did witchcraft and therefore you are a witch.
Or vampirism where you became a vampire by doing vampirism in the sense.
Or pray upon and join in with it, type of thing.
But in recent stories, notably of course Harry Potter and things like that,
which is wizards sometimes vampires,
vampires, where we'll like a species or a race or something that you're born at.
It's not something you choose,
and are therefore, quote unquote, more neutral.
You can't condemn somebody for being a witch,
if they were just born that way, it's kind of the idea.
And I kind of thought of it in connection,
like maybe a connection with the idea
of your born or particular sexuality or something,
as a similar kind of argument.
But I think there might actually be something deeper,
and I'm not sure.
And also, I'm completely wrong,
but I know Father Steven has a much wider breadth
of pop culture awareness than I do.
And
than I do. God help us.
Like here's the observations valid in the first place, but also if there's something to this ship,
is it going to be employment on the 19th century German philosophers or what?
Yeah, I mean, I've, so I've noticed this too.
And I think alongside it also is an attempt to humanize the sort of the divine and the monstrous.
Right.
I noticed for instance that a lot of monsters are now
sort of teams domesticated and kind of cute.
And the example that I like to give for instance is,
even though I kind of like these films,
and my kids like them, and I let them watch them,
how to train your dragon, where dragons are literally trainable.
You know, I mean, they're fine, they're fine, right?
I'm not complaining against that, but it's a thing
in, you know, like, or like Pete's dragon,
I've noticed this, especially with dragons a lot,
Whereas if you look at dragons in...
mythology, they are not beings that you, yeah, yeah, they are not good beings ever, right?
They are monsters.
They are just sheer demons.
And so I think that part of what's going on is there's a materialism, right, which is
this idea that human beings don't actually interact with a kind of an unseen world.
It's all sort of inside them.
at the same time there's a there's a societal desire to interact to
like get in touch with the unseen, right? There's a want for that. And so then that gets
psychologized and internalized, right? So yes, some people kind of are magic. It's sort
of the idea, like with Harry Potter, for instance.
You know, so it's, yeah, it's interesting. I'm not quite sure what to make of it, but I
I do think that it's part of the general kind of,
this sort of contested world that
that is talked about, for instance,
in James Taylor's take on what he calls the secular three world.
Right?
Everything is contestant contestable.
There is no dominant narrative.
And I think that it's a manifestation of that.
And it's interesting, this is just gonna give more fuel
to the one guy who claims that this is the same podcast
as the Amundiwool podcast.
But it's interesting to look at the way
that Tolkien kind of deals with this,
where there is this notion that some people
have.
like divine blood, right?
But that doesn't necessarily give them magical powers.
So much as it actually enables them to have the possibility of
enoblement, which the whole point is then to a noble others.
It's sort of the way that that goes.
So I don't know.
I don't know.
I don't have any conclusions to any of that, but that's kind of my swimming around
in some of what you're talking about.
Father, what do you got?
Yeah, I think it all comes down to the X-Men.
man.
Yeah, right.
Yeah, and here's what so when when Stanley and Jack Kirby came up with the X-Men, Stan
leaves to joke that the reason he made the mutants was he couldn't think of any more good superhero
origins.
So he just said, well, they're mutants.
But in actuality, what's going on there is, you know, the mutants got their superpowers
when they went through puberty.
Right.
So this was to
connect with like young readers who are the audience for comics at the time, not people in their 40s like me.
And
and to kind of say, you know, when you're when you're a kid and you're going through puberty, all of a sudden your body gets weird and gross and you don't know what's happening to you and you feel like an outcast and a weirdo, right.
And so that was sort of the idea behind it. But then
Like as it goes on as the X-Men comics went on
of a sudden that became a metaphor for race in the late 60s and then it became a metaphor
for sexuality in the 90s and then on and on.
And so it's this kind of trope and this is why you see it's so concentrated in like
teen literature now like twilight or Harry Potter or whatever, right?
You have a group of people who feel weird, you know, and picked on and gross and that
kind of thing and appealing to them is the idea that, hey, that thing that makes you weird
and everybody picks on you about is actually like your superpower. That's what makes you
special and great, right? And so this isn't just sort of apologize for it because I think
there are some problematic things there, right? Where, where, when you tell people what's
important about you is how you're different from everyone else. Right? So like...
your rebellion is the core of your personhood,
the ways in which you have rebelled against societal structures.
That's what makes you unique as an individual and special.
So if you don't have that, right?
If you're sort of normal, that's bad.
Yeah.
Yeah, like that's a whole YA genre.
Yeah, like it's bad to be a muggle, right?
Like it's bad to just, you know,
live quiet and decent life.
life in godliness and sanctity. Like, as St. Paul says, we should try to. Like you need to be
different than everybody else and unique and question everything and, right? And that creates
a certain idea of what identity is where identity again is what makes you different from
everybody else, right? Whereas earlier and more ancient concepts of identity was your identity
with sort of a series of overlapping circles of where you fit.
Not where you-
didn't. Right. So my identity is made up of being my wife's husband and my
parents' child and the community I'm a part of and the the parish I'm a part of
and the right all of those roles and all those capacities you pile those all up
and you get my identity. My identity is not the way in which I reject all those.
Right. So I think that's at the core of what's going on and I think it is
super destructive.
to society, right? Yeah.
To start to view your own identity that way.
Yeah. Yeah.
Well, does that, does that, uh,
how would you write a story that the
verse goes true? Yeah. Well,
see J. R. Tolkien. I don't know.
You know, I mean, it's, it's,
it's true. Like, like, you know,
a lot of the things, um,
for instance, that our friend,
Jonathan Peugeot talks about is
you know.
reestablishing hierarchy in a healthy way.
And that's exactly this, right?
It's exactly putting things in their proper order, you know.
So, yeah, I mean, it can be done
and I think people do connect to it
when it's done really, really well.
I mean, you think about, I mean, just think about the,
like, it's interesting, for instance,
just look at the Marvel Cinematic Universe,
which plays with both of these ideas.
On the one hand, there is,
you know, these people are
and that's what makes them who they are.
But then on the other hand, there's like, okay,
there's problems in the world
and we need to fix them and need to put things back
to, you know, we need to have peace again
and, you know, this kind of thing.
So it's constantly dealing with this problem
of order versus chaos and how you navigate that, you know?
So, yeah, so.
All right, well, thank you very much for calling.
James, we're glad to have you on
help us let
us nerd out a little bit. So I mean, the whole thing is nerdy got, but this is a pop culture
nerdy got. All right. Thanks. Okay. So now, now that we've talked about just outright demons,
now we're going to talk about human beings that are kind of functioning in demonic ways.
And with the first, we're going to talk about werewolves. Everyone's favorite Halloween
Monsters, werewolves, right? Alexander brought up werewolves a little bit from from Romania
But yeah, I mean, werewolves, this is another one of these beasts that's like everywhere.
Like everyone has a werewolf.
And, you know, it's pretty much every culture and mythology.
And you can do your old English, etymology here.
Yes.
I'm your trumping at the bit.
I am.
It's a good, old English word, so were.
Yeah, it's funny.
Yeah, were is one of the many words from old English, that means man.
In other words, a human.
And then wolf is wolf.
It's just it's spelled with a U and
in Old English typically, but where Wolf is just man Wolf actually, that's all it is.
So yeah, that's where we get where Wolf.
It's a good, good classic Old English word.
Yeah.
And it's sort of a tri- transliteration of the Greek Lycanthrope.
Yes, right.
Winter Poets is man.
Yeah.
So that's Wolf Man instead of man.
Yeah, it's, yeah, it's a, what they call that a calc, a C-A-L-Q-U-E, where you translate
each of the parts and then come up with a new word, you know, like that.
Yeah.
I can throw up, yeah.
Yeah, so you have the classic television program,
Manimal, but that was a whole lot of thing.
Okay, so let's go to ancient Greece, Father Stevens,
because that's where our werewolves come from,
at least the earliest ones we know about it.
Well, and ancient ancient Greece.
Right.
So super ancient, like Titanic almost Greece.
Yes, we're talking about like the, the,
we're talking about Arcadia.
Ergries.
Yes.
were LA knows yeah so Arcadia is an area in Greece right a mountainous area
in Greece still but it was in the ancient world considered to be the beginning
this is where Greek civilization began and this was sort of the golden age back
of the past. And I'd be remiss if I didn't hear it.
a shout out to Arcadia Knight, the greatest wow guild in the history of Dragon-Plate US server.
But anyway, so in Arcadia, right, the first king there, sort of in this Greek prehistory,
was a fellow named Pulaskius. And that S, that Pulaskius part is important. This
is Pulaskius not Poulagius.
But spelled basically the same except with an S in there. Yes. Now if you want to scare the dickens out of your local Calvinists on Sunday
dress like Pallegius
but
This is how I try to imagine what a Pallegious costume would even look like I don't know
I don't know you'd have to look like you were working really hard to earn your salvation
Scottish to I mean I remember I remember there's an insult
I think the scene Jerome hurls at at Pallegious where he basically says that he eats too much haggis
if I remember correctly, which he was British. Yeah, right, right. I mean, it was definitely on the table. So there you go. Carry some haggis and yeah.
So, yeah, this is plastic. Only people who eat a lot of haggis could think that they could save themselves by their own merits.
If you can manage a large quantity of haggis, you are capable of many things.
Anyway, so this first gig.
Pulaskius. The archadians are also later known as Pulaskians, and that's named after Pulaskius.
And again, the founder of their their society, whatever. Right. That's like a G sound in there.
Pulaskius. This is not like Dr. Pulaski of the second season of Star Trek, the next generation.
And second season only. So they're not Polish. More well-known than Pulaskius.
other than the fact that he lends his name to the people.
in some accounts is his son, Likéon. And Dalai is his son named Likéon. Mout Likéon is a mountain
in that region. That mountain has two peaks and it is the southern peak which now concerns us
of the two. And what's on that southern peak of Mout Likéon is the oldest known alter to
not just known to us today but when you read ancient Greek sources they say
this is the first altered to Zeus. That altar is was so ancient and so sort of
renowned in Greek religion that was referred to its own name. They referred to
that altar as the Bemos. And that is important in showing you the age of this
tradition because
Bemos is derived from Bema or Bema in Semitic dialects, going back to Akkadian, which is the word for altar.
Yeah, and we use this even in Orthodox Christian liturgic history for a particular location in the
temple as well, the Vema in the middle of it typically. Yeah.
But this was not the regular word for altar. This one was just called the Bemos.
and we've mentioned this before.
the show but this is one of the reasons why Greece is the last ancient Near Eastern civilization,
not the first Western one is because when you get down to the Urlair of all of these,
particularly religious words in Greek, they're derived from akadian. They're coming from further east,
not further west. And so what the Bemos actually is, is, regardless of what you may be thinking
of what you think.
of an ancient altar, it was actually a big mound of ash from centuries of sacrifices
and then a retaining wall around it to mark out sort of the sacred precinct, right, around
the altar itself.
And the story was that anyone who walked into that sort of sacred precinct who went inside
the retaining wall inappropriately, sort of without permission.
or without the blessing to do it who wasn't a priest would be dead within a year for having
trespassed. And the reason they said that the altar was there in particular is that they believed
that that peak was the birthplace of Zeus like chaos, sort of the localized hypostasis of Zeus
from that place. Right. The zoo's who was worship there was actually born there.
And that's the reason for the altar. So this ancient site is there.
Here's where things get ugly again. Repeat the parental advisory.
So in the story of King like K-On, he goes to this place and sacrifices a human infant who was an enslaved person.
and the child of an enslaved group who he had come.
and offered the infant as a sacrifice to Zeus, including eating some of the entrails.
Yeah, because just as a reminder, everybody, human sacrifice, it doesn't involve just killing humans,
it involves eating humans. Yes, cannibalism and in the form of blood drinking and in the form of cannibalism.
eating peace. Yeah, right. And so when he did this...
horrible thing. He was transformed into this sort of cannibalistic wild wolf creature.
Yeah, so there's kind of a like, here's the question I have, and this is a genuine question.
Like it's a chicken egg issue. Like, is the Greek word for for wolf
derived from this guy's name? Lecaon or is his name wolfy? I mean, what's what's going on here?
It probably goes the other way.
that that that wolf is derived from his name.
No, that he's being named Wolfie.
Yeah, he's being named Wolfie.
Okay.
That yeah, this is Wolf Mountain and yeah.
Yeah.
Right.
And, you know, we've, I don't know if we've mentioned this
on this show in the past, but just to say it now.
Like, you know, of course, sacrifice puts you in communion
with your God and sometimes like big, super sacrifices
are done to have kind of big effects.
And so to sacrifice a human is done in an attempt to, I don't know, have a really super intense
communion with your God in like gain powers, you know, like it's considered a very powerful,
powerful, big sacrifice to sacrifice a human being versus just like an animal or a
grain or a drink or something like that, which is sort of the usual, like, like, this
This is unusual even for paganism that you would sacrifice a person, right?
Because you get in the ancient world, you get pagans who don't do that.
Looking down on and sometimes attacking and destroying other pagan tribes who did it,
looking at them as sort of way beyond the pale like that's just so wicked, nobody should
do that.
But the idea is that it's this monstrous thing to do in order to get monstrous results.
Right.
And it's interesting.
You see this migrate in the telling of the story too.
the earliest Greek tongues of this story.
It's kind of portrayed as this kind of powerful,
or magic thing.
I need to stop using or I've used it too much today.
But when you get to the later stuff,
especially when you get to like,
Avent talking about it, when you get to the Romans
had a particular aversion to most,
repeat most forms of human sacrifice,
see the Punic Wars.
So they saw him getting turned into a wolf
as more of a punishment from the...
Yeah, like a curse from the gods.
Yeah.
That's the version I think you usually see if you're reading if people are reading this story at all
Which it's not usually in most kind of collections of Greek mythology that are out there
But most of the ones you see it's this idea that he did this wicked thing and so he was cursed by the gods to be like a wolf
But like you said in early ones. It's like
like
He was gifted by the gods to you know like he gained wolf powers
Yeah, and even the later Greeks got super embarrassed by this stuff
And they're sort of super they did some revisionism
Um, how about one does?
Yeah.
Um, that's what would be a little embarrassed.
Um, so, uh, but not only do you have this cultic activity going on,
but related cultic activity, we don't usually think of it as modern people as
cultic activity, but there were also, uh, like,
Hay and games that were held in the valley at the foot of Mount Leichand.
Like Olympic games, but they're cannibalistic werewolf games.
Yeah, they worked that.
Yeah, so we and it's worth noting. We don't think of the Olympics as cultic activity today. No, but they were games were in the ancient world.
Many of the earliest games, especially the Greek games did not have spectators.
Hmm people didn't go to watch them as sporting events
Yeah, they went out and they performed these things they were performing for the God
in their mind. So this was a sort of a weird sort of offering, right, of their prowess
and beauty and strength, right? Yeah. To try to gain credit with the gods, try to impress them.
Yeah, I mean, it's this whole notion of like doing quests to get
Yeah, yeah, yeah, raise your rep. Yeah
But so the most famous champion
of these games was the first champion, a fellow named Demarcus of Parhasia, and the way he won the
games was before the games, he went up to the altar and offered an infant and ate part of it,
and got the wolf powers, and then the wolf, the wolf and transformation allowed him the additional
strength and prowess and everything to be this great victor in the game.
and be crowned as the as the victor. So much later in the second century BC there's a fellow named
Poussinius who was a geographer who traveled around Greece and sort of he was sort of the Anthony
Bourdain of the ancient world. He went around and talked about the food and the culture and the
Geography and the way of life and sacrifice right yeah
and all these things in these various places.
And he tells us in the second century BC,
so this isn't that long before Christ.
This may be 150 years before the birth of Christ,
tells us that these infant sacrifices
were a regular occurrence there.
This wasn't just this crazy thing that happened
in the distant past, but this is something that,
I mean, not every day, but every few years,
this is a thing that happened.
Um, um,
And there's a related story connected to this that's told by Pliny the Elder, who says
that they chose a man by lot every 10 years.
And this person who was chosen by lot would sort of go into this sacred forest and become
this like wolf creature.
And he would spend nine years roaming in the wilderness as this kind of wolf and creature.
And if he...
didn't eat any human flesh during that nine years, then in the 10th year he would be restored
to his humanity. But if he did, he would remain in that state permanently. And so when
Caesar Augustus comes to power and he's putting together, he has Enius put together,
or not Enius, Virgil put together the Enid, the new history of the world that culminates in Augustus.
He also had
the world and collect sort of all the folklore of the stories so he could form them all into one sort of master epic again leading up to Caesar Augustus.
And Ovid includes in this Roman material both pausanius and Pliny's accounts for together of this where Wolfism thing.
And so this is this this well known
phenomenon in the ancient world, or anybody will about what happens with
cannibalism, right? Particularly. And this kind of human sacrifice and the
spirits associated with it. Such that St. Augustine talks about it in city of
God, 1817. And he recounts the same story that Pliny the Elder did, but he also
also talks about those who in
who say Mutaum, right, those who are changed into wolves, right, they're transformed into wolves, and says that this is a particular type of sorcery or witchcraft, right, pagan ritual,
that people participate in to do this, to have this effect, that there are demonic spirits related to this, right, and that by participating in these rituals, one takes on this sort of monstrous,
animalistic, cannibalistic aspect.
Then, in the going on from St. Augustine in the Latin West, there's this text called the Canon Episcopie or the Capitulum Episcopie.
And this was believed for a long time in the medieval period to have been canons issued by the Council of Enciro.
Right, but wasn't actually.
was not actually. But because they thought that they were
these cannons entered into Western cannon law. So they are still to this day,
they're in there in Western cannon law, and includes this condemnation of what we
would call werewolfism, of rituals to cause yourself to be possessed by these
animalistic cannibal spirits. And because it's then in Western cannon law, when you
get to the Inquisition, the Inquisition has R.
records of executing in various countries a handful of werewolves, of people who had participated
in these kind of rituals, had become demon possessed like this and then who were executed
for cannibalistic activities.
This becomes in French the Luguru, which for those of us in southern Louisiana is the
origin of the Rugeru, his Cajun cousin who wrote
the values. And you can see how this starts to participate in some of the stuff we said about
Lilith because like when you get to the Rugeroo, this is something to scare kids with, right? It's
a sort of demonic being who's prowling around that's going to get you if you don't behave.
This kind of fury idea that we that we talked about. And then you get Hispanic
traditions, the kakui and some of these things.
that are also sort of similarly related.
But now's your chance father,
I had to talk about some Indo-European paganism.
Yeah, right.
I mean, so as a lot of people probably know,
I've been reading a lot of Germanic literature lately,
both like Norse pagan and of course,
then Beowulf, which is Christian literature.
And like this idea of where will
is there all over the place and it's often associated with warfare, particularly like you would engage, you would do something to become like a wolf, or occasionally like a bear.
Before you go into battle, in some of these stories, you see them people actually being transformed into wolves. And interestingly enough, there's a Germanic word, like the word for wolf, which is wolf.
which is wolf.
is also used to refer to outlaws in general.
So this idea that outlaws are participating
in this tradition on some level.
And what's interesting if you read some of these,
these North stories, particularly like in some
of the cigarette legends and stuff.
And I noticed this when I was reading this
in some of my class as I've been taking lately,
but a lot of times right before they become quote unquote wolves,
there's references to eating and drinking human blood
and this kind of thing.
So like this connection between cannibalism and wherewolfism, I mean, it's just, it stretches
from one end of the world to the other, you know. So yeah, it's crazy, crazy stuff.
But yeah, I mean, there's a whole series of like these wherewolf legends.
And, and it's an interesting question, like, what's, you know, are like,
And then we're gonna talk about like you brought this.
Native American stuff to, but like underneath it, are we talking like, you know, there's
the modern notion of werewolves, right? Like we've seen these movies and stuff twilight
and all this kind of stuff. And then, and then Teen Wolf, hello, that's about getting
power. So you can be really good at sports. Hello. Hi, ancient Greece. You know, sorry,
Michael J. Fox. Yeah, you heard it here first. Michael J. Fox is a nephilim. You heard it
of course.
the shortest whatever, but still, yeah.
Right?
Because they're not necessarily tall, everybody.
But yeah, I mean, like what's underneath it?
Well, I mean, do we believe that if you go into communion
with demons in weird ways like this,
you can gain supernatural abilities?
Yes, I mean, it's a tested throughout history.
And in the Bible.
The demon possessed.
man who throws off the people who try to change.
and breaks chains.
Yeah.
Okay, so mention the Native American stuff,
because I mean, that's on the other side of the oceans now.
Right, yeah, and it's worth,
really, especially the Indo-European form,
this is especially related to initiation rituals.
Yes, becoming, crossing into manhood,
crossing into soldierhood, becoming a king,
like this stuff is connected to all of that.
And so what that means is,
we talked about with the
giant clans, what makes the giant clans giant clans is this ritual life and participation in it, right?
So what we're talking about here with wearable fism is really a sub species of
Giantism, right? If you want to use that term. Yeah, it's about communion with demons in order to sort of gain
powers. Yeah, so the the native of American version of this this is actually
a queso, a wide swath of Native American groups, but the one that's been
the most by sort of Forkloris is the Ojibwe. And that's where these
spirits are known as the Wendigo. And here's where I make like a ravenous
joke that you won't get, but some listener will somewhere. And hungry like the Wolf
joke, so you could get out into the playlist. But so the idea in popular
culture when they do horror movies and stuff with women.
It's usually some kind of hairy beast man kind of creature, but that's that's white settlers assimilating the Wendigo stuff with
Where wolf stuff from Europe, right?
Right and we're not saying it's unrelated but when you look at sort of the original Ojibwe Wendigo stuff. This is
Actually a spirit a demonic spirit
Which is a giant
They describe it as being this giant spirit.
appears as sort of a withered, emaciated human. And when I say withered,
it emaciated, I mean, they describe it as like a skeleton with some skin
hanging off of it. But it's sort of ice cold, giant skeleton thing. But the
spirit comes and possesses people who are greedy or who are gluttonous or who
engage in cannibalism. And regardless of why it possesses you, it then causes
you to engage in cannibalism. And so there's these
initiation rituals involving cannibalism from ancient times in among North American
tribes as well. So this is one of those sort of universal, just like giants are
universal, this sort of subspecies of giant that's associated with this kind of
gluttony and greed, the devouring of flesh both metaphorically and literally
and these rituals involving the sacrifice of...
of humans and eating a flesh and blood, right?
It sort of just cross the board thing, right?
Of demonic activity.
Yeah.
Okay.
So we've talked about werewolves, and now we're going to, as you'll see everybody, the
line between that and we're about to talk about is actually kind of narrow at points.
But in popular imagination, there's another thing called a vampire.
Right.
And most people think of the whole Brahms Stoker thing
and Dracula, who by the way is a Romanian folk hero.
But weirdly enough, vampires are a thing
in wow, a lot of cultures.
So what's the deal with vampires?
Yeah, it's also not a feat people living in New Orleans
or people who sparkle in the sunlight.
So
So basically at its root to sort of boil it down in bottom line it, right?
What we're categorizing here as under the category of vampire is a demon possessed corpse,
a dead human body that has been possessed by a demonic spirit, as opposed to a living
person who has been possessed by a demonic spirit.
And so what you find in this phenomena is...
people who have died in some sort of cursed state, right?
So whether this is in paganism,
they were under some kind of curse
or had done some kind of horrible evil
in life that had brought a curse upon them,
or once Christianity comes into the picture,
this is people who died excommunicated,
were buried in unhallowed ground, right?
This kind of thing.
that then opens up the possibility
of this demonic possession. And there's also because this father
editor just said the line between what we're categorizing for
sakes of this episode as vampire and what we're categorizing as
where wolf is pretty thin. There's cannibalism and blood
drinking involved with this too. And in fact, sometimes you find
this view, sometimes the people who come back as some kind of
vampiric thing are people
who were sort of demon possessed, were wolf types, right?
Can't believe it's in their life,
and then they die and continue this sort of demonic existence.
Yeah, and there's, I mean,
and in a lot of ways vampires are kind of closely related
to imagery having zombies,
demon possessed corpse coming back
that wants to eat humans on the level.
Yeah, yeah.
Yeah.
And this is also, I mean, this...
of everything we talked about, demonic lilythes in the first half all flows into this too.
So you have this thing called a Strix, which is Strega in Latin or Strix with sort of a G in an
X the way it's usually transliterated from Greek, which was a night demon who eats flesh and drinks
blood particularly praise on infants.
from that word is derived street, street,
in Romania and in the Balkans in general.
The first person in history who we have,
who was sort of publicly labeled and written about as being street
boy was the fellow, I'm assuming,
I'm assuming this pronunciation,
my Croatian is rusty, shall we say.
But it looks to me like
Yuri Grando Alilovic, who lived at Croatia in the mid-17th century.
In the year 1672, 16 years after he died, he showed up in Austria where he came from and
came back and was this demon possessed, being that attacked people in the area until he
was decapitated by the village priest.
and numerous people wrote about this at the time.
This was the talk of Europe at the time,
and much reported on.
Yeah.
And so we mentioned the Balkans when you get into Greek discussions
of these creatures, they're referred to as Vrykolaqis.
Yeah, which is not, you know, the proprietor of your local
Eurostand. It's yeah, I saw I looked this up so I could see where the stress is. We're
of Rikolakas. Mentioned by a number of modern Orthodox saints. Surprise, surprise everybody.
So Saint Kusmas Etalos, who's 18th century, he said this, this is a direct quote, when
And we hear the word devil.
It is he who is once the first among angels.
It is he who moves people to pride, to murder, to theft.
It is he who enters into a dead person,
causing him to appear living,
and we call him a vricola cas.
So Sinkosmas says that the devil enters into a dead person,
causing him to appear living,
and that's called a vricola cas.
Which often gets translated as vampire,
but it's sort of like part the way between,
Again, vampire and werewolf and zombie.
And then, okay, so here's another one.
So much, much more, even more modern
saying St. Paiusios the Athenite,
who just died in the 1990s.
So this is from the life of St. Paiusios
by his disciple, Elder Isaac,
who writes this, the elder related quote,
I knew an old woman who was very stingy.
Her daughter was very good.
and whatever she wanted to give his arms,
she would throw out the windows
so she could leave the house with empty hands
because her mother would always check to see
if she was taking anything.
But if she told her mother that the monk, that is me,
had asked for something,
then her mother would be willing to give it up.
After her death, I saw a young man, her guardian angel,
and he said to me, come so and so wants you.
I couldn't understand what happened to me,
but we were standing in front of a grave in Konnitsa.
He moved his hand like
like this, and the grave opened. Inside I saw a grimy mess, and the old woman who had
started to decay. She was calling out, monk, save me. My heart went out to her. Feeling
sorry for her, I climbed down inside, and without being repulsed, I embraced her and asked,
what's wrong? She said, tell me, didn't I always give you anything you asked willingly?
Yes, I said, that's true. All right, so the young man soothing her. He moved his hand
like this again and close the grave like a curtain and I was back in my
Well, the sisters from Surat-i asked me, by the way, I'll just say, it's Surat-i is
the town where the monastery that he founded and where he finished out his life was.
And that's where he's buried, by the way, too.
So the sisters from Surat-i asked me, what happened to you on the feast day of Saint Andrew?
I answered, pray for so and so's soul.
Two months later, I saw her again.
High above in a bis, there was a plateau with places, a lot of houses and many people.
The old woman was up there.
She was very happy with the face of a small child that had just a tiny spot that her angel
I'll see you in the next video.
also scrubbing to clean off. In the abyss, in the distance, I saw people being beaten
in her ass and trying to climb up. I embraced her out of joy. I took her aside a little
so the people in the abyss wouldn't see us and be hurt. She said to me, come on, let
me show you the place where the Lord has put me. So in this St. Piusios is brought to the
grave of this woman who was mostly evil in life, very stingy. And then he sees her as
is like this sort of...
animated corpse decaying and so forth, and then through his prayers she's brought to paradise
on the Feces of St. Andrews.
Hey, the Feces of St. Andrews.
So that's a couple of modern saints that refer to things that are like what we're talking
about.
We're going to talk a little bit more about modern Greece and this, but there's a couple
the things we wanted to mention that are connected with this, right?
Yeah, so this is this is something that goes way back again back to the Neolithic period
We have found in Neolithic burial sites and it's only certain
Burials within a burial site there will be certain burials where the
Remains were
like weighted down or pinned
inside the grave with like heavy things like rocks and things somewhere they
down. And again, this isn't like every grave in the site is that way. This is particular
graves in the site. And only those particular ones. And very common in the Incenshirt world
are to find again, just some of them buried sort of facing down. The idea being that if
they came back they would since they're facing
they would go down into the underworld, down into sh-
all rather than coming back up to where living people were.
Those are sort of the pagan ways of handling it.
But you see this being seen as a possibility
right away in the Byzantine period,
because we start finding certain, and again it's only certain,
Byzantine burial sites where there are these wax crosses,
that had the what looks like an English in ICXC, which is actually six.
And then Nika, right, Jesus Christ conquers, Anowax Cross, that was put on a body as a sort of a seal to protect it from demons.
Yeah, sort of sigil or sign against demonic influence.
Yeah, Christ is sort of the symbol of Christ's victory over the demons.
right, that would prevent the demons from disturbing the remains.
or attempting to use the remains. But the clearest thing, oh boy, that Father Andrew's
going to get to read, I'm so excited about this, you have no idea. You didn't see this
coming, did you? I did not. When you sent this to me, this is great. So, in 1867, this little
book called the Nomo Canon was issued to all of the Orthodox priests in Greece.
And it had, it's sort of like a small book of needs kind of, right?
It had canonical rules for how to do certain things in procedures for handling certain things
canonically.
And there's a section, which Father Andrew is about to read, which is called, concerning
those who burned Rikolakis.
Okay.
So this is what it says.
who have burned vrykola cas and were coded.
in their smoke should not receive communion for at least six years.
Vricolas are submissive instruments of the devil
who appear at night wandering too and fro,
harming, destroying, and predicting the future.
These are those who are many days or even many years dead
and return among the living as one who is young with flesh and bones.
Thus, when these people hurried to burn the dead,
having exhumed them and seen the brick.
Kolakas filled with blood, with long hair and long nails, they should have known that his
accursed relics would be resurrected again on the day of judgment when he would stand
before the dread and impartial judge.
Then he would be sent to the outermost eternal fire, damned fraternity, unless he truly
repents of his impiety.
When this kind of satanic demon is identified, the priests should have been called to perform
a supplicatory cannon to the their tocos and a blessing of the
waters, then they would serve a divine liturgy and ask the help of the panellia for all of
the people and also celebrate a memorial service with Koliva, chant the exorcisms of the baptismal
service, and the exorcism prayers of St. Basil the Great, and sprinkle the entire community
with holy water, pouring the remaining holy water on the Rikolakas. By God's grace, the demon
will flee. So before we discuss this, I just
to point out that even if you were to say that, for instance, when St.
Kusmas was talking about this phenomenon, that he was just sort of passing on some kind
of tradition he knew about, or that St. Paiyusius was just having like a vision.
I mean, you could explain what they said in those terms.
This is a book of instructions, two priests telling them what to do.
Number 1, if someone was going around burning the bodies of these.
people. And number two, what should be done instead of this kind of vampire hunter thing
that was going on. So, I mean, this is very, this is, these are solemn instructions,
like these are liturgical instructions. You know, like this is not, you know, book of crazy
things that priests should know about. This is, this is, you know, yeah, like I said,
are liturgical instructions.
This is a-
part of a manual, right? So it's very clear and it's not just like, you know, do
exorcisms, whatever, but even includes this definition of what this, what this is, that
these are human corpses that are inhabited by demonic presence and that come out of their
graves and, and, you know, do bad things, right? So, okay.
Yeah, right.
Yeah, yeah.
So yeah, okay.
It's it's
important how this is phrase too. What's it get past the initial like?
What? Right. Right. Which I'm still kind of there, but I've
read it ten times now. Yeah. So. Right. How is this phrase?
Right. Concerning those who burn freegulacus. Right. So the problem
from the perspective of this text, the problem is that there are people going
around burning these bodies.
Digging them up and burning them.
That's the problem that this is is set out to address right so taken for granted is the idea
That there are these people
Who through living an evil way of life have ended up becoming these monstrous things these monstrous dead things right
You didn't end up this way accidentally right
They become these and these monsters are menacing the community
Right.
And the problem from the perspective of this text then is that in many of these communities,
the response to it is for these people to go and identify the person who has become this monster
and destroy them. That's the problem because what should happen according to this text
is what? That the community, the community is being menaced by this monster,
by this formerly human monster.
needs to gather together and they need to pray to God for the soul of this person to try to drive out the demon and redeem this person,
which they can't do if someone has burned them.
Right? And so burning one of these gets you six years excommunication, right? That's like murder.
Yep.
Right? This is seen as like murdering that person's soul by this text.
And so that to me is the key thing here is that you know, you don't go and try to destroy the monster that's menacing your community, your community gathers together to repent on behalf of that person because they're dead and they can't repent anymore.
And to seek that, that...
formerly human monsters salvation somehow.
All right, well with that we are now going to go to our next break and we'll be right back with
the third half of the show. Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Steven DeYoung will be back
in a moment to take your calls on the next part of the Lord of Spirits. Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
That's 855
A.F. Radio.
Ancient Faith Publishing presents, I Live Again, a memoir of Iliana, Princess of Romania
and Arch Duchess of Austria, who in later life became Mother Alexandra, founder of the
Orthodox monastery of the Transfiguration in Pennsylvania, who wrote this memoir shortly
after relocating to the US in the 1950s.
It tells
the story of a life full of suffering, tragedy and exile.
But all is diffused with the author's deep faith, hope, love and even joy.
This reprint includes additional material collected by the Nuns of Vermont Asterie that sets
the memoir in the context of Mother Alexandra's Later Life.
To find this book and others like it, you can go to store.ancientfaith.com.
Again, that is store.ancientfaith.com.
We're back now with the Lord of...
the father, Andrew Stephen Damick and father Stephen DeYoung.
If you have a question, call now at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF radio.
Welcome back everyone.
We're going to take a couple of calls, but first I wanted to just mention something
that I think a lot of you out there are going to be into.
So, you know, we've made reference a number of times on the show
to R.
friend Jonathan Pejo's work on the symbolic world. And so I wanted to mention a new project
that he's got coming out that I think is going to especially appeal to you, Lord of Spirits listeners.
It's a graphic novel that's called God's Dog. Now this isn't an ad, but it's just something
that's really relevant that I think you guys are going to like. He actually sent me a draft of
the piece I read through it. It's really cool actually cool art interesting writing.
It's a fantastic and kind of imaginative weaving together of stories and figures from Christian tradition
including yep the Nephilim
St. George
St. Seaman the Stylight and of course St. Christopher
And you know of course very relevant to tonight's episode
So anyway, so Jonathan has a crowd funder that's going up in just a few days
You can learn about God's dog and sign up for updates at God's dog calm. So it's God's dog calm
Um.
The crowd funder starts up on October 31st,
but you can, like I said, you can sign up for updates.
All right, well, we do have some callers waiting
on the line and first is Jewels.
So Jewels, you've been waiting very patiently for a while.
So welcome to Laura Spears podcast.
Thank you, father.
Oh man, it's this guy.
Wow, okay, I guess we know each other.
I thought for the sake of professionalism we were going to pretend like we didn't know
each other but I'm about to roast you in front of like 12,000 people.
Wow, this is exciting.
You know, I'm going to say something guys, I'm going to say after the last that I just
became even more pre-modern than I usually was.
What?
What I said, the next question.
So you guys are talking about what's respective vampires like a bazette.
that body, but I noticed that there's a lot of myths and stories where you'll see sort of like an
innocent passerby who gets abducted in the night or walks in the long, like wrong side of the
woods and then they get, you know, they get abducted and turned into some kind of monster. And I think
the example I want to go with was there's the vampire myth of Savasavana, which I think I mentioned
to the father's student a couple times, but where I'm not going to say the whole myth because that's
Let's go take forever.
but there's basically a woman who marries this young man and they live in the middle and the vampire used to live in the mill.
And the woman's sleeping one night and the moth, there's a moth that uses the vampire that just enters into her mouth.
And then that's all it takes to just turn her into a vampire herself.
And so I'm kind of curious about that sort of thing,
which have the sort of innocent people who didn't really live
these, like, at least not described as them.
living these sinful lives, but these monsters still get hold of them and turn them into
something demonic.
Like what's going on there?
Father.
Since this guy, you're going to embarrass him from a 13,000 people.
I thought there was one place where I wouldn't have to answer his questions.
And he's not safe anymore.
No.
I assume he's local to you.
I guess he is.
Okay.
All right.
This is love then.
That's good.
He is my prodigal spiritual son in fact.
But so yeah, so part of this is related to the answer we gave to a color in the last half
when you probably weren't paying attention.
Where?
Wow.
No.
Where there's this tendency.
This is another place where paganism kind of tries to creep back.
in. Right? So sometimes I mean, the way you've described them in, I think it's this sometimes
it's an idea of light. Well, you need to conduct yourself in a certain way. This is more like St.
Jerome's idea with the the lamia, right? You need to conduct yourself in a morally pure way
in your life in order to be safe from these things, right? Or something bad might befall you.
But more often...
than not, we get into the mode of that paganism is creeping back in and saying, well, you
need to do X, Y, Z, right?
Eat a lot of garlic, right?
Or, you know, do these.
What are usually ancient pagan practices and charms and that kind of thing in order to
protect yourself from these demonic spirits and demonic creatures?
Because otherwise, even if you're an innocent person, you may fall victim to them.
That ends up becoming a sort of more subtle temptation in its own right, in that it's
tempting you to put your trust in those kinds of what's really a form of technique, a form
of know-how, even though it's magical know-how, to try to protect yourself and control the
world around you in your environment rather than trusting in Christ and remaining faithful
to him and having that as sort of your protection.
So the particular casting of a lot of those stories is where some of those old pagan things
try to keep creep back in.
And while it's subtle in a story like that, there were unsuttle forms of this in the
ancient world, like when the western half of the Roman Empire was collapsing.
There was a huge move by the pagan saying, this is because you converted to Christianity,
We need to go back to the pagan gods and then they'll save the west.
Roman Empire. This isn't that sort of gross and unsuddle. It's a more subtle way for those same pagan
rituals and traditions and things to kind of try and creep back in under the radar and distract
people from Christ and faithfulness more subtly. Does that make sense? Thank you for me.
All right. Thank you very much for calling, Jules. I think you got off pretty well.
Well, it's, so yeah.
I went easy. It's a problem. I went easy. All right. Okay. All right. We're going to take one more call and that is Sarah. So Sarah. Are you there?
Yes. I am here. My question is pretty basic. It's just it's just wondering where in this discussion, we put legends like big foot, the Yeti, the
snowball and snowball snowman, just these giant these creatures are they just kind of another
their offshoot of the werewolf turned in.
or are they kind of their own unique thing?
Yeah, I mean, to me, it's interesting that they're often
depicted as giants, right?
That they're physically large.
But yeah, I mean, to me, it seems like it's emerging
of that, of giant stuff, along with werewolf stuff.
They're sort of halfway between either wolves
bears and people.
right? You know, like this actually gives the opportunity to kind of mention one thing, right? We sometimes refer to
pagan stories as being demonic propaganda and they kind of are, but there's also a layer of just human beings
interacting with this stuff
you know in ways that then it gets recorded in a particular way and so
So like in this case, what's I would say that the under
understanding is that there's these phenomena that people are aware of, but then the way that the stories get told
manifest themselves as these creatures like this, right? That there's this beast man that's out in the wilderness
Who's ready to maybe eat people or do violence in some way or another like that?
So I mean that's that's kind of my take on that so father
I don't know do you have any um-actual ease or
expansions or whatever on any of that stuff?
of what with Sasquatchin.
Yeti in particular what tends to get left out right and leaving this out
Helps assimilate it to more of a werewolf type thing is that you especially see this with the Yeti
But you see this was some of the Native Americans stuff regarding Sasquatch also is that the Yeti is actually sort of the wise man of the wilderness
Right that these weren't sort of seen as bestial creatures, but they're seen as sort of these ancient creatures
that had this
kind of ancient wisdom about them, right?
That they were in touch with something maybe that humans weren't,
or they occupied this kind of weird semi-divine ground,
even though they're kind of bestial at the same time.
And so, yeah, I think that's an important element
that sometimes gets left out because you see a horror movie
with a Sasquad.
or on the other end you see Harry and the Henderson's but
and we tend to think of them as creatures or as some kind of ape or some kind of caveman or that kind of thing
but the more ancient stories about them is always that you know you would go seek the Yeti
into bet because it had some kind of in some cases even antiteluvian kind of wisdom about it you know
that it might be able to impart to you or it's sort of like sort of like whom
Baba, if you're familiar with the epic of Gilgamesh at all, in the Cedar Forest of Lebanon,
right, who's sort of this creature favored by the gods. There's a little more of that element to it,
I think, that is missing from some of the werewolf. So they're not clearly human in the way that,
like, werewolfism is a human who's entered into this kind of relationship with the spirit.
Does that make sense, you, Sarah?
Yes, that does make sense.
And then is there time for a quick follow up question?
Sure.
Is it about El Chupacabra?
No.
No, it's more about the where wolves,
like going back of why?
Is there reason that the wolf's form gets harped on?
Like it's not like a where beast.
There seems to be this theme of wolf specifically.
Yeah, you do see some.
It's a really logistical thing.
You do see some bare stuff.
in there in the Indo-European, but the wolf across the board is by far the most predominant.
That may be related to dogs, which of course are related species being one of the earliest
domesticated animals. I'm partially conjecturing here.
Yeah, and and and also like you know human interactions with wolves legendarily
especially are not good, especially human beings traveling in the wilderness and that kind of thing.
And wolves, especially when they go in packs, can be particularly dangerous. But then there's also
at the same time, especially wolves in North America, for instance, can act in a very solitary way.
But they're huge. I mean, if you've ever seen a wolf in person, they're big, big animals,
and very scary.
So even though they insert their natural sort of biological state often will avoid people and are therefore not that dangerous, people who encounter them are rightly kind of scared because of how big and scary they can be.
But yeah, it's really just this prototypical sense of violent, you know, be still presence amongst human beings.
You know, it's not that people who...
who gain this sort of demonic ability become wolves,
it's that human beings understand what's happening to them
as being in a wolfish way, if that makes sense.
Like this is the way that it gets talked about.
It's not that they become that animal, you know,
in reality.
Yeah, cause a human being cannot take on the nature
of a wolf.
Right, it's a predatory thing.
Yeah, right.
It's about predation.
And b-
There's aren't predators of the way a wolf is.
Right, right?
Yep, that's true.
That's true.
How does that work for you, Sarah?
That was perfect.
That was very helpful.
Thank you.
Great.
All right.
Well, thank you very much.
I said we were that Sarah was going
to last call we're going to be take.
But we actually have a deacon calling
and who has an urgent question about the no-mo-canon having
to do with Bricola Coss.
So is facing this situation, as we speak?
I don't know.
OK.
Yeah
but we're going to let him in under the wire before we talk about demon possession.
So how about that? All right, so Deacon, are you there?
I am here. Hello.
All right, welcome.
So, okay, so what's your deal, Deacon?
Well, some of my results, well, some people know I'm a vampire scholar myself.
And I was originally going to have cannons, but you guys kind of covered the question I was going to ask.
the question was gonna ask so I had something different it might be
later what you're going to talk about.
All right, I'm laying on this.
I did a lecture once on heresy and extra systems of vampires
and the thought that most of the time
when these vampires appeared, but they weren't necessarily
seen, they were just found in the grave in corrupt.
So do you think that the demons might
have chosen that form of an corrupt body
to because holy people were easily incorrect.
Yeah, it's a kind of parody of holiness, you know.
Yeah, I mean, that makes sense to me.
I don't know, Father, what do you got on that?
Yeah, I think there's that element.
And, you know, if you've read all this stuff,
then you probably already know this.
But part of what happens then once the demon is sort of dispeled,
spelled is that the body decomposes normally.
So, and that's connected to, of course, you know, our bodies, you know, ashes to ashes
dust to dust, right?
Our bodies return to the earth from which they were formed.
And so, there's an element there also of sort of what is natural not being allowed to take
it's course, but there's this unnatural
that this this demonic spirit is sort of rebelling against the natural order
that God has set up for our life in this world, right, where we are mortal.
But it's again, it's not actual resurrection or actual continued life.
It's just this parody of it, right?
Yeah, false life.
Usually it was just a misunderstanding of medicine, you know, people didn't know
how about you can post like then?
Yeah, yeah.
They've viewed everything.
is something supernatural when it was really all bodies bloat and leak and things like that.
Yeah, but sometimes it is. Yeah. Yeah. It's giant. Yeah. It's not always giants,
but sometimes it is giants. All right. Well, thank you very much for your call.
Okay. Well, this is the final half of the show tonight. We've gone on for a while, but we wanted to
talk a little bit.
about demon possession and about King Solomon's magic ring. So
Yes.
Ring do your thing. Yeah.
Digging in the crates with the references tonight.
One ring to rule. No, sorry.
Too obvious. Wait. Yeah. Too obvious. But I mean, super, super
applicable in this particular case, as everyone will see in just a
second. So yeah. Yeah. Yeah. So we've, we've talked about demon
possession of several.
points along the way on the show. We talked about how that was seen in the ancient world in many
cases in a positive light. I mean, not like we talked about with werewolves, that werewolfism
was even seen in sort of a positive light very early on. Yep. In a lot of big in context. But you
know, we gave the example before of Socrates who had this demon that whispered wisdom to his soul
And that was part of his defense.
Right?
Yes.
I'm getting this from a demon guy.
you know, oh, okay, let him go then. Yeah. So I mean, this was seen in a very different way.
And we see that reflected, of course, as we mentioned before in the book of Acts,
when there's the slave girl who is possessed by the demonic spirit who tells fortunes,
right? Like we saw one of the things that the Rikolakas does is predict the future, right?
Is possessed by the demonic spirit and St. Paul casts out the demonic spirit and then the
the owners get mad at him.
Cause the
owners of the slave girl get mad at him because they say, you know, how dare you. This is how we made our money, you know.
And even some modern episcopalians think that was a horrible thing to do to her because that's what made her unique and special to go back to that point was being possessed.
Yes. You're not making that up.
Yeah.
So, this isn't a case where Christianity comes along and starts talking about people.
being demon possessed, right? There's this phenomenon of people being possessed by spirits, right?
And Christianity comes along, well, second-time Judaism and then Christianity come along with a
different interpretation of that same phenomenon. Yeah, right. Right. And so we've talked about that
before, so that was just sort of a quick review, but sort of a related element of this now
that we see play out in a lot of stories about saints.
has one of its points of origin at least in a text called the Testament of Solomon.
And we should probably say right out of the outset, we're not saying this is some kind
of canonical scriptural text.
We're not saying that anyone should regard this as anything but a really interesting
text about some weird stuff.
Yes.
We've talked.
before about how I'm sure we've talked before on this podcast about how right in the east
there were three categories of books right that there were books to be read in the churches which
is what we would call canonical there are books to be read in the home right and then there are
books not to be read because they're like heretical right yeah and this is kind of on the it's
someone on the edge of the things you can read at home kind of text right so so yes so that's
That's what I was going to say.
So some of the text we talked about.
about on this show, like for Ezra or the first book of Enoch, and those kind of things are sort
of on the borderline of what's red in the church and what's in the home because some churches
view them as canonical and some don't, right? So kind of on that borderline, the testimony of Solomon
and that we're about to talk about is on the borderline of red in the home and not red at all.
Alright, so yeah.
Right. It's not a recommendation. It's it's it's it's we should take this as a really interesting story that reflects certain
motifs
That we find yeah, right. There's a motif. We're gonna run through this book quickly to highlight a single motif within the book and
Then talk about how that motif plays out
Within the Orthodox tradition. We are not saying that this text is in any way a part of the Orthodox tradition. Yep
83 disc...
now finished. Okay. Delete that angry email you are working on. Yes. Yes. So this text also has
just last Sunday we read once again we read it a lot but this time we read it from St. Luke's
Gospel, the story of Legion running around in the tombs. Right? So demon possessed man is where
He's out in a graveyard. He's out in the ruins. That's where the demons are.
are. This text is the other place where Legion shows up. So what we'll get to that in a minute.
So the testimony of Solomon is a text that is probably, I mean, again, journal articles,
dissertations. So we argue about it. But pretty much everybody agrees that this is late for
century, early second century in air quotes, Christian text.
And by Christian, it just means this person is aware of Christianity.
Right. It's not saying this person is Christian in any kind of apostolic sense.
It will get to why here in a minute. But what this is doing is it's taking the story of Solomon
from the Old Testament and then interpolating with it a lot of Greek and Jewish magic,
Like literal magic, right?
Tradition.
and superstitions and that kind of thing, right?
So there's a lot of pagan stuff in here,
is the short way of saying that.
So in this book,
at the beginning of the book,
this angel shows up and gives Solomon
this magic ring with a pentagram on it.
Already, I know, we're not endorsing this, okay.
And what this ring allows Solomon to do
is enslave demons.
F
one is. It is the one ring to roll them off. Yeah. So you could use this ring to enslave demons.
And so he slaves a couple of demons. He ends up enslaveing
beelsable. Right. Who's bail? Who's the devil? Who's the prince of demons, right? Lord of the
flies. Yeah. He ends up, well, no, this is beelsable. This is the original title. Not
Oh, excuse me. Not be making fun of him version.
Okay, so
but because
Now he's got like the demon boss, so now he's kind of got all of them now that are on the payroll
working for him subcontractors as it were. So wow okay. Solomon now most of the text of the book
is then Solomon sort of having chit chats with all of these different demons and these demons
are mostly less than impressive. These are kind of like the Bob Larson demons if you've ever watched.
him exercise demons from middle class housewives as his want.
The demon of sore throats the demons.
There's literally a demon of like sore throats who he talks to
and he would then ask them like, hey, what's what what do we do to ward you off
demon of sore throats and the demon of sore throats is like, well you write this
Greek word on a leaf that you put in
in a pile of leaves and then I won't be able to come and give you a sore throat.
So that's the level of this text.
Yeah.
Not super worthwhile.
So it's a lot of folk remedies and magic and this kind of thing, right?
So there's a couple other interesting little bits.
So he catches Legion in a bag out of the desert.
This one does.
Yeah.
he explains
What the whole my name is Legion thing means because he says it's because he's got a bunch of other demons who are like his boys who he brings with him every place.
So it's like the Roman army unit is what he's yeah, yeah, and he's described as being lion shaped, which is presumably because of the lion banners that the Roman legions used.
And then there's this bit. This is why they say whoever wrote this or whoever edited it at some point had some knowledge of Christianity.
is because Solomon asked Legion like, well, who's the angel who wards you off, right? His usual thing.
And Legion says, oh, there's no angel that can warn me or to be off. Only one who will come and will suffer many things.
Obviously talking about Christ. Right. So he's obviously sort of like, quote unquote, predicting the story that we read in St. Luke's Gospel. Right.
So whoever it was was familiar with Christianity even though he was into other all this other wonky.
Yeah, stuff, folk remedies.
And so Solomon uses some of these enslaved demons to build the temple for him because
you got to lift all those heavy stones and stuff.
You know, and so there's sort of an ancient aliens element, element to this.
We're like, who could have possibly built that?
It wasn't the demons.
Yeah, not saying it was aliens, but it was demons.
Yeah.
and he at one point he used to eat.
He's trying to get one of the pillars for the temple and for some reason it's at the bottom of the Red Sea. It's not quite explained.
So when he pulls it out of the Red Sea magically, he also releases this ancient Egyptian demon that was trapped down there.
At the bottom of the Red Sea, who was the one who gave the magicians an Egypt their powers and who got stuck there when Pharaoh and his armies got drowned.
So Solomon sort of enslaved him to
and makes him install the pillar. But so anyway, right, and I'm making light of all this on purpose,
because it's weird and goofy, right? And not to be taken super seriously. But at the end,
Solomon meets a woman. So he would come full circle back to Lilith being his wife.
meets this woman and really wants to live.
with her. The text is kind of explicit on this point. It's not like he fell in love with
her. He wants to lie with her. So yeah, makes her one of his wives. And then because of
sort of his lust, he loses all of his demon controlling powers. Yep. So the end of the
book is sort of this cautionary tale, right?
like the end of Johnny Cash's deal is gone where he sort of turns to the camera
and breaks the fourth wall and says, hey, don't do what I did and
let your lust make you lose your demon controlling powers
Wow
So again, we're not endorsing a recommending really this text, but but this is one of the first incidents we have of this motif of
of a holy person.
because of their personal holiness, being able to command or control demons.
Yeah, right. I found recently this icon of St. John of Novgorod,
who is a 12th century Russian bishop. And the icon is of him riding
what looks like a like a Pegasus a winged horse, except you look closely at it.
like it's a serpentine winged horse.
It has like claws and a pointy dragon tail.
And...
And it turns out that the story is that while he was praying that this demon wouldn't leave
him alone, and so he turned around and then he forced the demon to become this winged
horse thing to take him on a date to pilgrimage to Jerusalem and back to where he was in
Novgorod.
So I guess one of those kind of things is like stop a demon.
Okay, well, you're working for me now for at least a little while.
Right, right.
And there are stories of like a monk who forced a demon to sing one of the hymns of paradise.
the whole thing we talked about
last year with St. Nicholas and Slaving, Krampus, or Schwarz-Sopiette, or...
Bill Schnickle.
Yeah.
All of these kind of things.
And like with Solomon in this river,
while he's sort of holy, he has this ability,
as soon as he becomes lustful and gives into sin, he loses it.
Yeah.
Right. So this is because of personal highs.
And this is really, ultimately, this whole motif is flowing out of what we see back in Genesis.
we see back in Genesis.
four. When Cain is angry at his brother and God comes to him and says,
sin is crouching at your door like this demon. It wants to master you. You must
master it. Right. Right. And so what we're seeing in the lives of these saints,
what this is about is not about like, hey, you can make demons do tricks. Right.
Like it's about the fact that because of their holiness and their way of life and
having dry.
close to Christ and being conformed to the image of Christ, they now have mastery over the power of
darkness, rather than the powers of darkness having mastery over them. So this is the inversion of
demonic possession. Hmm, possessing demons rather than being possessed by them. Right. Right.
Yeah. Wow. Yeah. Right. Yeah. I mean, it's interesting that this whole episode is kind of about
that Giants on-
level two. Again, it's not about like told people. It's not about tall people. Yeah, because,
yeah, because when, when, when the demons master you, you become less human and more like a beast,
more like a monster. Right. And when you become like Christ, you don't just become like God.
You do become like God because Christ is God, but you also become more human because Christ is
both where we see who God is.
and where we see what a human person is.
Yeah.
Yeah, you know, and there was one thing,
you know, when I was, you know, trying to connect
with some of the research for this episode,
one of the things I ran across was this legendary account
about Kane getting killed, right?
I mean, because the biblical text does not mention
Kane's actual death, but it does mention Lamek,
you know, who is his descendant,
either bragging about that he has killed people
or apparently in some...
some readings of the text, it's that he's saying he's super prone to violence.
Like he's boasting that he's ready to kill people, including like, you know, a boy.
But either way, there's this legend about Lemic hunting out in the woods along with his
son, Tublecane, and that they see like a rustling in the bushes and it looks like an animal
so so Lemic shoots him with an arrow and it turns out that it's keen and the reason why
they didn't realize that it was Canis because he looked bestial. They looked like a beast.
So there's this theme of human beings becoming bestial, as they get demonized, as they become sinful.
So it's interesting just how fructally this plays out across cultures, across legends,
across time, across geography, it's crazy. Right, yeah. And so
So, to reiterate some up when we talk about giants as giants or any of the things we talked
about tonight, giants are at the far end of that spectrum.
It's not just tall people, it's not people who are born tall, it's not a genetic thing.
It is people who have through the conduct of their life, through the rituals they have
participated in through the worship and relationships and fellowship they've...
formed with demons, become demonized to the extreme. Right? They are at the far other extreme
from the saints who have become like Christ. Right? They represent the far negative end
of human possibility, right? Of what it is to cease being human, become inhuman, to become
a monster, as opposed to becoming more human and being formed to the likeness of Christ.
Yeah, yeah.
Okay, well, we're going to give our final thoughts.
So, I mean, I think the bit that really hit me the most in this episode was the thing about the vrikola,
as you know, Greek vampire slash zombie slash werewolves.
And the reason why it hit me is not because, like, monster stuff is cool or whatever, or like,
Wow, look at those backwards mid 19th century Greeks who believe in this stuff.
But rather that number one, it's taking very seriously this reality of the interaction
of the spiritual with the material, the immaterial with the material.
It takes it very, very seriously.
I mean, this is from a manual for priests.
This is not, you know, a book of legends or whatever.
But also the thing about it that really struck me, and this is where I think it comes home
for all of us, right?
again the point of everything that we
doing this podcast is actually to make our spiritual lives better, to, you know, to be better
at this thing called Christianity. It's interesting. Number one, first it condemns people who,
uh, their approach to human beings who are monstrous is to burn their bodies, literally
dig them up and burn them. And it condemns that. It says, don't do that. In fact, people
I thought it would do that should be true.
murderers, you know, that they're excommunicated for years, right? And then, and then it says,
what should have been done or what should be done is that there's this needs to be this cleansing
done with holy water, with prayers of exorcism, with the divine liturgy. Notice the divine liturgy
being used to fight against demons, with praying for that person's soul with Koli Vah, you know, so
so that there's the
There's the memorial prayers that are prayed for them.
And this is because this is a person who has died and so he doesn't have possession of
his mortal body anymore so he can't repent.
And so the church engages in acts of repentance on his behalf in hopes that God will grant
mercy to him.
And so on the one hand, this is a pretty clear model based on, you know,
uncontestable Orthodox tradition about how to deal with demonic presence and how to deal with,
how to pray for people who are departed, especially those who are departed and lived very sinful lives.
But on the other hand, we can also
analogize this even to our day-to-day life. So there's a big temptation in our time,
especially in our time to look at people who are
are not just, you know, okay, so people we disagree with, but let's just go and say people
who we regard as super evil, okay? Now in many cases they're not, where they're just
people we disagree with, okay? But let's just go ahead and say these, you know, people
are super evil, right? That really are people who are super evil. What are we supposed to
do with such people? Well, the way that the world wants us to deal with them right now
is to burn them, whether metaphorically or what...
whatever, that's what the world says, destroy them. They must be destroyed. These are evil,
subversive, horrible, destructive people. They must be destroyed, right? Whereas this instruction,
this normal canon says that the way you're supposed to deal with people who, again, admitting that they are monstrous, understanding that they are monstrous, right?
is actually through spiritual acts of mercy.
that that's the way to deal with them, to try to get the demon to go out.
Because even if someone really has descended into evil, it's because there's a demonic
presence there.
You know, that's what's going on.
A human being who is acting in a truly evil manner is a slave.
They've enslaved themselves.
Okay, it's not like they're not culpable, but they're a slave.
And what we want is to free them from slavery.
And so that's the approach.
Now a lot of the time, like I said.
people are not actually evil, we just disagree with them and we're letting our passions take over
and we're seeing them as monsters even though they aren't. But even if they really are,
right, what does Christ say to do with our enemies? Love them. He says to love our enemies.
That's what he says to do. It's very, very clear, right? We're not called to burn them and to
destroy them and so forth were called to love.
them. So that's, I mean, that is an amazing takeaway for me in a really unlooked for place, frankly.
I mean, I, you know, despite being really interested in some of this kind of stuff, I have not
ever wondered to myself, wow, I wonder if there's a canonical approach to what you're supposed to do
with vampire hunters and vampires. But surely not sure enough, there is. But it's not just about
vampires and vampire hunters it's it's it's it's simply it's
illustrates foundational clear principles of what it means to live the good Christian life.
What it means to actually be like Christ, to do what is, you know, to follow His commandments,
to obey Him and to live as He told us to live.
Father Stephen?
So dovetailing nicely off of that.
You know that sort of the whole theme of Lord of Spirits, the overarching thing is
as the voice of Steve says in the intro is about trying to reunite our experience of reality,
right?
The spiritual and the material together that have been where they've been pulled apart.
And one of the places where they've been pulled apart and one of the places where I think
least realized they've been pulled apart is in our understanding of our
year of quote unquote morality. We have in addition to separating all the other things we've
talked about on the show separating, we separate sort of religious acts from other acts, right?
So you know, probably most of our listeners and even a lot of people who aren't listeners
would say that, well yeah, if you go and participate in a pagan ritual or...
some kind of ritual of another religion, some idolatrous ritual, if you eat meat-sacrifice titles,
that yeah, that would be participating in some kind of demonic activity, right? Yeah.
But when it comes to sort of our day-to-day decisions about whether or not to lie,
whether or not to cheat, whether or not to take something, whether or not to show mercy,
whether or not to forgive.
We tend to treat those in this other way, this very material way of morality,
where as Christians at least, most people would say, oh, well, there's these rules.
God has these rules. If you follow those rules, you're a good moral person. If you break those
rules, you're a bad person. But this is a question of God's judgment of your behavior.
There's nothing particularly demonic or angelic or spiritual about it.
hopefully
As I said that, at least our Orthodox listeners were saying,
well, we'll wait a minute, right?
We have an understanding of theosis.
We have an understanding that when we quote unquote,
do good in a positive sense,
we're not really doing good things independently,
but we're participating in the work that God is doing in the world.
We're participating in God's activity in the world.
And that's why it's transformative of us.
It isn't this sort of separate thing that God kind of judges
from afar.
work, we're actually working. And the reason God can call any work we do good is because it's actually his work that he's doing through us, right, that it's not coming from us ourselves. But this has a coordinate on the other side.
That that means when we sin, when we do evil, it's not just that we broke a rule, but that we are participating in in something demonic.
Because the truth is
everything we do is on a continuum. When we come and celebrate the Eucharist together,
as a parish family, and when you gather around with your immediate family at the dinner table
and pray and eat a meal together, those are not two different things. Those are two things
that are on a continuum.
The Eucharist obviously is at the very top, right?
The very top.
top of that continuum. But the fellowship you share in the bread you break with friends
is on that continuum. It is doing to a lesser degree in a smaller way what the Eucharist
is doing to the nth degree. And so when you give a cup of water to someone in need, right,
It's not that oh well rationally this person's in the image of Christ and the rule is...
I should treat other people as I would treat Christ, doing that is on the same continuum as serving Christ.
Everything we do and vice versa. I think there are very few people listening. I hope there's
no one listening to this who has ever seriously contemplated sacrificing an infant to a pagan
God in order to receive powers.
I hope there's nobody who's even given that a moment's thought.
Right?
But every time we participate in evil, every time we ignore it, every time we excuse it,
every time we participate in it, every time we do it ourselves, right?
We are performing actions that are on a continuum with that horror.
We are on a continuum with that kind of nightmare.
Right and and you see this even in what we talked about tonight
Right where will fism doesn't start with that
Where will fism ends with that where will fism starts with being greedy and gluttonous
With always wanting more with being ravenous with wanting to devour and
Devouring other people metaphorically
Long time before you get to literally
But those aren't two different things those are on a continuum
are on a continuum. And so we need to take every choice we make and how we live and what
we do and what we pursue very seriously. There isn't neutral. There isn't, well, I
didn't do anything all that significant either way. All of these things are on one continuum
or the other. All of these things are leading us closer to Christ and becoming more human
and more like God or they're leading us in the opposite direction.
to become less human and more bestial and more of a monster.
As you pointed out, it's never too late,
even if you're dead, even if you're demon possessed corpse.
The church presents that there is hope for you in Christ.
But we need to reconsider the value
of our everyday morality and actions
and the kind or unkind words we share with people,
even those smallest things.
because everything starts small and then gets bigger.
And every footstep we take leads us down one road or the other.
Well, thank you very much for that.
Well, that is our show for today.
Thank you very much, everyone, for listening.
If you didn't get a chance to call in during the live broadcast,
we'd love to hear from you either via email at LordofSpirits at
AncientFate.com.
You can message us also at our Lord of Spirits podcast Facebook page.
We do read everything, but we can't respond to every-
We do save some of it for possible use in future episodes.
Join us for our live broadcasts on the second and fourth Thursdays of the month at 7 PM Eastern 4 PM Pacific.
And if you are on Facebook, you can like our page, join our discussion group,
leave reviews and ratings everywhere, but most importantly, share this show with a friend whom you know is going to love it,
and don't forget to buy our books, please, thank you.
And if you enjoyed hearing me uninterrupted this evening, that's thanks to Ancient Faith,
paying for my new internet connection.
If you really appreciate it, go throw them a few shackles to keep it going.
It's at ancientfaith.com's last support.
Thank you very much everyone. Good night, and God bless you and be with you always.
You've been listening to the Lord of Spirits with Orthodox Christian priests,
Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung, a list
inner-supported presentation of ancient faith radio.
And I be held, and I heard the voice of many angels
round about the throne and the beasts and the elders.
And the number of them was 10,000 times 10,000
than thousands of thousands,
saying with a loud voice, worthy is the land
that was slain to receive power and riches and wisdom
and strength and honor and glory and blessing.
Revelation, chapter 5, verses 11 through 12.
The kingdom is characterized by humility and gentleness of heart.
It is the combination of these two qualities that constitutes the perfection of the