Sir, to be integrated, our body-minded spirit.
You can find Garden in the East and much more at store.inchantfaith.com.
Again, that is store.inchantfaith.com.
Glory to Jesus Christ, glory forever.
You're listening to ancientfaithradio.com.
He will be a staff for the righteous with which for them to stand and not to fall.
And he will be the light of the nations and the hope of those whose hearts are troubled.
All who dwell on the earth will fall down and worship him.
And they will praise and bless and celebrate with song the Lord of Spirits.
1st denoc, chapter 48, verses 4 through 5.
The modern world doesn't acknowledge but is nevertheless haunted by spirits, angels, demons, and saints.
In our time, many year into break free of the prison of a flat, secular materialism,
to see and to know reality as it truly is.
What is this spiritual reality like?
How do we engage with it well?
How do we permeate everyday life with spiritual presence?
Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew Stephen Damick, and Father Stephen De Young
post this live Colin show focused on enchantment in creation.
The union of the scene and unseen as made by God and experienced by mankind throughout history.
Welcome to the Lord of Spirits.
Welcome back to the Lord of Spirits podcast.
My co-host, Father Stephen De Young is with me from Lafayette, Louisiana.
And I am Father Andrew Stephen Damick in a Mayas, Pennsylvania.
If you're listening to us live, you can call in at 855 AF radio.
That's 855-237-2346.
And Matyska Trudy will be taking your calls tonight.
And we'll get to your calls in the second part of today's show.
So Lord of Spirits is brought to you by our listeners.
We have help from St. Athanasius Academy of Orthodox Theology.
St. Athanasius is an online academy for kindergarten through 12th grade,
offering live classrooms and core subjects, foreign languages,
various electives, and Orthodox studies.
To learn more about St. Athanasius Academy,
please visit www.saot.edu.
And let me add, I want to assure everyone, I talk to Deacon Adam
over at the St. Athanasius Academy.
And he assured me that when you go and you take courses from them,
he is not going to use your tuition money to launch himself into space.
Hey, so you don't have to worry about that.
Big bonus.
Yeah, I mean, that's what I'm looking for in online education
for my children.
So yeah, you don't want people just using that money to go to space.
Right, right, right.
So we know that when we titled this episode, Apocalypse Now and Then,
a lot of people got excited that we were going to talk about the end of the world.
We know it.
And you know, it's great.
It starts with an earthquake, birds, snakes, airplanes.
But that's not actually what this episode is about.
Apocalypse isn't actually just a word that means the end of the world.
It turns out to be a biblical genre.
But before we get to that, and you know, we always take a while to get where we're going,
we want to back up to our previous episode on the news because this episode is its sequel.
And we got a lot of questions about thoughts from our last episode.
And the one that kept coming up was this one.
Does the idea that all of our thoughts coming from outside mean that every single thing
we think is being whispered to us by God, an angel, or a demon?
So Father Stephen, is that what we met?
No.
Yes.
And I mean, no.
No, yes, right.
No, not yet.
Yeah, you're confusing everyone.
Okay.
No, comma.
Celebratory.
Yes.
Okay.
There we go.
Yeah.
For the transcript.
Right.
Yes.
And everyone.
Yeah.
So the stuff we were talking about last time was a little bit complicated, maybe, a little
bit in depth.
So now we're going to just throw everyone in the deep end at the beginning of this episode.
As we sort of clarify where we ended up last time, you know, when you said complicated,
I started forming an Avril Lavigne related joke in my head, but just didn't quite get
there.
Right.
Like the original Avril Lavigne or the before she was required to act her Avril Lavigne
who has taken her place.
Yeah.
We should have a doppelganger episode there we go.
So to start with, and believe it or not, this is hopefully going to help clarify what we
were talking about last time with the news, we're going to start by talking about pre-reflective
consciousness.
When I woke up this morning, I said to myself, today, I want to talk about pre-reflective
consciousness, but then you had already reflected.
And so it was, it was all over so long.
Yeah.
Right.
So what does that mean for those of us who are not, you know, reading the latest in psychological,
I don't even know the right noun for this, but yes, existential psychology and phenomenology.
Yeah.
Correct.
Right.
So, right.
So this is another way of talking about what we were talking about last time with the
news in terms of a point of attention, right?
And the news is a sensory organ, and a point of attention or a point of focus.
But the term pre-reflective consciousness is talking about, it's pre-reflective because
it's sort of this level of consciousness before you get to thoughts.
That's the pre-reflective.
Right.
So you get to the actual thoughts before you get to the stream of consciousness.
Yeah.
This sort of kind of direct apprehension, you know, where you don't have to think about
something in order to get it.
You just sort of receive it.
Yeah.
All of a sudden, I was about to use the term fundamental a perception that I realized that
would not help, but too late, I already got it.
Come on.
I'm barely getting this.
Yeah.
Right.
So this is going back to that stream of consciousness is not you, right?
And so when we talk about pre-reflective consciousness, we mean that this point of attention is back
before that, which the important part of that is that that means you can focus it on
or your mind can look at or your mind can consider whatever language you want to use for this,
right?
Contemplate.
Yourself.
Right.
You can contemplate yourself.
And so that means the news, this kind of consciousness we're talking about has to be sort
of before yourself so that you can look at and think about yourself as an object and
come to know yourself, right?
So it's possible to live in an unreflective way and not know yourself or not know yourself
very well, right?
And this is something that's sort of a constant in both ancient philosophical literature and
ancient Christian literature is the idea of coming to know oneself, that that's the beginning
of knowledge, right?
It's to come to know your own soul and your own self.
And so the news has, again, has to be prior to that.
It can't be, when we say, I am thinking, right?
The eye is ourself.
So that means we're starting with ourself, we're not thinking about ourself, right?
And then we're talking about, you know, something then related to ourself.
And so when we talk about the news, this is back behind our sense of ourself.
Yes.
So like, for instance, you know, I've had a lot of pastoral conversations in which I might
say something like, like, listen to your own thoughts.
So if you're listening to your thoughts, you're observing your thoughts, whatever, you
aren't, you know, your thoughts aren't thinking, aren't thinking your thoughts, you're thinking
your thoughts.
There's a you that can, that can observe the thoughts, you know, that can actually kind of,
it's not dissociative exactly, but, but you realize that they are not, they are not you,
you know, I think that's, that's, that's my understanding of what we're talking about
now.
Right.
And, and, and so then you can also think about you, you can think about yourself, yeah,
right?
And to use an analogy, right, if, if you have a weird feeling in your gut, right?
You can sit there and think about what is going on in my gut, right?
And try to ponder what's happening.
This is the same kind of thing, but in your mind or in your soul.
Yeah, right, that you can sit, what is going on in my mind, right?
What is going on in my soul, because there's, there's this, there's this pre-reflective
other consciousness, the news is separate.
And this is, this is also what's being talked about.
We had a call last time where we got into a little bit, whether the spirit and the soul
are different things, and we talked about how some of the fathers, they're sort of used
as being the same thing, just referring to the immaterial part of a person.
And then other fathers, there seems to be a distinction.
And so when there's a distinction, the spirit is referring to this, to the news, to the
noetic part of a human person, right?
Yeah, because sometimes spirit and soul are used as basically synonyms.
Right.
Yeah.
It's just all, it's just all lumped together.
Right.
Because some of the fathers talk about body and soul, some talk about body, soul and spirit
as three, you know, separate things.
Yeah.
And, you know, I think it's, well, number one, it's important to realize that even though
we're talking about the stuff in this way, obviously we're not necessarily using strictly
biblical terminology because the Bible doesn't talk in this way, but it does, it does speak
in a way that is evincing the same, the same things we're discussing.
So for instance, in the Psalms where the writer addresses his own soul, right, oh, my soul,
my soul, you know, and I mean, we have, you know, we have lots of church hymns like
that, you know, the big one from the great canon of St. Andrew of Crete, the Kentucky
and my soul, my soul arise, you know, or, you know, in the Psalms, bless the Lord, oh,
my soul, right?
And, you know, so much of what we talk about in the show is about kind of saying, okay,
what if what's in the scripture is not always a metaphor like we seem to so often take
it as being, you know, what if you actually can talk to your soul?
What if you can observe your soul?
You know, what if it's not quite the same thing as the you, right?
And of course, that means that, you know, Descartes' famous dictum, Kajito ergo sum, I think
therefore am, is actually wrong because you're not your thoughts, you're not your thoughts
and thinking is not what makes you, you but by the way, do you know how he died?
I do not remember how he died.
He was trampled by a horse.
Wow.
It is true.
And that is the origin of the saying never put Descartes before the horse.
Oh, man, I felt like I was walking into something.
You were.
It was a trap.
But that's okay.
I'm going to look up on Wikipedia to find out how he really did die.
He did really die.
He was really good.
He really did.
Oh, man.
Well, okay, so at least it is a well-founded joke then.
Yeah.
Irony.
But right.
And yeah, as you said, you know, and this is something that the church fathers said very
quickly.
Right.
They said, you know, in order to, in our Greek language, describe what's going on in the
scriptures.
We sometimes have to use terms that are not themselves in the scriptures.
Yeah.
Right.
And that doesn't mean you're importing theology.
They're importing philosophy that's foreign to Christianity, just because those terms are
used right in philosophy, per se.
This is one of the common misconceptions about the church fathers by a lot of our friends.
Yeah.
Mostly our non-orthodox friends, but even some of our orthodox friends that they just
brought in all of this Greek philosophy rather than just, you know, they're using
the Greek language.
Yeah.
There's, I mean, for those who have that, for those who are receiving that thought, there
is a wonderful book called Christianity and Classical Culture by Yaroslav Pelikan, which
addresses this very directly.
And actually he shows how the church fathers take Greek terminology, but then put different
meanings into it.
They're not just simply importing philosophical concepts.
They're just using the Greek language and giving new meanings to the words that they're
making use of.
So there is, you know, it's a wonderful book.
And of course, Pelikan is an unparalleled historian of Christianity.
So I do recommend it.
Yes.
It is a good book.
The key importance, not just for understanding the hymns that you mentioned, for which this
understanding is helpful.
But also this is important that the news, in some sense, is before the self is critically
important to our understanding of how humanity has free will.
The way Father Duma True Staneloi, whose name I always mispronounce, describes this is
that humanity is in some sense absolute, meaning not determined by his physical and material
circumstances, that we're able to, because we're able to look at our thoughts from behind
our thoughts, look at ourself from behind ourself, that gives us the freedom to comport
ourself.
We can change reality with our will, right?
We can't sort of reach out and bend, there's the brute facticity of reality, but we can
choose how we are going to comport ourselves to reality, how we're going to receive what
comes into our life and our mind, right?
We have freedom in that because of this distinction, because of this separation.
Yeah, because if you are your thoughts, then that means you are at their mercy.
You know, you're simply at their mercy and attempting to, you know, there's been many
times I've had personal conversations with people where it's like, I keep having this thought
and I just can't make it go away, and you know, I feel like something is wrong with me.
You know, if you are your thoughts, then the answer to that is yes, there's something
wrong with you, right?
I mean, what other possible conclusion could you come to?
And then people find themselves helpless to just make a thought go away.
You can't just will a thought to go away unless you, you know, if you realize that you
are not your thoughts, then you can actually begin to develop the discipline to do things
to your thoughts.
But you're still going to have thoughts that come unbidden, but that doesn't mean that
there's something fundamentally flawed, you know, you know, I mean, I can't peer into the
mind of Christ, but Christ himself was tempted, right?
But he is not his temptations, obviously, you know, because he did not sin.
So hopefully I'm not getting across any crystallological lines.
I should not by saying that, but I think that seems pretty clear from the gospels.
That's what happened.
So yeah, free, you know, free will is kind of based, not kind of free will is based in
this, that you're not your thoughts, you know, you can observe your own thoughts, you
can do things with your thoughts, you can reject the thoughts, you can accept some thoughts.
It's, this is a thing, and it's a very freeing thing.
I think, I think we mentioned that last time.
It's just the experience of freedom comes, I think, from, from realizing that.
Right.
And if you look at the other side, right, if your brain is just sort of a chemical machine
that generates your thoughts, right, and then those generated thoughts in your stream
of consciousness, are you, right, then, then, you know, Sam Harris is right and free will
disappears.
Yeah.
And the person who has the thought that he should kill someone or rob someone or right,
there's no free will involved.
It's just purely mechanical.
Yeah.
And how can you, how can you ultimately blame someone then who just simply obeys their
thoughts?
Right.
You know?
Yeah.
So, yeah.
So, okay.
So, we have talked about where thoughts come from, that they come from outside.
So let's unpack that a little bit more.
I mean, we talked last time about the various ways of knowing other than the news, right?
Like there's, you know, technique, which is the know how there's a piece to me, which
is, you know, sort of observational mathematical scientific knowledge.
Yeah.
There's, there's that kind of stuff, right?
And you know, this, of course, is, is, and the idea of course, the news as a sensory
organ, receiving thoughts and images from outside, that's contrary to solipsism, we're
not just brains and a vat, you know, there, there is actual contact with the outside going
on in your, in your mind.
But I think a lot of our problem is that we tend to reduce knowledge to language, right?
And then this is what we think of as thoughts, is a kind of internal monologue, like the things
that are being said in my head.
But actually, you know, an interesting thing about that is, I occasionally see people
like posting on social media, they're surprised that people experience an internal monologue because
they'll say things like, I don't have an internal monologue, that's not the way that I think.
You know, I don't think in words like that.
And that's interesting to me.
That seems to be an indication that that person has somehow, just as approaching it from
a different angle.
I don't know what that's like.
I do have an internal monologue, there are words that roll through my head all the time.
I'm a very word oriented person.
But, but, you know, can we reduce thoughts to just words?
I clearly not.
So you're more like the theatrical cut of Blade Runner rather than the director's cut of
Blade Runner with the monologue coming in in the background, okay?
Right.
Well, yeah, and, and, you know, we spent most of the, because of course, the episode is
about the news.
So we spent most of the episode not talking about the news, just like we're spending most
of this episode not talking about apocalyptic, but the, we'll get there.
I think some folks, you know, we got to the news and, and, and settled there, right?
The other four ways of knowing that we talked about are also ways that thoughts come into
your, yes, your mind, right?
They're just not always turned into language, right?
So when you're, if you're out wrenching on your car, and you know what you're doing, right?
And there's, there's technique involved, but there is a knowledge of this is, oh, here's
the problem.
This is what I need to do, right?
Right.
That's not an angel of car repair, right, or the ghosts, the ghosts of click and clack coming
to help you.
Unfortunately.
So you're saying that as I'm looking at my bookcase right now, there's not an angel there
sending pictures of my bookcase into my brain.
No.
That's your eyeball.
Yeah.
Right.
So these things come in.
We just, we don't always reduce them to language.
But what, what we're, when we call something a thought, when we talk about thought, like you
were saying, we're thinking about that internal monologue, right?
Yeah.
Uh, to give it a, give an example, right, when, when you look with your eyes and, and I
look at the tree out the window, right, the, the image of the tree is coming into my mind
through my eyeballs, right?
Right.
But I can also then turn that into language, right, the word tree, right?
But when I do that, the experience of me standing in front of a tree, touching a tree,
looking at a tree, smelling a tree is very different than having the word tree in my
brain.
Right.
This is what we mean when we say reducing it to language.
Yeah.
Right.
This reduction has happened.
It's been boiled down, right?
And most of the content has been lost in favor of this word.
And so the same thing happens, the same thing happens with the news, right, that you can
have things coming through the news, not at the level of sort of discursive language,
right?
That's feelings, emotions, impressions, right?
You feel sad.
You could put that into words, I am sad.
But the words I am sad do not really convey the fullness of what you experience when you
are sad.
Right.
At best, it can function as a kind of shorthand, you know, you can invoke the idea of sadness
and someone else by saying it, but even then there's kind of different kind, you know,
and of course language tries to deal with the complications.
You can see a tree, you can say okay, it's an oak tree or it's a maple tree or it's
a Japanese, you know, maple or something like that.
These are all different looking trees, but the Japanese maple that's in my neighbor's
backyard does not look like the one in my front yard and it is an objectively different
experience to see those two trees, you know, the one I have is much younger and smaller
and there's as big and lovely, you know, so even though language can work on those
complications and try to become more precise, it's still, it's still, you know, I could,
I could qualify it, it's a small Japanese, oh, okay, it's a small one, but still the
specific one in my yard, you can't, you could not, you could never describe it with language
in such a way that someone would get the exact experience of being there.
Right.
At best, at best, you can invoke a memory.
Yeah.
Right.
Of a similar experience.
Do you remember when, yeah, do you remember when you were there?
You know, even the memory of the same tree, like if someone saw the tree before I pruned
it, that would not be the same thing as it is today, you know, and that's, that we consider
someone to be a great writer when they are able to evoke those actual experiences in
us in the form of memory through the use of language, but we more commonly are doing it
the other way.
Yeah.
We're taking the experience of boiling it down and the same is true, right?
I was just talking about a tree, but the same is true when we're talking about the news
with, for example, the word God, or even the name, right, Jesus Christ.
It's a very different thing, the word, and we can use it very discursively, right, the
sort of bad kind of theology, which is, you know, like putting together tinker toys, right?
Yeah.
You, you know, just get the pieces and put the pieces together to construct something.
Right.
I was supposed to coming to know Jesus Christ.
Yeah.
It's a very different thing.
Right.
Like, you can see, I mean, I see this all the time on the internet, people arguing Christology
and the way that they argue makes me really wonder whether they know the person they're
talking about, you know, it's just, yeah, yeah, even if what they're saying is correct
factually, you know, it's still not the same thing as the one that they're talking about.
Yeah.
So, I mean, it kind of raises the question, right, if there's this knowledge that's beyond
language, and the, for instance, an example might be that, you know, it's sort of a
noetic example is sometimes people, you might go somewhere and you have a feeling like something
is just wrong.
Like, it feels sort of spiritually wrong or spiritually right, you know, that there's
that sense, but it's not, it's not something that's just pure, that you can get by observation
alone, right?
So this will be an example of the new apprehending spiritual reality, but then that kind of
leads you to the question, you know, like, well, do my atheist friends have spiritual experiences,
right?
Because they would probably say that they don't because they would, especially if they're
really a materialist, a real materialist, they would say that spiritual experience that
there's no such thing as that.
There's only the material senses.
So, you know, but if, if such experiences are just reduced, are reducible to language,
I had a feeling that something was wrong, right?
Well, then you can kind of much more easily kind of explain it away.
And the classic example of that is in a Christmas Carol, when Ebenezer Scrooge, we've all read
it, or at least you've watched some chrome version of it, probably everybody, or a sitcom
episode.
Yeah.
Right.
I mean, this is one of the most reused stories of our time, where he encounters Jacob,
I'm about, I was about to say Bob Marley, but then I remembered it's not, that would
be a much more interesting story in some ways.
Oh, yes, yes, yes, yeah, yeah, anyway, I'm just pushing aside all the jokes.
It just came to Jacob Marley, his former, his former partner.
And you know, he identifies himself as Jacob Marley, and then Ebenezer Scrooge basically
tries to explain him away as being based on whatever he ate last night, right?
So undigested beef, a blot of mustard, you know, essentially he's just, he's saying that
this unmistakably air spiritual experience he's having is just, you know, an indigestion
problem, right?
But he's having the experience, and of course, you know, as the story goes, he eventually
reconciles himself to that fact, you know, and is able to change as a result of that.
But yeah, he's a disbeliever, and he's explaining it away because for him it's reducible to some
kind of physical process, you know, I just ate the wrong thing last night, right?
And we definitely need to get this Christmas visit from Bob Marley's ghost meme going.
Yes, because this can be amazing.
Yes, absolutely.
Get to work people.
Yeah, yeah.
So, yeah, and we've talked about previously on previous episodes about, you know, sort
of the classical four, four ways of interacting with reality that humans have language, our
music and ritual, and we're going to come back to this later in the episode.
But this is, this is important because to mention here, because we as modern Western people
tend to try to reduce all of these just to language.
It's not just our thoughts and experiences that we reduced to language, but it's all of
these things, right?
And so we go and we look at a beautiful icon, but then we're like, okay, well, this represents
this, and that represents that, and we try to break it all down into language.
But even if you write it up really thoroughly and really well, right, and you have all
your citations from art history, right, and you have this whole thing, reading that is
a very different experience than standing in front of the icon.
Yeah, and, you know, people sometimes do the same thing with liturgy, right?
They're like, well, this part means this, or it represents this.
And I mean, like, while that's not entirely wrong, right, it can be problematic when people
like, oh, now I get that this is, this is the thing that that means, you know, and so
it becomes a meaning that you received observationally rather than an experience that you participated
in through ritual, you know, it's, it becomes a spectator sport, so to speak, yeah, yeah.
Or again, again, like, there's, there's a whole history of interpreting the divine liturgy
and other services with these kinds of ways, but they, they're, they're not reducible to
that.
It's not, like, for instance, when, when, you know, the great entrance happens in the
divine liturgy, it's not, you're not supposed to get a meaning from that, you know, you're
supposed to participate in it, you know, yeah, because I mean, you could get a meaning from
that by watching it on a YouTube video, right, and that's also why we shouldn't have our
noses buried in books during liturgical services, right?
I know it's very comfortable for us as modern Western people to try to, again, process
everything as language.
I want to follow along and read what is being sung or read what is being said and try to
just process that mentally in the form of language, right?
But when you do that, you're not participating in ritual, you're participating in a linguistic
exercise, right?
And you can sit at home and read the text of the divine liturgy, but I think we would
all agree that is a very different experience than actually being in and participating in
the divine liturgy, right?
And even though we may feel comfortable doing that, right, it's good to be uncomfortable,
right?
And the same thing's true with music, obviously.
We talked about ritual and iconography or art, but obviously the same is true with music,
right?
There's a big difference between reading a lyric sheet and listening to music, right?
But like these are not the same, the same thing, right?
Unless you're like everybody in the movie Amadeus, and you can just like look at sheet music
and hear it in your head, in this case, go ahead, but I'm not that person, so.
Okay, so, so, you know, we have this problem where we kind of divide this stuff out into,
you know, the physical, the material, the, the, the, the immaterial, the material, you
know, it's, I don't know, as modern Western people, we like to have things categorized.
And the problem when we do that is we tend to, when we divide it up into pieces, then we
just pick the one piece that we prefer and kind of leave the rest aside.
And I think one of the projects that we're trying to pursue on this podcast is to show
that everything really is, is one, you know, there's not natural and supernatural, right?
That's not it.
Like we, there's a little bit of reason why we use the phrase the scene and the unseen
when we're describing what we're doing on this show because, because there's a distinction
there.
There's things you can see and observe with your senses and there's things that you cannot
see with your senses.
But, but natural and supernatural is a different kind of distinction, you know, there's the,
the Cartesian notion of the soul, which is basically that you're this, you are this immaterial
soul that's kind of trapped inside a body, you know, or, or to use the name of a very famous
anime film, Ghost in the Machine, you know, Ghost in the Shell, noob.
Ghost in the Shell.
Oh, that's right.
I have seen that, but I'm sorry, I'm sorry, man, I'm just ashamed of myself now suddenly.
I did like that movie, but it's been a long time since I saw it.
Now, you liked the anime one, just, yes, I have not seen the opera, super problematic live
actual.
I have not seen that one.
No, I have not seen that.
Yeah.
I appreciate, I appreciate the anime film for its aesthetics largely.
I mean, I obviously was not on board with its philosophy.
It was interesting to watch them sort of struggle with a philosophical problem of, you
know, if a person is enough of a machine, can it still hold their soul, right?
Obviously, it's based on this Cartesian idea of the soul, you know, yeah, right?
Right.
So, yeah.
So, in the ancient world, right, there's just creation, there's just the world, the cosmos,
right?
And that includes both material and spiritual realities, right?
Everyone just accepted that.
There are gods, there are spirits, there are, et cetera, et cetera.
They are also in the creation, right?
We don't see them with our eyes, but there are things that we hear with our ears and don't
see with our eyes.
So the idea that there are certain things that we only apprehend with our minds rather
than the other senses kind of made sense, saying, should people, right?
Just like there's a few smell, but can't see or hear, but can't see or hear, but can't
smell.
And so, these are all just different aspects of the one reality.
And then, modernity happens and everything gets lame.
I feel like 19th century, German, we're going to get there.
Theologians are about to be mentioned.
We're going to get there.
We're not even there yet, though.
We're still like the 16th, 16th, 17th century.
Yeah.
So we're building up to them, right?
That is where you get, as you mentioned, the Cartesian idea, right, from Descartes, what's
called Cartesian dualism, the idea that the material realm and the spiritual realm are
separate realms, just that realm language, right?
That they begin to be spoken of as if.
Now, no one's saying these are actually separate, quote, unquote, places, but they're being
spoken of in that way, right, that there is, you know, the human body is the body and
we have access to that in a certain way.
And then the soul is the ghost in the machine.
The soul is, the ghost is there somewhere connected to it in some way, right, it's not entirely
clear.
You can have access to it, really, in the same way.
So you get the beginning of the division, the vision between natural and supernatural,
right?
Right, right.
Supernatural doesn't just mean this is a happening that is outside the things that usually
happen.
Right?
This is miracle.
Yeah.
A very unusual occurrence, right, but supernatural is meaning not material.
It's all the woo woo stuff.
Yeah.
Right.
Angels are supernatural.
Yeah.
God is supernatural.
You know, yeah.
And not true.
Not true.
Yeah.
And then as that develops, we're not even into the 19th century yet, but you get the beginnings
of German idealism and you get a friend, a manual Kant, and you get not only sort of the
taxonomy of these two realms, but there's sort of an iron wall between them now where,
so for Kant, sort of classically, you have the, the new middle realm, that's what he calls
it, right, related to the news, related to the mind, where you have God, the self,
being the soul, the thing in itself, the essences of things, right?
These are all things that can only be known by the mind through what he basically calls
a kind of intuition in religious circles, especially Protestant religious circles.
That's how faith ends up getting kind of defined.
Faith is that sort of intuitive knowledge of those things, of God and of the soul.
And then you have the phenomenal realm, which is all the stuff we know through the senses,
which is all the material stuff, right?
And these are these two separate boxes, and most conservative Western theology ends up
evolving out of this kind of viewpoint, right?
So there's maintained that yes, God exists, the soul exists, the essence, things have
essences, things have natures, things are what they are, but that's something you know
by faith or intuition or through the application of mental categories, that's not something
you know through the senses or through science or through any of those things, right?
So you have these two realms, and so this is how we end up as conservative modern Christians
sort of having this box or the set of brackets where we put all that stuff, all that
numerals stuff, right?
And then the rest of our life, everything outside the brackets, we basically interact
with everything else the same way atheists do.
Because that's all in this just phenomenal material realm, and so then now we get to
our 19th century German friends, friends, though, not really, friends, scouts, they're not
good friends, so they'll like totally invite you to go see a movie and then flake out
and not show up, not text, nothing, that's the kind of friends they are, they just toast
you, yeah, so thank you, they geist you, even there you go, so, and we get, we get to
Hegel, and so what Hegel does essentially is collapse, that idea of a new mental realm,
of a spiritual realm, he collapses, geist and spirit, he just collapses that into the
material world, so what does that mean?
Like how does that play?
So yeah, what that means is that essentially then, right, all of these, everything from
God to spirituality, to the soul, all of these things sort of get reduced to a kind of spiritual
metaphor related to material processes, right?
So you get out of this, and this is what then liberal Western theology evolves from,
so you get like the social gospel and liberation theology, right?
That's all very this worldly focused, all right, so spiritual liberation, what spiritual
liberation really means in this kind of view is the transforming of the material conditions
of your life to give you freedom, right?
That's now spiritual liberation, right?
And so sin gets replaced with tyranny and oppression, right?
Everything gets reduced, so you still have a concept, right?
So for Hegel, God is sort of in the creation evolving and working things out, right, along
with everybody else, right?
And God is just sort of this animating, positive spirit within the cosmos, right?
And so you still use this language to talk about it, and you still see this spiritual
dimension, but the spiritual dimension is now more about feeling and sentiment and solidarity
and kinship than an actual connection to an actually existing creator God, right?
Right.
And so yeah, so that's then, you know, our conservative Western theology comes from sort
of more of the Kantian kind of view and the liberal theology comes out of more the Hegelian
kind of view, and from that comes process theology, all of that, all of our 19th century
German friends.
And so then, you know, the response, right, for people who then reject Christianity
altogether, right?
Then this is how secularism comes about, because then you just rather than collapsing the spiritual
into the physical and the material, you just sort of peel away that layer.
You just rip the spiritual material layer off the top and leave only the physical and
material.
Yeah.
Because if it's really just a metaphor, well, why not have some other metaphor, you know,
if there's not actually a God that you can encounter, why not come up with some other, you
know, way of organizing your values around material flourishing, you know?
And what's interesting about this to me is, like this seems to be the way that public
discourse is just sort of expected to go now, like there's this polite thing that we don't
do, right?
We, I should say there's this thing we politely don't do, which is, you know, you don't
talk about spiritual things in public because, well, that should be either kept private
or it's kind of sort of a joke, you know, that don't, don't talk about that.
I mean, you know, when we were putting our notes together, you gave the example of, you
know, Neil deGrasse Tyson, the, is he an astronomer?
Is that what he is?
Yeah, I think so.
He's an astrophysicist.
Astrophysicist, okay, so I was pretty close.
You know, he made some reference, he used the word God's speed on Twitter and then had to
like apologize for that because, of course, he doesn't actually believe in God, you know,
so you shouldn't say that.
His fellow atheists came after him.
Yeah, right.
It's with her dog pile for God's speed to ask her, yeah, how dare you, yeah, what does
that mean?
You know, on their own, just on rockets.
And I, you know, it's the thing that you're sort of not allowed to say, right?
Like this, we just politely don't do that in public.
And I was thinking about this in contrast to an experience that I have once every week
or so.
So my family, we buy, we get raw milk from a, a men and a night family, about 30 minutes
or so, 35, 40 minutes south of us.
They have a greenhouse and a dairy farm and, you know, they make lots of wonderful things.
And when you go there, though, they will openly and easily talk to you about God and about
the weather, usually in relation, one relation to the other, you know, and it just really
strikes me in how, and it's not like they're not proselytizing or anything like that.
It's just simply their experience of the world and that's how they talk.
That they just don't participate in that polite agreement that everybody else has.
You know, they have no problem saying, you know, God was really good and gave us really
good weather this week, you know, like it's just, it's just something they just sort of
openly do, you know.
So I think about that when I drink my, my men and I milk, right, right.
And even, even, again, we were talking about the brackets, right, even most, most modern
Christians who thoroughly believe in God, right, thoroughly believe, would talk about it
that way comfortably in like mixed company, maybe with their church, right, or with their
church.
Yeah.
Like you're not to do that church, yeah, but not like at the mall, like not like, you
know, talking to a store clerk, you know, yeah.
And so, yeah, so that's sort of ways it all went wrong in the modern period.
And so probably the question we've gotten most often since starting this show has been
like some version of, can we really go back to like, can we like unmodern, like is it possible
to demodern oneself right now?
Do you go back unmodern as a good old English construction?
And I affirm that.
So and, and you know, you can't unlearn there are some things that you can't unsee, right?
So, like you can't sort of, right, reverse things and use the way back machine that way.
Right.
Yeah.
I can't just decide not to be modern, right, yeah.
But then, so what is then sort of the way back into the ground, right, in terms of trying
to come back to something more like that?
And it's not to again, to set the clock back, but it's to, we have to actively work, and
that's what the rest of this episode is going to be about, if to actively work to reintegrate
what's been pulled apart, right, we can't just pretend it was never pulled apart.
Yeah, right, but we can work to bring it back together, right, and so that is the key to that
is understanding that for every spiritual reality, there's a concomitant material reality
and vice versa, right, right, right, these vice versa always, always go together.
Right, and this is at the level of like we've talked about in past episodes,
there being spirits or angelic beings assigned to the elements of the created world.
There's no neutral ground who are participating in their government, that there are spiritual
as connected to every physical reality and physical realities connected to spiritual realities.
Right, and the place where we, so, you know, this is the relationship between, you know,
the mind of the brain or the mind in the heart, right, that, that, you know, we all talk about our heart.
You know, I left my heart in San Francisco, last Christmas, I gave you my heart the very next day,
gave it away. Oh, man.
Right, and, and you know, even when we like use the heart emoji, it doesn't actually look like a
biological human heart, right, unless someone's doing that on purpose as a joke, right?
You don't see like the Vena Kavanaugh's, right? So, you know, we get that when we're talking
about our heart, we're actually talking about a spiritual reality, right, but we're connecting it
in talking about it to this organ, right, and the same thing with the mind and the brain, right,
that, that, you know, yes, you've got this gray mushy thing with electricity firing around in it,
right? And that's not completely unrelated to your mind and your thoughts, right? It's not
ghost in the machine, right? So, when someone vents his spleen then, yes, I knew it. His blood is up.
Yes, yeah, the better one is in Greek when you have compassion, you spleen at someone. That's great.
That's literally what it means. So, in the Gospels, Christ literally spleens at like sick people,
is what the Greek literally says. Wow, standing here beside myself. Yes, so,
right, but so these aren't, these aren't disassociated, right? Yeah, these aren't disassociated. And
one of the key, probably the key place, the key place, this is setting up what we're going to be
talking about the rest of the episode, the key place where we do this and we do this ritually is in
the idea of sacrament or the mysteries of the church. Exactly, right? Where you have material
reality and a spiritual reality permeating each other, right? Whether it's water or a male and a
female human or a or bread and wine, right? There's a divided spiritual reality that comes to permeate
those material things, right? Right. Right. All right. Well, on that note, we're going to be back in
just a moment and we're going to start talking about apocalypse as a genre within scripture,
but first we're going to take your calls, but before that we're going to take a break. We'll be right
back. Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung will be back in a moment to take
your calls on the next part of the Lord of Spirits. Give them a call at 855-237-2346. That's 855-AF
Radio. Big in Heaven, a collection of short stories available now on the Ancient Faith Bookstore.
Sometimes poignant, sometimes funny, sometimes heartbreaking, sometimes convicting.
These stories of life in an inner-city immigrant Orthodox parish are guaranteed to shake your
assumptions and make you see your life and face in a new way. They're not for the faint of heart,
but they are very much for all who want to embrace the truth more fully. And you didn't have to
ask Rusk over for help, cleaning, polishing, carrying, in or out. Any work in the church, the woman
was a stalled, a tallotish, you could count on. No one knew her suffering. They never bothered to
look into her eyes. It surprised me that most of the church folks at St. Alexander, the
whirling dervish parish, didn't even know her name. It wasn't anything they thought about.
To find this book and others like it, you can go to store.AncientFaith.com. Again, that is store.AncientFaith.com.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits, the Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung.
If you have a question call now at 855-237-2346. That's 855-AF Radio.
Welcome back. This is the second half of the show where you start to take your calls. Thank you
very much for that voice of Steve. So the first caller we have on the line is someone with an
excellent name. And that is Andrew from Indiana. Andrew, are you there? Yes, I am Father.
Thank you for having me on. Welcome to the Lord of Spirits. What's your question or your concern?
Well, my question is what is accomplished in the worship of God by those who are outside of the
people of God? And that's sort of the broad question about thinking specifically with three
I guess these circumstances. The first being the people that are akin to the Israelites and
they'll testament like the Edamite, the Midianite. On the show you said that for the point where
they were worshipping God still. But they didn't have the worship of the Torah. They didn't have
the rituals that were a participation in Christ saving work like the rituals of the Torah were.
So that's one sort of stance for those people's legal testament. So it was with the Americans,
because Americans did have the Torah, or at least a version of the Torah, I guess we could check.
And they held Passover and the various other feasts and festivals, but I think they were
separated off and they worked on the wrong locations. It was accomplished in their worship.
And then to bring it to the present, or those who are the turgable Christians who are outside of
the Orthodox church, as they were accomplished for them. Yeah. So, okay, so I'm just going to
restate your question the way that I understand it. You can tell me if I've got it. You're essentially
asking if someone's not actually sort of what we might think is canonically part of the people of God,
whether that's Israel and the old covenant, or Israel and the new covenant, which is the church,
then what exactly does their worship accomplish if anything? Is that correct? Am I getting it right?
Correct. Yes. That's what they're worshiping accomplishes for them. Yeah. Yeah.
So I have some thoughts on this, which I'll say first, but I know that Father Stephen probably has
a lot more to say. But I'll just say this, that whenever someone is being obedient to God,
they're being obedient to God, right? The idea that the idea that outside of the canonical boundaries
of the people of God, there is nothing but unmitigated darkness, is simply not true, right? It's
simply not true. And we have Orthodox saints, for instance, commenting on even within the past
couple of centuries, commenting, especially on the problem of what are often described as separated
brethren. And one of the problems with that phrase, of course, is that people tend to emphasize one of
those two words over the other, like they'll really want to emphasize the word separated and forget
about brethren, or they really want to emphasize brethren and forget about separated. But you know,
like Father George Florovsky said, you really need to emphasize both words. They're both important.
But there are Orthodox saints, like, for instance, St. Sylone the Athenite, and I'm kind of blanking
on the name right now, but there are, I think there were some 19th century Russian saints who
commented, especially on Catholics and Protestants in Russia. And they said, you know, when they do
something that we agree with and recognizes their own, we should affirm that. And like, they do
well to do those things, like they never say, well, they're not Orthodox. So, you know, I mean,
what are they really doing, right? So I'm going to go ahead and then punt over to Father Stephen
for especially, if he wants to come in on that, but especially, you know, the Old Testament piece,
which I don't know, I mean, I, you know, we talked about this, but, but I'm sure he has a lot more
to say about that. So Father, yeah, right. So I mean, what the, what the Midianites and Ishmaelites
and Edamites, and it's Ishmaelites and Edamites who make up the Midianites, what they're doing when
we re-encounter them, is they're continuing the kind of worship and the patterns of worship that
they got from Abraham and Ishmael or Abraham and Isaac and Esau, right? They're continuing
those forms of worship, right? As you mentioned, they had actually received the Torah,
you know, which gave the specific, the specific commands. But here's the thing,
those commandments are commandments given to humans. And that cuts in two ways. First,
they're not restrictions God imposes upon Himself. It's not God saying, I am telling you to worship
me this way as my people. Therefore, I am now restricting myself to only work here in this place
at all, right? Never, never do anything else. And then secondly, right? Liturgy is not the work of
the people, right? So ritual isn't something, isn't a process that we do that then results in us having
certain benefits, right? Ritual and Liturgy is the means given to us by God through which
God tells us he will work and do certain things when we are obedient and do the Liturgy
in that way. So the question, whether we're talking about the the Midianites or the Edomites
or the Samaritans or Roman Catholics and Protestants or anybody else, you know, the guy living
on an island who's never seen an Abrahamic religion in his life, right? The question amounts to
what is God doing there? Right. And the ultimate answer to that is we don't know most of the time.
This is the St. Irenaeus of Leone's famous. We know where the Holy Spirit is. He's in the church,
right? And we know what he's doing in the church because God made certain promises to us as to
what he would do in the church. But we know he's outside the church, but we don't know what he's
doing outside the church always. In fact, most of the time we don't. Sometimes we find out later.
You know, some people group comes comes to faith in Christ, right? And you can go back and look and
you can see these sort of seeds, like St. Justin Martyr talks about, in their previous beliefs and
culture that kind of helped lead them to Christ. And you can say, oh, well, that was the Holy Spirit's
doing, right? But in real time, we can't always see that. So, you know, the Holy Spirit blows
where he will and he's doing that. And God can choose to honor what he chooses to honor. He can
show mercy on whom he will show mercy and compassion on whom he will show compassion. So the issue is
we're accountable for the riches and the wealth that we have received. So those of us who are in
the Orthodox church are the ones who are going to be the most responsible on the day of judgment,
because we've received the whole thing, the whole tradition, everything, all of Christianity,
we have it and have access to it. And so that makes us more accountable for what we do or don't do
with it. And what we learn and what we don't learn and what we practice and what we don't practice.
God is also Christ is going to judge everybody. He's also going to judge those people outside the
church. He's going to judge non-Christians. He's going to judge ancient people outside of Israel.
We know he's going to hold them accountable for what they did with what they received. And that
in pretty much all cases is less, right? Unless they, unless they, you know, were aware,
also like an Israelite who's aware of the Torah and decides to move to Moab and become a Moabite
and worship Kimosh, right? Then he's going to be super accountable because he received the whole
thing and rejected the truth, right? But your person who's in ignorance who's sort of doing the
best they can, right? Your person who lived his whole life and died in 13th century France and
never saw an Orthodox church, right? He went to the only Christian church in his village.
Right? God's going to judge that person based on what he did with what he had, not on what he
did and didn't have. Does that make sense, Andrew? Yeah, but it just raises a, I guess it's quite
issue because I've heard this problem with the context of evangelism discussion.
Where some of you said, you know, if you, I heard someone on a closet day, or if you go and you
teach people about Christ, then when they die, there's going to be a more, if you're judgment on them.
And so, so on the one hand, that is true, but on the other hand,
didn't God send that person to teach them the good news, right? He's sending someone to do that for
them, you know, and they will be better off having received more. Correct, you know.
Right. And St. Paul points out, right? St. Paul talks about Romans 2 about these Gentiles who keep
keep the law, right? Because just because they're conscience, right? They live relatively more
lives, right? There are some of them, right? Some of them live more, more lives than than Israelites,
right? But is it easier to follow Christ when you know who he is? Or to just kind of figure out how
to do it on your own when you don't know who he is? Yeah. Yeah. So all right. Well, well, thank you very
much Andrew for your call. We're happy to have you on the show. Okay. So we've got another caller
and George is calling from Illinois. So George, are you there? I'm here. Is that coming through?
Yeah. We can hear you. So what's your question, George? Very good. Okay. Most of my impression or
my knowledge about what the news is I got from Clark Carrollton. Did we lose George? I think we lost
George. All right. Father Steven, are you still there? I'm still here. Okay. Well, hopefully George
can call back and we'll talk to him. So okay. Well, we do have another caller waiting. So
Cristiana from Ohio. Cristiana, are you there? Okay. Well, we don't seem to have her connected
either. Yeah. A traffic phone system. Yeah. Yeah. I don't know what happened here. All right. Well,
someone's cut the phone lines. Do you hear eerie music in the background?
It's coming from inside the studio. All right. Well, hopefully we'll be able to get these folks back. So
George, are you there yet? I am here. Okay. We lost touch with you for just a second. And I heard
you saying. Yeah. Yeah. Welcome back. I heard you saying that you had learned about the news from
from something from Clark Carrollton. Is that right? Yes. It's a big podcast based on philosophy
which is discontinued now. Okay. And the way he handled it, he contrasts the news to I think he's
the word is the O'Neil discursive reasoning. Right. That it might seem that Greek word correctly.
The O'Neil. Close enough. Yeah. Okay. And with that in mind, the news is not a reasoning
or not. Discursive, not a discursive issue. Some years ago, I heard a science podcast.
And in the end, episode, which raised the question, can a child think before he or she can talk?
And they give a few of the gifts. I think three stories. I know two. And adults,
man who was taught to talk. And then he lost his ability to communicate with others
like him who couldn't talk because now he could reason and use words. And he lost his ability
that he had to communicate with some other guys. And there was another woman who was
just called dedicated and something had grew brain. She wasn't able to talk or think
and that she regained it. And she was able to reflect on the period of time when she could not talk
or think. And she or she couldn't talk or speak in words. But she had, she sort of talked about
some method of thinking that she had during that time period. And they think maybe this
and organic reflection of the news. Is there like in a child's brain that can't talk yet? Is there
with the news? We're told to be happy. It's like a child with
depth to what might be going on there. Does that make sense?
Yeah, you're making sense. I think that, I mean, I did not listen to what you listened to
from Carlton. So I can't comment on what he in particular said. I have heard this distinction
between the news and the, you know, I don't want to say dionetic because then that's Elron Hubbard.
D&E. Yeah, the D&E, yeah, yeah, yeah, the discursive reasoning faculty. And, right, that is
that is true, right? That they're not the same thing. And I think that's an important place to
start. Like that's what we're talking about, that you are not your thoughts. And also that the
news is not the only way to receive knowledge. Right? And so when you talked about people, for instance,
who are either physically immature or then had an injury or something like that,
and yet they still were able to perceive, and then even later could kind of comment on that,
just showed that's just an illustration of what we're talking about, that there's lots of
different ways to know. And there's lots of different ways that thoughts come into, you know,
into your mind, right? So, Father, do you have anything you want to add to that or correct,
or whatever? Well, just a couple of quick. Yeah, we've got to be careful
when we use, when we distinguish between Greek words. Not that what he was saying was wrong,
but I can give you examples where the word DNA is used in the Bible, for example,
where it basically means the same thing as news. Right? So, exhibit A would be when
Christ quotes Deuteronomy and says, love the Lord your God with all your heart, soul, mind,
and strength, the word for mind, there's DNA. And he doesn't mean discursive reasoning,
he means your mind, right? So, but I mean, it's helpful as a label, and any label you use,
we just have to say this is a label we're using to make a distinction, it's not a technical term.
Because if people start to look at it as a technical term, then, you know, for example,
they start thinking different Greek words for love mean different things.
Um, um, screw that pot again. Well, yeah, it is definitely true that there is, there are ways of
interacting with the world that do not involve language. Right? And if you if you work with animals
at all, you know this, right? Animals can learn to understand comparable commands and understand
certain words and sounds mean certain things. But you could, they also are able to process and
strategize, right? And interact with their environment in a way that they're not, they don't have
thoughts formed into language in their brains, right? When they're when they're doing it, right?
Um, so yeah, there are there are multiple levels and putting it into words like we said earlier
is reducing it in a certain sense, right? You might, if if you're a craftsman and you're making a
chair, right, you probably don't, if you're a professional craftsman, every time you make a chair,
think in your head discursively like, okay, now I need to make this measurement and make sure
the curve is the right, like you just you know how to do it and you just do it, right? You don't have
to go to the language level, right? And, and, you know, and like I have four children and I watched
that I interacted with them before they could talk to me, you know, they were responding and not,
you know, in a linguistic way, they didn't have words initially. And yet it was, they could
still communicate, they could still interact, you know, they could still they knew who was who,
you know, like, you know, a baby that prefers mom over dad, which is what usually happened in
my house, what, but we did have one baby that for a period of time actually liked me better,
only one out of four though. But, you know, like it's, it's definitely a thing, you know,
you know, the idea that they can't think or can't know doesn't make it just because they don't
have language doesn't, the evidence doesn't line up with that. So I hope that makes some sense to
and watch a baby interact with an icon sometime. Yeah, right, right. Yeah, yeah, it's fascinating.
So, all right. Well, thank you very much for that question, George. It's, it's a useful distinction
clarification to make. Okay, we're going to take one more caller before we continue on,
start talking about apocalypse. And that's Cristiana from Ohio. So Cristiana, are you there?
I'm here. Can you hear me? We hear you. Yes, I'm back. So I am the woman of many questions.
Oh, well, okay, you get one. And if it's good, we'll let you have a follow-up.
Yeah, so I was, so I was driving the other day. And there was a morning dove in the road and
the way that they walk, they sort of bob their heads so they feel like they're going faster,
but they're really not going any faster. And I nearly hit it. And I felt a sort of horror inside
of me. And I was like, no, I can't hit a dove. That's the image of the Holy Spirit. And I'm like,
wait, is it? What is what does that mean? Can we honor the Holy Spirit by honoring a dove?
If we heard the dove in a bad way, are we dishonoring the Holy Spirit?
What sort of connection does the Holy Spirit have with the image of a dove?
So like, as opposed to, for instance, if you hit, I was going to say a pigeon, but pigeons are
doves. If you hit a turkey buzzard with your car, which is a little bit more likely, probably,
because they like to hang out on roads, you know, would that be sort of not the same thing?
I mean, so in the scripture, we do get the Holy Spirit alighting on the Lord Jesus at theophany,
as it says in scripture, in the form or the shape of a dove, but he did not become a bird.
Okay, so what's, yeah, he did not become a bird. Okay, I don't know if I rescued myself by saying
that. Father Steve was about to, yeah, no, he did not become a bird, right? So he's not,
he's not a dove. The Holy Spirit is not a dove. Certainly, I can agraphically where you see a dove
appear usually, usually that's what, you know, that it's a symbol of the Holy Spirit because of that
description that's given in the gospels. But I mean, I would, I don't know, I'm just
shooting from the hip here, but I would not say that the morning dove that you accidentally hit
with your car, it would be on a front to the Holy Spirit any more than hitting some other bird or
animal, right? Now, if you were like, gunning for it and you were trying to just run this thing down
out of a sense of glee of killing things with your car, that's another problem entirely.
But I don't think it has to do with the particular species that you're hitting. I don't know,
like I said, I'm just shooting from the hip. So unless you take it over and eat it, then it's okay.
You're hunting at that point. Car hunting. Yeah, I live at Louisiana. Not the best way to hunt, though.
Yeah, no, right. Yeah, so yeah, the key is that in that instance, right, it's describing the way
in which the spirit descended. It's giving an image. This is why technically in Orthodox
iconography, you're not supposed to depict the Holy Spirit as a dove in any other icon
in order to not sort of give that impression that the Holy Spirit was incarnate as a dove or something.
Wow. This, this may scandalize the people. You do see it that way in some places. In most, in most of
the scriptures that in a lot of ancient near Eastern literature, the dove is not an image of like
peace and beauty the way it is today. People, the people of things are usually compared to doves in
the Old Testament. And this is not why the Holy Spirit, let me be clear. This is not why the Holy
Spirit is compared to that, right? It's describing a white descent, right? But in the Old Testament,
and in a lot of ancient Near Eastern literature, doves are actually considered to be stupid birds.
Jonah's name means dove. And that's at play in the book of Jonah that he doesn't have his head right.
The truth is figure out what God is doing. The reason why the dove returning with the branch at the end
of the flood is so important is that doves aren't very bright. So if it was able to go and find a
branch and get back, that means, oh, the water must be mostly gone now. Mikey likes it, right? So the
dove can even go and find it, right? And so what happened in sort of the tradition, it wasn't actually
the peace thing didn't come from the Holy Spirit, actually. It came from Noah's dove with the
branch in its mouth. The olive branch was originally the symbol of peace or the token of peace.
If you look at our Orthodox prayers, our older prayers, they talk about the branch, the olive branch
as the symbol and token of peace, but they would depict the dove with the olive branch in its
mouth. And so that whole image became a symbol of peace. And then people sort of forgot about the
olive branch and it was just doves. And then people started letting them loose at weddings and they
went to the bathroom everywhere and it was a nightmare. Or funerals. Yeah. Yeah. That's the worst.
Sorry. If anyone out there has had at least doves at your funeral, yeah. Because the idea there
that some people have is like, oh, that's the soul going up or whatever. Please don't do that.
No. That's why we don't make these things up. So in essence, if you do hit a dove with your car,
it's because the dove was too dumb to get out of the way.
Hopefully that's not scandalous there for you, Christiana.
Oh, Noah. So do we? So were you saying that the Holy Spirit came down as the image of a dove just
to describe its whiteness and how it sort of was like bright in the way it flew? Right.
Right. He just said the motion like a dove. It's about the descent of the Holy Spirit.
It's not describing the Holy Spirit. It's describing the descent of the Holy Spirit.
Does that make sense? Yes, it does. Okay. Great. Well, thank you so much. You're welcome.
Nice to hear from you, Christiana. All right. So rolling on Apocalypse now. Apocalypse now.
Or actually, Apocalypse then. Yeah. Apocalypse then. Yes. Yes. Then. And now we had to take a few
calls because we were going to get to the actual topic of the episode far too early episode.
That's right. Yes. That's right. So that we're safe to actually start the actual topic.
Yes. Okay. So Apocalypse is not about the end of the world or about, you know, like it's funny.
Like we have this genre of stories, you know, post-apocalyptic, which doesn't actually mean the end of
the world, although it usually means the end of a world, you know, a civilization end of the world
as we know it. Yes, as we know it. Right. Right. That's where we started this episode.
Yeah. Yeah. You know, but yeah, it's not about mass destruction or giant comment,
comments or about giants. Zombies. Zombies. Yeah, zombie apocalypse. Although as an interesting
side note, I just have to share this with the world. There is a, there's a Facebook account that I
like to follow called Confessions of a funeral director, which the guy who writes it actually went
to seminary with our mutual friend Mike Landsman. So that's kind of fun. And I want
point he posted, this is like a couple of years ago. At one point, he posted this sort of confession
that when he's now, some people may not appreciate this humor. So I'm just warning you now. This is
the scandal episode. This is the schedule. Yeah. He says that when he's putting, when he's putting
bodies in coffins, if they're wearing shoes that he ties the shoelaces together because if there
ever is a zombie apocalypse, then it would be hilarious. That's what he, that's what he said.
It could save lives. It could save lives. That's true. That's right. Slow them down just a little bit.
Yeah. There was some televangelist who said the COVID vaccine was going to start of zombie
apocalypse. Oh, nice. And he was serious. Well, as serious as those folks get. Yeah.
Yeah. Still good. I mean, you don't know. Yeah. So that's not what apocalypse is. What if
what is genres of films? But no, this, this is a genre of ancient literature.
Right. It's a very different genre. Right. So yeah, it's not about mass destruction. It's not
about nuclear war. And so the word, the word apocalyptic in Greek just means revelation.
Yeah, we're unveiling literally. Right. We're, yeah, we're moving a cover, unmercy seating
something. There we go. Now we've been doing episodes long enough that we can have cool callbacks
like that to previous previous episodes in joke inceptions. There we go. So yeah, you're peeling
back a layer and revealing something, showing something, right? But that's why you will sometimes in
your old timey Bibles, it will be the apocalypse of Saint John, right? And in your new timey,
Bibles, your lame ones, it'll be the revelation of Saint John. Not just revelation.
Ever revelations. Yes, there is no moral. That's not the book of revelations. There is no plural.
There was one revelation to Saint John and he recorded it. Yes, right.
So, right, but those are those are synonyms basically to reveal something to uncover something.
Right. It shows something. And so what it is uncovering is the spiritual reality
that is always, as we said at the end of act one, that is always connected to and right behind
the physical and material reality. Right. But then we don't usually see that most people don't see.
Right. Most people don't see. And we're going to get into this more in act three why a lot of people's
their news isn't all that active. But so because our news isn't all that active, we don't see this.
Right. But it is revealed to people whose newses are like prophets and apostles. And then they
are able to fill in those blanks. Right. They're able to then show here's what's going on behind
the material reality that you're seeing. Right. And far from this being something that's just
relegated to that last book in the Bible, it's actually everywhere. So whenever a prophet receives
revelation from God, it's an apocalypse. You know, something's being pulled away. And now he sees
something, you know, that God, God has given him this vision, which is why they're often called
seers. Right. There's this notion of like Moses, for instance, in Orthodox liturgical texts,
is referred to as the prophet Moses, the God seer, you know, God revealed himself to Moses.
He God apocalyptic. I don't know that there's a there's not a verb is there. I don't know.
But God pulled away the veil. Apocalyptic. Yeah. No. Oh, man, that's bad.
That's is it really? Yeah. Oh, wow. Okay. Well, there we go.
All right. Well, there's first versus Apocalypse. Yeah. Yeah. Right. Right. Yes. Yes.
That's I am revealing. Yeah. Right. Yeah. Right. Right. So, so this happens all over the
scripture. So I mean, we do have this book called the Apocalypse of Saint John, but it's
happening all the time. It's happening all the time. You know, whenever you've got a prophet or
a apostle receiving something or anybody receiving something from God, that's it's an apocalypse.
It's what the whole Bible is. Right. To varying degrees of obviousness. Right. Yeah. So there's
places where it's more obvious, but it's what the whole Bible is when we understand the scriptures
correctly. That's why the Old Testament was written by prophets and the New Testament was written
by apostles. And there's less than a hair's breadth between what a prophet is and what an
apostle is as we discussed in a previous episode. But the the earliest. Yeah. You mentioned
Seer. The the earliest Hebrew term for prophet is actually Seer. Hmm. That goes back earlier than
than the word Navi that gets translated as profitease in Greek in Greek. What's the earlier word?
What's the Hebrew for Seer? It's a it's a form of the verbra to see. Okay. All right. Which is also
and I think not coincidentally part of the route that gets turned into bishop. Yes,
overseer. Right. Yeah. Right. But so that's the idea. This is even the earlier that was the person
who sees. Right. And then by the time you have sort of the Navi, the prophet idea sort of firmly
established, you still have that element because, for example, the book of Jeremiah, the definition
of who is a true prophet is the true prophet is the one who has stood in the divine council.
So the one who has seen God, the one who has been, you know, in in the presence of God stood in
the divine council and seen him. Yeah. And the angelic hosts. And another good example of this sort
of newetic sight is the story of Alisha and his servant, Gahazi. Right. Right. And Gahazi
underutilized biblical name, folks. We got like a thousand Georges and nicks in all of our churches.
Zero Gahazis, folks. I mean, but you do need a nick in a in a Orthodox church for that church
to be canonical. Like literally no matter what traditional jurisdiction, it is. There's always
some guy named Nick. It's just the way that it is. So I don't know that we can't set up a
Gahazi requirement. Right. No, but just just a token Gahazi or two. So yeah. So for those who
aren't super familiar with this story, the prophet Alisha had this the servant Gahazi. And there was
this point at which the authorities were closing in on Alisha. As many of the prophets in the Old
Testament, he was not a popular dude. And so they were persecuted. Right. As you know, Christ would
later say in the Gospels, which of the prophets did your father's not persecute. Alisha was one
of them. But so as as they're sort of close again, his servant Gahazi is sort of terrified that
they're going to die. And Alisha is on the other hand, totally calm. Right. And so then there's
this episode where Gahazi doesn't understand why Alisha is totally calm. And so Alisha sort of
praise and Gahazi's eyes are opened is the language that's used. His eyes are opened. And he's
able to see the angelic hosts, right, the armies of Yahweh, the God of Israel, like surrounding
them on all sides and protecting them. And the implication is this is what Alisha sees all the time.
Yeah. Right. Alisha is just living in the full world, spiritual and material. And that's why he
operates the way he does. That's why he has the the contentment and the the ability to face the
suffering and persecution. And giving that to Gahazi then then helps Gahazi. And so when the
writers of scripture, when we talk about the Holy Spirit inspiring scripture, this is mostly what
we're talking about what that inspiration is. Right. Sometimes people think about that inspiration,
like, oh, he went into a trance and then like he came to and he had written all this stuff. And
oh, what's this? It's like reading it for the first time himself, you know. Right. It's the
God reveals things to them. Right. Right. This is where the Holy Spirit comes and allows them to see.
Yeah, which if you think about it, okay, so like we're going to talk about some places in
scripture where this happens, but like so Genesis obviously a good place to start at the very beginning.
Like there's events that happen at the beginning of Genesis that literally there was no one
around to write them down. You know, like there was no one there when God, you know, no human being
there, when God separated the the waters from the, you know, and the firmament and the earth. And
like no one was there. And then, you know, there's all kinds of stuff that happens long, long before
any of this gets written down. And the only way that someone would know those things or that a
prophet would have that that knowledge is if God had revealed it to him. Right. You know, and
and and yet further than that, right, is what exactly is scripture doing when these stories are
being told through the prophets. Right. And then and this is really interesting to me because
like it's often said, for instance, and rightly so, that the Bible is not a science textbook.
Um, that, you know, people who attempt to turn it into one, whether it's people who are trying to
do that to debunk it, you know, or those who are trying to do it say no, no, it's sort of the
greatest of all science textbooks. Um, I'm looking at you arc experience. Um, that's a joke for my
dad. Um, yeah, yeah. He and I feel just wait, you just wait till global warming raises the sea
levels and see who's laughing. There we go. Right. Right. Um, you know, that that's not what
its purpose is. And the fact that it's not doing that and we say that it's not doing that is not
some kind of cop out. Right. Um, so, you know, when when, uh, when the creation is described,
it's not described in what we would think of as scientific terms. And it's not even trying to do
that. Right. It's not talking about chemical processes. It's not talking about, I mean, it's,
it's not talking about any of that stuff. Right. And so, I mean, that's why for me, like,
I know, this is just a personal opinion, but that's why for me, the whole kind of creationism versus
evolution versus how old is the earth, like this stuff is, is, is just missing the point of what's
going on there. Like, I mean, if someone wants to talk about that stuff and it's interested in that
fine, but, but that's like not what Genesis is about and Genesis is not even trying to supply
that knowledge, you know, um, you know, it's, it's not bad science because it's not science. And
it's only in a world where we think that science equals knowledge and science is the only kind of
knowledge that that's a problem, you know, like, well, if it's not science and how can we possibly
trust it? Well, we just spent a whole episode and a half talking about why that's not all there is
to it, right? Right. And it's, yeah, it's, it's, the creationist is really to us what God was doing.
Yes. And what it means. Right. And, and, and things about it that God wants to communicate to us.
He's not telling us how he did it because we can't understand how he did it. Right. Right. He's
that type of material level. Yeah. And it's well known, I think by now that I hate this how old is
the earth stuff. And it works in the tears. Um, but yeah, I mean, if someone's arguing some position
on that with an agenda, right? Like if somebody, you know, I mean, Darwin was put to like horrific
uses in 19th century colonialism and early 20th century, like fascism. Okay. Yeah. Right. Yeah. I'm
again, that. Okay. If they have an agenda for today, based on that, then, then, you know, I might
need to get involved in the discussion. But if it's purely at like an academic level of exactly how
old the earth is, I don't care. Right. Yeah. Or, or, you know, like the cold kind of, you know,
again, I mentioned the art experience, the whole answers and genesis approach, uh, which is the
idea is like if this doesn't line up according to these scientific categories, and that means the
entire scripture is bunk. You know, that's like saying that the, the manual that came with my microwave,
if it does not line up to Elizabethan forms of Iambic pentameter, then it's junk and we can't use it.
Like it's not meant for that. That's not what it's, what it's doing. Although I think it would
be pretty, pretty amazing. If one of you people out there who writes, uh, you know, manuals for
appliances, considered putting them in blank verse, just an idea or a little, a literative,
Anglo-Saxon verse, another idea, just throwing that out there. Uh, but no, that's not, that's not
what it's for. Right. And, and to paraphrase, uh, and to write, uh, there aren't any 19th century
Germans around anymore. So we don't need to cow-tow to them. Right. Right. So, yes, they
wrote as if, right, their culture, civilization, form of religion was the day new law of history.
Right. Yeah. Uh, we obviously don't believe that. Yeah. Right. Things didn't go so well for
Germany in the intervening years. There were some problems. Um, yeah, and there's been some history
since then. We have, we have just a similar mindset. Right. So, for example, we assume that if
God explained the creation in scientific detail, that would be 21st century science. Right.
Not only would it have made no sense to Moses. Right. If he actually explained it, it would
probably still make no sense to us. It'd probably be three or four thousand years, if ever,
before it made any sense to anybody. Right. Because we just assumed that our science now is
v-science. And yeah, we look at science a hundred years ago and we think a lot of it was dumb,
but we're not going to think that a hundred years from now, because we're smart and have it all
together. Um, so the whole premise behind the idea that it would be science is flawed. Right.
But the point is it isn't. It's apocalypse. It's revealing what God is doing. And so the same
thing's true when you come to the flood. Right. Right. Which every very ancient culture
acknowledges happened on some level. Right. There is a material reality there. There are events
that happened. Right. The world and everything in it. The cosmos was created. That means it came
into being at some point. Right. So there is a material reality that happened there. Right. But
we're saying that the scriptures are there to describe that material reality. They're there to
describe the spiritual reality. Same thing with the flood. Right. The material reality is probably
almost everybody agrees on this is the material reality are the earth changes that happen at the
end of the last ice age. Right. But the point is not of the story of the flood as recorded in
Genesis is not to say here is exactly what happened. Everybody knew what happened. Everybody knew
there were these earth changes. Everybody knew there was a flood. Everybody knew that that
human civilization was nearly annihilated by it. Everyone knew all of this. Right.
It was what does this mean? Why did it happen? How did it happen? How did God preserve humanity
through it? Yeah. What is God doing here? Right. That's what the scriptures are telling us. They're
not just trying to tell us about the historical material event. Though there was one. Right.
We're not going to the other extreme and denying that there was one and saying this is just a
spiritual event or some spiritual truth. Right. But what's revealed to us in the scripture is the
spiritual truth that is always there behind and alongside the material event. Right. Yep. Yep.
Yeah. Same thing. Same thing with the Babel story. Like, you know, linguists and philologists will say,
yes, we can look back and see that there's these divisions of languages and civilization kind of
splits up and, you know, all this kind of thing. But that's not what, like, the Babel story is,
you know, sorry, philologists. It's not, it's not a philological textbook. You know, that's not
its point. It's about the spiritual reality behind it. It's about human beings attempting to
sort of control God and the fragmentation that happens as a result of that. And then, you know,
we're still that human, you know, the various tribes and nations become subject to, you know,
initially, well, initially it's good. I think that God puts them in the hands of angelic powers.
But then it becomes bad when they, when those angelic powers fall by accepting worship from those
those nations, you know, it's about the rise of paganism and the rise of idolatry. Right. Which,
and we read, we quoted in a previous episode from anthropologists and sociologists talking about
this. This is a thing that happened in human history. Right. And what the scriptures is revealing
is what was going on there, the spiritual reality that laid behind those events. Same thing is
true with the Exodus. We talked about the Exodus in the Pascale episode. Right. There were these
locks connected to the Red Sea that the Israelites had to cross to get out of Egypt. Right. Physical
water locks. Right. They also passed through the Sea of Reeds in the underworld. Right. That is
the spiritual reality of what was happening there. And so the scriptures are about revealing to us
the spiritual reality, not trying to give us a date for the Exodus, which is why that also forced
we get to. Yeah. And it's, and it's the same reason why, like again, that that approach, you know,
it's, it's like, like when I was an undergrad, one of my favorite poets was John Keats. And he's
got this amazing poem called Two Autumn, which I read every year at autumn. You know, but a physics
textbook cannot explain why that's beautiful. That can only be understood in spiritual terms. I
can only make sense that way. Right. So, so yeah, I mean, you know, this, this, this problem gets
repeated over and over again as people are trying to read scripture. We have to understand it's
all apocalyptic, you know, you know, another example is the conquest of Canaan, right, where you've
got the, there's a material thing happening migrating, this migration of these, these, these,
these Hebrew tribes. But there's also spiritual side, which is the gigantomaki, the defeat
of the giant clans. That's also happening. That's, and that's what the scripture is revealing to
us. You know, it's passing on this apocalypse, right? Right. And, and then you get to the other
historical books, you get into the books of kingdoms, or first and second Samuel, first and second
kings, the parallel and first and second chronicles. And first of all, it's sort of like it's
chronicling the kings of, of Israel and Judah. But then also it just zags for a whole bunch of
chapters, it talks about Elijah and Elijah, who aren't kings. Yeah, they're profits. But
on top of that, when you compare what's going on in scripture to what's going on in the archaeological
record, it's, it's kind of fascinating because you have, you know, most of first and all of
second Samuel, or first and second kingdoms about David. And there's barely mention of the
existence of David in the archaeological record. Yeah, it does exist, but not barely. Yeah. And only
recently has it been found, whereas you look at Omri, the founder of the Omride dynasty,
which Ahab was part of that dynasty. But Omri, he gets six verses in the Bible that basically just
say like three times how wicked he was. And then he bought the hill where they built some aerial later.
Right, that's it, right. But you go outside to the archaeological record and all of Israel's
neighbors referred to Israel as the house of Omri, fate Omri, long after his dynasty was even gone.
He was one of the most powerful and successful kings in the Northern Kingdom's history,
if not the most and influential in terms of Israel's neighbors and the global scale, Bible just
said six verses he's wicked. Right, that's it. And you see this refrain all the time in those books
where it says, you know, as for everything else this wicked guy did, is it not recorded in the
annals of the kings of Israel? Right, so yeah, you could go there and get the material history,
right? It's there in their official annals, all the battles they fought, the territory they,
they took the taxes they raised, the things building projects, you can read all that there.
Scriptures are here to reveal to you the spiritual reality behind that. Right, and the spiritual
reality of Omri is that he was wicked, he contributed to Israel's downfall and its spiral into
destruction by the Assyrians. Yeah, so then, you know, perhaps in a more obvious section of the
Old Testament and the prophets that this is apocalyptic as well, right? And so you then you start
getting prophets like Isaiah who sees God on his throne, right, and reveals that kind of thing,
like this is this is apocalypse in a way that makes that's a little bit more obvious to us, I think,
right? So what are some more examples of that from those prophets? Right. Well, there's yeah,
I mean, there's obviously there's more subtle examples. I mean, what Isaiah Jeremiah and Ezekiel
are essentially doing is Isaiah, you know, before the fall of the northern kingdom or at the fall of
the northern kingdom, Jeremiah at the fall of Judah to the Babylonians and Ezekiel in exile is,
you know, the people know either, hey, the Assyrians are coming to kill everybody or the Babylonians
are coming to kill everybody and enslave the rest or we're in exile, they know that, right? The
prophet doesn't have to come and reveal that to them, the dates where they were living, right? The
prophet comes to reveal to them, here's why here's why the Assyrians are coming. Here's why the Babylonians
are coming. Here's why you're in exile. And here's how God is going to bring you out of this.
Here's how we ended up here. Here's what you need to do now in terms of repentance. And then here's
how God is going to deliver us from this, from the consequences of our own of our own sins and wickedness
and then you get the really obvious ones like Daniel and Zechariah where they're actually apocalyptic
texts, right? Yeah, like they're directly like recording visions, right? Yeah, these massive
world history spanning kinds of things, you know, right? And the book of Revelation is that too,
right? Exactly. And this is where that end of the world stuff comes in because in these more
expansive apocalyptic and the book of Edenic is this too, right? The book of Edenic is actually
several of these put together and and other inoclic literature is mostly apocalypses, but it has
this vast sweep of history. It covers from the beginning all the way through the history of God's
people all the way to the end, right? And as modern people, I guess, we're more fascinated by
trying to figure out what's ahead, what's in the future for us, which is the end, rather than
trying to actually understand our past and our heritage and how we got here, which to me is backwards,
right? But yeah, so that it's the whole sweep, right? Not just, not just, here's a bunch of stuff
that's going to happen in the future, so that you could figure out when the end is coming. Exactly.
And so when we say this is everywhere in the Bible, right? Probably the place where
people would think this exists in the least might be the epistles of Saint Paul.
Because modern Western Christians, we've been taught that, you know, Saint Paul's right in theology,
right? Of course, isn't true either. He's writing letters to churches and to people, but
he's right in theology. This is discursive reasoning. You know, we're going to go and analyze
his grammar and his logical arguments, right? But if you read Saint Paul closely and you look at
the actual structure of his epistles, he will make a series of theological points. And these aren't
just any theological points. These aren't sort of premise one, right? These are theological points
like the first chapter of Ephesians, right? We've been adopted as sons of God. We're already seated
with Christ in the heavenly places, right? This is this is visionary type stuff, right? This is
revealing spiritual reality type stuff. This is this is the spiritual reality. And then at some
point in the epistle, it's almost always translated into English as therefore. Yeah, right?
Therefore. And the corneal chestnut is when you see that, you ask, what is it therefore?
I heard that so many times when I was going up. What's the therefore? Therefore, like, oh, he's
saying it again, pastor, whatever your name is. Yeah. But what it is, is it Saint Paul doing this
transition now to the very practical and the material level. Yeah, right? This is true. This is
the spiritual reality. This is what's going on. Therefore, this is what you need to do.
Therefore, you need to love your brother. Therefore, you need to put off sexual immorality.
Right. Right. Therefore, you need to worship in this way and not that way, right? Exactly.
So even in Saint Paul, this apocalyptic element is fundamental to what he's to what he's doing.
And that's what's behind. You'll sometimes hear this eschatological tension between the already
and the not yet. But what's really going on is actually more this apocalyptic transition.
This is the reality. This is the truth, right? Now and back then and in the future, right?
This is the truth. Therefore, this is what needs to happen now, which isn't just sit around hoping
for stuff that's going to happen someday in the future. Saint Paul always does stuff he wants you
to do. Yes. Sorry, some of our non-orthodox Christians. Right. Right. And I mean, you know,
also known as the repent for the kingdom of heaven is at hand, except Paul puts it the other way,
you know, the kingdom of heaven is at hand. Therefore, repent and proclaim the gospel and
live in unity with your brothers and sisters in Christ and you know come together in worship and
don't divide into factions and fight over stupid things. That doesn't align with the spiritual
reality that is actually present. Right. Right. That is false to the reality of who you are in Christ.
Yes. Yes. All right. Well, we've had a nice BV second half to the show, but it's the Lord of
Spirits podcast. And that means there's a third half coming. So we're going to take a break in
just a second. And when we come back, we will be talking about apocalypse now. So let's go to break.
Father Andrew Stephen Daimick and Father Stephen DeYoung will be back in a moment to take your
calls on the next part of the Lord of Spirits. Give them a call at 855-237-2346. That's 855-AF
Radio. No one of books these days offer us techniques for self-improvement. But in the newest
release from the ancient faith store, gratitude in life's trenches, Robin Phillips takes a different
tack. He shows us that God made us where we are in the pain and heartache of the present moment.
Instead of looking for a way to escape from hardship, we can cultivate an attitude of gratitude,
peace, and self-acceptance that will transform our experience of suffering,
drawing on his own experiences and his work as a consultant in the behavioral health industry,
as well as stories of saints and sufferers, teachings of the fathers, and recent discoveries in
neuroscience. Phillips shows us that the journey to personal well-being is one we can all travel,
regardless of the hardships we may face. To find this book and others like it, you can go to
store.enginefaith.com. Again, that is store.enginefaith.com.
That's Father Steven's book, The Religion of the Apostles. This is an unpaid advertisement,
but I just had to mention that for everybody, because it's selling very well. Thank God. But there's
a big new printing in the warehouse, so there's lots more to go. For now. Yeah, I mean, we've sold out
in the past, so get your copy while you still can. Before we continue, we actually do have another
caller, and Samuel is calling from Virginia, so Samuel, are you there? Be well, Father.
Be well to you. Welcome to the Lord of Spirits Podcasts. We're happy to hear from you. What's on
your mind? It does the liturgy include some sort of apocalyptic unveiling. Yes.
Right. So how does that, yeah, you might be thinking, well, in what way or how does that work?
And that would be a very rational thing to wonder. Right. I mean, we could do like whole episodes
on this, and we actually do plan to do some episodes on stuff that specifically in the liturgy.
There are a lot of things revealed in the liturgy, but I would say that among the foremost would be
the presence of God to His people, like when we say Christ isn't our midst.
You know, remember that the liturgy is fundamentally a sacrificial meal that we share with our God,
and He offers Himself for us to us, right? And so we feed upon Him, and He is revealed to us. He
becomes known to us, you know, just like happens in the breaking of the bread at a mass. He becomes
known to us in the breaking of the bread, right? So fundamentally the divine liturgy reveals
Christ. There's a lot of other things we could say about that revelation of Christ, but that's
the most fundamental part of it. It is an unveiling. It is a pulling back of the veil. And certainly
there's liturgical bits that kind of indicate that, like for instance, the opening of the Holy
Doors and the kind of stances. You know, that's an indication of part of what's happening there. So
Father, you got anything to add? Well, yeah, there's the very literal, right? The opening and
closing of the doors, the opening and closing of the curtain, the veiling and removal of the
veils from the gifts. But yeah, this idea of noetic revelation is deeply built into the words
of the liturgy. And I think exhibit a of that is actually in the epiclaces of the liturgy of St.
Basil the Great. The epiclaces of St. John Chrysostom, it's make this bread, right, to be
the body make that which is in this cup to be the blood of Christ. Thank you to change by the Holy Spirit.
The epiclaces of St. Basil the Great, it is show this bread to be and show this cup to be.
So the idea of showing, revealing, seeing, right, the spiritual reality of Christ's body and blood,
right, that permeates the, the gifts is sort of right there in the language. Yeah, and it also
occurs to me, I don't know why this didn't occur me earlier, but you know, after we receive Holy
Communion, then we sing, what, we have seen the true light, we have received the heavenly spirit,
right? We're basically saying we've received this apocalypse, right? That's what's happening right
after you commune. You know, so, so yeah, I mean, it's, it's, it's everywhere. It is an apocalypse.
Yeah. Yeah. Does that make sense, Samuel? Yes, it does, Father.
Awesome. Well, thank you very much for calling. We, I think, I think I'm going to start advertising
our Sunday service of the paper as a liturgical apocalypse. Yeah. Let's see if it drums up some
more visitors. Apocalypse, 10 a.m. at 9 a.m. St. Paul's Amaze. I don't know when you do your
service. Yeah. Yeah. That's a great idea. That's a very funny idea. So, all right. Well, thank you
very much for calling, Samuel, and we're happy to talk to you this evening. So, all right.
All right. Well, we're going to roll on here with a third half of the show, and here is our
therefore. Right. Right. Therefore. Yeah. Exactly. Therefore. Therefore. Right. So, again, like we said
at the beginning of the last act, right, the question we get all the time is, how do we actually,
I guess, was the end of act one? What, what's the way back into the ground of, you know, the, the,
the ancient world, right? In terms of their way of seeing the world. And so what we were talking
about at the end of act one in terms of language and music and art and ritual,
talked about how we in the modern world, due to what modernity has done to us,
tend to try to reduce everything to language. Part of the way back is to sort of follow that path
back the other way. Yeah. Right. Moving out of that kind of linguistic rationalism that has
so come to cat to to categorize and describe Western theology. But to try to move from reducing
everything to language to going back to iconography. And we have the, we have the tools to do this
in the Orthodox Church. Yeah. You can, you can make yourself, even if you have to make yourself at
first, right? Stand before or sit before an icon. You can make yourself put away the lyric sheet
and just listen to the liturgical hymns, right? And be in and listen to the liturgy. And you can come
and participate in the sacraments and the mysteries in the liturgy. You can, you can, you can actually do
this, right? And fight that desire to try to boil it down to language and try to deal with it
in that way. If you're not in an Orthodox Church, this becomes much more difficult. Yeah, because
of the heritage of four bear walls and discernment, right? You know, the, like, iconoclasm
leads to this reduction to language. Because when you pull those things out, then what do you have left?
You just have that. And now mind you, we're not in any way knocking language, right? But language
is one, one of the ways that human beings interact with the world. I mean, how can I knock language?
You know, I'm, I'm going to go full diogenes the cynic. And when people come and try to talk to me,
I'm just going to waggle my fingers at them in strange ways. Yeah. Um, yeah. So, you know, the
thing about the four bear, so this is something that hits home, okay? So, you know, again, this is,
I guess this is our scandal episode. But, but when, when that's your heritage, when that's the core
of what church is, um, even when you then do have, say, music, which is another way that human beings
interact with reality, uh, the way that music is ultimately, um, evaluated within that context is
in terms of the lyrics. You know, and that's why, for instance, then you can change the genre,
I can sound, have you like? And there's no, within that particular context, there is no argument against
death metal in church, if the lyrics are good, right? Because all that matters is the language. Now,
almost every Christian, uh, would sort of viscerally understand that death metal doesn't work in
church. I'm sure there's some of you out there that probably don't agree with that. But, you know,
and the reason why I would say that they viscerally understand this is because that's super rare in
churches. Well, so it's like, no, we will not put that in there. The problem is is that there's no good
argument against it when, when four bear walls in the sermon is the core of what your religion does.
You know, there's no, there's no good argument against it. Um, so, you know, that's, that's, that's
the difficulty when you make church essentially a kind of lesson. Um, I mean, I'm in favor of
lessons and lectures and language and, you know, all that kind of stuff. But that's, when that's all
that you've got, it's going to be much harder, much, much harder to, uh, to get back to, I mean,
if we could put it this way, why not? This enchanted experience of the world, you know, the
noetic apprehension of what's going on, the full panoply of, of human knowledge of, of who God is and
what he's doing in the world. Um, and I mean, not to, not to do too much, you know, follow
civilization kind of stuff of this. But I would say that, you know, that a religion that emphasizes
language to the exclusion of this other stuff, or at least to the detriment of it tends to help people
become secular, frankly, you know, um, that's, that's what I think anyway. So yeah, yeah. Yeah,
language, language is, is kind of frankly the lowest level of this, which is why we talked about
reducing it to language. Yeah. Right. And we all kind of realize that, right? Like if the only way
you ever communicated with your spouse was talking on the phone, yeah, that would greatly reduce your
relationship. Yeah. And in a way that if you both lost the power of speech, but you were together,
that would be less of a reduction. Right. Right. And, and, and we all have this concept of that's
just talk like we have this sense that there's something deeper and more authentic than than,
than language. Now language becomes verified when it's filled with authentic life. Right. When it has
the whole, when it's within the context of all the rest of this, then it becomes what it should be.
So like liturgy itself has a lot of language. Right. Has a lot of language, but it's only able to do
what it does within the context of the ritual of the liturgy. Right. If you sit at home in your
armchair and read the words of the liturgy, you will know it is not remotely the same experience.
Yeah. Even course. And people, I think realize this. I've had a lot of people who over the course
of the lockdown told me that at first they would like watch the liturgy on a stream. And then they
stopped. It started just doing typical or prayer services themselves or with their family. Right.
And they found actually doing those prayer services far more fulfilling than just watching the
liturgy on a screen. Right. As a spectator. Yep. Yep. Right. And so this is, we talked last time
about how the news is the capacity through which we as humans image God. Right. That that
imaging takes place. And we talked about how what we choose to focus that point of focus on.
Right. Is is going to be transformative for us. Right. But there's also a liturgical shaping
that happens to us. And it happens in again through the news in the same noetic way.
But the ritual of the liturgy shapes us. And that's why in the Orthodox Church, we understand
that the liturgy worship ritual has to be completely inflexible. Right. Because to mold something,
the mold has to be completely firm. You can't mold jello with jello. Right. Right. If you try to
mold something with jello, the jello will be shaped to the thing. The thing will not be shaped to the
mold. And so if if liturgy and worship and ritual aren't inflexible, then that is exactly what
happens. We shape our worship to ourselves rather than the worship shaping us to it. And the worship
given by God shaping us to Christ, to God himself. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. And I mean,
we can't state this strongly enough because there are a lot of kinds of worship out there
that within particular traditions that have this idea, the tradition has this idea that it needs
to be constantly changed to sort of keep up with the times, for instance. But if worship is
supposed to shape you, but you're constantly shaping it, then all you get is worship that's shaped
like you. That's what you get. You know, it's not then going to do the work of cleansing your
news so you can apprehend spiritual reality. And, you know, worship should not be altered to
the times because then it doesn't do the work. And also frankly, you know, it can't just be changed
by issuing a decree. Let's just radically revamp it or, you know, cut this off or whatever it might
be. That's not the way that that's not the way that the worship that actually does this work
works. Right. Because again, then it's, then it's being, then it's subject to a human will.
Right. Now that's not to say, I mean, we could get this as a long rabbit trail potentially,
but that's not to say that like, for instance, I'm not claiming that the way that we worship in
all its exact details on Sunday morning in our church here in Emmaus is the exact way that the
apostles worship. That's not what I'm saying. You know, the liturgics have changed over time.
But, but not in any utterly radical or fundamental way. Right. The kinds of changes that have occurred
are not the thing that we're talking about now. You know, when, the problem is when someone
essentially says, we need to reenvision what worship is. That's when you have the problem or we need to
basically stop doing the tradition we've done for all these, you know, centuries and start something
else now. You know, that's the kind of problem that we're pointing out. Right. The zeitgeist
is a spirit that exists, but it's not the Holy Spirit. Yeah. You don't want to be in the spirit of
the times. I mean, I remember that another corny old saying from back in the day was, you know,
he who marries the spirit of the age will soon find himself a widower. You know, because
because it's constantly changing, you know, are you going to just keep getting married over and
over again to new spirits of the age, right? You know, yeah, yeah, it doesn't work. And beyond this,
we have in our head, there's another modern, right, Western Christian thing. We have this idea of
the two tables of the law, right? We have this idea, right, that, that, you know, there's these first
four commandments. That's like worship stuff. That's like God's stuff. And then there's these other ones
and they're like moral stuff. Yeah. Right. And so there's there's faith and morals,
right? And these are these sort of two different things. Yeah. So first of all, I'm inclined to point
out that they're, we're not actually, it's not that, you know, God could only fit four commandments
on the one tablet. And so he had to bleed over on to see attached sheets. Wait, wait, are you
saying Cecil B. Demille lied? Yes. Oh, man. Charlton Heston is a collaborator. No, even though
you'll Brenner is orthodox. Wow. It's true. You know, it's orthodox. It's not, it's not that, you know,
he still is. It's not that he's still alive. Actually, I haven't done well. Oh, okay. No, he's
buried at a monastery in France. That's right. That's right. He is. But he's still orthodox. That's
my point. Yes. Yes. Yes. So it's actually two copies. Right. That's where there's two tablets.
Yeah. That's why there's two tablets. But aside from that, right, there's also not this schism.
Right. The way that the scriptures see what we call morality is not detached from. It is the same
essentially as the way that they see worship as we were just talking about it, especially in
relationship to the news. Right. This is why you constantly see over and over again, and especially
emphasized in the New Testament, right? When Christ has asked what is the first and greatest
commandment, right? He gives two that some of all of them, one of them from Deuteronomy and one from
Leviticus. Love the Lord your God with all your heart, soul, mind and strength that we refer to
earlier. And the second is like it. Love your neighbor is yourself. Those go together. And St. John
and first John says he who says he loves God and hates his brothers a liar. Right. These two go
together. Right. These two always go together. Well, why? Well, we've talked about worship.
Worship is hospitality. Right. Right. And this showing of hospitality to God, especially in the
form of food, especially in the form of sacrifice, this showing of hospitality to God, this worship
we're talking about, this is part of what knowedically shapes us in the image of God and allows us to
image God. And because we understand that not just me, but every human person, every human person
who's ever lived is the image of God. Right. Then the hospitality that I show to that image
is the hospitality I'm showing to God in as much as you have done it to the least of these you have
done it to me. And those are all examples of the parable, the sheep of the goats of hospitality. Yeah.
Every single one of them. And so this is why you see over and over again in the fathers giving
alms, giving money to a poor person to help them as an act of worship of God. And though it's too
big of a rabbit hole to go into here. We'll do this in a future episode at some point. The fathers
are all very clear and they're getting it from the New Testament, the giving of alms, giving aid
to the poor, a tones for sin. How about that? There's a bunch of drop. Right. Because it cleanses, you
know, it cleanses that place, that person that cleanses you, you know. Right. Yeah. And the reason why
all of these things are ultimately acts of worship. Right. Like I know one of the one of the big
conversations surrounding our podcast is like, what exactly counts as worship? You know. But the
reason why all these things are acts of worship, as you said, it's this hospitality frame. But it's
because everything that you do fundamentally is a ritual in the sense that you're interacting with
reality. Right. So when you do the works of God, when you behave the way that God behaves, when you
do, you know, his works and creation, especially towards other people, that cleanses your news.
It allows you to have the apocalyptic experience seeing God, seeing spiritual reality more clearly.
Now, it's not going to be like an instant thing. Like, well, I gave alms yesterday. How come I can't see
that I have only hosts? You know, like that's not the way that it works. Right. But, but, you know,
because the people who have those kinds of experiences, it tends to be something that is formed in them
over a lifetime or in some cases, God chooses certain people to work through. Right. In a way that we
can't quite understand why or whatever. But, but that's what happens. And doing the opposite of that,
like, you know, not loving your neighbor as yourself, that darkens your news because you're
not behaving like God, you're not doing his works. And so then your ability to see spiritual
realities is going to be more limited. You know, there's some things that you can only understand
after, you know, a life of all of these things, worship, almsgiving, prayer, sacrificing your own
time yourself, your preferences, like all of these things, that that kind of knowledge only comes
through that kind of experience is not something you can get from simply hearing a lesson or reading a
book. Right. And that's why, frankly, you know, when, when, when, you know, if someone's going to
to be like a teacher, right, of theology, and they don't have this experience of struggling
in the Christian life, then while the words that they might use might be true, they're also
transmitting a darkness alongside it because they're functioning with a darkened
news because they have not done the work, you know. And that's something that everyone, I mean,
like, this is a warning to me, right? I'm, I'm, I'm a teacher, like, this is my task, you know,
so I need to be always struggling to do that. And I need to make sure I'm constantly being prepared,
and I need to make sure that I have that blessing for my bishop. And I, you know, I need to not check
out of the spiritual life, not check out of doing good works and provoking other people to do good works
as St. Paul puts it. Right. And, and like, make no mistake, the parable of the sheep and the goats
is apocalyptic. Yes. Right. This is not because it's happens at the end. Right. But what is,
what is the last judgment? Right. That's, we read it on the Sunday, the last judgment. What is the
last judgment? That's the day when everything is revealed. Right. That's the day. That's why you can
call that day the apocalypse. That's when everything is revealed. And what Christ reveals to those people
is when you met that man in the street and you told him he smelled bad and he should get a job
and he was a drunk and to get away from you, you were saying that to Christ. Right. And when you met
that man and you bought him some food to eat and you tried to help him and you were kind to him,
you were being kind to Christ. And you can't tell Christ to get away from you and call him names
and be disgusted by him in the street and then walk into a church and share a meal with him in the
Eucharist. Yeah. St. St. John Chrysostom says essentially almost exactly that. I think like something
like if you can't find Christ in the beggar at the door of the church, then you won't find him in
the chalice. Right. I'm paraphrasing. And so the keeping of the commandments, all of them, both
our worship and our lives. Right. This is what cleanses the news and allows us to see and understand
spiritual reality. And in the same way, when we fall into sin, our news is darkened and we become
less able to see what is happening and understand the spiritual reality that that underlies our life.
Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. So to wrap up, you know, one of the things that this conversation has really
helps to underline for me is how really everything is ritual. And I don't just mean that it's
everything is like ritual, right? It's not just a metaphor for, but it actually is like everything
that you do, you're interacting with reality, you're interacting. And because all of the material
interaction that you do has a spiritual aspect to it, that means everything that you do is
interacting with spiritual reality, right? We talk about reenchantment. And sometimes people think
of that in just in terms of like what you see. And certainly that's one of the elements and we've
been talking about that because episodes about apocalypse. But, but there's also this sense of
participation, the question of participation in the spiritual world, right? And it can be tempting
to want to have a greater awareness of the spiritual world or interaction with the spiritual world
in a quick and easy way, right? So we've talked for instance about people who get into the occult
or into psychedelic drugs, this kind of thing. And it's true, that takes you there very quickly,
right? But you're heading into it without having put on the whole armor of God.
You know, you're leaping off the cliff without a parachute or without wings or whatever metaphor,
you know, you know, I use. And there's a reason that the scripture does not ever provide a quick and
easy way to open the eye of the soul, the news, right? To apprehend spiritual reality. There's
no quick and easy way because it requires cleansing requires cleansing. So if you go with a darkened
news, you might receive some kind of spiritual reality, you know, my perceive or whatever. But it's
going to do something very bad. You know, we talked the last time about what that does, right?
You know, just a scripture says the the eye is the lamp of the soul. If you're full of light,
then you're going to be light. If you're full of darkness, then you can be darkness, right? But
where this comes down for every person is that this
this should lead us to understand that the Christian life is a holistic life. It's not a life that
has some spiritual things in it, you know, it's a holistic life that everything that you do,
every single thing you do is a spiritual act. Everything that you do is a ritualistic act.
A lot of our problems that we don't understand that that's true. We think that there are sort of
neutral acts or sort of non-religious things that we do. But there is no such thing. And the question
is not, am I going to do spiritual things today? The question is how how am I going to do the
spiritual things that I'm going to do today? So, you know, we're all going to eat food, right?
Am I going to eat food that is blessed by God because I asked him to? Or am I going to eat food
that I did not ask for God's blessing? And so it is a different kind of spiritual act. It's a
spiritual act, but it becomes a different kind of spiritual act, right? Again, there's no
neutral ground, no neutral ground. So the way that you wake up in the morning, the way that you
clean yourself, the way that you talk to your family, the way that you go to work, the way that you
do your work, the things that you look at, I mean, all on and on and on. It's not just a list of
sort of moral things, your moral or immoral, like you have plus or minus points on a moral scale.
It's that you are interacting constantly with spirituality and you can do it in a way that is going
to make you more like God, or you can do it in a way that's going to make you more like the demons.
I mean, this is one of our great themes. You know, everything is about everything.
We've emphasized apocalypse, particularly. And what I want people to walk away from this
episode with is a sense of the apocalypse of the ordinary. That actually does when we understand
that every ordinary moment is an apocalyptic moment is the ordinary then becomes for us
extraordinary. And by that, I don't mean supernatural. I mean that we begin to understand and to
interact with the whole of what reality is in a way that we can do it much more intentionally.
Because like I said, you're always interacting spiritually.
You cannot escape that because you are a being that has a spiritual element and the world
is creation that has spiritual elements. So everything that you do is spiritual. Right. So the question
is simply, am I doing it in a way that's like God or am I turning away from him and becoming like
the evil one? So, so that's my that's my encouragement for everyone is to seek the apocalypse of
the ordinary father. Yeah, so we gave earlier in the episode in act one sort of a very brief and very
oversimplified history of philosophy related to this. Yeah. And the reason for that
was it just to nerd out about it. But it was because we need to understand how we got to where we are.
Right. Sometimes I worry that the way I in particular talk about these things, including on this show,
they come off, especially in our current climate, political and cultural climate, as trying to
identify the bad guys. Right. Like 19th century Germans, bad guys. Some people might even hopefully
they don't, but some people might even think, you know, non-orthodox Christians somehow bad guys,
anybody low church bad guy. I'm saying these are bad guys. It's got nothing to do with that. Right.
It's about the actual history. Right. We're in a place. How did we get here? Right. Doesn't matter
who's to blame. We're all to blame. Plenty of blame to go around. I'm to blame as much as anybody.
But now we're here. And we've lost something. To be honest, we had it we had it taken from us
historically. Right. When the altars were stripped in Britain, that was top down.
The English reformation was not a move of the peak common people. It came top down. It was taken
away. And what you see after that in the whole and continuing in the whole Anglophone world,
what you see is an awareness at some level of what's been lost. That we've been reduced to
language, that that some element of noetic side of the spiritual has been stripped away. And it
comes out in all these weird ways. You have somebody like Sir Isaac Newton getting obsessed with
Alchemy and finding bizarre symbolism and structures in the book of Revelation. You have weird folk
remedies and cures and and what are essentially remnants of paganism and superstition cropping up
in puritan communities in the US who fled to have their totally pure English Calvinist religion.
Right. Have all of these things going on. And and relatively except just because they're part
of life. We are aware even when we want to deny it no matter how fiercely we want to deny it,
we're aware that the spiritual is there. We experience it all the time. And so it's going to come out
those unhealthy ways if we don't come up with a healthy approach. Right. And so Father Andrew just
talked about the the idea that these things have spiritual resonance, all the things we do in
our life. I'm going to come at it from the other angle. Right. We tend to try to pursue the spiritual
as spiritual. Right. That's what Sir Isaac Newton's Alchemy is. Right. We want visions. We want
experiences. We go out and we because we still got this bifurcation. We realize I have all this
I'm a materialist. I have this mindset. I need to get the spiritual back. And so we start just
pursuing purely spiritual experience in this sort of purely spiritual way. And there are folks
out there who bounce around from mysticism to mysticism and from you know meditative practice
to meditative practice. It's trying to chase after that experience. But since the reality is that
the spiritual underlies the material. The only way to get to the spiritual is through the material.
These always go together. This is why St. Paul says, you know, I can have all visions. I can speak
in the tongues of men and angels. I can have all gifts and prophesy. I can do all these things. And
if I don't have love, I'm nothing. I'm worthless. I'm garbage. It's pointless. Right. Love is the
way we approach these things. So if you want to get the spiritual back in your life and you want
to really get it the real thing, not the counterfeit, you want to get the real deal. Then the next time
you see it, you won't have to wait long. The next time you see someone who needs someone to smile
at them, smile at them. The next time you see someone who needs someone to talk to them or more
importantly listen to them, listen to them. The next time you see someone who needs help help
and you'll be amazed at how as you start doing those things, the spiritual starts to come alive for
you. You start to understand the world more. You're not going to go and find the spiritual on its
own and add it to the material you already have. But through love, you're going to draw close to God
and your news will begin to be cleansed. You'll get your mind right and you'll start to see
what it is that's been going on around you this whole time and you'll start to understand.
And that's also why St. Paul tells us in Hebrews that faith, which should be translated faithfulness,
is the substance of things hoped for. When we're faithful, all of a sudden, all of those hopes and
dreams, all of these things that we're just sort of believing by faith or intuition suddenly have
substance, suddenly become real to us. So that's my closing thought. There's a very practical
way to try to get back to where ancient people were. And it's not through esotericism or even
mysticism. It's through loving your neighbor in very real and very practical ways that every single
one of us can start doing right now if we really want to. Amen. Well, that is our show for tonight.
Thank you, everyone, for listening. If you didn't get a chance to call in during the live broadcast,
we'd love to hear from you, either via email at lordofspiritsnationfaith.com or you can message us
at our Lord of Spirits podcast, Facebook page. We do read everything but cannot respond to everything.
And we do say what you send for possible use in future episodes.
Join us for our live broadcast on the second and fourth Thursdays of the month at 7 p.m. Eastern 4 p.m.
Pacific. And if you are on Facebook, like our page and join our discussion group, leave reviews
and ratings everywhere, but most importantly, share this show with a friend whom you know is going to
love it. And if you're on Facebook, watch for what happens on my sister's birthday tomorrow.
Yes. And finally, be sure to go to ancientfaith.com,
stroke support, and help make sure we and lots of other AFR podcasters stay on the air.
Thank you very much and may God bless you.
You've been listening to The Lord of Spirits with Orthodox Christian priests,
Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen De Young, a listener-supported presentation
of ancientfaith radio. And I be held and I heard the voice of many angels round about the throne
and the beasts and the elders, and the number of them was 10,000 times 10,000
than thousands of thousands, saying with a loud voice, worthy is the land that was slain to receive
power and riches and wisdom and strength and honor and glory and blessing. Revelation,
chapter 5, verses 11-12. Welcome to the Thursday edition of The Path.
You're connected to The Path, offering strength for our journey towards salvation.
Here's Father Tom Soroka. Today's epistle reading is from St. Paul's