You will, and I offer myself as a sacrifice to thee.
You have said, O Lord, a man's mind plans his ways, but the Lord directs his steps.
Do not forsake me, O Lord, for I have put all my trust in thee.
I have no other desire than to fulfill thy will.
Teach me how to pray, pray thou thyself in me.
A prayer from Metropolitan Fillerette of Moscow on ancient faith radio.
He will be a staff, for the righteous with which for them to stand and not to fall,
and he will be the light of the nations, and the hope of those whose hearts are troubled.
All who dwell on the earth will fall down and worship him, and they will praise and bless,
and celebrate with song the Lord of Spirits.
The modern world doesn't acknowledge, but is nevertheless haunted by spirits, angels,
demons, and saints.
In our time, many year into break free of the prison of a flat, secular materialism,
to see and to know reality as it truly is.
What is this spiritual reality like?
How do we engage with it well?
How do we permeate everyday life with spiritual presence?
Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew Stephen Damick,
and Father Stephen De Young host this live Colin show focused on enchantment in creation,
the union of the scene and unseen as made by God and experienced by mankind throughout history.
Welcome to the Lord of Spirits.
Good evening, and welcome back to the Lord of Spirits podcast.
My co-host Father Stephen De Young is with me from Lafayette, Louisiana,
and I'm Father Andrew Stephen Damick in Emmaus, Pennsylvania.
And if you're listening to us live, you can call in 855 AF radio.
That's 855-237-2346.
John is going to be taking your calls tonight,
and we'll get to your calls in the second part of today's show.
So the Lord of Spirits podcast is brought to you by our listeners.
That's you with help from St. Athanasius Academy of Orthodox Theology.
St. Athanasius is an online academy for K-12 offering live classrooms and core subjects for
languages, various electives, and Orthodox studies.
To learn more about St. Athanasius Academy, please visit www.saot.edu.
And I talked to Deacon Adam again over, St. Athanasius Academy.
And he wanted people to know because those photos the paparazzi took got out
of him at Tiffany's.
And he wanted me to assure everyone that despite those pictures,
he is not using St. Athanasius tuition money to buy an engagement ring for J-Lo.
There we go.
So you don't have to worry about it.
Yeah, yeah, especially since he's already married.
So tonight, we're going to be talking about St. John the Foreigner and Baptist.
Before we get to that, though, I just wanted to say thank you to all of the physicists.
And the many more people who wrote and said,
I'm not a physicist, but who filled us in more on the details of what happens to matter,
both biological and inert in response to our previous episode, which was on relics.
And your emails actually confused me so much that I called my big brother on the phone.
He's a chemical engineer and he explained everything to me very, very thoroughly,
very interesting. So, you know, we don't claim to be physicists, biologists, chemists,
though, thank God. So even though we might have gotten a few of the details last time,
a bit off, the point, though, is about what matter has to do with being. That's the important thing.
So thank you very much for all those emails.
All right, well, let's talk about the one who is being the Foreigner of Jesus Christ in John the Baptist
that enigmatic figure who has prophesied in the Old Testament and is the last of the prophets.
In classic Lord of Spirits podcast fashion, we're going to go back first, though in this case,
we're not headed all the way back to Genesis. I know it's a big shock, everybody,
but rather back to the books of kings. And we're not talking first about the last of the prophets,
but rather the prophet that is sort of the prophet, the paradigmatic prophet. And that is the prophet Elijah.
So, Father Stephen, why is Elijah the paradigmatic prophet? Well, that's easy to say.
Paradigmatic prophet. Lots of hard consonants. We're going well. We're going well tonight.
Too many vowels for Welsh. Too many vowels for Welsh. And we are indeed varying up our usual format.
Yes, that is true, just to touch this evening. Well, in a couple of ways. So we need to prepare people.
Okay, people don't like change. A lot of them are orthodox, right? They don't want things to change
at all. But yeah, we're only starting with with with Elijah. So we're still in the first millennium
BC, which is a rarity. And also, though people might be expecting this now, we're not going to
spend the first act running through prophethood in the ancient Near East, right? And the earliest
problem. Though at some point, we probably will in some other future episode. Mark that on your
bingo card future episode. But we're starting with with Elijah and Elijah or St. Elias or Elias or
Louis, if you're French speaking, is a is the paradigmatic prophet not just in the sense that
well, this is this is the prophet we have a lot of information about or a lot of other prophets
look like him or act like him. But in the way, first and foremost, that he's treated by the text of
the Old Testament. Yeah. So, I mean, so why isn't Moses the, I mean, if someone just threw that out
me, who's the paradigmatic prophet, I would probably have guessed Moses. Why isn't Moses the one?
You could make a good argument for Moses in the sense that, you know, you have the prophecy of a
prophet like Moses in Deuteronomy, right? But Moses has a different role than most of the later
prophets. And I don't want to go too far down this rabbit trail. But Moses at the beginning of his
calling is actually sort of a prophet, a priest in a king all it wants. Yeah, right. And part of that
gets taken away from him. And that's a whole other discussion. So, when we're talking about
Moses as a paradigm, it's usually Moses as a type of Christ himself.
The law giver, right? Whereas when we're talking about who sets a standard for prophethood as such,
and we're going to see a lot of ways as we go on. But it begins with how he's treated in the text
because we sometimes take for granted or haven't thought about the fact that the story
of Elijah and Elijah, who we're also going to talk about tonight, that story is in the
is in the books of the kings. Neither of them are kings, right? So these books, first and second
Samuel, and first and second kings, or first through fourth kingdoms if you're in the Orthodox study
Bible, are very clearly written by the same person. But they completely change format
in order to tell us the stories of Elijah and Elijah. So, let me just suggest we've got an
insertion from some other author. No, because they're very clearly written by the same author.
Stylistically. Stylistically. And everything they match up. And they're part of the overall
arc of the story that's being told. But you get the story of Samuel, the story of David,
or which leads to the story of Saul, which leads into David, Solomon, then you get the divided
kingdoms and the books of the kings. And you have these lists of the kings, a few things about them,
whether they're good or bad or few stories. There's this rhythm that gets set up. And then all of a
sudden, once you get past Omri to his son, Ahab, all of a sudden, that pattern breaks. And it's
now we're going to follow the prophet Elijah and then the prophet Elijah. And then after Elijah,
it goes back to that previous rhythm. Yeah, which kind of suggests that God is sort of
following the kings. And then because the king becomes a complete jerk,
then you know, I can say those kinds of things about him. And then, you know, the focus then is
on the man of God, who is the leader of the people effectively. Right, right. And there are other
prophets, most of the other writing prophets are alive somewhere in the time covered by that narrative.
And a few of them are briefly mentioned, like Jonah is briefly mentioned in second kings.
Right. But nothing really about it. Just he has this bare mention. So it's not just like,
well, I'm writing about kings, but I really wish I was writing about prophets,
darn it. Right. And so he sees this opportunity. But he feels the need to tell these stories
of Elijah and Elijah in detail. And so that can then be seen as, okay, here's sort of the sin
quanon of prophethood. So when I talk about someone else who is a prophet, this is the kind of thing
I'm talking about. From the perspective of the, what we call now the historical books, right,
that they're the ones holding this up as, as here's the pattern of the prophets life. And most of
the books that we call the prophets now don't have tons and tons of details of the prophets life.
Yeah, it's mostly just that's, you know, thus say at the Lord. And then whatever it is that the
prophet had to deliver. Right. And there'll be a little bit of a narrative frame enough to tell you
sort of when it happened and what was going on and who the prophet was talking to, right, that kind
of thing. But, or if the prophet was doing some prophetic action that accompanied what he said.
But you don't get this kind of detailed narrative of the lives of other prophets. Yeah. Yeah, I mean,
these are in some, some sense, these very much look like scenes lives. Right. Yeah. Yeah. And they,
they, they become the life of Moses and the life of Elijah really become sort of the paradigms for
that. The life of David becomes sort of the paradigms for how that's done later on for the saints.
And even in extra biblical literature, the Old Testament, we're actually going to reference this
later on in act three. But what one of the older pieces of post for century AD Jewish tradition,
we have is a work called the lives of the prophets. And that is very much following this kind of
paradigm in talking about the, the other prophets of Israel who don't have those biographical details
in, in the Hebrew Bible itself. But so when we encounter Elijah, as we mentioned, it's within the
context of this feud with Ahab, right. Right. And that's because even though there's very little
about him in the Bible, archaeologically speaking, in terms of material history, the most important
king of the northern kingdom of Israel was Omri. Yeah. Right. And Omri was so important that the
neighboring nations referred to the northern kingdom of Israel as big Omri, the house of Omri,
pretty much until its destruction, for the time of Omri until it was destroyed. Even though
it wasn't actually his dynasty anymore after it was still referred to as the house of Omri because of
how he expanded it, built up its military, his building projects. The main one of those building
projects is that he actually built the capital of the northern kingdom. He bought the hill on which
to build some, the city of Samaria that was the capital of the northern kingdom. Right. And yet
in the Bible, he gets what like one verse, two verses, six. He gets six. Six verses, excuse me.
A couple of which are talking about him buying that hill. And the rest of which are saying
when he was born, how old he was when he died, that he was wicked. And the rest of the stuff he did
is in the annals. That's pretty much all we get about him. But his son is Ahab. And so another
of the things that he did in turn of building up the northern kingdom of Israel's status and power
in the world was formal alliances with his neighbors. One of those neighbors was the Phoenicians
who were who's civilization at this time was centered around Tyre and Sidon. And so
Lebanon. Yeah. Yeah. What's now modern. Modern Lebanon. Yeah. Right.
And so he marries his son Ahab to the daughter of the king of Sidon, namely Jezebel,
who has now become infamous with everyone, even if you've never read the Bible in your life.
Right. And so she brought with her her religion. Yeah. Right. Yeah. So she's a bail
worshiper. It's it's our old friend bail. I'm still looking forward to that bail book father.
Yes. It's down the road of peace. Yeah. Yeah. One book at a time. Yeah. So she brings in bail
worship. And and this is a major interesting point. She kills a whole bunch of the prophets of
Yahweh, the God of Israel. And you know, it's basically, you know, religious, ethnic cleansing
so to speak, right? You know, eliminate the the religious leaders from the previous religion,
bring in her own prophets that promote the worship of bail. And you know, the idea is to
essentially to convert the northern kingdom of Israel to bail worship. You know, there it is
at the royal court. I mean, this is the way it tends to go in history, right? You know, the
the royals convert and then eventually the the rest of the country kind of follows suit. And
I mean, it seems from what's written in the scripture that most people up there go ahead and
join the king and queen in their bail worship, right? Right. Most people are doing it. And we have
to remember before this, right? So before the own ride dynasty, the the worship in the northern
kingdom was already not in a great place, right? Yeah, right. Right. They were already kind of
verging on idolatry and engaging in some idolatry. Well, full on idol. Yeah. Jeroboam,
sort of Nebath, who was the first king of the northern kingdom as a separate kingdom of the 10
tribes, didn't want people making pilgrimage to the temple in Jerusalem. So he kept at least in name
the worship of Yahweh, but he built the two shrines at Bethel and Dan, which were at the extreme
north and extreme south of the northern kingdom. And he put golden calves there that were supposed to
be Yahweh. And we've talked before about how idolatry works, right? It's full on. That was it.
And then that was in addition to high places and shrines for other gods that he allowed to exist.
Yeah. So what Jezebel is doing is not just like, oh, hey, I want to add in mind to the mix,
right? That that mix was already going on. This was a deliberate attempt to bring the northern
kingdom under the religious and cultural and political because these things were separate.
Right? Hegemony of the Phoenicians, right? To essentially make the Israel, the northern Israelites
into Phoenicians into one of the nations and just gather them cease being Israel.
Yeah, and so it is like you said ethnic cleansing is really what it is, right? It was trying to
destroy this people as a people and make them and do another people. And we're told she murdered
hundreds of Yahweh's prophets, right? Because as you might imagine, you know, the Levites who are
working at these high places, at these shrines in Bethel and Dan were not sort of super strident
fundamentalists about northern kingdom worship, right? If they had been, they would have moved
back to Judah and gotten to the temple. Yeah, they were already compromisers and collaborators with
pagan rituals. Right. And so the whole doubts were trying to rally the people against this pagan
worship and against following the edicts of Ahab and Jezebel are the prophets. Yeah. And among them,
Elijah has this sort of forefront role. Yeah. Right. Right. So the whole this whole battle ends up
becoming between Elijah and Ahab who Ahab is portrayed as exceedingly weak and it's essentially
between Elijah and Jezebel. Right. He was kind of making the pronouncements and doing her bidding.
Yeah. Yeah. And yeah. Go ahead. I was just going to say, you know, just to kind of, I mean,
we talked about Bale lots of times, but just as a, you know, to remind everybody, Bale is depicted as a
storm god. He's a thunder god, right? You know, he's the one who brings lightning and rain. And
you know, as we've talked before, his story says that he sets himself up as the, he's installed a new
most high god who is his father L up on the divine council. And then he rules the divine council
directly himself. So this is the one that they're worshiping and the one that they're trying to
assimilate the northern kingdom to, right? Is this this storm god, this usurper? Right. He's a
cloud rider is one of his titles. Yeah. And we've talked before about how that imagery and stuff gets
gets taken in the Old Testament and applied, applied instead to to Yahweh to say no, it's Yahweh
who does this. Right. And so, so this is going to be where sort of the rubber meets the road.
Right. So what what Yahweh the god of Israel is going to do is through Elijah, he's going to
demonstrate to Ahab Jezebel and all the people of the northern kingdom who he is and who Bale
isn't. Yeah. Right. Yeah. And yeah. And you know, one of the cool ways that it kind of starts out
is the contrast between Elijah and the, the royals, right? So they're living, you know, in luxury,
right? Controlling everything. And where is Elijah? He's out in the Kidron Valley, right? He lives
by himself out in the wilderness. He lives next to this brook, a little river. And he's fed there
by Ravens, which you had a cool textual thing that we talked about in our notes. It's not super
important, everybody, but you're just going to sort of love this. So yeah, fed by Ravens. Yeah,
fed by Ravens is the way that most people understand what it says in scripture. But there are those
who actually say that it doesn't say Ravens and instead say what? So yeah, some of our, some of our
modernist friends, like our 19th century German friends at all, somebody being fed by birds,
that's ridiculous, right? No one could believe that birds are bringing him food. So they say that
based on a similarity in the consonants, they say, oh, well, that word has the wrong vowel
points, right? Because of course, when you write Hebrew in most Semitic languages, you don't write
the vowels. Yeah, right? And so later in the medieval period, they went and added vowels to the
Old Testament. They say, oh, well, they did it wrong. What it really says is that Arabs came and brought
him food, which, so that's as apparently a lot more believable that Arabs just came along every
so often and supplied Elijah with food out there at the Kidron Valley. Yes, just wandered by.
Because birds are ridiculous. Yes, birds are ridiculous. Yeah, and so he's out there
wearing, you know, camel hair and even his in the Hebrew, his dialogue is pretty curt and stunted.
There's a lot of, we see a lot of the writing profits, like it, Isaiah and Jeremiah and Ezekiel,
these kind of eloquent speeches and imagery and all of this, that's not Elijah, right? Yeah.
St. Eliza is, is it into that? So when he first comes wandering into the royal court to confront
Ahab, he basically says the equivalent of ain't going to rain no more. Right? Rain stopping. Yeah, no more rain.
Drops just drops that. Mike drops and walks back out. And that's it. And he leaves. And it stops raining for years.
So he's just informing them, right? It's not going to rain anymore. Now this, this already is a display,
right? Because the fact that Elijah comes and announces it as the prophet of Yahweh means
Yahweh is the one who's not sending the rain, right? And the whole purpose of worshipping bail,
right? Well, there were two purposes of worshipping bail as a storm god. The first one was
to get him to send the rains in their seasons. And the second one was to ward off like destructive
storms. Yeah, right. Those were the keep him happy, right? He gave you the rain you wanted and he
didn't give you this storm and lightning that you didn't want. Yeah, because because idolatry is
essentially a kind of spiritual technology. Keep the god happy. And this is what, well, he's really
good at this. So he'll do this thing for us. And Elijah making it or from Ahab's point of view,
Elijah making it stop raining. What that really does is it says, yeah, this guy doesn't
actually have control of the rain, right? You know, yeah, yeah. Because they're still out there
at the high places and at the shrines of it, they're doing the sacrifices. Yeah, they're doing the
rituals. They're doing the stuff. They're reading the guts of the animals. They're doing, I mean,
not to get too dark, but we got to be honest, they're shrines to Molek at this point. They're sacrificing
children and rain still isn't coming. Yeah, it's not working. Right. And it's discredited. So
this already is a display, right? So that's sort of the beginning, right? And of course, we're more
familiar with the culmination of that sort of showdown, right? What happens about karma?
Mount Carmel, right? And, you know, this was always one of my favorite stories in Sunday school.
I mean, I love this so much. I named my first son Elias. So that's pretty much the reason why.
Yeah. So for those of you who don't remember this from Sunday school, what Elijah does is he
proposes a showdown, right? Basically, a kind of prophetic duel of sorts and says, okay, I'm
going to set up an altar to my God over here. You guys, you set up your altar to bail, and you put
your bull on your altar, and I'll put my bull on my altar, and you guys, you can call down
fire from heaven. That's what it says in the scripture, fire from heaven. You just pray to your God,
and, you know, and if he sends it, then everybody will know that bail is our God, bail is God,
right? But if my God sends it, then everyone will know that Yahweh is God. And so the prophets of
bail, they set it all up, and they, you know, dance and circles around it and they call out to bail,
and they cut themselves with knives because apparently that's part of their ritual. And nothing
happens. And then this is the point where St. Elijah proves that he is the patron saint of
sarcasm, and he begins to mock them, very ecumenical move on the largest part. He begins to mock
bail, actually, he mocks the demon from our point of view, and says, you know, well, maybe he's
odd on a trip, maybe he's somewhere relieving himself, you know, he's on vacation, call out louder,
you know, maybe he's hard of hearing, but still nothing happens. And then after that,
after that failure on the bail prophets part, then Elijah says, okay, I want you guys to bring
a bunch of water and soak my sacrifice with water and pour it all over the altar, and he digs,
you know, they dig a trench around it, and they fill that with water too. And Elijah prays to God and
says, essentially show them that you're God, and then God sends the fire from heaven. And it
despite all the water consumes the sacrifice, consumes the wood, and even dries up all the water
that's in the moat around the altar. And all the people standing by say, Yahweh is God. And
it's a really embarrassing moment for for a ab and Jezebel and for those prophets. So that's
the summary of the showdown, very much worth reading, just great, great. But yeah, so fire from
heaven, is that like a big swirling thing of fire going, you know, like I've always seen that in
the comic books and stuff and the pictures and the flannel graph, you know, swirling flames like
a small tornado of fire. Is that, is that what we're talking about? Yeah. And yeah, and I'm about
to ruin your Sunday school, man. But yeah, and in fact, with when I was in seventh grade, we did,
we did a student film of this event. Oh, and special effects for the, yes, for the climax,
we got some GI Joe's and wrapped them up in toilet paper like robes and then had them like standing
around a little paper altar that we got a can of WD 40 and a lighter off camera. And we like zoom
in and like and flame the whole thing. And then we did like the slow zoom on like the melting GI
Joe face to do like great value Raiders of the Lost Ark. Please tell me you still have the VHS from
I do not. But yeah, so that was the best we could do on our budget, which was nothing. So, but
in actuality, in actuality, if you read the bail cycle, for example, or the bail cycle,
uh, bail is the one who sends fire from heaven. But what that's referring to is lightning.
It's the thunderbolt. Yeah. Right. Because of course, they didn't have the concept of electricity.
That's the bail fire. So fire. Yeah, fire, fire from the sky. Um, fire from heaven. So that's
what it's actually talking about. The thunderbolt was sort of the symbol of bail's power and some of
the bail statues we have, uh, uncovered. He's holding a thunderbolt. And you see that was Zeus too.
And with other storm gods. Right. Right. Right. That's that's the symbol of their power.
And, uh, so the idea that, you know, hey, tries you might you can't get him to send it. Right. But
it's actually Yahweh, the God of Israel, who has that power, who has the right, right? Who is,
who is able to do that? Right. That's then, uh, and the conclusion here, we usually leave off there.
But what happens immediately after that is two things. Uh, number one, uh, the prophet Elijah leads
them to go and kill a few hundred of the prophets of bail. Right. Uh, which is,
is distributive justice. Right. Yeah. Jezebel had gone out and murdered had murdered hundreds of
Yahweh's prophets. Right. And this is not just directed at Jezebel. Right. Because Jezebel is serving
bail. So in the same way that you get at the time of the Exodus. Right. Remember what the Egyptians had
done? They had gone and murdered all of the Israelite male infants. Right. And so when the judgment comes,
God announces that that 10th plague, the Passover, is his judgment on the gods of Egypt.
And so the gods of Egypt then lose their children. In the same way, bail now loses his prophets.
Yeah. I mean, this is, this is spiritual warfare. God against a rebellious angel, you know, a demon.
And, you know, if you don't, if you don't recall that act that Jezebel did on behalf of bail,
then this always just seems like a really kind of vindictive, awful thing for Elijah to do.
But again, if we believe that he is truly a prophet of God, which if we believe in the integrity
of scriptures, then we believe that. And that means that the things that he does are on behalf of God.
So when he takes out these bail prophets, he's not just doing it because he's trying to, you know,
he just wants to kill him or whatever. It's God's response to this action that Jezebel had done
earlier. Yeah. So that happens. And then also it begins to rain. Yes. Right. And it pours.
Yeah. That's about raining for years. Yeah. Because because God has the rain. It's not with bail.
The lightning's not with bail. Like this is about shaming bail. It's about utterly humiliating bail
in front of everyone so that they won't worship him. You know, because why would you worship a powerless
God? Right. And so Elijah's ministry, this central portion of Elijah's ministry is a prophet.
He is basically serving as an officer in spiritual warfare. Right. That's sort of literally what he's
doing. And so he's sort of one of the officers, right? If you think about the, we're going to talk
about this more in a minute, but if you think about the heavenly host as a host as an army,
right? Elijah's sort of, even though he's a human, is an officer, sort of an officer in that army
already in what he's doing and how he's operating in his life. And then if you're familiar with
another prophet Elijah story, and it's I don't know, how common do you think it is at Orthodox
churches that it great vespers for the prophet St. Elias? They actually read all three old
Testament readings in Toto. I think that's usually, I think they're usually
abridged a little bit. Although, I mean, I feel like the last time we did it that I read
rather long bits. So it's chapters and chapters. Yeah, yeah, you basically get, you basically get,
you know, kind of the highlights of the whole of his whole story. You know, the major, the major
events. But so you, if you, if you remember another story, it's, it's probably right after this,
and it's usually portrayed as prophet Elijah's at this real high and that he has this low. Yeah,
he's all bummed out of the wilderness. Yeah. Right. That's not really what's happening here. That's
not really what's happening here. I won't go into the whole thing right now. Well, maybe we'll
have another time to do that. But the the the the offening element of what happens. But
what's important here for our topic tonight is that at the conclusion, God tells him
that Elijah is not actually alone. He's not the last one left who's following
who's still faithful to Yahweh. He's not the last faithful one. But there are 10,000,
right? And we shouldn't think that that's a precise number, right? Yeah. The idea is it's 10
myriad, right? There's a whole bunch. Yeah, there's a lot. Yeah, who have not as as and the
lay in the line is have not bowed the knee to bail. You know, it's it's the the faithfulness to God
exists expressed explicitly in terms of not engaging an idolatry. Yeah. And
this little story while we look at it as sort of this vignette where Elijah gets bummed out
and God encourages him, like, no, you're not alone Elijah, right? This though in terms of the
scriptures becomes crucially important. Yeah. This idea that that no matter how bleak and how bad
things get, what God is doing throughout the history of the Old Testament is preserving
and refining and purifying a remnant for himself. Yeah. That it's never about all of Israel is saved,
all of Israel is blessed, all of Israel is is following Yahweh all the time. It cracks me up
so much when people with PhDs in Old Testament say, well, hey, we found this archaeological evidence
that Israel was worshiping God's other than Yahweh. So apparently, the Bible's wrong.
Have you heard the Bible? Yeah. Yeah. Have you read the Old Testament that you have a PhD in?
The Bible says they were hours, right? So wow. Yeah. So the idea is that there was this
remnant, right? And that's what God was about, and that's what he was doing, that the whole project
of the Old Testament was to create and preserve and refine this remnant. And again,
someday, when we do our second episode of the Theotokos, we'll get into how the church is
understanding of the Theotokos builds on that as well. But St. Paul then, probably the most famous
place that this is appealed to, is by St. Paul and Romans 9 through 11. I'll drop it a sorry
Calvinist now, but where St. Paul addressing the fact that most of the Judeans of his day
who were seen as right, the because the Old Testament prophets picked up in this idea of a remnant,
your average Pharisee saw himself and said, well, we're that remnant,
they identified themselves with that remnant, right? We are the remnant who's come through and survived
and been purified. Yeah, which ironically, like, like, no, you guys are the establishment. Yeah.
Yeah, well, and that's what that's what, what St. John the four-ruttered Christ are always telling them.
Yeah. Because you're not the remnant. You're the priest at Bethel and Dan. You're the,
that's who you are. You're the religious adulterers. Yeah, you've wrongly identified yourself
in this story. But so they see themselves, but St. Paul is addressing, well, most of this, what was
claiming to be the remnant, most of that did not accept Jesus as the Messiah when he came.
Right. How's that work? And his answer ultimately, and we will go, you know, we can spend the rest of the
night on this. But the answer he gives in Romans 9 through 11 ultimately is, why would it be any
different now than it has been throughout the history of Israel? Yeah. Where it was just this remnant.
And he says, and there is this remnant that is faithful to Yahweh because they're faithful to Christ.
Right. And you know, for me, there is a, there is an immediate kind of pastoral application to that.
And even, you know, whether you're in pastoral ministry or not, you know, like one thing,
probably a lot of pastors have noticed is, wow, you know, most of the people I work with kind of
don't do the things that I advise them to do. There's only this handful that are actually really on
board, right? And, you know, but even if you're not a priest or a pastor and just kind of like looking
at the world and thinking, oh man, look at the world, it's so awful. You know, this is the narrative
that has always been. I'm not saying that there aren't lower and higher times in history,
there definitely are. There are definitely times and places where things are worse than they have
been at other times. But like, this is actually the norm. The norm is that most are not following God
truly and faithfully. But there is always this remnant. And the application for the individual is
not to say, oh, I'm the remnant. The application is to say, okay, I need to go be, I need to be part
of the remnant. I need to be faithful because I'm not as faithful. I'm not faithful in the way that I
should be. So, so yeah, I mean, this is this is one of these things that if you, if you misidentify
yourself, then it can become a kind of sectarian impulse. But if you realize, like, no way, I need to
apply this to myself. I'm the sinner. I'm the sinner. Then, then you've got it right. Yeah.
Right. And, and by the way, especially to our orthodox listeners, this is true of church history,
yeah, totally, just like King David, sort of the paradigmatic king committed some awful
sins. So did St. Constantine. Yeah. That doesn't make him not a saint, right? But that the fact that
he's a saint doesn't mean he didn't do those things, right? Just like with David. And just like
almost all of the kings of Israel and Judah were wicked men, almost all of the Byzantine
emperors and almost all of the Zars were wicked men. There are a few here there who are really righteous
and holy, right? Most of the Byzantine emperors are not saints. Yeah. And I mean, and you know,
even frankly, you know, not that we're trying to condemn everybody or whatever, but like there's a
reason that, for instance, St. Gregory the theologian said, flee the reunions of bishops. I kind of
want to have anything to do with with all with my fellow bishops. Like, well, there must be a problem
there, you know, if if a saint says that about his own time and place, there was, but there was
always a remnant. Yeah. Yeah. There was always a remnant every every in the new theologian. Yeah,
right. Right. There's there's always a remnant. And that remnant was not sitting around cursing
everyone else. No. And talking about how everyone else was in apostate and just condemning everyone
else. That remnant was busy being faithful to God. Yeah. So if you're one of those folks seem to
be a lot of them on the internet who are convinced that 90% of the Orthodox churches corrupt, you know,
we won't argue about numbers, but you need to find them that other 10%. You need to go find the
remnant, the faithful people, the faithful Christians. Yeah. And you need to get with them and get
on board with them and be faithful yourself. Yeah. They're they're not going to be the ones, you know,
cursing everybody else. Yeah. That is not the remnant. Yeah. Sorry. Okay. So the last major,
you know, Elijah event is the, you know, the sort of succession, right, where yeah, the handoff,
where it's time for Elijah to go and to be with God. And it's I mean, he doesn't he doesn't die,
right? He gets taken up in a chair to fire. Yeah. He gets taken up in a chair to fire.
And this also says a lot of interesting things about what it means to be, you know, as we said,
the paradigmatic profit, right? And so, you know, one of the things that we talked about in our
prep for this is a passage from Jeremiah 23, which talks about the sort of the mark of the true
profit, right? And I just want to read this. So this is from this is from Jeremiah. And this is
what he has to say, for who among them has stood in the counsel of the Lord to see and to hear his
word or who has paid attention to his word and listened, behold, the storm of the Lord,
wrath has gone forth, a whirling tempest, it will burst upon the head of the wicked. The anger of
the Lord will not turn back until he is executed and accomplished the intense of his heart. And the
latter days you will understand it clearly. I did not send the prophets yet they ran. I did not
speak to them yet they prophesied, but if they had stood in my counsel, then they would have proclaimed
my words to my people and they would have turned them from their evil way and from the evil of their
deeds. So the point of this is Jeremiah is making a contrast between false prophets and true
prophets. And he says the true prophets are the ones who stand in the counsel of the Lord to see and
to hear the word. And he also says that they stand in the counsel and they proclaim his word
to the people so that they would turn away from their evil ways, right? So that's what Jeremiah says
that the prophet is one who's in the divine counsel and who is a messenger of the divine counsel,
right? And you see that very clearly with you look at the call of the prophet Isaiah and he comes
before the throne of God. And there's a who shall we send to make this announcement? He famously
says here I am send me, right? He stands in the counsel or becomes a messenger for the counsel.
And the prophet Ezekiel, Jeremiah, in his call, and he says here, and by the way, if you haven't
read religion, the Apostles yet, this is what happens with St. Paul on the road to Damascus.
Yes, right? Right. Yeah. So he says he's been sent with a message by Christ himself.
And so this makes sense then with the way the Elijah goes because what's happening is he's
being taken up into the divine counsel very very visually like you it's not just okay he's dying and
now we believe he's like it's it's quite literally happening before the eyes of Elijah, you know,
that this chariot takes him up. And of course what's the whole point of the chariot? This is this is
the image of the the mobile throne of God, which is everywhere. So he's being taken up up by the
throne of God, so to speak. Right. And and God's throne is a chariot because it's mobile. The whole
counsel is mobile, right? When you when you get to Daniel and when Daniel's standing in the divine
counsel again, thrones are set. Yeah, right. And and the counsel is seated around the the the throne
of God. So yes, so this is this is one of those throchards coming to get Elijah so that he can now be
permanently permanently there. Right. Right. But he's already been sort of acting as we saw in this
whole spiritual warfare. He's already been sort of an officer in the the heavenly hosts. He's already
sort of been serving in this role. But now is the time for him to go there permanently. And you see
him still serving in that counsel role on Mount Tabor at the transfiguration, right? That's why it's
that's why when St. Elias and and Moses appear with Christ, it says that they're conferring amongst
themselves. Yeah. Right. It's just counsel function. Right. And that's that's the idea. That's what they're
that's why it says that they're talking. They're not like exchanging pleasantries. Right. Okay. What you've
been doing since you or yeah, philosophical ideas or something, right? That's what that's what this
is, right? This is and what it's meant to show us. So and we know that this wasn't I mean, we're
going to get way more detail here in a second into this transition from Elijah to Elijah, but we
know that Elijah had the same experience from the whole incident with his servant, Gahazi,
right? Where they're facing and invading army and Elijah's servant Gahazi is terrified. And so
Elijah prays that Gahazi's eyes are open to see the heavenly host to see the angelic beings arrayed
around them, protecting them. But the reason of the text that Elijah was afraid is that he already
saw them. Yeah, which means he's kind of in the divine counsel all the time, even while walking around
on this earth because he sees them out there. You know, he sees that the hosts of heaven are also
present. You know, he sees the bigger army, the more powerful army, which Gahazi can't see.
So Elijah has to ask his eyes be open to see that. Right. And that's why this way of life, the way
of life that we see with the prophets and the Old Testament that we're going to see with St. John
the Forerunner begins to be referred to as the angelic life, right? It's not just like it's a
angelic life because they're superhuman or because they're not married or yeah, no, it's they live
with they're basically they live with the angels. And you know, like how many hymns do we have in our
liturgical tradition that talk about saints as being companions with the angels? Like that's
everywhere. Like almost every single day the manan has something about that particular saint being
a companion of the angels or dancing with the angels or you know, there's this there's this
equal to the angels idea just like the Lord says and Luke 20. Yeah. Right. And so this is this is the
means by which this happens is the spirit. And and it's particularly connected with worship,
right? Worship is being in the spirit. So the beginning of the book of Revelation say John is in
the spirit, meaning he's worshipping on the Lord's day. And as he's worshipping, he sees,
right, Christ walking among the candlestands that are there in the church. Yeah, right. I think a
lot of times when people see that in the spirit, they're like, oh, we went into a trance, you know
or something like that. But but you know, like you said, there's this indication that it's a
liturgical experience. Yeah. And so this then is what is continued in the church as the
monastic way of life. Yeah. Right. Because who live in the church who live in worship. Right. Yeah.
Because there's you know, there's these Old Testament communities of prophets. Right. Right.
Who are basically living in this way. I mean, it's not going to look exactly like, you know,
modern monasticism, but the essence of it is the same. Right. And that's where Elisha goes after
the transition after he receives the mantle from that we're going to talk about that more in a
second. But as he was after he receives the mantle from Elijah, he goes to the community of the
prophets. Right. To begin his measure. But that community had existed a long time before that.
Right. Yeah. I mean, monasticism is not invented in the fourth century or whatever. Right. But
these these prophetic communities go way back to one of the craziest passages. Yes. In the story of
David. Right. Yeah. I you pointed this out to me the other day. I'm like, I don't remember this
from Sunday school. Okay. So first Samuel 19, this would be what first kingdoms, if you're looking
at the Orthodox study Bible. Yeah. Yeah. First Samuel 19 versus 18 through 24. This is part of the
David and Saul story. I'm just going to read this. Now David fled and escaped. And he came to Samuel
at Rema and told him all that Saul had done to him. And he and Samuel went and lived at Nihoth.
And it was told Saul, behold, David is at Nihoth and Rema, then or Rama. I'm not sure the correct
pronunciation but then Saul sent messengers to take David. And when they saw the company of the
prophets prophesying and Samuel standing as head over them, the spirit of God came upon the
messengers of Saul and they also prophesied when it was told Saul he sent other messengers and
they also prophesied and Saul sent messengers again the third time and they also prophesied.
Then he himself went to Rema and came to the great well that is in Seiku and he asked where are
Samuel and David. And one said, behold, they're at Nihoth and Rema. And he went there to Nihoth and
Rema and the spirit of God came upon him also. And as he went, he prophesied until he came to Nihoth
and Rema and he too stripped off his clothes and he too prophesied before Samuel and lay naked all
that day and all that night. Thus it is said is Saul also among the prophets. Again, I've never seen
a flannel graph of that. I think that story self explanatory, don't you? Yeah, there's something
about being at that spot like you go there, you know, the spirit of God is going to sort of take
you and it even does this with with Saul. Right because because what we see here is Samuel
standing as chief among them. So Samuel is there leading this community of prophets, this prophetic
community in worship. Yeah, he's like their abbot or bishop effectively. And so what's happening is
they have this worship going on in the spirit. And every messenger who Saul says to come down there
right is is sort of seized by it. Yeah. Right. And it's up joining in and staying. Right. So a sort of
modernization of this would be if if some wicked king wanted to seize the land of a monastery
and so he sent messengers to them and they ended up becoming monks and then he sent some more
messengers and they ended up becoming monks. Right. Right. Yeah. And that's that's the idea with him.
Right. He prophesies as he goes and then when he gets there when he strips naked, he's taking off
all of the symbols of his office as king. Right. All of that is stripped away from him.
And then he just lays there naked exposed before God and before Samuel. And then and then leaves
without troubling anyone. Right. So so yeah, it's it's a weird passage. It's a little bit of a
weird passage. Right. But that's that's sort of what's going on. And it gives us a window into
these these communities. Right. But we have stories from anasticism of things like I mean
St. Moses the Ethiopian right is on the run. He goes into this monastery and he gets up joining it.
Right. Yeah. Yeah. You know, the famous messengers of St. Vladimir, you know, come into the church and
don't know whether they're in heaven or on earth. Right. There are times where the spirit is present
in a place where worship is happening and grips people who come in. Right. People, people who
enter are seized by hopefully they don't take off all their clothes and roll around on the floor.
I prefer you not do that at my parish. If you don't mind. Yeah. We have a dress code. If it's if it's
it's all the same to you. But yeah. Right. So so then the last little piece of this we want to
touch on here in terms of this transition. Yeah. The actual handoff. Yeah. That passing of the mantle.
Right. Which is both a physical piece of clothing and a mantle in the way that we now use that
term analogically. Uh, and I don't mean over your fireplace. I mean, isn't taking up the mantle. Yeah.
It's yeah, it's a long piece of cloth, right? Right. That's the yeah. That's what it is. Uh,
and so Elijah prays as Elijah is being taken up in heaven to enjoy the council. He would have a
double portion of Elijah's spirit. Yeah. What's that about? And that that wording is kind of
important, right? Because he doesn't say I want a double portion of the spirit of God that Elijah had.
Like this isn't I want to be twice as good as Elijah. Right. Yeah. I would be twice as powerful as
Elijah. Uh, this is about, um, about his relationship with Elijah. Right. Because what's happening is
Elijah, his beloved friend and mentor is now being parted from him.
Yeah. And he's praying that this would not separate him from Elijah, but their relationship now
as Elijah goes ahead, their relationship would be redoubled would be deeper and richer and greater
rather than less because it continues it continues. Right. Right. Right. And then and then he
receives the piece of cloth. Right. As a symbol of this being answered of this being true. Right. He's
going to walk around wearing this piece of Elijah's clothing. Right. That as as the sort of sign of
this continued relationship. And what he does with it is because since he has to cross the Jordan,
is he takes that mantle, strikes the Jordan with it and the Jordan splits in two. So yeah. Cross
over. Yeah. Where where is the God of Elijah? Yeah. As he says that, which of course, this is one of
the passages that gets read at theophany. Right. Uh, where you get almost every single passage from
the scripture having to do with water. Um, but but I this one is not the real reason, but anyway,
we will. Yeah. Right. Right. Well, yeah. We'll have to do an episode of that. But it's true. Yeah.
This is connecting that to Joshua entering Canaan. Yeah. Right. We're the Jordan parts in the same. Yeah.
The Jordan parted so they could march in. Marched in arc first. They marched in as an invading army.
Right. And so this is the sign that that spiritual warfare that characterized the ministry of
St. Elias is now going to continue with Elijah. Yeah. Yeah. Very cool. All right. Well, that wraps
up act one and we're going to take a short break and we'll be right back. Father Andrew Stephen
Damick and father Steven DeYoung will be back in a moment to take your calls on the next part
of the Lord of spirits. Give them a call at 855-237-2346. That's 855-AF radio.
Hi, this is John Maddox. You know, when you support ancient faiths radio,
you're not only helping to make this ministry possible for you, but also for people like
Bryce in Australia. I'd firstly just like to say that I love your show and what you do.
It means a lot to all of us listening. I'm down in Australia and over here,
orthodoxy is basically unheard of. I'm not orthodox. I was raised into an evangelical Protestant family.
However, from a gradual exposure and desire to learn more about orthodoxy, I've come to agree and
see truth in pretty much everything that church teaches. The nearest English-speaking orthodox
church is several hours away and I feel all alone in my pursuit of the faith. Yeah. Currently,
my only exposure to orthodoxy is through ancient faith radio and my friend. How should I introduce
the idea that I may be inquiring into orthodoxy to my parents? Thanks again, Bryce. Would you consider
a donation to AFR right now? You can do so on our app or go to our website at ancientfaith.com
slash support. Ancient faith radio. Here for you and for people all over the world.
You voice of Steve. Welcome back, everybody. We have a couple of callers that we wanted to get to
who have been patiently waiting. And so the first one that we've got is Perdomo in Texas. So,
are you there? Welcome. Hello. Yes, I'm here. I'm having an audio. All right. Good. Well,
welcome to the podcast. What's your question for us this evening? Well, I've got a question
about the the worst sacrifice, if you will, of April. And I guess also the sacrifice of King,
because those always come together. If you don't mind, I'll bring it up into a couple little
questions. The first being no, since the, you know, since they, since folks didn't meet until
the time of Noah, so we're told it's what the, you know, the first sacrifice, just the sacrifice
of blood and smoke. So you're asking exactly what was being sacrificed in the time
of Abel and Kane. And what was, what was being sacrificed and how, what, what was the nature that
of Abel sacrificed, you know, at his block? Right. I mean, so we're not given much in the
way of details, but if you listen, for instance, to our episodes where we've talked about sacrifice,
then you can hear an outline of what we do know in terms of the details of, of sacrificial
worship in the ancient world. But I mean, the basic outline of it is it's, it's food being offered
to your God, right? And then it's a shared meal with that God, right? So in, in Kane's case, he's
offering a vegetables and in Abel's case, he's offering from his flock, right? But the scripture
tells us that what's different about them is not just, is not so much the thing that they offered,
because, you know, it's not that God rejects vegetables, because he commands vegetables,
later to be offered, especially grain and stuff. But rather that the way that they did it,
though, you know, what, what was in their hearts was, was really the difference.
Father Stephen, did you have anything you wanted to add or correct for that?
Yeah, well, I think he was getting at the, the eating part. And yeah, presumably it would have been
on Abel's part a whole burnt offering. Yeah. So offered completely to God, then,
and then probably a sprinkling or anointing or something like that with the ashes. Yeah.
Yeah. Does that make sense? Yeah. That makes sense,
verification of the space. And then go with, with Kane's offering, since, you know, again, not,
not, not a bad offering in this, you know, are you, Chris, does a, in part, a grain offering?
Um, but, so is it, you know, sorry, but, but even he was, he was presumably partaking of it,
um, which makes it a, because it bit more like the, um, the fruit from the garden.
And is it, you know, is it safe? Would it be safe to say that, um, the, the angels that
Tyler taught Kane to make that sort of sacrifice, you know, before, before he was ready,
before it was permitted? Yeah, there's, there's famously not a lot in the
text to tell us why, I mean, people have all kinds of suggestions and surmises about why Kane's
offering was bad. And I think the best guess is, uh, as, as Father Andrew said, that it wasn't
about the offering itself or even how he did it, but it was about what was going on in his heart
and, uh, and who he was. Um, that's alluded to in first John, right, where it talks about how
the works of, of able were good and the works of Kane were evil. And I don't think it's just
talking about sacrificial procedure there. I think it's talking about works like their deeds,
the way they lived in the world, right, because one of the big problems in the Old Testament
is that most people had the idea, because this is sort of how pagan's operated, like the pagan gods
didn't care what was in your heart, right? Like you make offerings to them and you tell them
they're great, they don't care if you really mean it, right? They're not like, you know, super
investigative of this. And so we see points in the prophets where the Israelites are, you know,
raising Kane, pardon the pun, and, uh, but still doing the sacrificial offerings. As if that makes
it okay, right? Well, God will still be happy with us because we're giving him his goats and his
bulls and his blood. And so he's taking care of so we can just do as we please, right? And so God
eventually through the prophets is telling them just stop with the sacrifices. I don't like the blood
of bulls and goats. I don't want them anymore. So I think that's probably the best idea of what's
going on with Kane is it's not the problem isn't that he offered the wrong kind of sacrifice or
followed the wrong procedure, right? That would be how, how the pagans would think you, you, you would
have God not accept your sacrifice. Oh, you blew the procedure, right? You, you made a mistake
somewhere, but that it's the fact that Kane's heart was far from God. And so God wasn't interested in
his sacrifice if he couldn't have his heart. All right. Well, does that make sense to you, Pradoma?
Sure, sure, that makes sense. I mean, is it I mean, I guess one follow-up question coming to me now is
so then it's that it's it's an open question whether whether Kane and Abel were caught by God
how to make the sacrifice or not. Well, yeah, we're not told. Yeah, it doesn't say. It just simply
doesn't say. We just see them doing it. All right. Yeah. Yeah. All right. Well, thank you very much.
So we've got Nick on the line calling from California. So Nick, welcome to Lord of Spirit's podcast.
Thank you, Father. God bless you. What's your question or comment for us this evening?
So, I was when you were talking about David and his scene and repentance come to my mind and
a protocol. So he asked for his inheritance. The father gave it to him. He weighed,
wasted, and came back. And the father was pleased and happy. And he gave him a dress, ring,
and a piece. And the other son said he asked the father why he's doing that and the father said
because he was dead and he's alive. And also, father, that all what is mine is yours. So my
question is what happened to the protocol son inheritance? And I have teenager boys and I always
compared this to in case it goes a trade. I always tell them boys watch out for your inheritance
because I'm not sure if you're going to get it back. And am I right or wrong or I don't know
what should I say for that situation? Yeah. Well, I mean, the the the the protocol son definitely
goes and wastes what he takes with him, right? That's gone. But the point that the the the the
parable is making is that it's really not even about things that he gets from his father, but
rather being part of the father's household and that what the father has is what is what really
is important, right? So I mean, it's not like it's not like God has a finite amount of
gifts to give mankind that he's going to run out, right? So so we shouldn't come away with a kind
of economic reading of the parable, you know, in terms of application for our own lives.
But but you know, so I mean, if if yeah, it just doesn't work, just doesn't work well that way.
Does that make sense to you? Well, then, you know, some people can be oppressed and they commit
something uh way simple than appropriate to be a priest. They're not allowed to be a priest or
this day, they lose their inheritors to be to I don't I for me it's in complete answer. I don't
to give me father, but you know, then why the father is saying, oh, what is mine? It's yours for the
older son, right? Let me let me let me um actually father Andrew. Okay, go ahead. So um
and this is this is why this is a really important question is the term inheritance is incredibly
important in the Bible, right? Right. Uh and uh understanding this is incredibly important, but
one of the things we chronically misunderstand about the parable of the prodigal son
which is emphasized by the fact that we call it the parable of the prodigal son is that it's not
just about the prodigal son. Right his brother too. If you read the the parable closely it begins with
there was a man who had two sons. Two sons, right? Two sons. Um and uh it's also important that
the other son besides the prodigal son is the older brother. Okay, the older brother. Right. He's
the one who gets the inheritance. Right. So so if things had functioned the way they were supposed to
right then when the father died right and this is what he says in the end every when the father
dies the oldest son inherits everything in that system and then it is his job to then distribute
the inheritance to his siblings to the other sons, right? Because the the the the daughters would have
become part of other families. Um so uh part of why the older brothers upset is that uh the prodigal
son had no right to that money. Right then he took it wasted right that money would have actually
gone to the older brother. Uh but the the theme is not just about the prodigal son the theme of
the parable is about the older son learning something. That's where it ends is with the older son
learning something because part of what the father is telling him is that when the father dies
it's going to be the older son's job to take care of his brother. Right because regardless
the prodigal son under no circumstances would have inherited anything directly from his father.
Right and so the older brother can either maintain that grudge against him and cut him off and
throw him back into the pig pen right or he can learn the lesson and learn to love his brother the way
the father loves his son. So this parable was being directed by Jesus in part to the Pharisees
who were begrudging the sinners the tax collectors the repentant later on the Gentiles who were
were coming to follow God. Right and it wasn't just a question of of God loving those people so leave
them alone it was God loves you need to learn to love them too because in fact you're the ones who
have received the religious inheritance like Saint Paul is a Pharisee you've received the Torah
you've received the oracles of God you've received the revelation and the worship of God you need to be
loving them and taking care of them and helping them come in not being resentful
or angry toward them. So that's really what's going on I think in the in the parable
so so that's you know we we all find our salvation in the church together not as a bunch of
individuals yeah and if inheritance is our salvation we don't find that off on our own because we
deserve it and we have this direct relationship with with no community right with God but we find
that together right as we love each other and support and help each other and you know and Nick
to your question about if if a priest commits a particular sin he can lose his priesthood permanently
I I don't think that the reason for that is because of of what's in the parable the prodigal son
um rather it's you know they're all kinds that are all kinds of things that are impediments to
serving in the priesthood you know and and some of them are sins and some of them are not sins like
like if you know some say for instance someone is born without legs he he could not be ordained
that's an impediment to the priesthood he didn't do anything wrong right um but there are some
things that you can do wrong that make it so you could get to post from the priesthood um and it's
yeah I mean one could metaphorically call that squandering your inheritance but that's
a very broad use of it as a metaphor I mean the true inheritance is salvation right it's not
about serving in the priesthood because you know even someone has been deposed from the priesthood
could become a saint you know it's there's never a permanent loss for salvation as long as someone
is going to be faithful um it's much more about what's expedient in terms of serving in the priesthood
so it is not exactly a one-to-one you know application of this to that particular situation does that
make sense Nick uh yeah I didn't frame my question properly I meant to say if I do something this
will limit my ability to advance in my orthodoxy like uh become a priest or I don't know that's
what I meant to say sure yeah already because you know they're they're in the orthodoxy we have
limitations like who can be and who can't so that's good thing too and thank you fathers for
this wonderful explanation and can I follow up with the other previous caller about
Canaan and Abel and Noah well we have we have other colors waiting so we need to kind of move
on to them but I just wanted to add this one thing something you said which is um you know advancing
in orthodoxy does not necessarily mean ordination in fact ordination for some people could actually
be a regression in orthodoxy it could be be bad for their salvation but yeah yeah yeah yeah all
right well thank you very much Nick okay we're gonna take one more call and then we're gonna move
on and we have Matt calling from Houston so Matt are you there yes fathers I am can you hear me
yes we hear you welcome to the Lord of Spears podcast now is is your name really Matt or is this a
joke about the Matt Houston television program wow no no okay well uh legally my name is David uh
but uh huh they get complicated they get in the crates of the TV room yeah my point is David
Matthew so there's an abundance of Dave Matthew's references to be made oh wow it's go marching at all
that yeah oh yeah so what's what's up David Matthew from Houston okay so a few times on on the show
you guys have have talked about how humans interact with with the cosmos in in four primary ways
right to language music art and ritual and how one of the the big issues that we have in western
culture amongst you know the the many that there are is that we tend to reduce the the last three
into language so you know that's like people having their noses buried in their service books during
liturgy rather than than than just participating so that's what bad looks like but but I mean
presumably there is some value in using language to explain the the last three forms and to
attest to that I mean there's a that's a sorry there's a huge body of work on ancient faith that
is using language to describe the liturgy and iconography um so I guess what my question is
is could y'all just flesh out a little bit uh what that balance looks like uh between using
language well to describe these things that sort of transcend language uh and and and how to know
perhaps when you've taken it too far hmm I so I would say the point at which you've taken it too far
is when you're excluding the other things I know when you're distorting them or excluding them
right so you know the person who refuses to go to church but says I can read it at home
and that's you know because I don't want to go to church there's people there
you know the the priest is a bad preacher or the the choir is terrible or I don't like the way
the incense smells I'm just gonna read I'm just I can read it at home and that's the same thing
so that is it wouldn't be an obvious uh distortion or reduction of it um you know by no means are we
by saying that things should not be reduced to language are we you know denouncing language
I mean we're this is a podcast right uh we're sitting here talking um so so you know by no means right
Father Stephen and I both love language and are dedicated to it in a lot of ways um but yeah
I mean there's a lot in the Bible about bad use of language right so lying is is a misuse of language
um you know idle talk right just going on about nothing useful especially when it becomes harmful to
other people around you um those would be you know uh you know persuading people for your own
advantage rather than for the truth right so there's all kinds of ways to misuse language
right just as there's ways to misuse music and mis you know misuse ritual like these things can
all they all have their their abuse um as well as their their proper use but um but yeah I think
balance is the key and and I think that balance is maybe going to look a little bit different from
from one person to the next like if you're a monastic your engagement with ritual is going to be
way more than the average person right if you're if you're a preacher a teacher your use of language
is going to be way more and quite different from the average person sure right so so I don't think
that we can necessarily set up a one-size-fits-all but but the but I think the point when you're
cutting stuff out um it is should be a red flag and of course like I said abusing it for for
nefarious ends rather than to use it to the glory of God as all these things were designed. Father
Stephen did you have any any um actuallys or not not I'm actually percent but I mean I I
mean I think there are examples right that might help explain because it's it's a balance right
it's like all virtue it's the mean between two extremes right yeah um so you look at right the
hymns of the church right if if you have no idea what the words are and you walk around humming
tone eight right you you would very clearly know that okay well that's missing something right I'm
missing the language right I'm missing the words I'm missing the communication the hymn the words
what's being taught by it yeah at the same time we know full well that sitting there and just
reading the text without the music right without it being chanted without anything just reading it
as prose on paper there's something missing right like that's not the same experience as as
singing the hymn right and so the correct is when you have both of those together right and then
when you're singing those hymns together in the liturgical space in the context of the liturgy
now you've added ritual right and when it's on a feast day and you're singing the troparian of the
feast and the icon is there of the feast right these things all get brought together so the the issue
isn't just that like there's some perfect percentage of or ratio of language to art to ritual to
music it's it's that these things have to operate together and can't be pulled apart and separated
out without losing something sure sure and and now now that y'all have blessed it out a little bit
more I think that I've realized that my that the area in which I'm in which my mind is focused on
it is particularly engagement with non-orthodox Christians and I'm a very
naturally argumentative person say and so I recognize that about myself and I try to limit that
as much as I can and I try to limit you know over explaining things to people because I really
enjoy explaining things but you know I've heard stories of people who had a lot of questions
and then they go and sit in front of the icon of the Virgin Mary and and and just somehow their
questions feel answered yeah and so I think that that's a little bit more where my mind was
thinking about perhaps encouraging non-orthodox Christians to just go to liturgy and then when they
get there don't over explain it to them maybe I don't know yeah you were you were sort of you were
sort of reducing the question of reducing things to language to language which is like an
exception so you know the other thing that I would add Matt as as someone who's who has a strong
proclivity to be a talker is you know it's easy to spend time trying to convince people of
something and and that you know that that maybe can be fruitful sometimes but there is a use of
language that is actually very powerful and that is to pray for those people right we shouldn't
enter into theological conversation without prayer before and after because it's just very
dangerous to do that otherwise right and and I mean I'll be the first to admit that I don't always
do that because I often forget because I'm you know I'm a sinner but I have found that when I'm
going to have conversation with somebody about theological things or even just like okay I'm
going to be you know interviewing somebody or being interviewed by somebody or just having
a conversation with my wife or my children or whatever I try to pray beforehand even if it's
just to make the center of the cross and say Lord bless this conversation even if it's just that
right and and then then you're offering the words to God and and asking him to bless them
and and shape them and that's going to be much more powerful than you know even if you're just a
really great debater right people being convinced into worshiping Christ through the power of debate
is is just not a thing yeah you know I mean I've watched people be destroyed by the power of
somebody else's debate who then later who then later you know dedicated themselves to Christ but
but generally speaking when someone just sort of destroys someone else by the use and I'm not saying
you do that I don't know but but you know this is as a as a distortion or abuse of the use of language
when someone destroys someone else with a debate typically what what happens in response to that
is not faithfulness to Christ it's usually that that person is like you know is turned away from
Christ especially of that person who's debating them sets themselves up as as his representative you
know yeah there is a there is a place for for debate you know especially for defending the the
simple and the faithful against being undermined um but you know that's that doesn't happen that
often in most people's lives uh you know that that you're called upon to protect the flock um the
the flock has shepherds you know and and that's not most of us so you know for whatever that's worth
so is that helpful yes it's very much so great all right well thank you very much for calling
okay well rolling along and this is weird here we are Lord of Spirits and we're actually in act two
we're going to explicitly talk about uh the subject of our uh episode right so
bearing up the format yeah it's yeah we got to shake things up I just I just wanted to add since
apparently we're getting a fair number of calls uh guys go easy on John it's his first day
haha be nice I'm doing fine thanks oh hey wow so all right John Maddox everybody um my boss by the way
um you know after god in the bishop but yeah uh and my wife uh but all right so so okay well
this episode is about to change on the forerunner and we need to establish exactly who he is and what
better way to do that than to talk about his parents dying right it's like a Disney movie seems
right exactly why is it so many Disney movies always start with the main character being orphaned
like Disney loves to kill people's parents man that's frequent yeah it's like every movie but yeah uh
yeah so but that is that is sort of how the story of say each other forerunner starts uh but
the the the specifics of this is important to uh the reason we were talking about St.
O'Liet is about the prophet Elijah is uh that he is connected in many important ways uh to uh
St. John the forerunner and so to show a very important one of those connections we need to talk about
uh the eventualities surrounding the death of uh his parents right Zachariah and Elizabeth
and so both saints in their own right and um there is not a lot
as in almost nothing about this in the new testament itself uh we've got basically one verse and
that's Luke 1 verse 80 yes there are more than 80 verses in the first chapter of St. Luke's gospel
right yeah yeah i mean it's a very slight little reference to St. John having been taken into
the wilderness by his mother and it says in the child grew and became strong in the spirit
and he was in the wilderness until the day of his public appearance to Israel
um and you know he's he's brought out there by St. Elizabeth because
Herod is slaughtering all of the two-year-old boys and under in the region of of Bethlehem
and so you know with this massive massacre going on um she takes him out to save him so that he
doesn't get caught up in that and and that is uh well first i i want to highlight uh notice it says
he was in the wilderness until the day he revealed himself yeah but low and behold when we read the
story of him revealing himself he's still in the wilderness yeah he doesn't get it like an apartment
in town yeah and so there's there's folks out there who need to hear this the word until in the
Bible doesn't mean that something changed afterward yeah just means up to that point um doesn't
say anything about what happens after uh you know who you are so
right so living out there in the desert right so we have this one said that just he is a child
is living out in the desert and growing up out in the wilderness uh that's all that's the way
reference we have now uh church tradition which is a fancy way of saying the history of the church
right that's been handed down to us um and we've talked before about how uh modernism somehow
thinks that history written down by pagans is history and history written down by Christians
is a pack of lies but um the reality is that it's justice valid if not more so when written by
Christians and so uh they fill that out with this story that as part of of Herod's murders
this lot of the innocence as you're describing they came for uh Saint Saint John and uh when his
father Saint Zacharias at the temple refused to reveal his location they killed him and then
his mother Saint Elizabeth took Saint John out into the wilderness as an infant and ended up dying
there 40 years later which 40 days 40 days later sorry 40 days yeah 40 days later and so then
Saint John grew up in the wilderness not alone right but with the angels right basically he was
fostered by angels right and then so he was living the same kind of life right that um that we see
the prophets of the Old Testament leading and there is actually another passage that refers to these
events uh in the New Testament but for reasons not entirely clear to me uh people are very hostile
towards reading this passage as endorsing what the church has universally said about the the childhood
of Saint John the Forerunner for 2000 years right yeah so this is Matthew chapter 23 verses 34 and 35
and this is the Lord speaking um he says therefore I send you prophets and wise men inscribed some of
whom you will kill and crucify some you will flog in your synagogues and persecute from town to town
so that on you may come all the righteous blood shed on earth from the blood of righteous
able to the blood of Zachariah the son of Barakaya whom you murdered between the sanctuary and the altar
so the traditional reading is that when Christ makes reference to this Zachariah who gets killed
between the sanctuary and the altar that this is in fact the Zachariah who is the father of Saint John
the Forerunner um now the the the problem with this you know for those who don't want to believe that
this is the same one is that there's a lot of people name like it's a really common name Zachariah
is a really common name right well yeah there's there's a yeah there's a bunch of so for those who are
motivated to just say that anything in church tradition is wrong for some reason and these are
mostly Christians so again I don't understand exactly why that's your race on debt but hey that's
where we are so that there's a whole bunch of problems with reading so first of all you have well
if he's not well we'll start here the natural reading is that he's talking about
Saint Zachariah Saint John's father and the reason I say it's the natural reading is that
you may have noticed when father Andrew was reading those two verses
that you and it's a plural you y'all it's all y'all right yeah is is use several times okay I say
if you prophets you abuse them you fog them you persecute them right yeah you will do this you will
do that's future tense right right so he's talking to the Pharisees and the scribes right it's very
clear at the beginning he said dig to them to to the leaders of Judah he's sending them prophets he's
sending the people and they're going to persecute them right and and then they will come on you
will come on the people I'm talking to all that blood from able to Zachariah is going to come on you
and then he says Zachariah whom you killed yeah right so to take this as not referring to someone who
died real recently right unless this is someone who died in the last you know 40 years right the
last generation you have to say that that you mean something different than all the other use
in those sentences right which doesn't make sense right so that's the natural reading is this
is someone who this is something that just happened right yeah now you can add to this the kind of
preposterousness of or preposterosity I don't know what the word is but of the counter suggestions
the funniest one that I've heard is someone who I guess was just reading this in the
King James or something in only in English because they said look this is all the martyrs from
A to Z yeah able to Zachariah yeah which like like I mean there is no A to Z in Hebrew or in Greek
right like that's not the way that's where the Greek alphabet is alpha and omega omega yeah Z
Z is Z as a way a ways back yes so and not Hebrew not Aramaic Z is not the last letter so that
that makes no sense that's kind of four six Z Z for our commonwealth listeners oh yes welcome
Canada so with our Canada anyway so one of the more common ones that's not
utterly ridiculous right is people will point to the Zachariah the the priest who has killed in
the temple by the way between the altar and the high place right remember the altar of Bern
offering was was sort of outside the central building around the the Holy of this isn't in the
Holy of Holies yeah right this is between the place where the holy place the Holy of Holies were
and the altar of Bern offering that's outside so this is in the temple courts that people are being
killed so there is a Zachariah who is killed in the temple in second chronicles 24 versus
20 and 21 right so some people suggest that that's him instead right right and and I have a
guess at the reason for this and and that's that in the ordering of what becomes the Hebrew Bible
once they collect all the books in Hebrew into the what the Hebrew Bible second chronicles is
the last book right so in this this is an A to Z sort of our right Genesis to the first book right
yeah just able Genesis before all the way to the end of second chronicles so this is see it's the
whole quote-unquote canonical scripture so if you're of the bent and we all know who we're talking
about who hold the Hebrew Bible to be the canonical scriptures then you could say ah and I've even
heard people use try to use this as a proof for the Hebrew canon turn it around and try to use it
as a proof for the Hebrew canon there's a couple problems with this number one the books hadn't been
compiled in this way yet at the time Jesus said it right so if you think Jesus actually said it which I
do then that don't work there's also the problem that that Zechariah and second chronicles is the
son of Johoyada yeah not Barakaya not Barakaya and you will get some people who engage in some extreme
special pleading to try and say well Johoyada is his grandfather so he's the son of both you know
or something but there's no evidence of that actually in the scripture they're just trying to come
up with something right so and so there's another there's another candidate right which is the the
Zechariah who writes the book of prophecy in the Old Testament right called Zechariah yeah and he's
and he's and and and slightly more believable his father is named Barakaya but again these are both
really common names you know and but here's the problem is that Zechariah was not murdered
right right there's nothing in the Old Testament whatsoever indicating that he was murdered and the
earliest record we have of his life that lives of the prophets I mentioned earlier the earliest Jewish
source we have says that he died peacefully and at a ripe old age yeah not that he was murdered to
the temple right so so that part doesn't fit yeah yeah now father Andrew's said a couple times
out that that Zechariah is a very common name there are 27 Zechariahs in the Old Testament
right 27 different people identifiably different people name Zechariah and Barakaya
means blessed by Yahweh right so again very common name right so there's there's yet another Zechariah
who was murdered in the temple who's mentioned by Josephus but he was murdered in the temple
in the 60s AD so after Christ said this right yeah decades out yeah so this would be yeah right
right so I mean you would think and people present as an argument well how many people name Zechariah
do you think were murdered in the temple well at least two or three things right like this seems to
be a thing yeah and one of the reasons why people get murdered in the temple and you know in the
basically from the Hasmonean period on a lot of people became high priest by assassinating the
previous high priest yeah that was fairly common during that period the Sadducees are not good folks
right right so there were unfortunately right so all all of that is to say that the Christian tradition
that we've received received uniformly for 2000 years about this being a reference to St.
John's father and him then going and being raised living with the angels and the wilderness
and coming of age there just Occam's razor right right this is the only thing that really makes
sense of the biblical and extra biblical data that we have yeah yeah yeah and then you know the
traditional life of St. Elizabeth says that she dies 40 days after she takes John into the wilderness
the text that I looked at didn't mention how she died just simply said that she died so the
point is is that he's two years old living out there in the wilderness by the Jordan River
and being raised by angels angels are basically his his foster parents so to speak literally living
the angelic life in the way we talked about in the Old Testament yeah yeah yeah yeah exactly okay so
so yeah now that might seem like a long long sort of divergence right but you know it's important
to establish that his parents are dead from an early early age because it shows the way that he
the way that he was formed right I don't think there's anyone else in scripture and you know
that that we get who basically grows up as an angel so to speak then this man
they don't host as close yeah right right right you know I mean it's certainly like like we said we
get other you gather prophets living the angelic life but but he's getting it from the beginning from
about being a two-year-old I mean he's a toddler right and and that's the man that we meet out at
the Jordan right but there are prophecies about him that connect him directly and and things
said about him in the New Testament that directly connect him to the prophet that we talked about
an act one and that's the prophet Elijah Elias right so it's not just that he lived the prophetic
life it is a continuation of the Old Testament prophets but there is also a particular connection
between him and yeah yeah yeah yeah there's a couple of very famous passages from the prophecy of Malachi
so you've got Malachi chapter three verse one behold I send my messenger and he will prepare the
way before me and the Lord whom you seek will suddenly come to his temple and the messenger of
the covenant in whom you delight behold he is coming says Yahweh Yahweh Sabah of Lord of hosts
and then Malachi chapter four verses five and six behold I will send you Elijah the prophet
before the great and awesome day of the Lord comes and he will turn the hearts of fathers to their
children and the hearts of children to their fathers lest I come and strike the land with a decree
of utter destruction so there's this prophecy about Elijah coming back this this messenger being sent
to prepare the way before the Lord comes to his temple and the day of the Lord comes right so this
is there you know that Elijah is coming back every we see this this is the concern for God's holiness
again right just by holiness if God just shows up right there's going to be utter destruction
if there's no preparation right because of because of his holiness and so he's sending this messenger
to prepare them right by turning their hearts right this idea of repentance he's going to send
someone to bring about repentance so that those who repent will not be destroyed those who don't
will be and so we could call those who then do repent at our pure line through this remnant
right that remnant here's the remnant idea coming back and being associated with this ministry of
Elijah when he comes right yeah yeah and I mean this is what Saint John
preaches out there at the Jordan right you know there's that point where he says
you know who warned you to flee from the wrath that is to come you know he asked did you come out
to hear to see you know read shaken in the wilderness or whatever um but it's he is by his preaching
he's fulfilling this prophecy about him which is specifically about avoiding wrath that's to come
you know Saint John is out there gathering this remnant together by his preaching by his baptism
and calling them to repentance baptizing them for repentance yeah exactly and telling them how to
repent you soldiers repent this yeah you soldiers repent this way you you know like he's he's
giving specific pastoral instructions you know this is how you repent after do something not
just feel bad that's right they have to do something not just feel bad I'm also always been a fan of
how Saint John greeted inquirers which was you brood of vipers who want you to flee from the wrath
that is coming I think we should put that on a sign over the door of our churches just a great
people who show up for the first time you know wow um but um so yeah so so this is exactly what he's
preaching right exactly what what Malachi uh was talking about and the the other main uh passage from
the Old Testament that's quoted in terms of Saint John the Four Writers Ministry and when I say
one of the main ones quoted I mean all four gospel writers this is one of those rare things where
even Saint John's gospel is is aligned with the synoptics um is uh I say a forty first three
yeah right right this is the very very famous um probably the most famous prophecy about
Saint John the former runner a voice cries in the wilderness prepare the way of the Lord
make straight in the desert a highway for our God and then it goes on to say you know
every valley is going to be exalted every mountain brought low etc um so okay so why you know a lot of
times the way that this gets quoted you know sort of um it's about the punctuation you know a voice
some will say a voice crying in the wilderness prepare the way of the Lord the the ESV which is what
I just read from wrote a voice cries colon in the wilderness prepare the way of the Lord so what's
the difference there and why does that matter right yeah and and the ESV is right on that um
the uh in my non humble opinion um but uh yeah and and because the way that's read is you know a voice
crying in the wilderness calm and people sort of ignore the vote right like voice crying in the
wilderness oh yeah yeah say John's out in the desert yelling right that's him right see prophecy
fulfilled um but the focus is on preparing the way of the Lord in the wilderness yeah because this
is a part of a prophecy about the end of the exile yeah and and you know look at what the next thing
it says it talks about valleys being exalted and you know hills but like it's literally talking about
things happening in the wilderness yeah you know uh it's making a road from battle onto Jerusalem
right so that the remnant who has been preserved through the exile can return home
right yeah that's what the prophecy is about and so that's that's what Saint John is doing
and that's what they're saying with this quote remember the quote is it just of one line
and superficial things he's in the desert wilderness hey there you go um it's uh it's
referring bringing to mind that whole passage yeah right that this is what Saint John is about this
is what he's doing preparing a way is literally a way a road a path right and he is he is preparing it
and he is gathering this remnant right and so then we get at the end of the main part of
Saint John's story in the gospels we get this transition at the Jordan just like we saw with
Saint Elias and uh Elijah um where uh John hand say John hands over to Christ that remnant
who's been purified by baptism and repentance yeah which gives that remnant over to him
to be now the starting point of of his people right and i i have to point out that one of the people
who are part of that remnant is my patron saint the apostle Andrew so he's explicitly described
as as a disciple of Saint John uh and then you know John's like okay he's yours now Jesus
i i thought you were gonna say saint steven so well he's all right i want to continue to confuse
people about what your name is yeah so um right and and we see right in our himnography and in our
iconography right again as we've commented on before at theophany that that himnography that
iconography talks about and depicts the Jordan parting yeah right right so there's you know
this this echo then of what happens with um you know Elijah right the Jordan parts as part of
that handover and um i mean it's not explicit in the scripture but iconographically himnographically
we talk about Jordan turned back right if you've ever gone to the theophany services especially the
great blessing of the water you hear the priest say that over and over again Jordan turned back
Jordan turned back there's this idea that it it parts when this handover happens from
john to jesus now right so so again this other echo from Elijah um right yeah that that's so we've
got you know uh saint john has the same kind of lifestyle the angelic life this prophetic way of life
that Elijah does he's doing the things that these Old Testament prophecies predicted Elijah would do
when he comes yeah and then probably the most superficial one but nonetheless worth worth mentioning
is that they uh look alike and dress alike right right yeah so you've got okay second kings one
eight and Matthew three four here's the second king's reference uh they answered him he wore a
garment of hair with a belt of leather about his waist and he said it is Elijah the tish bite
that's about Elijah Matthew three four now john wore a garment of camel's hair and a leather belt
about his waist and his food was locusts and honey um so yeah they even look alike you know they
dress alike right and and then and then what's funny then okay like it becomes very explicit in
multiple passages in the new testament uh Matthew 11 7 through 15 and 17 10 through 13 and then
mark 9 11 through 13 I'm just reading them off stick and look them up later folks but all of those
basically someone says yes this is Elijah yeah this is Elijah the question comes up are you Elijah
right and all those Christ are basically Christ saying yes he's Elijah yeah and then john himself
john 1 19 through 22 is basically john saying no I'm not what's that about how can he both
why would he deny it if Jesus is saying that yeah he's Elijah I think we found a contradiction
in the Bible so we're just going to check this whole thing and go home good night everybody yeah
um no so so there's this idea communicated that he is and he isn't right yeah um and um
part of the way through this right the way to understand what this relationship is where he
is and he isn't is comes through going back a little and looking at the prophecy that was made
to his father Saint Zechariah before birth back in Luke 1 um verses 13 through 17 you'll hear this at
the feasts of his uh I think of his conception and also of his birth if I remember correctly um
but the angel said to him do not be afraid Zechariah for your prayer has been heard
and your wife Elizabeth will bear you a son and you shall call his name john and you will have
joy and gladness and many will rejoice at his birth for he will be great before the Lord
and he must not drink wine or strong drink and he will be filled with the Holy Spirit even from
his mother's womb and he will turn many of the children of Israel to the Lord their God
and he will go before him in the spirit and power of Elijah to turn the hearts of the fathers to the
children and the disobedient to the wisdom of the just to make ready for the Lord a people prepared
I mean when Zechariah heard that I'm sure he thought wait wait wait malachi chapter 4 all that
they wouldn't have verses or whatever yeah I'm not sure he was thinking of that passage from
malachi chapter 4 because it says I will send you Elijah the prophet he'll turn the hearts of the
fathers to their children the hearts of children the fathers I mean it's like this it echoes it
directly this is this is an angel speaking to Zechariah right and so right you see all that that
mouth calling which but note here the the language used about Elijah that he comes he doesn't say
he's gonna be Elijah reincarnated right in the spirit yeah right he says in the spirit power of Elijah
where have we seen that kind of language before we'll have to transition from St. Elias from Elijah
to Elijah yeah where he wants a double portion of his of Elijah's spirit right and so what this
is setting up as the idea that in the same way Elijah continued to have this relationship with
his friend and mentor who had now been exalted to the heavenly places in the same way
now St. John has a relationship with St. Elias who has been exalted to the heavenly places and
as part of the divine council and so would have been one of those beings who he was growing up
among yeah out there wilderness right that he would have known him because he's in living in the
divine council yeah and so then there's this there's this reference and it's funny like until we
sort of talk about this I didn't read this this way but now it makes sense so John 133 and this is
so this is John the foreigner speaking talking about recognizing Jesus I myself did not know him
but he who sent me to baptize with water said to me he on whom you see the spirit descend and remain
this is he who baptizes with the holy spirit now like most of the time I read that that phrase he
who sent me to baptize I always thought okay well God sent John to baptize right but like if God
appears to John the foreigner who who is that that's appearing to him that's going to be the son of
God because that's who appears to people right why would he appear and say now you're going to
recognize me because the holy spirit's going to descend on me like like you're like well he would
probably say well once you just look like I see you now you know right and and while I say John
is sent to go start baptizing the second person of the Trinity is living in Nazareth yeah already
incarnate living in Nazareth yeah so yeah he who sent me to baptize it makes sense then to read
this as Elijah sent him to baptize and said this is how you're going to recognize the son of God when
you see him right and and we see this pattern that that when one of the prophets one of the human
prophets is it is in the divine council right in these scenes right where they're commissioned for
example right like the prophet Isaiah there's an angelic being who comes and a sort of their guide
yeah right and explains things to them and shows things to them and interacts with them right this
happens with Isaiah you see this happen with Daniel in his visions you see this happen with St. John
in the apocalypse in the book of Revelation right he has these angelic beings who show him things
and explain things to him and tell him and he asks them questions they tell him so presumably as
St. John is living the angelic life he has someone who is his guide and we've been told
that he's coming in the spirit and power of Elijah yeah it makes sense that that's his guide
and you know we see this outside scripture too obviously Enoch you know when he in his in that
text he's guided by an angel and of course you know the one that probably everybody's gone their
mind now suddenly is Dante being guided when he you know makes his trip into into paradise
um so yeah yeah um powerful power stuff okay well we are going to uh go ahead and and go to
break and we're going to be right back and talk some more about St. John the Forerunner
Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung will be back in a moment to take your
calls on the next part of the Lord of Spirits give them a call at 855-237-2346 that's 855-AF
radio. We tend to faith publishing presents I live again a memoir of Iliana Princess of Romania
and Arch Duchess of Austria who in later life became Mother Alexandra founder of the Orthodox
Monastery of the Transfiguration in Pennsylvania who wrote this memoir shortly after relocating to
the US in the 1950s it tells the story of a life full of suffering tragedy and exile but all is
diffused with the author's deep faith hope love and even joy this reprint includes additional
material collected by the nuns of her monastery that sets the memoir in the context of Mother
Alexandra's later life to find this book and others like it you can go to store.ancientfaith.com
again that is store.ancientfaith.com we're back now with the Lord of Spirits the Father Andrew
Stephen Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung if you have a question call now at 855-237-2346 that's 855-AF
radio okay welcome back to the third half yes I mean to say third half we do have a couple
of colors on the line we've got Samuel calling from Virginia Samuel are you there right
speak to a Samuel Samuel are you there you all right yeah okay I'm here okay welcome my my question
is about how a lot of the talk of God speaking through the prophets in the Old Testament it focuses
on the third person of the Trinity the Holy Spirit but how how much of a presence of the
the second person the son is in the speaking through the prophets explicitly in the Old Testament
oh that's a good question I mean I'm gonna have Father Stephen mostly answer this but I want to
just begin by saying there's in many cases it says and the word of the Lord came to fill in the name
of the prophet right and who is I mean the word of the Lord is our Lord Jesus Christ as the son of
God so Father Stephen take it away yeah well yeah because there are a bunch of examples right one of
them is when when Samuel is being called right beginning of that's right it says at that time
there I think that King James has to say poverty of the word of God there was there was a lack of
the word of God it says there were not many visions yeah it doesn't say they're the you know people
weren't hearing from God it said there were not many visions and then the word of God comes to Samuel
and staying the side of his bed and there's a place with Jeremiah the word of the Lord comes
to him and touches him yeah so the word of the Lord is used in this sort of bodily way to represent
a person throughout the Old Testament and one of the key words for prophets the Old Testament is
actually here so we have in the contemporary west kind of the weird idea of Old Testament prophets
that's basically based on hearing a voice in their head and then we associate that with the Holy
Spirit or maybe even more subtle than that that the Holy Spirit is just sort of nudging them or you
know giving them ideas or just making sure they do say right things but in the text of the
scriptures itself you see prophets doing is having visions yeah entering the council of God where
the word of God the second person the Trinity is and he commissions them talks to them and sends them
right and that's why as we were talking about in the first half this is why what happens with
St. Paul and the road to Damascus is in such total continuity with what happens with the prophet
and this is this is what St. John is getting at sort of as a summary statement St. John says at
the end of his prologue to gospel he says no one has seen God at any time but the unique God who is
in the bosom of the Father has made him known he's not saying hey you remember all those times of the
Old Testament where people said they saw God that's the bogus he saw him until Jesus came right
because that doesn't make any sense right St. John could only books that all that happened in the Old
Testament what he's saying is all those times where it says they saw God in the Old Testament
and interacted with him and he spoke to them that was Christ yeah that was the second person
of the Trinity that was the word of God capital W the logos who they saw and heard from and interacted
with and now has become flesh all right does that make sense Samuel okay great all right so we're
having a couple of audio issues with Father Stevens connection so Father Stephen I'm just going
to ask you to switch over to the other system that we have but meanwhile I'm going to attempt to
take Christopher on my own while he does this so Christopher calling from again the Holy
State of Virginia I think I hear a train a plane going over there in Virginia so Christopher are
you there yeah we can hear you what's what's your question or your comment Christopher
and forget me for the back I know it's on the train oh you are on a train all right yeah it's very
about that but my question was about edge on the map and I recently was reading some work on
about a Catholic then that edge on the map this was part of the ASEAN community that produced that
pretty good as these roles not the same one but of the similar community that's who we was
learning with while he was in the desert that he wasn't alone I haven't heard about him being
with angels like you guys were just not talking about it's gonna be interesting or it could be
that they he was living in the end of lifestyle like modern day long to do in a way in the desert
I want to get your guys comments on that it that was a plausible interpretation of history and
change on the basis yeah well I think we've got Father Stephen Beckani but the first thing
that I'll just say is I mean in the scripture it talks about him living you know there's no indication
that there's anyone else out there living with him you know that he's that he is alone essentially
and like when it says that he I mean look at the verse actually here yeah it says the child
grew and became strong in the spirit and he was in the wilderness until the day of his public
appearance to Israel that's Luke chapter one verse 80 it makes no references to sineles with
taking him out there and handing him over to a community that's out there you know of human beings
right you know the church's tradition is that he was there living the angelic life
but Father Stephen are you are you able to connect now are you there they can you hear me now
yeah yeah okay good so the question is about whether Saint John was with the community
yeah whether he yeah whether he was part of the Essenes essentially is the question
so right so there's a lot of vaguely about who and what an Essenes right so Josephus refers to
the Essenes and for example most people now think that Kumron the group at Kumron the Kumron community
was part of the Essenes but even that is questionable because we don't know if the Essenes
was a big organized group and the group at Kumron for example was clearly not there were
separateness group they weren't sort of in line with anybody else they were sort of fundamentalists
and ironically enough old calenderists that's why they split but yeah so so the idea of Essenes is
historically tenuous there's a lot of it most of what you read when you read about the Essenes
is conjecture and it's sort of assuming that certain groups were Essenes that are never explicitly
called Essenes and didn't call themselves Essenes but yeah I was saying when I reconnected here
there is no discussion of any group with Saint John anywhere in the scriptures or anywhere
but most of the the Essen groups and like the group if we if we that the group we have at Kumron
where we have a lot of information that they represent sort of what an Essenes was there really
aren't a lot of things connecting Saint John to that the Kumron community for example split over
the calendar they follow the anachic calendar they believe that the Pharisees were liberals
for using sort of an updated calendar based on on field and assages these who used the
Julian calendar or write out because the Julian calendar was clearly a pagan Roman calendar
for for Jewish groups in the first century that's the main reason they split and what they did
is they went out in the desert as a community and reconstructed a version of temple rights because
they said here it's temple was legitimate and they reconstructed here the temple rights there
so that they could carry on the worship not including sacrifices but so that they could continue
worshiping God themselves that community to be the faithful remnant uh the the only remnant
that was saved uh and they believe that following the calendar and conducting these ritual
was the way it definitely oriented yourself or and there's nothing about any of that with Saint
John reading about him doing any ritual worship any calendar each day so the things that were sort
of essentially important uh I mean the the the book of Enoch there are more copies of the book of
Enoch book other than Genesis book of Enoch uh then I believe that this and then fourth is
a huge portion of Enoch is laying out the calendar they were using quote-unquote proving that it's
not finally given so I visit a lot of evidence to suggest that there's any connection between
that and say John being a... All right well we're unfortunately losing Father Stephen
uh from his connection again so um but uh Father Stephen hopefully you can hear me I'm just gonna
ask you to call in the regular 855 AF radio and hopefully we can get him on the phone uh because
it's just been super super choppy here this evening so um all right well uh so is that uh is
that useful to you Christopher I hope you were able to get something from from some of that I'm sorry
about the the bad connection I know it's a relatively positive grain of salt yeah in terms of
referencing it back to what's always been known as the church yeah I have a I have a Catholic background
so the uh and currently look it up and so I understand between those current
work yeah yeah all right um yeah yeah I mean I think I think part of it is just that what we see
actually seen scripture doesn't indicate that he's with anybody else right um so you know
conjecture can be interesting but the the the tradition that we've received just simply makes more
sense and actually makes better sense of what's actually there in the scripture so yeah yeah okay
so Father Stephen do we have you back on the phone now okay John is still working on trying to
get him on there so all right well okay so just a kind of roll along um uh thank you very much
for calling everybody but um so the last thing we wanted to talk about with regards to St John and
I think you know if you've been listening to what we've said about about St Elijah then this will
become very clear you kind of know where we're going with this right and that is that St John is
part of the divine council now we saw Elijah taking up on the chair to fire to become part of the
divine council and functioning as this guide now for the forerunner you know who comes in his spirit
and power um and so what does St John do as part of the divine council so he's growing up in the
divine council but then you know especially after his beheading which on the new calendar are about
to celebrate that feast in just a couple days here on Sunday after his beheading he takes up his
place as the divine council and if you look at you know the icon of stasis on most in most orthodox
churches or if you especially look at an icon that is called the deesis icon what you see there is
Christ on his throne so he seated on his throne at his right hand is his mother right and we've
talked you know about why she's there at his right hand there is an episode that we did late last
year called the queen stood at the right hand okay so go listen to that if you're interested in
that it's fascinating stuff um but at his left hand is St John the forerunner at his left hand is
St John the forerunner um father seen if you're there why would he be why would he be at the left hand
this is now the third connection by the way they would get a cut in with us so why would he be at the
left hand can you hear me yes yes okay good can you hear me now now yeah i know yeah so this
this is how we celebrate our what year anniversary is technical difficulties yeah right uh yeah but
it brings me back to you this would happen yeah i kind of worried you this would happen due to the
seasonal weather out here um so uh we talked about in that episode uh the queen stood uh that is
about how the uh royal court of david in particular was an icon of the divine council the heavenly
council and so in the same way that we see the queen mother at the right hand of david at the left
hand of david is the prophet of the lord who was there in the court and we see several episodes
um uh state alliance was sort of a haps for profit or should have been but you did barge in
uh but um for example would have had a more right or uh clear role and Samuel before him
um and so we see saint john again taking that place uh as the fulfillment of that role
uh there's one reason why he's there at the left hand um and then there's also the uh tradition
within the church that saint john uh as he uh experiences the osus it takes this place in the divine
council uh replaces the devil who fell right and and the devil as we talked about way back when
is described as having been a cherub we talked about how the serpent description
uh is connected to the idea of the seraphs or off being the Egyptian word uh for serpent
uh and that is a throne guardian a protector of the throne someone who and protecting in terms of
protecting the holiness that's why there's a uh a cherub at the gate of paradise yeah yeah people out
and protect them from the holiness and so we can see saint john taking that role near the throne of
christ and what of course was his his ministry on earth was repent because the kingdom of god is at hand
you need to repent you need to turn your heart back so that you will not face the wrath so that you
will not be destroyed by god holiness uh not gatekeeping in the sense of trying to throw people out
but trying to prepare them to be able to come in and so his his standing at the left hand
at the throne of the continuation of that ministry uh as well right right yeah and and you know uh
we we mentioned i think we mentioned the angel wings i'm sorry get a little a little discombobulated
by the audio issues but that's okay um you know he's depicted often with with wings and many
icons of him not every icon but certainly a lot of icons of him he's got wings and you know often
people say well it's because he's like an angel literally true um but it's not that angels have
wings it's that wings are used as a way to signal that the figure you're looking at is a messenger
because a messenger uh is expected to go fast right so wings on a uh wings on a on a bird or whatever
you know enable it to go fast and able to fly really quickly and so when saint john is depicted with
wings it's not to say that he is the same has the same nature as the angelic beings it's
that he's functioning in the same um he's functioning in the same role that they do as one who is
sent from god to to speak uh on behalf of god right so um that's that's what's going on with with
the wings you know but again like he's closely associated with the angelic hosts because
that's what he's doing their their task like he's he's being one of them he's being part of the
heavenly hosts right right right he is now uh continuing to share in the lives of the angels but at
the same way that we see saint alliance making this transition right we see Elijah who's already
living the angelic life on earth already participating in the divine council the spiritual world on earth
he comes to sort of the fullness of that um as he goes into the heavenly places
yeah yeah yeah beautiful all right well we've now gone on for two hours and 20 minutes just about um
so i think we're gonna go ahead and wrap up our conversation i mean there's so much more that we
could say about this awesome awesome saint like you know the fact that according to our tradition he
he you know is the foreigner of christ even into haides and preaches the gospel there um to those
the both that departed righteous and also to the wicked spirits who are in haides for whom it is not
good news it is good news the righteous obviously um but uh but perhaps we'll just have to save a lot
of that for another time i wanted to make a few final comments and it's something we've been sort of
hinting at a lot along the way um but we did not actually use i think the the particular term
and and that's this question of patron saints right so we see this relationship between Elijah
and john set up in the scriptures you know it's demonstrated very very well right you've got
prophecies about saint john the forerunner talking about him as being in the you know in the spirit of
Elijah um you know that that prophecy directly from the angel to his father talking about him
in this way it's brought up again again you know in the gospels right he does the things that Elijah
does um he's he's clearly connected with him and he's not just meant to you remind us of Elijah
but it's clear that Elijah is part of his life right because he's connected to the divine council
where Elijah lives and functions so this is a patron saint this is how a patron saint
functions right so if you have a patron saint you look at elements from that saint's life
and you try to imitate them in in the way that's appropriate to you right um uh and but then also
you look to them for guidance they are there to guide you in the divine council because they're part of
it they're there to lead the way for you to show you what to do to sometimes to send you to do
what it is that god would have you do you know that's why we have patron saints um you know we often
bear their name right now say john did not bear the name of Elijah they don't have the same name
but over and over again he's basically called Elijah in one way or another so even though he didn't
literally have Elijah's name he comes in the name of Elijah in a very real and powerful sense
right um you know patron saints um sometimes when people become orthodox the you know acquiring a
patron saint becomes kind of a difficult thing like oh I like this one I don't like this one or
I feel attracted to this one or not this one or whatever most people get their patron saints by
somebody being born and their parents assigned with the help of god their parents assigned that
saint to them by naming them after after that person um but can you have more than one
yeah you can have more than one saint who who functions in this way for you right that's definitely
a thing um the idea of patron saints is is you know a concept that existed in the ancient world
even outside of of uh christian theology and practice you know you've got the ancient Romans concept
of patronage right where an established person in the community has you know what they would
call a client right that we don't use that word in quite that way in in our time but they would
have someone usually a younger person who's being introduced into civic and public life and the
patron helps to provide for them introduces them into it um you know supports them and then you
know the the younger person by excelling is a credit then to the patron right that's the way that it
works in the roman world and it's clear that this kind of arrangement is happening uh with
saint Elijah and saint john the forerunner right but you can have multiple patron saints and of course
many of us have multiple names you know first name middle name um and you might have a family
patron saint at the same time you have the saint who is assigned to your church you might have a
saint who's the patron of your nation all of these saints can help you all the angels and saints
can help you so it's not necessarily that there's just one and you know people can actually have
their sort of main patron saint changed in their life like when someone becomes a monastic
their name is changed out and they have a new patron saint assigned to them by the abbot
when they get that new monastic name so um you know when you're thinking about what the the
relationship of a patron saint to the christian is this is what you should think about look at this
relationship between Elijah and john now most of us are not sent in the spirit and power of Elijah
right but but we are sent to be um a credit to the saint that we're named after and we we should look
to them and we should look to that name of theirs that we bear as being providential from god whether
it's one that you chose you know when you became an orthodox christian and maybe the priest said okay
you can choose one or one that was assigned to you by virtue of being born and your parents
assigning that name to you or in many cases people who convert to the orthodox church the priest
assigns it to them right or having it assigned to you if you become a monastic these are all ways
that you can have it have the patron assigned to you um it's just as much of a blessing right and
sometimes the assignment is actually more of a blessing in some ways than then picking somebody
because you're receiving that in humility and obedience so it's it's a beautiful beautiful relationship
that person does not get between you and god that person is there to lead you to god they are a
guide in salvation a guide in the divine council they're not us you know uh uh someone who stands
between you and god that that's ridiculous and they would never see themselves that way right so
it's uh it's it's a wonderful amazing remarkable powerful helpful relationship that we as
christians can have to have these guides these patrons saints to help us out along the way
Father Steven your final comments yeah so i want to talk a little bit about we brush out a few places
including in answering one of the uh the questions we answer tonight um on the fact that even
when we're talking about people like St. Elias and St. John the forerunner who lived alone out in the
wilderness for a good chunk of their life uh they still experienced what they experienced and did
what they did and we're working toward the purposes of god in terms of a community not just the
community the prophets that we talked about that we saw that the prophet Samuel was a leader of and
that alaisha went to but in terms of the people of israel right the the people of the northern kingdom
who are apostates to paganism essentially but who uh the prophet Elijah's whole purpose
and these great spiritual victories he wins are all in an attempt to win them back to their first
love and attempt to bring them back to Yahweh they are the important thing that community the people
that remnant within the broader community and we tend very much as do not think in terms of community
we tend to think in terms of individuals our self as an individual when we think about family we
don't think about like a big extended family we think about mom dad kids right we think about
the nuclear family the small unit and we have certain responsibilities within that small unit and
none outside of it and even when we approach salvation even when we approach church we approach it
as individuals and sometimes even as as consumers so for most of history the church sat in the middle
of a village and the people who went to that church were the people who lived in the village
and so their worship life their ritual life everything that happened in the church
was one with the rest of the life of the community everyone knew each other
right and and they were worshipping and praying together and then doing business with each other
and living next to each other as neighbors participating in all the aspects of community life
we don't have that anymore in the United States we live in cities I live in a city with dozens of churches
those churches are broken up ethnically racially economically right there's different groups that
grow to go to different churches we look at religion is sort of like a hobby that some people have
and some people don't and what they're into is different depending on who they are
and they go as an individual to the place of their choice or nowhere if that's their choice and
try to get what they want out of the experience and then and then come come home
but that's not how salvation works because that's not how God works
God doesn't work just with isolated individuals by themselves unrelated to anyone else or anything else
the work that God is doing involves everyone it involves the whole community the experience
salvation is to be part of something and to become part of something and so our lives as Christians
have to become part of the life of a Christian community and that doesn't just mean staying for coffee
hour and chitchatting a little bit that means really getting to know the people in our church
and having our church become a community become people we talk to not just on Sunday not just when
we bump into each other at church people who we know what's going on in their life and they know
what's going on in ours people who when they see our kids acting up straighten them out
for us right when they see us acting up straighten us out right then we're responsible to all the time
that we're in communication with all the time that we love all the time so that what we do in
worship is the fulfillment of that relationship and that love and that joy that we share with each
other all the time every day everywhere we go because God doesn't save any of us as individuals
and he doesn't save us as individuals as an end in itself what God did in the life of St.
Elias when he did in the life of St. John the forerunner was not just oh he picked them to give them
these special blessings and experiences and to have this role in heaven but he picked them to bless
the world he picked them to proclaim a message to bring salvation to countless people to countless
generations of people in the case of those two men so if we're working out our salvation then God
is saving us and we're being saved it's because God wants to use us to do a whole lot more than just
try to get our own act straight now it's to get our act straight now and to do that by blessing
the world beginning with our community beginning with our churches so that's if it was audible
it's entirety or near so is my final comment thank you all right well that is our show for tonight
thank you everyone for listening if you didn't get a chance to call in during the live broadcast
we would love to hear from you either via email at Lord of Spirits at Ancient Faith.com or you can
message us at our Lord of Spirits podcast Facebook page we read everything but can't respond
everything and we do say what you send for possible use in future episodes unless you're sending
us an angry screen about why you're not listening anymore in which case.
ha ha ha ha
and if you're on Facebook you can like our page join our discussion group leave reviews and
ratings everywhere but most importantly share this show with a friend whom you know is going to
love it or even be just a little bit like it and finally be sure to go to Ancient Faith.com
Stroke Support and help make sure we and lots of other AFR podcasters stay on the air
thank you very much and may God bless you through the prayers of his foreigner you've been listening
to the Lord of Spirits with Orthodox Christian priests Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father
Stephen DeYoung a listener supported presentation of Ancient Faith Radio and I beheld and I heard the
voice of many angels round about the throne and the beasts and the elders and the number of them
was 10,000 times 10,000 and thousands of thousands seeing with a loud voice worthy as the land
that was slain to receive power and riches and wisdom and strength and honor and glory and blessing
Revelation chapter 5 verses 11 through 12. Welcome to the Thursday edition of the path
you're connected to the path offering strength for our journey towards salvation
Here's Father Tom Siroka today's epistle reading is from St. Paul's second letter to the
Corinthians chapter 1 verses 1 through 7 Paul an apostle of Jesus Christ by the will of God
and Timothy our brother to the Church of God which is at Corinth with all the saints who are in
all Akeah grace to you and peace from God our Father and the Lord Jesus Christ
Blessed be the God and Father of our Lord Jesus Christ the Father of Mercies and God of all comfort
who comforts us in all our tribulation that we may