He will be a staff for the righteous, with which for them to stand and not to fall.
And he will be the light of the nations and the hope of those whose hearts are troubled.
All who dwell on the earth will fall down and worship him, and they will praise and bless and celebrate with song the Lord of Spirits.
1st denoc.
48 verses 4 through 5.
The modern world doesn't acknowledge,
but is nevertheless haunted by spirits,
angels, demons, and saints.
In our time, many year into break free of the prison of a flat, secular materialism,
to see and to know reality as it truly is.
What is this spiritual reality like?
How do we engage with it well?
How do we permeate everyday life with spiritual presence?
Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew Stephen Damick, and Father Stephen De Young
host this live Colin Cho focused on enchantment in creation.
The union of the scene and unseen as made by
God and experienced by mankind throughout history.
Welcome to the Lord of Spirits.
Welcome back everyone to the Lord of Spirits podcast.
I am Father Andrew Stephen Damick in the borough of a maus
and the Commonwealth of Pennsylvania.
And with me is my co-host, Father Stephen D'Young
in Lafayette, Louisiana.
And if you're listening to us live,
you can call in at 855-AF radio.
That's 855237.
2346 and we're going to get to your calls in the second part of today's show.
So last time we talked about sacrifice in the ancient world, why it was done, what was
sacrificed, how it was done, and what it accomplished.
And we touched only very briefly on how that applied to ancient Israel.
Well, this second episode in this three part series is all about ancient Israel.
and we're gonna look at what we...
in the modern world would call the religious life and what it looked like for ancient Israelites,
what it accomplished, how it differed from the surrounding paganism, and also how it was oriented
toward the whole world. So let's go back in time again as best as we can and see what the Holy
Scriptures tell us about prayer and worship, both before the giving of the Torah and after it.
And we should add as a caveat here at the outset that we are largely going to be talking about what was
North.
for ancient Israel, not all the stuff that anyone in Israel did.
So when you see Israelites drifting off into bail worship,
for instance, that was not the norm.
So Father Stephen, what was the norm?
Right, and we're not talking about norm Peterson or norm McDonald
or even the late great norm Crosby.
What we're really talking about is in terms of the norm.
what the Torah said Israel was to do.
What God told Israel in terms of how he wanted to be worshiped in particular.
Right.
And this is an important caveat to make because one of the frankly worst arguments
that our atheist friends like to make, I guess the Old Testament in particular
and Christianity.
in general is they will they will come and say well the old Testament says that
Israel where ancient Israel was monotheistic and believed in unitary and
monotheism but when we do archaeology we find all this pagan stuff so see
it's all a lot wow everything in that sentence is wrong yes yes this is
another thing that is frackedily
wrong. Right? Every early wrong just as wrong as the whole thing. That should be on we should
get a t-shirt that says fractually I mean I'm sure there are people right now making t-shirts for us
but one of them folks should be should say fractally wrong. We've done a lot of debunking of the
whole monotheism bit. But if you actually read the Old Testament and
some of the people who make this bad argument have and are deliberately
misrepresenting it for the sake of rhetorical points because they know even most
Christians haven't read most of the Old Testament or they haven't read it either
right they just think this argument from somewhere that if you actually read the
old testament. You see that the Old Testament after the Torah...
is the story of how Israel didn't follow the Torah.
Yes, right. There's all kinds of moments where God sends a prophet to
Israel and says, you did it again. You wondered off into
idolatry culminating in the exile, right? Like that's right.
It's disopensied and then exile. That's what it says
happens. So the reason we know, for example, that from Solomon on,
They were worshiping...
Shemesh and Shemesh Zedekah the Sun God in particular
In the temple in Jerusalem alongside Yahweh the God of Israel is because the Bible tells us they were
Yeah
The reason we know about the golden calves at Bethel and Dan is not because we found them in an archeological dig. It's because the Bible tells us they were there
Yeah as the official state religion of the northern kingdom. So
If you believe that what the Bible is telling us of the Old Testament is true
them when we go and dig in Israel.
we should expect to find a bunch of pagan stuff.
Right? That's what they say is going to be.
So what we're about to describe in sort of talking about the religious experience of an ancient Israelite is
we're presupposing that this is one of the faithful Israelites.
Right.
Yes. Exactly.
Who were in the minority but did exist.
Right. There's the 10,000 in the Northern Kingdom who never bowed their need of bail.
There's some presumably larger group in Judah, the same thing.
So we're talking about those folks and what their religious experience consisted of.
Right.
And perhaps another, I mean, you've already mentioned this, but another point to kind of
underline is that this is not the stuff that they came up with, largely speaking, right?
This is stuff that we have...
direct commandments from God, this is what you should do.
You know, celebrate this feast in this way, offer this sacrifice in this way.
Like the book of Leviticus in particular is like a liturgical book pretty much.
You know, explaining how to do worship in ancient Israel and when to do it and all that kind
of stuff.
And that's largely what we're talking about is these, these are the commandments from God.
This is what we're you're supposed to do.
Alright.
And like everything in the Old Testament, this isn't material that fell out of the sky,
but it's speaking into an existing cultural situation. So a lot of what we're going to be
trying to bring out tonight is just like with, you know, the flood story in Genesis is in many ways
similar to the other flood stories you find in the ancient Near East, but then there are important
differences right right where it's correcting things and we've seen that with
stories as well in past episodes. It's the same thing with the commandments regarding worship.
This is within the context of the sacrificial worship we talked about last time, right?
That was universal, but then there are certain particular qualifications and changes made
in terms of how Israel is to do it. Right. So it's not a question of just take what
your neighboring nations do and do it for Yahweh instead.
Yeah.
And I think...
another thing we should also mention, because we got a question about this from someone,
in our Lord of Spirits group, who thought that what we were doing in this series of episodes
was, and the first one we're going to talk about pagan worship, and the second one we're
going to talk about ancient Israel, and then the third one is going to be about atonement,
by the way.
And he was saying, wait, are you guys trying to say that, that, you know, ancient Israel
Isra Light Worship was derived from
paganism and then Christianity is derived from from ancient Israel Israel's worship and the answer that is
No, that's not what we're saying at all
Yes, we're dealing with it in this specific order
But as you said sacrifice was happening it was happening all over the world
We see can enable offering sacrifices and they sure didn't derive that from some kind of surrounding paganism
They are at least as far as the Bible depicts them.
Some of the only people in the world at that point.
point. So, it's not a question of derivation. So, when we talk about distinctions and stuff,
it's, as you said, it's not that Israel says, okay, let's take this pagan worship, and
we're going to make some tweaks here to make it appropriate for Yahweh. That's not what's
going on. It's that everybody is offering sacrifices. And then Yahweh comes in and says,
this is what I want you to do in the sacrifices that you're offering to me. So, I think that's
another important point is we're not making a kind of chronological argument.
argument that paganism is the earliest form of religion. And then and then Jewish monotheism
comes along, you know, that that's not, I mean, there are scholars who say that stuff,
but that's, that's not, that's not consistent with what the scripture actually shows. So
if you believe that the scripture is true, then, then you're not going to take that tech.
And there's, and it's not like you have to, you know, pit the scripture against all scholarship
because, because it's not a universal thing that all scholars say either. I mean, we, this
This is gonna mess the rub.
which we could go down.
But I think that's an important point too,
is we're not saying that ancient Israelite worship
is derived from pagan worship,
that they start out as pagans
and they become something else.
Right.
But it's also not completely antithetical.
Right. Right. Right.
God doesn't come and say.
Radically different.
Everybody else is offering incense and sacrifices.
I want you to come for a period of music
followed by some Torah exegesis.
Yeah. Right.
Right. He doesn't say that to the angel.
He could have.
Yeah.
Right.
But he doesn't.
And so we have to take seriously both the continuity and the discontinuity.
Right.
Exactly.
So now we've done 11 minutes of caveats.
Yes.
Qualified.
But there's.
The rumors.
Exactly.
The big warning terms of service.
Yeah.
Exactly.
Click here.
Click here if you agree to as my father says the most freak
told lie in the world is I have read and accepted terms of services and conditions.
Yeah, someday we're going to find out we've all put ourselves in indentured servitude
without knowing it. All right, so okay, now that we've said all that, let's begin.
And we're going to be talking about both before and after the Torah.
I mean, let's talk a little bit about before the Torah. So before the Exodus, before Moses brings
the people out of Israel.
And you already, the giving of the law does not happen until after the Exodus occurs.
And so, and yet, the people of Israel go to Pharaoh and say, we want to go offer sacrifice
to our God.
And yet there's no Leviticus yet.
There's, you know, but they're offering sacrifices.
It's an existing thing that they're doing, right?
Right.
And you see that in, of course, of the patriarchal narratives in Job.
Alright, hey.
Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob build altars and sacrifice to God in various places.
Exactly.
And one interesting note is that if you actually track through Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob in
the places where they built altars and sacrificed, you'll find that there's one in the territory
of each tribe.
So, huh.
There was an early pre-toral air where tribes sort of had their own historic.
shrines related to their forefathers.
Interesting.
But so, yes, there's this earliest layer
where it is essentially the father of the family,
who is the one active in worship.
And that's not just the father.
Again, we have to think not nuclear families.
Right?
This is, you know, extended families.
So you're talking about the father of the family
maybe the granddad or the great granddad.
if he's still alive, right?
It was the head of the whole clan.
And he's the one who would go, we see this with Joe
back offering sacrifices for his wife and for his children.
And it was the father and the family who offered sacrifices
for his family and the worship that was involved.
that then passes on to the elders.
of the clans and tribes.
Once those small clan units form sort of larger tribal units,
there are elders who are basically those people
for all the different clans that make up the tribe.
Yeah, it's basically the father figure
for each of those tribes, right?
Right, right.
Yeah.
Who is in charge of that?
And so when you get to, and most of what we're gonna be talking
tonight is gonna be in this
Torah period. Right. Right. I mean, we have the most
period. Yeah, we have the most detail about that. Right. Right.
Yeah, we're simply told, for example, Jacob sacrificed at the
altar at Bethel. Like we're not told what?
We're not told how many or how or any of that. It's in the
Torah where we get these instructions from God. But so again,
we have to cure ourselves. There's this perpetual danger of
that is really plagued a lot of Western theology,
in particular, of assuming that the local Jewish community
is what Judaism has always been,
even back into ancient Israel.
All right.
So we probably know better if we think about it
for a few minutes, but ancient Israelites
were not like going to the synagogue on Saturday
to hear a sermon from the local rabbi.
Right, that just wasn't happening.
Yeah, and I think part of the reason, I mean not only that this religion has changed so much over time
but also our understanding of what religion is has changed a lot over time.
You know, and I mean it's it becomes a pastoral issue too like even in our time
you know, what is the task of a husband and father according to
to Christian tradition, he is the one who's supposed to be leading his family.
in prayer. And when we who are husbands and fathers are not doing that, we're actually
falling down on the thing that we're appointed to do by God above all else. And I think
part of the reason why that happens is so much now is because, even for people who are
devout Christians, is because of this concept that religion is a thing that you go do somewhere
else. It's not a natural expression of the family life. You know, so...
So, but we're looking now at this kind of earliest layer, I don't know what layers are right
word, but this earliest stage where there isn't a thing called religion.
Right.
There's simply the things that you do in your family and then that expands to be the things
that the tribe does, they're the same things.
And then you get the nation, but it's still not regarded as, oh, we have this religion.
You know, it's not a religion.
Right.
Not at all, is there no cuts?
of A religion, right? That's a 17th century innovation. But there's no concept of religion as opposed to
other things, like religion versus politics versus... Right. Capitalism versus... Right. Yeah.
So there's there is simply no concept of it. So what we're really talking about
is a way of living your life in your
family and in your community, in your clan, in your tribe, in your nation, right?
It's a collective and public way of living life.
It evolves at the small level of your family.
So this isn't purely an internal thing, the way we think about religion in the modern world
where it's about what you believe in your heart or what you think in your head.
This is a public way of living.
and of worshipping your God and interacting with your God
and with your community and with your family
and with others in general.
Yeah, I mean, yeah, it's notable that at no point
that I can recall on the Old Testament
did anyone ever say, how did you feel about worship today?
Right.
Did you get anything out of it?
Where did you get it?
Yeah, that was a great sacrifice today, Aaron.
Yeah, they might have said,
They better, they better said where you fed.
they were talking about how much you ate at the feast after the feast.
Right.
They were literally talking about whether you were fed.
Yeah.
The Levites were really on today, weren't they?
Right.
Well, it ends.
Yeah, well, yeah, it's a little bit of a rabbit trail, but you see some of the earliest
sins you see attributed to clergy like Eli and his sons and the Old Testament are basically
gluttony.
Right.
That they're like fat off the sacrifices.
Yeah.
that it's about...
indulgence. But so to talk about the way of life of people at that time, we have to sort
of, it's very different from any way of life that we live as modern people, at least in
first world industrialized, technologically advanced countries. So the, we're living under
late capitalism there in a primarily agrarian economy.
So most people are farmers living on ancestral land that they were granted in the Torah
And working that land in order to feed their families and survive
Yeah, and then once once Israel is settled in the land
You have the beginning of towns and cities and so that brings in the elements of
Mercantile economy and
and a T-Z-DL economy, our T-Z-DL economy being making things, right?
So you have people making furniture.
and the mercantile economy of people taking resources
and the things that people make from one place
to another place.
Right, training them around.
Yeah, moving them around.
But so that's sort of the economic background.
And so one of the reasons why you don't have
this separation of religion
or your interactions with your God from
everything else is that the structures that we have now in our modern society that allow us
to compartmentalize quote unquote religion and compartmentalize God and our interactions with him
richly and otherwise it weren't there right so if the crops are bad one year one or more of your
children is probably going to die of starvation in front of you.
Yeah, there's this insulation that we now have because, frankly, because of our technological
advancement, right?
Like, I mean, literally, what do I do for living as I sit in front of this microphone,
among other things?
I mean, we do have a garden in the back, but you know what, we can decide, you know, we're
not going to do a garden this year.
And it's, and no one in our house is going to starve as a result, right?
And I think that this lack of dependence on
Vine help is one of the reasons that we have this concept of religion as a kind of boutique
piece of life, right?
Or just like, yes, yes, you should have some religion, even at best, right?
That when your life depends upon things that are totally outside of your control or significantly
outside of your control, then you're much more likely to be calling upon your God.
right and it's interesting to know that even like in the pagan world how much of how much the
association of the gods was with things that were necessities of life and survival right you know
you've got gods of agriculture and of warfare and of you know all of that kind of stuff
And the modern world has become so convenient that we feel
like we don't, it's not that we really disproved
the existence of God is that we just don't feel
we don't need him.
You know, man, we don't need him, right?
Or like, let's add a little blessing.
Oh, we're about to do this thing.
That's, okay, God won't you bless it,
but we all know it depends on us
because we got this, right?
And this is a radically different world
we're talking about.
This is a world where if you go off into the wilderness,
There is no one in charge out there.
If you get beat up by robbers, there are no police to call.
If you go out into the woods and you encounter something, there is no certain rescue,
you know, from the local government that's going to come take care of you.
There was no like Israelite police state or state in general.
They were not practicing some kind of war fascism or something in.
Yeah.
in Asia, Israel, where they were, you know, the state was there to hold your hand and take care of things.
and make sure you were fed.
And you are on your own.
And it's you and your neighbors and your God.
That's life hangs on that.
Yeah.
And so this is an everyday thing, right?
You're constantly aware of your dependence on God,
your direct dependence on him.
And so, uh...
But it's not a coincidence then that the most basic level of the Israelite calendar, that
the first layer of the Israelite calendar is based on the agrarian calendar.
And we're going to talk later on tonight about the, at least a little bit in brief, about
the feast on that calendar.
But they're related to the harvest primarily.
you're living it in a gray and worse.
world. Right? And so the Harvard planting, C time and harvest, these things are events of
religious significance. Yeah. Right. And form the basis of the community between the human
community and God. Right. Right. So, so how, okay, so if we've got this world in which
Sacrifices are being offered.
in the home and in the neighborhood essentially, right?
But then eventually we get to the point where we see that Israel has this kind of priestly
tribe, the tribe of Levi, right?
How does that happen?
Why does it that then they become the ones who are offering sacrifice on behalf of everyone
else rather than just being, you know, this is something that dad does, right?
Why is it that gets separated out?
the
elders were bad. Oh, so they were they were very bad. So we won't go into it because this
is an episode in and of itself in terms of priesthood being removed from Moses and given to Aaron.
We're going to touch on a lot of things this episode that will someday get blown up into a whole
independent episodes and that is our deal.
But the priesthood being taken away from Moses and high priesthood being given to Aaron.
But there's this second episode where the priesthood gets taken away from the presviders,
from the elders of the people.
And that happens in the episode of the Golden Calf, where the presviders, the elders of
people join with Aaron in sacrificing
to the Golden Calf while Moses is on the mountain.
When Moses comes down to settle things up
and take care of the situation, it's the Levites,
the tribe of Levi, who comes to stand with him.
And so because of that, the priesthood was taken away
from the presbyters, from the elders,
and given to the Levites as a separate class.
And the part that we're really gonna only touch on in brief,
but maybe more in a future episode
is that bit?
that, just like priest and king from Moses and Eric, it's reunited in Christ.
We see very clearly in the New Testament that
eldership, the press bitter it, and priesthood get reunited in the church when this judgment is
taken care of. But that will have to wait for another time. But so that means there's now a
a particular priesthood.
And we talked about a little bit when we were talking about God's body about the
imports of God says there's only going to be one place.
Right?
Which is here's a big point of discontinuity from paganism where in the various
pagan systems you created a body for your God and idol of a particular place
you localized. Every God was localized to a bunch of different places and sort of
had these different instantiations and these different
places, whereas Yahweh, God of Israel says, I'm going to put my name in this one place.
My body is going to be in this one place in the temple.
So to worship him, you have to go there.
Right.
You can't offer sacrifice in your backyard anymore.
So this means for your average Israelite who lives probably weeks journey from Jerusalem.
he's a faithful is.
real life. This is one of the lures of paganism and of the sort of false religion of the
northern kingdom under Jeroboam with the golden calves is you didn't have to go as far.
Yeah. Well, there's one of these just down the street. There's a high place right outside
the town. Yeah. Right. But to be faithful, you would have to make this journey. And so
That means you weren't doing it every Saturday.
Yeah, it's just...
too much. Because it would take you weeks to get there. You literally functionally could
not. And so for the average Israelite, this becomes usually a single annual pilgrimage.
If they were well to do or if they were involved in the mercantile trade so they're moving
around more, that they might be in Jerusalem for more of the major feasts. But for the average
and this would be, you would make a pilgrimage once a year for Pascar for Passover to
Jerusalem, and that would be the main time.
And so there's even instructions in the book of Deuteronomy saying to do this, accepting
that this is going to be the reality, and saying that therefore a person should save
up their tithe.
the tithe, the first fruits, all the things that you would have offered to God.
because you can't get to the temple to do it,
you're supposed to save it all up
for the time of the Passover for Paska.
And then when you make the journey,
you take all that money,
and it says to buy wine or other strong drink,
meaning fermented drink, sorry to our Baptist friends.
And food and to eat and to drink them before the Lord.
Yeah, before the Lord.
Right. Does it mean in front of him? It means it means with him in his presence. So with the right with him. The meal. Yeah. Right.
And so this is this is sacrificial language, right?
And it's talking about having this communal meal once a year because realistically, that's when you could do it and you saved up the
tied, you saved up everything for that.
Yeah, and I mean, if you're saving it all up, so PASCA...
not so much over is in the spring, right?
But you've got these other ties that are coming
at other times of year, first fruits, et cetera, et cetera.
You probably can't, it's not gonna necessarily
keep all that time, right?
So what do you do?
You sell some of it so that you have the money.
Yeah, you got the money set aside.
Right.
And bring that with you.
It probably the most famous biblical example
someone doing exactly that is a
Christ and the Apostles, going to Jerusalem for the Passover and renting a room and buying
food and wine and other strong drink and literally eating and drinking it with the Lord
because Christ was sitting there at the table.
Yeah.
Yeah, he's actually sitting there.
God is at the table.
Yeah.
or the last supper is
is the fulfillment of this in a very literal sense.
This is the place in time where it most really and truly
happened.
But the religious experience of the average
Israelite really was about faithfulness.
This is why faithfulness is so important with Abraham.
Abraham and Genesis doesn't have a temple.
He doesn't have priests.
He doesn't have any of this stuff.
Bye.
But it's about how he lived each day, how he conducted himself with his wife and his
children and his servants, how he conducted business, how he interacted with the people
he encountered as he sojourned in different places.
And so it was the same thing for the average Israelite.
Being faithful to God was not about believing certain things in his head, or feeling certain
things in his heart, or holding to certain doctrines.
was about every day what
he did from when he woke up to when he went to sleep, most of which was farm work.
Yeah.
And I think it should probably be mentioned that we're not talking about only being sort
of ethical, right, being a good person, although obviously that's included, right, you're
expected to behave ethically, but rather that all is done with prayers that all is done with,
you know, like for instance the ties are literally taking your
your
livelihood and giving it to God, right? That it's not a system of doctrine and morals,
although certainly those things are included. It's, as you said, it is a whole way of life.
Right. Well, we have this, probably the biggest difference between the religion of the Torah
and every other religion in world history.
I'll go that far.
Is that...
Ethics is religious in the Torah.
There is no system of ethics attached to Greco-Roman paganism.
Right.
But because the closest thing you get in paganism is the idea of religiously,
is the idea that there are certain ways you have to act when you're in a temple or towards a temple or towards an idol, towards a God.
Right?
But what happens in the Torah is we find out that humanity is made in the image of God.
So every human you meet every day is the image of God,
is God's body in that sense. And so how you treat them and act to them, that is a religious act
you're doing into God. Right. Yeah, it is an act of piety. Yeah. Right. Yeah. You're
So generating them right yeah so you know
a little bit related to that. Before we go to break, we received a question from Evan,
who sent this to us, and this has connected somewhat with our previous episode, where we talked
about incense, but this actually does integrate into this episode because we were talking about
as we would think of it, religious life of the average faithful Israelite. Right? So Evan has a
question about the use of
incense in the home. So this is what he says. With incense being something that is offered to God
and with the sacriotal priests and bishops being the ones that offer the sacrifice of the
Eucharist and offering incense in the services of the Church, how are we to understand the practice
of using incense at home during family or personal prayers? Does it have the same kind of propititory
and or expiatory effect there when used by lay people as it does during the services of the church
by the priest, or is it different perhaps even to the extent of just
being a pleasant smell for us when we pray in that context.
So what do you think, Father?
Right.
Well, there's continuity and discontinuity.
Yeah.
There you go.
That's, so you do find for the average ancient Israelite,
we'll stay where we are, right, historically.
And this is a massive flash forward from last time, by the way.
We're only talking about the second millennium BC now.
And some of it's your first millennium BC.
This is...
recent times. But we find, you know, incense boats, ways of offering incense in the home,
but not altars of incense. Right? So there is a distinction between what's going on when
incense is offered on the altar in the tabernacle or the temple. And when incense is offered
with prayers at home, although incense is offered with prayers at home.
Right now this isn't a complete discontinuity. It's not two different things right so it's not just
This is my
Febris plug-in right
Yeah, like an active worship right and I sometimes I hear people say oh, I like this
I like to smell when I pray at home like well that's good, but it's not the reason that we offer in sense when we pray at home
Right right and so
So it is in a sense those
things you do at home, like when you have an icon corner and you offer incense there when
you pray, it's a way of participating in the worship of the church when you're not there
in the church. Right. And so there's a connection. Now, it wasn't feasibly possible at that
time for somebody to go and get a call from the altar of incense and take it home with
them right. Yeah. Again, it's.
week's journey and don't ask your priest for that now.
Yeah, please.
I want to use charcoal.
But but the idea is the same.
Right.
And so it's different enough that it's what is not a substitute for the other.
One is more full, more rich, right.
but it is a sort of lesser degree of participation.
right in the reality.
Exactly.
All right.
Well, we're going to go ahead and take our first break
and we will be right back.
Father Andrew Stephen Daymak and Father Stephen DeYoung
will be back in a moment to take your calls
on the next part of the Lord of Spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF Radio.
Are you struggling in your walk with Christ?
Do you want to rediscover your reason for living?
The person you are created to be.
Renewing you, a priest, a psychologist, and a plan gives you the keys to unlock areas of
your life that hold you back from fully experiencing the renewal and transformation God has in mind for
you.
Co-author by a priest and a psychologist, Father Nicholas and Dr. Roxanne Lowe, renewing
you combines principles of spiritual growth with secular
to help you become your best self, fully connected with God's
purpose for you. To purchase this book, please go to store.
www.ancientfaith.com
Hi, this is Father Evan Armitas, priest at St. Spirit on Greek Orthodox Church in Luland, Colorado.
In the host of the Ancient Faith Radio Sunday Night Call and Show, Orthodoxy Live,
I am pleased you're now
Today the release of my first book for ancient faith publishing, title, toolkit for spiritual
growth, a practical guide to prayer fasting and armsgiving.
It seeks to provide a guide to the three basic and primary disciplines of Orthodox spirituality.
Through these disciplines Christ opened for us a path that frees us from the disordered
way of life has become normal for many, even though their hearts and minds tell them otherwise.
Please join me in exploring the three-legged stool of Orthodox spiritual practice.
are fasting.
and I'm giving books now available at store.ancientfaith.com
And the title once again is Toolkit for Spiritual Growth.
I look forward to sharing it with you.
God bless.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits,
the Father Andrew Stephen Damick
and Father Stephen DeYoung.
If you have a question, call now at 855-237-2346.
3, 4, 6. That's 8558.
A.F. Radio.
Welcome back. This is the second half of the show. We're ready to take your call. So you
just heard the voice of Steve. Feel free to give us a ring. 8558F radio. All right. We
were just talking about incense. So that actually leads very nicely into the next part of our
discussion. So, you know, it's not like, again, it's not like religion as we think of it
right now where we tend to think...
religion is something that happens, you know, for most of us, it happens on Sunday morning.
There's religion down there at the church and then we come home and I remember, you know,
even when I was pastoring, I did have, it just didn't happen very often, but I did have
people like, well, what do you do during the week, Father? And it's like, well, actually,
you know, we have services during the week. We do come to the church and pray and offer
Incess among other things.
things, right? So was it the same in ancient Israel? Were they doing services every single
day at the Tabernacle and then later the temple?
Yeah, I mostly play Assassin's Creed during the week, but it's good that I'm glad you're
there. Nothing else to do. You're there praying for me, I'm glad.
Oh man, you just ruined a lot of pastor's day.
Look, father Steven.
please assess its creed during the week,
but you'll handle the prayer for me, won't you, Father?
Yes, of course.
Well, yeah, no.
No.
You can tell I was being facetious because I said it.
Um, so yeah, that's what we're going to talk about in this
half of the several haves we have this evening.
Yes, that's right.
Is we're talking about the different offerings going on at the
tabernacle and then the later
temple and these different types of offerings also serve as building blocks. They're like
Legos, right, or the knockoff duplow blocks that I used to get. No bitterness here at all.
Anyway, they're sort of like Legos in the sense that they existed their own right and
they're going on at the Tabernacle and Leader temple in their own right. But then when we get
to the Feast.
right, they'll sort of put together in different ways for sort of larger ritual celebrations.
So as one example that we'll talk about more next time when we talk about atonement and
the day of atonement in particular is, you know, sort of the first instruction for the
day of atonement is that the high priest and his sons who are assisting him need to go
and offer sin offerings for themselves.
and it doesn't spell that out at the time because it's already told you what a
offering is. So he's just sort of plugged that in there. So these not only are offerings
that were done, but they're also building blocks for larger ritual realities from
beasts and other celebrations. And so that starts with the very first commandment concerning
worship. And let me, this is another brief digression, but let me go ahead and do it.
We're talking about...
we're talking about worship. It's important that we already mentioned this that God gave particular commands, but worship is something we're offering to God, right?
Which means we need to offer him what he wants, not what we want to give and what we want to offer.
Yeah, and it's not it's not a show we're putting on for the people who come.
Right.
So that runs against our idea of worship. We like to be
We want to express ourselves and our creativity and that kind of thing from a biblical perspective is really bad
and dangerous
But but if you even think about it for a minute, I mean the things that are offered
In sacrifice are universally referred to as gifts and we talked about how it's hospitality
Right, so when you're giving hospitality you're giving something to please the guest not like what you like
and you want to give to them. But the example I give a lot of the time is that if my anniversary
or my wife's birthday rolls around and I get her a Makita cordless power drill, right,
she's not going to be happy. That's not because it's a lousy drill, right? That's not because
it's not a very useful tool. Or there's something wrong with it. It's that that's not what she wanted.
right my wife wanted a saber-toothed tiger skull not a bikini cordless
actual Christmas gift. Yeah I was gonna say this sounds too specific to just being made up on the spot. So yeah. So yeah, my wife once wanted a
a a limonator. So that is what she received. Right. So that's that. So if what God wants, right, are these things, that's what we we give to him and and and bring it.
Yeah.
So
the first commandment he gives, so sort of the baseline, right, for what's going to happen
to the Tabernacle and then the temple is given in Exodus chapter 30 and that's basically
the incense is to be offered on the altar of incense at morning and at evening.
Right.
Every day.
I don't know if you want to actually read that.
Read those.
Yeah, I'm going to read that and then we actually have a call coming in this directly related
to this.
the column seconds. Okay.
So this is Exodus chapter 30 verses 7 through 9.
Aaron shall burn on it, sweet incense every morning.
When he tens the lamps, he shall burn incense on it.
And when Aaron lights the lamps at twilight, he shall burn incense on it,
a perpetual incense before the Lord throughout your generations.
He shall not offer strange incense on it, or a burnt offering, or a grain offering,
nor shall you pour a drink offering on it.
So it's...
reserved for incense only and it particular times.
It being the altar of incense, yeah.
Yeah, right.
And not the strange incense.
So there's a particular kind you're supposed to use.
Right.
So, all right.
So we've got James from Washington and he's calling specifically about incense.
So James, can you hear me?
Welcome to the Lord of Spirits.
I can hear you.
Thank you for having me on.
Great.
What's your question or comment, James?
So I actually recently started thinking about this in context of the last episode, talking about incense and how it was used as a
purgatory type thing where you're cleaning out for demonic worship as well of like one kind of demon that you're being worshiped and you use incense to cleanse the area.
So I was wondering why would that, what is it being cleansed from, is it other demons that is being cleansed from and why would they not like that particular
older in a sense. Maybe they have like different factions.
of different kinds of smells that they might have.
And then I was thinking about going back into the actual regulations in this particular
passage in Exodus 30 about how God gave a very specific recipe for what kind of incense
supposed to use and not use strange or foreign incense and then when Moses or Aaron's sons
used that strange fire, they were killed for it.
and so there's like a very strict rules about that.
But then I also noticed in my-
modern in usage, we have some people who use that same exact recipe for incense and other
people who use other ones like for another, you know, for an imagi when they have particular
incense for them or for the initiation they use different incenses for different time
periods. So it's like if this not, it's strict anymore. So I was wondering if you could comment
on that part.
Well, that's a great question and I have no answer to any of that but I'm pretty sure
Did it bother Steven or something?
Yeah, it's really interesting actually.
just don't know. Alright so father I'm sure you know something. Yeah yeah I've
tempted to reinsert my highest reference from last time but I'll spare everyone
because whether Andrew didn't get it anyway. But yeah so it's not an issue of
like that particular smell drives them away drives evens away like garlic
with vampires or something. Yeah so there's sort of there's sort of two pieces
pieces here. So the first piece is...
The purgative element has to do with the fact that, and we'll get into this a little more in just a minute, but
We have a very trans, we talked about this a little last time. We have a very trans-
Xactional view of sin, right? Sin is breaking a rule committing a crime
And that's been sort of
Invested in us through our American Puritan religious culture, but in actuality
we talk about this power or force that's out there.
active in the world. And that's how St. Paul talks about sin not sins most of the time.
And that leaves a residue, the way it's talked about in the Torah and the rest of the Old Testament
is very much more like a disease. And now that we've all been quarantined for a year,
We all have a much better idea of this.
It's not just the idea.
It's not just the disease or a person with the disease that we have to worry about.
It's things that have been touched by the person with the disease.
Right?
Coming into the place afterwards, the air that's been breathed out by the person with the disease.
That things become tainted or infected by sin.
The material creation becomes affected and tainted by sin.
So the the
Pergative element of sacrifice that expiation element is
is cleansing and removing and purifying from that tape.
So it's not just driving the demons out
but removing the residue that they've left
and the residue of our sins.
So this is when people ask me why I need to come every year
and bless their house after the offeneer,
I say, well, I don't, as long as you don't sin in it.
Right.
And we don't tell people that.
We don't need to bless and be dedicated
as long as you don't commit any sins there.
Bye.
You know, let's sit into your house.
And so that's the same kind of thing with incense.
That's why we sense the sanctuary at the beginning
or right before the beginning of all of our services.
It's cleansing and rededicating the physical space.
And that's something that we, as Margaret Mary
and so on, have this ontological understanding
of sin and sort of stuff is sort of grime,
the sort of literal filth.
That's why there's such a connection between...
in an uncleanness in the Torah and in the Old Testament.
So you're kind of cleaning the air.
In terms of the, I'm sorry.
So when you're worshiping demons with incense,
does that sense that you're actually like putting slit out there,
like you're deliberately consuming the air with sin?
And that's in the court in the reverse of that thing?
Yeah.
In some cases, they use it to cut.
certain spirits, but even even pagans had an idea that there were spirits they wanted to interact with
and spirits they didn't want to interact with. Yeah and I imagine I imagine that offering
incense to a particular spirit is part of like it's not just like like you were asking about
the sort of recipe James but I can't imagine I don't know correct me off this if I'm wrong about
this father but I can't imagine that particular recipes kind of drive away certain kinds of
the spirit. Like you said, go.
with vampires, but rather that it's a question of participation in offering this as a sacrifice to
the spirit that you're offering it to, right? And not then to the other ones around. Am I getting that right?
I feel like a heraldry kind of thing where I'm doing this because this is related to you. This is your
pattern. And so I'm using that same pattern to put an address on the fair in a sense.
Right, and the pagan gods and other spirits were involved in these come.
constant conflicts with each other. So you're driving away the enemies of the
God that you want to write the the antithetical enemy spirits of the God that
you're wanting to be there and interact with. Yeah in terms of the recipe and
us not having a recipe per se, this is one of the major things that happen. We're
We're going to talk about this a lot more last time, our last time, next time.
I'm apparently time traveling now.
But we were talking about this a lot more next time
when we talk about atonement.
But part of what happens in Christ's atonement
is that the entire material world becomes cleansed.
And so you no longer have material objects and things
and animals and trees and plants and places that are
necessarily unclean by nature anymore.
And so you'll find in the Torah things being very limited in terms of material, right?
What material things can and can't be made out of.
And of course, all the food laws.
And all of this is a product of that is that they're there.
We have to view ancient Israel or the camp of the wilderness and then ancient Israel
when they were functioning the way they were supposed to be as sort of this island,
island, the Set-A-Part Island of Holiness.
in this world consumed with darkness.
Right, and so-
And I can utilize.
Yeah, so there's these particular things
that are made clean and holy and sacred
and everything else in any deviation from that
is still part of that corruption.
And there's this major transition
and we're gonna talk about this with Christ's atonement
and then the coming of the Holy Spirit
and how this...
island comes to then expand and encompass the creation.
But that's why there is no now particular recipe for incense that is more or less clean. But
if you get orthodox incense, when the incense is being rolled and the incense is being made,
there are prayers that are said and blessings that are asked for. So it's sort of parallel to foods,
Right now we receive all foods with prayer and thanksgiving.
right as opposed to only certain foods being clean and certain other foods being unclean.
It's the same thing with incense essentially.
Yeah.
Does that on us?
Yes.
In incense sense as it were.
Sorry.
All right.
Well, does that answer your question then, James?
It absolutely does.
I am slightly on the point of there's no, you know,
you know, pomegranate, pumpkin spice,
peppers, or demons, where the others.
Yeah, it's really fun. I really appreciate the answer there excellent pumpkin spice pumpkin spice
Summons white girls and drives me
For the record
All right, well, thank you for calling in James nice to hear from you all right
So we talked about incense offerings
There's a bunch of other offerings we would talk about in this particular segment
So let's let's get rolling here. So what's the next one?
in this of our
have. Yes, right. Yeah, and some people ask like, how can you have a third half? It's like because
this is one and a half shows. Yeah. This particular episode is kind of four halves because this is
a double double show. Two shows for the price of one. There you go. Cheap is free, right? Yes.
Exactly. So the next set we're going to tell you is sin offerings, right? Right. And these are
sacrifices, obviously, that are sacrificed on the altar of burnt offering, not on the altar of
in sense.
And these importantly, sin offerings, if you read Leviticus closely, I know it's hard,
and I know no one wants to do it, but it's worth what it pays off if you actually do it.
Leviticus is very clear that it's not always animals.
Right.
It's always food.
Yeah, it's always food.
Sometimes it's cakes, right?
it's it's uh alcoholic beverages.
Right?
And oil.
Oil.
And sometimes then there's also meat from an animal that has been killed because that's
where you get meat.
But in sin offerings, the killing, again, as we talked about last time, is not ritualized.
You have to kill it so you can eat it, right?
You have to slaughter an animal to prepare it as meat.
the killing part is not...
ritualized. It's just about again food and everything we said about we've said
about sacrifices already applies to this. Right. Right. But it's also not again
talking about that transactional view of sin. It's not responsive. It's not like
the priest were sort of sitting around the tabernacle going, oh we get to
do any sin offerings today. Oh here comes Simeon. Always lion. It's got a sheep
with them. Suppose we're gonna have to sacrifice it again. Right. Right. It's
Right, it's this ongoing thing.
Send offerings are being offered every day, right?
Right, continuously.
Yeah, because sin is in the world.
And it's a driving off of that effect, a cleansing of that effect.
It's not one to one.
It's not like paying a fine to God.
Oh, you know, we sinned, so we've got to make it, we're going to fix it.
Right?
And this, I think, is such a critical point.
because there's a lot of bad theology out there,
I'm just gonna call it,
there's a lot of bad theology out there
that thinks that's what sacrifice is.
But sin offerings, it's interesting that they are
specifically the sin offerings are specifically not that.
You know?
Right, so it's like,
I don't know, you know,
in some ways it's like that offering of incense,
which is done to purify and cleanse whatever,
and we don't...
I don't say, okay, how sinful I was this morning.
I'll put three pieces of incense in the censor today.
Like, oh man, I had a big fight with my wife last night.
Son, you gotta put 10 pieces of incense on the censor.
It's not like that.
There's not a, it's not quantitative.
It's not retributive.
It's not any of that.
Right, and there's this bizzara world idea,
and I call it that, because you just can't get it
from the old testament.
But a lot of people have it in their heads,
that, you know?
someone would steal something and so they'd say oh no I stole something God's gonna
kill me but if I kill this goat he'll take that instead. So I'm gonna go down
to the tabernacle of the temple and kill this goat. Yes and then everything will be
okay and I can go on my where Mary way. That's not it at all. Yes, citation needed.
The rest of what?
The sin offerings for all the thefts and all the lies.
and all the unfaithfulness and all the sins that are being committed are going on all the time
at the tabernacle in the temple. And when I steal something, what I do to repent is I
go and
pay back, make restitution, right? What I stole plus four times more,
right, to the person I stole from, right?
And then, right, then I have
have repented. Right?
And the combination of the sin offering that's going on at the Tabernacle or Temple,
that I'm nowhere near, I'm weeks away, and me repenting and making the restitution is
what takes care of the situation and restores the situation.
But the thing that I do is make the restitution.
Right.
Make it right.
And that's how sins are dealt with in the Torah.
There aren't like public beatings and floggings.
like in homerobies code to punish you for what you did.
There aren't, you aren't like maimed or disfigured, right?
Like in homerobies code, right?
Based on what you did, right?
There are limits placed on vengeance,
but see, even vengeance is a communal means
of restoring justice.
It's a way of rebalancing the scales, even vengeance.
And so the Torah limits vengeance to keep it
from going up.
of control. But restitution is what's called for.
Yeah, and there's also another side to this, which I think is also is really important
to underline, which is why, okay, so why do you need to deal with sin, right? It's not just
like I don't want to go to hell when I die or something like that. Like there's something
much, although, you know, we should maybe, we'll flesh that out in our episodes on sacred
geography. You know, I know.
people are waiting on those. But no, there is actually a reason to deal with sin. And that is that
God's presence is potentially dangerous. And so you deal with sin so that God will remain
present with you. And the reason why is because God's presence in the presence of sin
burns that away, right?
If you retain sin and you enter into the presence of God, then that is harmful for you.
Because God's holiness does that to things that are corrupted by sin.
And of course we see in the Old Testament a number of times where God withdraws his presence
in response to great sin, not because I'm going to punish you by leaving, but rather I'm
going to leave to give you a chance not to be annihilated by being in the
Presumably.
of the holy God. Right. And that's why it's necessary. And our color James, and I'm not picking on him.
I'm not picking on you, James. But you notice when he brought up Aaron, sons,
Nehda, and Abahu, how he just defaulted into expressing it. They broke the rules about incense,
until they were killed. Yeah. Right. Which which isn't actually what the story says of Leviticus.
What the story says in Leviticus is that they came in
to God's presence unworthily and the fire of God's presence
incinerated them.
Yeah.
That's very different, right?
That's very different.
And so yes, this is for God to live among His people,
this holiness and purit needs to be maintained.
Because otherwise God is going to break out
and consume the camp or He's going to have to leave, which
He does in the exile.
Yeah.
Okay.
So we've got another kind of offering that's given.
There's incense offerings, sin offerings.
Next is peace offerings, peace offerings.
So what's that all about, Father?
And I'm using the Old King James,
Nomenclature on these.
That warms my dinosaur heart so much.
So, ye older, yeah.
Um, so, with those S's that look like F.
Oh, those are the best.
Yes.
So, sin offerings are helping restore the relations within the community and the community's
relationship to God and maintain it on a regular basis, sort of the sin maintenance system.
Peace offerings are whether there's been a major rupture.
Yeah.
So you've got to make that relationship, right?
And so, yeah.
And so this will happen in two situations.
Number one, moments of great repentance, right?
Which, and often these two things are related, right?
Where the community realized, wow, we've really messed up
or we've been messing up for a long time.
Right?
So we need to turn around and repent
and to make peace with God and reestablish
this whole relationship sort of from scratch,
like King Josiah's reforms.
Right.
And sometimes they know that that's necessary
because there's been...
a famine or plague, right? Right. Right. This. Yeah. Yeah. Like, oh, this horrible thing is
befalling all of us. We had better make it right. Right. And it's not. It's not. God gets angry and
punishes them. It's this is what it takes to get their attention. Yes. Right. Right. God permits
this suffering on a mass scale. Precisee to, you know, get them to repent. Right. To prevent
something worse.
down the road if they can bring down the road that they're going.
So relevant for our present moment.
Right.
And so these piece offerings are similar to sin offerings.
They'll often involve sort of more or more valuable animals,
right, or more and more of our grain offering, right,
more is involved to make a bigger-
not because, like, oh, well, this is more powerful.
If you do two bowls, then God will really listen to you.
It's there for the Dunwo.
Right?
It's right.
Keep up those phrases.
Right.
But it's too emphasize, right, to add display,
actual contrition, right?
So if we put this into our hospitality metaphor, right?
There's a difference between me inviting somebody over
who is my friend and I'm just maintaining
deepening that relationship.
and something's come between me and someone else.
I've done something that offended them or hurt them badly
and I'm inviting them to my home to try to make peace.
I'm going to be more giving and more to try to truly express to them how sorry I am.
And the sincerity of the fact that I'm going to try to change.
and not.
do that again. Right. And those same kind of relational terms. Yeah. Yep. Yep. So then to get through
the sort of the last few, these are relatively quick. There are thank offerings which are voluntary.
What they sound like. Yeah. That's what it says on the tin. Yeah. So God gives us gifts. Hopefully
were thankful for them. So we got off our thanks. Yeah. It actually is real a lot of
This was related to taking vows.
Yes, right, right.
Lord, if you do this, then I will, if you do this for me,
then I will offer a sacrifice in Thanksgiving.
Right, if God does the thing, you know, offers sacrifice.
Right, right, right.
Don't be like the nine lepers who just went off in detention.
Yeah, right.
That's it.
And then grain offerings, which are usually attached to,
their type of thank offering really but they're related to
the harvest generally. So it's the first fruits of the harvest. We'll talk about the
feast of first fruits. And then drink offerings which were just drink offerings just means
it's liquid, not that you drink it. And those are sometimes done independently like at the
olive and grape harvest, where you just offer oil or wine, but usually it's done in the
context of another sacrifice where the oil and the wine and or the wine are poured out
on what it is that you are offering.
Yeah, and so then question I have about that is,
like one of the things I think that oil and,
especially strong wine, maybe having common
other than being liquid, is that they're flammable.
Is that, is that an element of it?
You know, that you poured out on the sacrifice
to make it so it's easier to light?
To make it easier to light and that the light right
it would be hard to sacrifice water.
Um, right. Yes.
I should have pulled it off, but he had help.
Yes, so, but it's dead.
Yeah, so, should I do the Father Stephen Roons
your Sunday school since I brought this?
Yes, we might as well, before we get to our next break.
Yeah, it's time for Father Stephen Roons
your Sunday school.
Fire from heaven, particularly the context of the bail cycle.
And so bail is the, what's that issue in the story
of the Prophet Elijah, not Carmel.
Fire from heaven is a-
way of, uh, is the way that they described lightning. So it's actually say that lightning struck
the altar of the sacrifice and it wasn't some fiery funnel of fire coming down in a big
spiral and it was not. It was not. We made an amateur video when I was in eighth grade
of this episode where we took some GI Joe figures and wrapped them in toilet paper as robes
and made a little altar with a plastic cow on it and then like zoomed in real tight at
and spray some W
to D-40 over a lighter like in front of the lens
to incinerate everything, but that was not historically accurate.
And we'll be releasing that on YouTube later this month.
Yes.
All right.
Well, now that Father Stephen has ruined Sunday school
for all of you, let's take our next break.
Father Andrew Stephen Daymak and Father Stephen DeYoung
will be back in a moment to take your calls
on the next part of the Lord of Spirits.
Give them a call at 8.5.
52372346. That's 855 AF radio.
As the orthodox Christian tradition is filled with wisdom and guidance about the biblical path of salvation,
yet this guidance remains largely inaccessible to parents and often disconnected from the parenting challenges we face in our homes.
Parenting toward the kingdom by Dr. Philip Marmalakis, PhD, will help you make the connections between the
your life as we understand it in the Orthodox Church and the ongoing challenges of raising children.
It takes the best child development research and connects it with the timeless truths of
our Christian faith to offer you real strategies for navigating the challenges of daily life.
When I try and say, well, here's what parenting is, and then here are some strategies for
how we actually parent, and then here's how we understand some of the important aspects of
parenting.
and find parenting towards...
the kingdom and more at store.AncientFace.com.
Again, that is store.AncientFace.com.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits,
the Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung.
If you have a question, call now at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF Radio.
All right, well, welcome to the third half
for the show.
So we just kind of did a lightning fast, pun-fully-intended tour through the offerings, sacrifices
of ancient Israel.
So all right, well let's talk about the ways that some of this is different from the
surrounding paganism.
Because as we said at the beginning, we're not claiming that Israelite worship is derived
from paganism, right?
this is just sort of one paganism that we have privileged as being the one.
true one, right? But there are some really interesting and important discontinuities, right?
So let's talk about some of those. And I know that the one that we wanted to start with
is what is referred to in this wonderful King Jamesy English as the shoe bread, SHEW,
or show bread, right? It's for now. It's for now show either way. I just
Either way, I know warm your heart cockles.
It really does warm my heart.
I almost I almost about to pull down my 1611 King James from the shelf up here and look at those wonderful S's that look like F's so
All right, so show bread
He's the way it's spelled so what is that all right. What's what what is show bread father Steven? Well that thine excitement show with fourth
The it came to pass
Yes.
Yeah, so this is one of the.
So sort of overlooked things.
Yeah.
Maybe, maybe if when you were a kid, you made the little model of the tabernacle.
You made the tiny little table for the show bread.
But other than that, it gets passed over pretty quickly.
So I have to interrupt you there and say this.
I never did that actually.
But my great-great grandfather who was a Baptist preacher up in New England.
He was a
the pastor had a number of churches up there,
but he had a thing that he would do,
and he made a model of the tabernacle,
and he would go around giving presentations on it,
and their pamphlets and stuff from when he did this.
So I'm pretty sure based on what I've seen what he did,
he was very detailed about this.
So I'm sure he must have had a little show bread table.
So even though I never did that,
it is indeed in my blood.
Just had to add that.
He makes tiny-
bread to put on it. I don't know. That would be so cool. I don't know. So this is another thing that does
what it says on the tin, right? This is a sheet bread, a literal table with bread on it. And that
bread was replaced every day and that bread was there to be eaten by the priests during their service
this in the
tabernacle and then later in the temple.
And so I think it gets passed over because people are like,
oh, okay, so there's a place where they kept their sack lunch.
Right?
That was there.
So, that was there.
No, but it's obviously a ritualized thing, you know.
Right.
Because specific instructions about the replacement of the bread
and the exact dimensions of the table and what it was to be made out of
but how it was to be decorated.
And so what this represents is basically an inversion.
We talked about in the past how once a God had been localized in a pagan temple, it was
then cared for by the priests.
So they would dress it.
They would make sure it stayed standing up if it tipped over because there was an earthquake.
And they would bring it food.
So they were servants to and and slay.
to essentially, and providing for this divine spirit that they were worshipping.
So, the fact that there is this table in the presence of Yahweh, the God of Israel,
from which he feeds his priests. So, rather than the priest feeding God,
God is feeding the priests and providing for them is a direct sort of inversion
of what was going on at the pig.
temple and probably the most famous place that people actually have read because they probably
haven't spent a lot of time in Exodus reading the not one but two times that the exact
dimensions of the table are given. They may remember the episode where David while he's
fleeing from Saul needs food badly right where your needs food badly thank you
and I got that one
Okay, so warrior is about to die. So he goes, he's running the gauntlet and he goes.
He goes to the where the priests are serving and he eats some of the the show bread, right?
Yeah. And probably more people than have actually read that original story of the Old Testament,
have read the place where Christ refers to it.
Yes. In the New Testament in the Gospel where Christ refers to it during an issue, one of the
perennial issues between He and the Pharisees. Right. About the Sabbath. Yeah. Where they're like,
like, how dare you do this on the Sabbath? And Jesus says, whoa, guys, you know the Sabbath was made
for man and not man for the Sabbath, right? Right. Don't remember how David ate
the show bread.
Right.
Because the particular issue at that point was that the disciples were as they walked through
a field, clucking heads of grain and eating them.
And so the Pharisee said, hey, that's harvesting, right?
Red card, right?
Low-grade harvesting.
And so Christ talks about, haven't you read where David ate the show bread at the temple?
you don't know that the Sabbath was made for a man not man for the Sabbath.
And it might maybe have Strecus' audits like, well wait, what does one have to do with the other?
Right, right. So like David ate some bread. Okay, they're eating grain. I kind of see that.
And they're doing on the Sabbath. So then he talks about the Sabbath, right. But
the reason Christ is referring to this is, David's on the run from Saul. David is God's anointed,
and God provides food for him. The show bread is all about God feeding his people.
Yeah, and giving his
people what they need. And so in the same way, the same principle, Christ is saying, is
it work in the Sabbath? The Sabbath is a day of rest that's given as a gift. It's not
given as an obligation. Yeah, right. It's not set up as a test. Yes. And then I mean,
this just shows again how different Yahweh is from all of the petty gods of paganism in
that he loves his people.
Right. Right. I mean we see this with the men on the wilderness exactly the same God directly feeding
The people and then of course you know the feeding of the five. I mean we could keep going on and on about this
Right God gives provides us people with food and he provides them with rest on the Sabbath and not only for them
But for their fields for their animals for their servants. Yeah, right. He rides rest for the whole
For the whole creation. That's what connects those two things. Yeah. Yeah
.
All right, so the next one that we wanted to talk about and this was one that really intrigued me because I'd
I'd never paid attention to this
and that's the question of what exactly
the vestments of the high priest are all about so I know if our friend father Timothy
Honikey is listening and I know he is a fan of Lord of Spirits
His ears are pricking up right now because if you ever go to father Timothy's church
he has this vast collection of
of of of of vestments and I think a lot of them have been gifted to him but I know he loves
I love vestments and and well he should he is the best dressed priest in the OCA just putting
that out there.
Uh, anyway, so this is about vestments the high priest vestments. Um, yeah, how does
that compare a contrast to paganism? What's that all about?
Yeah, so, uh, and this is another thing that will probably eventually the whole high priest
and the high priesthood and how that relates to Christy. He was there probably be a future
episode.
No, yeah.
Definitely.
Or to itself.
But for our purposes here, this is another thing that a lot of people don't read through
is the .1, but two times.
We're told a great detail about the vestments of the high priest and what there to be made
out of and all of the deals.
And we're not going to go into super detail about that right now.
But as a broad overview, it atties for that future episode, when you compare that to the
ceremonial garments that were put on idols in pagan canonite temples.
they're virtually identical. So the priest, the high priest, is dressed like an idol, a
canonite idol, right? Is that what you're saying? Yes. Yes. Okay. Yeah. Right. So up to it,
including the Diadem, the crown that's put on his head that has on the front of it the name
of God. It has Yahweh on it, on his forehead.
And this goes back to, and we're going to touch on this again in our fourth half, but this goes back to, right, we've talked about on the show before.
Genesis 1 takes this form of the building of a temple and then Adam is placed there to serve in that temple and Adam is placed there as man is placed there as the image of God.
Right, which is the inversion of the pig.
pattern where man builds a temple, man builds his own image of God. Instead, here man is the image
of God. Right. And so the high priest wears a crown, but he's not a pagan priest king. He doesn't
receive worship himself. Right. Right. The pagan God kings do get worship like this, the people
are worshipping them. Right. Because they are what of the bodies of that God. And so they are that
God in some sense.
But again, this is an inversion.
The high priest images God through his service in the temple.
He serves as an icon of God through his actions, right?
The image is this verbal idea.
And so that service shows us the image of God.
And this, this, and again, we'll get into this more when we do the inevitable whole episode.
This whole theology surrounding the high priest as the image.
of Yahweh in the Old Testament serving in the temple is what, for example, your old friend
saving Nacius of Antioch, who I still wish somebody would write a good book about.
Maybe if you go to storedonancientfaith.com, you can find one.
The St. Ignatius of Antioch picks up on when he starts talking about the bishop in the
the church as the icon of Christ and his role in the
gathered community. And so there's a continuity there, but this is a major discontinuity
between with the priests kings of the pagan world and the music of idols.
Right. And this is really interesting to me. And this is just now kind of occurring to me,
too, is we made the point again that Israelite worship is not derived from pagan worship.
and that there's important discontinuities which are pointing.
out now, but notice everybody, the kinds of discontinuities these are. These are discontinuities
that say something specific about the character of pagan worship, especially of the demons
that the pagan's worship, right? It's not, oh, well, we have our own version of this, right?
It says something about who Yahweh is and how he is not like.
any of the other ones. And if you if if someone thing were being derived, if the one was being derived from the other like if if if
Israelite worship was being derived from paganism, you'd expect it to be like a
grander version, right, or just sort of a different version, right?
And that's the way the derivation generally goes. But these are direct negations about the very core identity questions of who's being worshiped.
So you know, it couldn't be derived from
because at the core there's this, it's an utter negation of those things, right?
And as a Christian I would look at this and say actually it goes the other direction
that pagan worship represents a reduction distortion of this.
Right, a corruption, a corruption of the corruption.
Right, in the same way that when we were talking about the five-ish falls of the eight.
the way that the succession myth in paganism,
where there's some kind of divine rebellion of a divine son
against his father who kills him, whatever else,
and overthrows him, is corrected to the fall of the devil
after his attempted insurrection.
It's the same kind of principle at play here,
but very functionally in ritual worship.
Yeah.
And acted and participated in.
Yeah, I have to...
Imagine if a pagan were present at this devout, if we could put it that way, pagan, he would
be offended by what he was seeing.
Right.
He would have to be because this is insulting his gods in a very direct kind of way, not
by saying Yahweh is better, but by utterly saying Yahweh is unlike, totally unlike those
gods.
Right.
And to offer that kind of pagan worship to Yahweh is therefore insulting to him.
Yeah.
Is it?
And just honoring of him because of what it says about him.
Yeah, you can't write exactly.
It would be like meeting, I don't know, if you were to get an audience with the president
of the United States or if you were to get an audience with the queen of England, right?
And a normal thing to do would be maybe to bring some kind of gift.
And you were to go and get a toy from the dollar store and offer that to them as a gift.
That would be insulting.
Totally.
inappropriate because that's for kids. So yeah, yeah, yeah, cool stuff. So the last big
discontinuity, and this is a major discontinuity, is sort of what was done or in this case really
what wasn't done with the blood. Yeah, because there's if you're offering an animal, right,
So you're dropping an animal, there's blood, right?
Yeah.
So, and we talked a little bit last time about some of the things that was done with the blood.
Everybody agreed there was power in the blood.
Right.
How they chose to use that power was different.
So, we talked about epigenism that often, for example, in Greco-Roman shrines, there'd be a shrine
to the God and there'd also be the grave of a hero and the blood would be poured in the grave of the hero.
here the blood
scene to sort of feed the shades of the dead would feed on it because that was sort of
your, your, the other world after life in Hades was you existed as the shadow of your former
self, right?
sort of slowly faded away as people forgot about you.
Yeah, just like, I think I, I think I made the, the comparison to Tinkerbell.
Right.
Or at least in my head, I did.
You know, you have to believe in her.
Yes.
a Martin McLeod's Polaroids. Yeah.
So, right, they sort of see, see, see, see.
So this was sort of feeding them, remembering them and feeding them.
It other rituals the blood would actually be consumed.
Yeah.
And so that's why there are such strict rules against the consumption of blood in the Torah
and Leviticus, the holiness code in particular,
and those continue at a-
We'll probably do an episode at this at some point, but that's one of the things that continues in the Book of Acts in chapter 15
that continues in the Church is about the consumption of blood.
But we'll get into that at some later point.
So that's what was done with the blood in pagan circles.
So for most of the sacrifices in Israel, the ones that were being done correctly at least,
The blood was collected just like it was collected.
in the pagan sacrifices, but then in most of them it was poured out at the base of the altar.
Yeah, why would you do that?
You're disposing of it, you're disposing of it by pouring it into the ground,
you're returning to the life to the ground from which it came, and you're disposing of it in a sacred place.
Right, not just any old place, not throwing it into the trash, not.
Right, so it seemed because blood is life, it seemed to be in some sense sacred.
And so...
So it's disposed of in a sacred place in a sacred way.
Yeah.
And isn't it also used like the way instances use in that it's
like it's sprinkled on people and on stuff and in places?
Well, it's understood to purify and cleanse.
In rarer cases.
Yeah.
Mostly it's disposed of in that way.
And then there are particular cases.
We're going to talk about the most major one next time when we talk about
tonement, how it's used on the day of atonement.
But at the giving of the covenant, it was sprinkled on the people at the
ordination of the high priest. It was put on his ear and his thumb and his
big toe. The high priest episode will talk more about that. But the
user wasn't actually applied to people. But yes, in those other cases, the
blood was seen as this cleansing and purifying agent, right? It was never
offered to anybody. Right. It did Israelite religion. It was never offered to
anybody it was never
used to pay for anything. It was not blood for the blood god. You got to go to
Mesoamerica to get that. Right. It was either disposed of in this sacred way or used for
the purpose of cleansing and purification. Yeah. Not you don't put it on the table and
eat and drink it with your god. Right. Unless you're a pagan or offer it to a man any other way.
Yeah, right.
A very important point.
Okay, well, having gone through those discontinuity.
and there's lots of other things we could say, of course.
We're gonna go ahead and go to our next break,
and we'll be back with the fourth half
of tonight's Lord of Spirits.
Father Andrew Stephen Daymak
and Father Stephen DeYoung will be back in a moment
to take your calls on the next part of the Lord of Spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF radio.
So here's a question for you.
What does it mean to think Orthodox?
What have the unspoken and unexplored premises and presumptions underlying what Christians
believe?
Orthodox Christianity is based on preserving the mind of the early Church.
It's Thronema.
Dr. Gigi Constitino brings her more than 40 years experience as a professor, Bible teacher
and speaker to bear in explaining.
what the Orthodox Phronomah is, how it can be acquired, and how that Phronomah is expressed
in true Orthodox theology as practiced by those who are properly qualified by both training
and a deeper relationship with Christ.
Thinking Orthodox, now available at store.enchandfaith.com.
We're back now with...
the Lord of Spirits, the Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung.
If you have a question, call now at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF Radio.
All right, well, now it's the fourth and final half of Lord of Spirits because this is twice the show.
Tonight, so we're going down.
That's right. We are. So, okay. All right. Well, let's talk now about calendars a little bit, right?
There's, as we mentioned at the beginning, there's these two, these two calendars that exist.
There's a calendar that's tied to the agricultural year, and there's a calendar that's tied to
Passover. So, okay. So, what is that all about? What's going on? This is the big, this is the big
big stuff right?
So like for us Orthodox Christians, Paska, Pentecost, these, you know, nativity, these are like, these are our major fees
So we're gonna be talking about some of those these major fees now. So what's what's going on?
Let's talk about the the most important one first the Passover cycle, right? So so what's happening in that?
Right, so there's one thing Orthodox people love talking about its calendars. Yeah, right?
Never been any controversy about them either.
either. Yeah totally totally unify
I don't have a question.
So yeah, as we mentioned, the agrarian cycle sort of comes first.
And then the Passover cycle that we're about to talk about
gets layered onto it later, of course,
when Passover happens.
Right?
So that's an actual event in the life of Israel
that ends up helping constitute Israel.
So that sort of comes, so you have these two separate cycles.
And so the Passover cycle appropriately.
enough begins on PASCA, on Passover.
And this is of central importance, obviously not only in the Old Testament because
in the Exodus it is the formative event of Israel.
It is what constitutes Israel.
But it is the formative event in the New Testament in the sense that when Christ
sacrifice is being talked about when his death is being talked about, it's...
identified the vast majority of the time with Passover. Right. Right. Christ is the Lamb of God, not the God of God, which day of atonement is a goat. Right. So we think about Christ sacrificed primarily in terms of atonement because we've grown up in the west, but that's not the way the Scripture does it.
He's the Lamb and not the bowl of God either. Oh, please know. Yes
For so many reasons. Yeah
Now that said, there are places, right?
And we're going to talk about those next time
when we talk about atonement, the day of atonement.
There are places, chiefly Saint Matthew's Gospel
and the Passion Narrative Minute.
First John, Hebrews, or the big ones
that are going to talk about Christ's sacrifice
in terms of the day of atonement and atonement.
So that is very, very, very testament.
But that's the minority report, right?
Right, that's right.
Yeah, he's the Lamb of God.
I mean, that's how he's introduced in John's Gospel,
especially when you get seen down the...
former runner, behold the Lamb of God who takes away the sin of the world.
Right. Right.
So it's important that that tells us that the New Testament is telling us that if we want
to get who Christ is and specifically what Christ does, if we want to get that right, we
have to understand Pasco, we have to understand the Passover in the Old Testament because
that's what they're using to explain what he does to us.
Yeah.
Yeah, and one of the cool things I notice about that parallel is in both the old and the
New Testament, you actually get the instructions from God about how to celebrate this thing before
the thing happens, right?
There's this is how you're going to celebrate the Passover, and now Passover occurs.
And then with Christ, there's the mystical supper.
this as my remembrance, you know, do this for his off use eat this bread and drink this cup,
right? And then he is sacrificed for the sin of the world. Right. He says this is my body broken
for you. His body hadn't been broken yet. Yeah. Right. Right. He was showing them how to
participate in it ritually later. Right. And just as a side note for anybody who gets hung up on
that word remembrance as I imagine some of our friends do.
The word
or an Amnesia or remembrance there is the same word that's used in numbers 10-10 in the Greek
to refer to sin offerings. Do this in the opposite of the word?
Are offered as a remembrance. Sin offerings are offered as a remembrance before the Lord.
So what Christ was really saying there, if you take it in the context of the Septuaget, is he's
saying do this as my remembrance.
Yeah, this is the worship that I expect.
This is taking the place of the sin offering.
Yeah.
He's transforming the whole deal at that moment.
The Eucharist is fulfilling the sin offering.
It's not sin offerings just stop.
Yeah.
Um, mic drop.
Sorry.
Okay.
So, um, so in addition to that, right, there is that.
And of course Christ dies at the Passover.
He doesn't die on the day of atonement.
He, he, he, the Passover.
Right.
See John makes that...
the past.
Same John makes that super, super clear.
Yeah.
All four gospels make that.
But yeah, right.
Yeah, same John has the element of setting it up so that Christ dies as the lambs are dying.
So the first important thing in terms of getting Passover right is there's no element of substitution,
penal or otherwise in the celebration of the Passover.
What do I mean by that?
Right.
Another one of those things.
that's in people's heads is that we're killing this lamb so that God doesn't kill my kid.
That's right. Because at the Passover, the angel of death comes to Egypt and kills the first
born son of every Egyptian household, including the son of Pharaoh. And so there's this idea
than the people have of if we kill this lamb, then then
and then my son's not gonna be killed.
Right.
But if you look at the instructions on what to do with the lamb,
it kinda doesn't actually work out that right.
Cause not only are there no instructions on how to kill it.
So again, the killing part isn't ritualized.
It's about eating it.
But they're not proportioned,
one lamb per first born son.
So if we think about it for a minute, right?
If I don't have any...
kids do I just not eat the Passover because hey you know there's nobody to die
yeah or if you only have daughters yeah for only have daughters or on the flip side
right if if great granddad and granddad and dad and son are all first born sons
and we all live in the same household we don't do four lambs right we still just do one
Right. Right. And there's instructions.
explicitly say, right? There's not supposed to be the leftovers.
Because again, the instructions are all about how to eat it,
not how to kill it. There's no leftovers. So if your family isn't
big enough to eat the whole lamb, you're supposed to share one
with another small family. Yeah. Right. It's not like half a
lamb for each son, right? Right. Yeah. The lambs are in no way
apportioned according to children. Yeah, there's no correlation.
It's an act of
worship, not an act of payment.
Right. Right. Not it or punishment or yeah, right. Right. Right. There's some impending death penalty. Right. And I mean,
that wouldn't make sense in the first place. Right. Because the whole reason the 10th plague happens.
The plague in the first one happens is that Pharaoh went and murdered all the sons of Israel.
Right, we had them thrown in the
denial. And God says those were my children. Right. And so this
tenth plague is balancing the scales of justice. Why would he
kill more Israelite children? Yeah. Yeah. So the point is to
make, I mean, we're going to make this point a little bit
more. But but there is a distinction coming, right? Right.
Right, trying to put...
some kind of substitution, especially penal substitution in there, that dog don't hunt.
It just doesn't. It doesn't work with what the Bible says. Yeah, right. So that's the
negative side and then we get to the positive side. Yeah, so what exactly is God doing here?
Yeah, and this is, you know, obviously, especially for this podcast in particular, we always
kind of love it when God puts the smackdown on demons. Right. That's kind of the whole,
That's our deal.
So yeah.
God says I am judging the gods of Egypt.
Right.
Tonight I will judge all the gods of Egypt.
So that's the first thing he says about what he's doing.
Right?
Nothing about I need to kill some kids for some reason.
It's yeah.
I'm judging the gods of Egypt.
Yeah, or to yeah, to throw back to our earliest episodes.
Not I will judge all these imaginary beings that you guys
worship for some reason, even though they don't exist.
Right.
I'm related.
I'm going to lay this back down on the Marvel Cinematic Universe, right?
Yeah.
I'm going to beat up fictional character Captain America.
So this is, yeah, this is war.
This is war on the Egyptian gods.
Okay, that's where it's directed.
Where Pharaoh was one of the gods of Egypt.
Yeah.
Right?
That's why he's part of this.
So then the second piece, and this is the clearest piece in terms of what's going
going out of Passover. I mean, the basic bottom line description of Passover, right? What
is Passover when it's at home, right? Is that this is a bunch of slaves being set free
from slavery, right? Right. Right. Which is slavery to home. Right. Yeah. Right. Nice.
slavery. Well, slavery to Pharaoh, but Pharaoh remembers what are the gods of each? He's
one of the gods right so these people being set free from slave
to the gods of Egypt.
And the fancy word for today is Manu Mission,
which I like because it contains the idea of Manu
Mittens, and the Mitt in there is the same Mitt from Remit,
and so remission, which is a word we use liturgically,
to talk about sin.
So the reality is that after Babel, and we've talked
about this, the whole world, there is no Israel,
That's right.
So all the nations, the whole world is in slavery to these demonic powers and the chains are sin.
Sin is the power that binds them into that slavery.
Right. So God is setting free
anyone in this event who chooses to worship him in the Passover.
right no matter who no matter what their family tree
He is.
Right.
Because he says, the other thing God says, it's always good to get it from the horse's mouth.
What does God say?
He's doing it Passover.
He says, I am going to make a distinction between Israel and Egypt.
Yeah.
So before that, he had sort of done that, right?
Because we read about the earlier plagues, like the darkness was over the land of Egypt, but
not over the place where Israel lived.
Yeah, right.
Not over the ocean.
Yeah.
Right.
places.
where Israel lived, right? But that's a geographic thing. And people descended from Abraham and
full-blooded Egyptians were living as next door neighbors, right? We know this, the text says so
because remember those Egyptians give them gifts while they're leaving, their neighbors.
So this distinction is different. This distinction is who is going to be Israel and who is going to be
be an Egyptian. And those who are
Egyptians are going to be those who are still enslaved to the gods of Egypt.
And Israel are going to be all those who are set free.
So that night, if you took the blood of that lamb, again, it's about what you do with
the blood, and you use that blood to mark your doorpost, to mark you out as an Israelite.
It doesn't matter if you're ethnically a full blooded Egyptian and asiatic cana knight,
blooded descended from Abraham himself.
night like Moses' wife, it doesn't matter. That night if you mark your doorpost, you're
now in Israelite. And if you don't, it doesn't matter if you're a full-blooded descendant
of Abraham. If you don't mark your door, you're now in Egyptian.
Yeah. And I think it's important, you know, as this sort of freedom from slavery occurs
and the creation now of this new nation of Israel. I mean, there is, you like to use the word
manumission, redemption, and that does include the way we tend to think.
about it is buying a slave and setting him free, but the important part of that is
that the setting them free because God isn't paying off the Egyptian gods. Here you go, guys,
we're going to give you this so I can have these people now. That's not what's going on. So there is
there is a redemption going on, but the important part of it is that being set free from slavery,
It's not about any kind of payment being made because God does not pay demons.
Right that's not a thing he doesn't owe them anything. Yeah, they don't have right. They don't have any rights
They're not really rights. Yeah, yeah, so
So and then going forward right so that night
Participation in the Passover and and circumcision that had come previously
Marked out who was in Israel light and that stays true going forward
Yeah, right the person who is the Israelite is the person who is circumcised and eats the Passover
Right. And so that's what distinguishes when you get into Levinicus and the holiness code what distinguishes
someone just living in Israel from an Israelite
is that
someone who is an Israelite eats the Passover and if someone wants to eat the Passover they have to be circumcised
Right, right? So it's circumcision and then participation in the ritual meal, right?
The right of initiation participation ritual meal makes you an Israelite. Yes, and there may be some parallels to that in the church
Right.
Yeah.
And notably, this is one of the things that is also parallel in paganism.
What is it that makes you an Egyptian?
It's that you make sacrifices to and participate in that worship, the Egyptian gods.
It's ritual.
It's richly determined, not genetically determined because they didn't have a concept of genetics.
Yeah.
Right.
It's not about genealogy.
Yeah.
And one of my favorite examples of this that I don't think I've done on this show before,
I will now is that
that Phineas, the grandson of Aaron, who was the high priest of Israel, was an African.
Right, so he would have been Moses's great nephew.
Right, right.
And we know this for sure. His mother was from Put, which it was Libya at the time.
And his name, Peenhas, an Egyptian, roughly your Peenhasi,
Literally means Newbian.
or dark skinned one. Right. So he was right up there in the leadership of Israel. He didn't look
like Abraham. He was the high priest. He was one of the most celebrated high priests in Israel
ite history. So this the ethnic idea of Israel did not exist in ancient Israel. It was ritually
determined. Yeah. Okay. So that's Passover, slash Paska. Two words that mean the same thing,
by the way.
for everybody. But that's not the only major feast in this cycle, right? There's also
Pentecost, seven weeks later. Right. Right. And it's often referred to, you know, our
King James titles again, the Feast of Weeks. Yes. In the Old Testament, which sometimes
confuses people, because it's clearly called Pentecost in the New Testament. At Pentecost,
At Pentecost, of course, comes from 50 days, right?
50, yeah.
Yeah.
But they don't realize that the Feast of Weeks is the same thing.
It's called the Feast of Weeks because on the 50th day,
you've got 49 days in between that seven sevens.
So it's a week of weeks.
A week of weeks, right.
Right.
So that makes it the Feast of Weeks.
And that was the participation that begins with,
and then is the future participation in the giving of the covenant
and amount sign eye.
Yes.
Right.
And that also involved blood, right?
At the sprinkling of blood on the people,
when they received the covenant.
And so it was celebrated later,
people who were newly admitted,
who had eaten the Passover for the first time,
this is where they celebrated becoming party
to the covenant with Israel.
And this was for people who were long-term Israelites
and later Judeans when they sort of reaffirmed
and re-committed and re-dedicated themselves.
to the covenant.
And an interesting detail, probably worth pointing out, since this is the Lord of
Spirit's podcast, is the giving of the Torah happens by means of angels.
Right.
It says in Scripture that angels are present.
It's not like such a big disappointment in some ways for me.
It's not like where you see Charlton Heston alone on the mountain side, you know, in the
10 commandments, you know, one, those should have no other, you know.
I wasn't at lightning. Don't they have lightning come down and write it?
It's right. It's right. It's right. It's right. It's right. It's right. It was at lightning. It was Jesus with his finger.
Yes, and that will be in a future episode, but yeah, there's there's angels
involved in the giving of the law. I mean it says this in the New Testament. Yeah.
Yeah, and so then this this sprinkling with blood that we see for cleansing and purification and dedication
at the giga temple.
when the Old Testament talks about the new covenant that's to come in Jeremiah 31 and Ezekiel 36, 24 through 28 and Joel chapter 2, we won't read all those now.
But it talks about being sprinkled with pure water, sprinkling with water as this making of the new covenant and the coming of the Holy Spirit.
And so lo and behold when we get to Pentecost in the book of Acts, we see...
the reception of the Holy Spirit and baptism with water.
And those two things brought and combined together.
How about that?
Ha!
Okay. All right, so that's Pentecost.
All right, there's also this other calendar.
The calendar that has to do with the agricultural cycle.
Right?
And I think this is a good place for us to finish up here.
here.
Because this helps to emphasize, again, for us,
that religion is not this separate thing.
It is simply the right way,
you know, there's the right way of life, right?
And so nothing, I think, well, I shouldn't say nothing,
but an agricultural, the surgical calendar
really emphasizes this because it's these things
that are necessary for survival,
now being suffused.
with a a festal liturgical, prayerful character, right?
So, okay, so let's just talk about a few of those.
The one we're not gonna talk about this time
is the day of atonement, also known as the Omkippur
because tuning in next time,
that's what that's gonna be all about.
So we're just gonna be all atonement all the time.
Oh, yeah, put a pin in that.
Goats all the way down.
Yeah, there we go.
Maybe that should be...
title of the episode of the whole the way down the cliff. Yeah, okay. All right, there's
Rochis on it. Rochis on it. Rochis on it. Yeah. I am now I suddenly remember so when I was in
college, I remember this now. Now is that the is this the day where they have the really serious
fasting or is it Yom Kippur that has the big fasting? Most of the fasting now is Yom Kippur because
they can't do the rest of it.
Oh, okay, yeah.
Because when I was in college, so we're not going to talk about Yom Kippur, but this
time.
When I was in college, I had a Jewish friend and she referred to Yom Kippur.
I mean, this is what she called it as, cranky, hungry, Jew day.
And I was like, oh, that's interesting.
Yom Kippur is marked by lots of praying and no breakfast.
Yeah.
Right.
Okay.
So, Raj Shashana, what's that all about?
Rocha Shana, which is on.
History one on the calendar.
That's the beginning of, well, that's New Year.
That's the beginning of this cycle, this agricultural cycle.
So on the Paschal calendar, right, Moses is told this month,
right, the month of Nissan when Paschal falls,
these that will be for you the first of months.
And then there's this other New Year's.
Yeah, that's the New Year's.
10 New Year's.
Yeah.
It begins then and this is in early September.
that this cycle, these are the cycle of sort of fixed dated feasts, right? Right.
And so we talked about this, we won't go too much more into it now, you're going to refer back to the astrology episode.
We talked about that in terms of Christ's birth and Noah's birth day and the coronation of David
and all the things that happened on Tisserie 1 and on that New Year's Day.
So we'll just put that back to that episode.
So then
The next major one on the agricultural calendar is first fruits, which is again, it's
a name, but that's what it says on the tin.
Right?
It's the beginning of the harvest.
But the reason why it's so important that you bring the first stuff, this is also
all the things related to the first born, right?
Yeah.
Being holy.
The male that opens the womb of animals and of people is holy and dedicated to the
and their sacrifices associated with that.
Also, the first fruit to the grain is because,
first born in the scriptures is not primarily about birth order.
It's a status.
Yeah, right.
Which is why Jacob, Jacob and Esau,
Jacob gets it and Esau loses it.
Right, right.
It defaults it to birth order usually.
Right.
But it's not always based on birth order.
It's about being the heir.
It's about having this...
status. Right. And and the air has this particular responsibility, right? Well,
sort of the air and herons everything. Right. And he's supposed to then share it out
with his brethren. This of course did not always happen. There's an episode in the
Gospels where someone comes to Christ and says, tell my brother to share the
inheritance with me. Right. I'm going to go get the rabbi on your case. Right.
I didn't have it run through probate.
Christ basically says, don't worry about that material stuff.
Come follow me and be my disciple.
Right?
Yeah.
But so, but they're supposed to share that.
But this language that we won't go into this now at some future date, this is critically
important understanding what St. Paul's doing in Romans 9 and in Colossians when he talks
about Christ as the first born and the heir us as co-airs with Christ.
We touched on this a little when we talked about sons of God.
but that Christ is the first born inherits everything,
literally everything, the whole creation.
Right?
And that he shares his rule and his reign
and his pre-sitter and all of these things with us
as his fellow heirs who become sons of God by grace.
So by offering the first fruits and the first born
and the first, you're effectively offering the whole thing.
Yes, right.
You offer your whole life, your whole self, right?
family's future was that air.
who is going to receive everything and carry on the family into the future.
So if that's offered and dedicated to God, you're dedicated everything you are,
everything you have to God in that action.
Right, right.
Yeah, okay, so then the next feast is called the feast of booths or tabernacles,
or I know I get this wrong Sukkot.
Sukkot?
Sukkot, yeah.
Sukkot.
And this is done at the end of the harvest.
Right, so you've got the first roots and now this is at the end of the harvest.
And it's called the Feast of Tabernacles or Booths
because during this period, Israel would go
and live back in tents, right, or temporary housing
of some kind.
Of sorts, shacks or hens.
Yeah, exactly.
And sort of remembrance of this,
of the time that they were nomadic peoples, right?
But it actually has this kind of greater purpose
and meaning, right?
So what's going?
on there exactly.
Yeah, it wasn't a love shack for you to get together with your friends.
The idea was over and over again.
I got that one too.
In the Torah especially in Deuteronomy, there's this constant warning from God.
Right now you're dependent on me out in the desert for food and water and to take care
of all these things.
But once you get into the land and you settle down and you plant crops and you get into
this rhythm, you're going to be tempted to forget. Yes. You know, forget about God, forget
about the fact that it's him who's providing for you, that it's him who's caring for you,
just forget about God in general. And so this was a one day, a year sort of reminder where
at the time when they were feeling the most settled, when they reaped their harvest, that
was the day that they unsettled themselves. Yeah, it would be like, it would be like,
Okay, everybody, we're gonna celebrate Thanksgiving.
by setting up tents in the backyard everybody.
Yeah, right? Yeah.
And this was so that we'll be thankful for all the things that we're doing without.
Yeah.
So, and this is, this is of course a theme that gets picked up especially by St. Peter
and the New Testament about us living as aliens and strangers in this world and not being
too settled.
But in the Old Testament, sort of the paradigmatic people who do this, not just on that one day
but all the time it's sort of an ancient asceticism.
that's referred to God praises them for doing this through Jeremiah and Jeremiah chapter 35 are the
Recovites who's who are bear who's for bear Yonadab or
Jonah dab or Johonadab depending on what translation you read taught them that they should never settle that
they should always live nomatically intense and they should never drink alcohol.
Yeah, so it's this ascetical way of life.
Right.
At alcohol, it's not just that alcohol is bad, but if you think about it, in order to
get alcohol, you have to let it ferment.
Yeah.
So it's part of being settled again.
And so they were to live in this unsettled way and they did that all the way up until
Jeremiah's day and the exile.
They came from Sinai in the wilderness and they just never settled to maintain, to try
to maintain in their whole life.
lives, this sense of dependence on God and their praise for that.
But then there's this other major ritual that was done at the Feast of Tabernacles that
is very important at Sukkot, and that's that 70 bulls were sacrificed to Yahweh.
70 you say?
Yes.
Meats back on the menu, right?
That one's for you, Eugene Strater.
Yeah.
He fits what's for dinner?
Yes, right.
70 bulls, 70 bulls.
So, right? Have we heard that number before?
That number, that's the number of the sons of gods, that's the number of the nations.
Yeah.
And so Israel is offering the 70 bulls to Yahweh, one for each of the nations.
Right.
So, in doing this, the nation of Israel is acting as a priesthood for the world.
for the world.
Yeah. So what we see in the holiness code and in other places that talk about
cleanness and uncleanness in the Torah are these sort of concentric circles
around the presence of God. So the priests, who are the ones who are going to go
most or at well the high priest especially but then the whole priest and the
Levites, we're going to go into the presence of God, have to maintain this
level of holiness and sanctity at all times. They have to wash more, wash their
clothing more they have to practice more ritual cleanly.
this impurity and holiness, then the average is real life.
Right.
And then the average is real life has these food laws, uncleanness and clean list restrictions
that they need to follow that the people who live in the other nations don't have to follow.
And they're never called upon.
The priests are never called upon to go and enforce their standards of holiness on the people.
And the people of Israel are never called to go and enforce their standards of holiness on
Theetherians or
the Moavites or right they were called to go to them and make them follow those rules
right right because that's now if they were going to become Israelites they had
to begin to follow those rules and practice those things yeah but if not then
they did not right so there are these concentric circles and those on the more
inner circles served as priests for those in the more outer circles right yeah
I mean that-
It's fascinating because as modern people, we tend to think again of distinction as
implying opposition, right?
So, well Israel, and it's interesting, often when Israel encounters ancient peoples, like
there's a sense that I think that some of the Romans have, Israel is weird, right?
holding themselves as different and separate.
But the point is not to say that we're better than the nations or anything like that.
It's that this thing that we're doing, these actions of purification, these standards
that we're being held to, are so that we may serve as the priests of the nations.
And then within Israel you've got the priesthood that is being held to another standard,
so that they may offer psych...
on behalf of the whole nation.
But yeah, I mean, like you said,
there wasn't this expectation that everybody has to do this stuff.
It's about preparation.
It's about, you know, allowing them to have this function as, you know,
and it's interesting.
I mean, there's all kinds of potential implications
for how we could look at things now, right?
You know, a good example, right?
Orthodox Christians we were expected to fast.
there's all kinds of times that we're...
expected to fast, but we're not expected to preach the gospel of fasting, right? We're
not, we're not, we're not sent out into the nations, you know, go into all the world and preach
that you must fast on Wednesdays and Fridays and half the other days of the year. That's not
the thing that is the, the gospel to the nations. Now, when someone becomes part of the church,
and they become part of the royal priesthood.
Then they take these things.
on so that they can then serve in this priestly function as well.
Right. And that's where that language comes from. Right.
In Exodus, Israel's told you're going to be a kingdom of priests.
Priest for who? Right. Priest for the world. Yeah.
It's on the bottom. And those priests had their own priests.
Right. So there were Levites who were the priests for Israel.
And then the people of Israel were the priests for the world. Right.
So there are these two phases and
And then Peter takes that same language about
that translated royal priesthood from the Greek usually.
Same language that applies it to the church
almost as if the church were Israel.
About that.
And it says the same thing, which means,
which means it's not just that these are these rules,
right, and these are especially sometimes
even in the Orthodox church, even with a good
Orthodox understanding of salvation,
we could fall into this idea that the goal
just about me saving.
myself. Yeah, no. Right. But that the reason we're keeping these disciplines and the
reason we're drawing close to God is so that we can service priests. We offer the
liturgy, we offer the sacrifice of the Eucharist for the life of the world and for its salvation.
Right. For the whole creation, which includes, but is not limited to all the people in it.
Yeah, I mean, I'm reminded of that fame.
You know, there's this quote from St. Seraphim of...
of sought-off that often gets quoted as a kind of slogan, you know, acquire the Holy Spirit or
acquire the Spirit of Peace and thousands around you will be saved. And I think sometimes people
hear that and they take it as like, oh, well, there's this wonderful secondary effect that other people
around me are going to be saved if I just work on my own salvation. And there's a certain truth to that.
But often it gets turned into this kind of quietism.
right that all I have to do, you know, just humble me a sinner, just a poor
sinner, is work on my salvation and, you know, and that might have a nice
effect on the people around me. But if you look at what St. Sarah from
himself actually did, yes, he did spend those three years out there kneeling on
a rock out in the wilderness praying and really praying. But then after that,
his life became
this open door for the world, right?
He became an offering for the world.
He became a priest for the world, right?
There is, it always goes like that.
It's like at the end of the divine liturgy,
there's the let us go forth in peace to do what?
To go to coffee hour, like or to go to,
that's not, it's go forth having received this,
having received the whole
spirit. We go forth now as priests of the world to bring the blessing of God into the world,
to intercede on behalf of the world, you know, to help cleanse the world. Like that's what we're
being sent forth to do. It's not just, I gotta make sure I get my ticket so that I can go to the
good place when I die and not the bad one, right? Yeah. Yeah. Or the other place where you just sit
and watch the same VHS.
over it over again. I remember VHS. Yeah. Yeah. All right. Well, yeah. Okay. So just some
final thoughts then. There's so much more we could say I think this might be the episode
where we said the most times but we can talk about that on a future episode. So there's
so much more that we could say about all these.
offerings and fees and sacrifices and so forth that we just discussed.
But I think that for me the big takeaway is the other integration of worship and prayer
into the human life.
I remember one time, I have somewhere in my collection of books, a collection of texts
from the Celtic Christian tradition
and part of that collection is occasional prayers.
And like there's prayers for rowing your boat.
There's prayers for washing your baby, right?
There's stuff like this, which it's funny,
like if you were to ask most people now,
like, you know, do you need to pray while you row your boat?
Like, what?
You know, or do I have to say a prayer while I'm washing my kid?
It's hard enough to watch my kid who hates the bath.
Anyway, why do I need, you know, like, right,
this stuff seems like non-sequitored us.
And yet, that stuff is even from the ancient world.
It's just a little pre-modern, you know.
There is this sense that God truly is everywhere present,
filling all things.
And also that the angels and the saints
are present.
with us. And if that's really true, and if we believe what the scripture says, then we have to
believe it's true. If we're Christians, we believe what the scripture says. So Christians believe this.
If that's really true, then that means that our task is to, if I can use this term, to enchant the
world and I love the fact that NChant refers to...
singing to enchant the world by constant prayer,
by as often as I can, participating in the sacrifices of the church by praying at home.
I mean, I think probably every single person listening to this, even if you have a prayer
rule, it probably needs some work.
Including me.
I am by no means accepted from that.
And if we feel...
as we so often do that God is far away or that maybe none of this is really true, whatever.
I mean, I'm just reminded of where the Lord says you have not because you don't ask.
You don't even ask. You know, like, of course you feel abandoned. You've abandoned your friends.
God who is your friend, the friend of mankind, the angels and the saints who are your friends,
because they're the friends of God.
We can...
bring them in
and
You know ancient Israel has all of these things. I mean, it's enormously complicated
We only just scratched the surface of the complexity of all of this
I mean like read the book of the Vedicist people like that is a complicated book
But it has all these detailed instructions on how to do all these things
Ancient Israel has all these tools and so does the modern church the church of right this moment, you know
So...
It has these things and it's not about keeping up lots of merit badges so you can
become a heavenly Eagle Scout. That's not, you know, nothing against Eagle Scouts. That's not what it's
about. It's about faithfulness and obedience to God in every single second and his giving of grace,
in all of that in order to show us forth truly as his imagers,
as truly his sons.
So that's my main takeaway.
I mean, there's a lot of things that I could say.
But I love this.
And it's funny to me, there are Christians who look at all this stuff
and they say, well, that was the Old Testament.
But in the New, although I hope that no one says that now,
I haven't heard the things that we've said.
But, but how can you say that, right? Like look at look at what this does. Are we to believe now that that that God has has taken all that away from us or maybe maybe I'm being slightly sarcastic here. We should believe as the early church did and say that this has been fulfilled transformed
filled to overflowing, given to us in all of its fullness now.
with the coming of Christ who says,
do this as my remembrance.
So that's my takeaway, Father.
Yeah, I may not be clear immediately how it's related,
but Christ says that we're in the church,
the salt of the earth.
And if the salt loses its saltiness,
you can't make it salty again if it goes stale.
And he says that we're to be the light of the world and he doesn't mean to leave a nightlight on inside the birdhouse in your soul.
Yes, I got that one.
That's directed, that's directed outward. Right.
And one of the big things we lose when our Christianity becomes materialist is we lose the priesthood.
and we lose sacrifice and we lose worship.
Because those aren't things anymore.
Priesthood is maybe something Christ
as the great high priest is doing often heaven.
But sacrifice isn't really a thing we're doing.
And what happens with materialist Christianity
every time is it devolves into politics.
If it's conservative.
materialist Christianity it devolves into right wing politics if it's liberal
materialist Christianity it devolves into liberal politics but in both cases
you're using fundamentally material means to try to bring about or enforce
some idea of justice or to create some kind of utopia on earth through purely
physical means which means material means means force. It means force either the form of direct force in violence or
social force, the force of public shame and
public will and public sentiment.
Your enemies become the people who disagree with you there. The enemy that has to be defeated and destroyed.
and we're trying to do all this without God being involved because we're doing it.
without priesthood and we're doing it without worship and we're doing it without sacrifice.
And so the only thing we can possibly create is hell on earth.
And so the answer to this is to realize once again who we are.
People who are in the church and people who are outside the church, people who love Christ and
people who hate Christ have the same enemy. It's not Christ. They have the same enemy and it's
demonic powers who want to enslave and destroy us. And we are here as priests, we are the hope
that has been placed in the world for those people outside the church. We are the ones who, as priests,
are able to bring Christ to them and bring them to Christ. We're the ones who are called and empowered
to connect, reconnect them with God.
to bring them into community of which Christ is a member so that they can come to
know us and be communion with us and be in communion with Christ. That's what
can transform the world. That's what can transform people. That's what can help
us all defeat our common enemies. But if we give up, if we forsake, if we ignore,
or if we give up that role that God has given us and called us to.
Then just like Christ said about the salt and about the lamp that gets put under a bushel,
there's no hope for the world.
Those people aren't going to find that hope.
The world is not going to be changed in any positive way.
So the gifts that God has given us of knowledge, of understanding of our own salvation.
He's given to us as a deposit that he expects to bear fruit.
He's planted something in us and he's
He's going to want the harvest from that to be offered to him at some point in the future.
And so I think when we come to understand Israel's worship and how it was directed outside
of itself, it wasn't solipsistic, it wasn't just contained in Israel and just Israel
concerned with their fellow Israelites and we're going to find salvation and to heck with
those people outside, they're all evil or rotten sinners.
That has to transform the way we view our own lives and our own worship.
and the purpose of all of this in the first place.
Well, that is our show for tonight.
Thank you very much, everyone, for listening.
If you did not get a chance to call in
during the live broadcast,
we would love to hear from you either via email
at LordofSpiritsAtAncientFaith.com
or you can message us at our LordofSpirits podcast,
Facebook page.
We read everything, but can't respond everything.
and we do see...
what you send for possible use in future episodes.
And join us for our live broadcast on the second and fourth Thursdays of the month at 7pm Eastern
4pm Pacific.
Like our Facebook page and join our Facebook discussion group if you still do that sort
of thing.
Leave reviews and ratings but most importantly, share this show with a friend whom you know
is going to love it and consider starting a Lord of Spirits discussion group at your
parish.
Hello everyone from St. Sava in Texas.
And finally be sure to go to...
www.anxfordfaith.com slash support and help make sure we and lots of other AFR podcasters
stay on the air.
Thank you very much and make God bless you always.
You've been listening to the Lord of Spirits with Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew
Stephen Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung, a listener supported presentation of Ancient
Faith Radio.
I'd be held and I
I heard the voice of many angels
round about the throne and the beasts and the elders,
and the number of them was 10,000 times 10,000,
and thousands of thousands,
saying with a loud voice, worthy as the land
that was slain to receive power and riches and wisdom
and strength and honor and glory and blessing.
Revelation chapter five verses 11 through 12.
This is the Church by praying at home.
I mean, I think probably every single person listening to this, even if you have a prayer rule,
it probably needs some work.
Including me.
Including me. I am by no means accepted from that.
And if we feel as we so often do that God is far away or that maybe none of this is really true or whatever,
I mean, I'm just reminded of where the Lord says you have not because you don't ask.
You don't even ask.
You know, like, of course you feel abandoned.
You've abandoned your friends.
God who is your friend, the friend of mankind,
the angels and the saints who are your friends
because they're the friends of God, we can bring them in.
And, you know, ancient Israel has all of these things.
I mean, it's enormously complicated.
We only just scratched the surface
of the complexity of all of this.
I like read
book of the vidicus people. Like that is a complicated book, but it has all these detailed instructions
on how to do all these things. Ancient Israel has all these tools and so does the modern church,
the church of right this moment, you know, it has these things and it's not about
heaping up lots of merit badges so you can, you know, become a heavenly eagle scout, right?
that's not...
although nothing against equals God. That's not what it's about. It's about faithfulness and
obedience to God in every single second and his giving of grace in all of that in order to
show us forth truly as his imagers, as truly his sons. So that's my main takeaway. I mean,
I mean, there's a lot of things that I could say.
But I love this.
And, you know, it's funny to me, there are Christians who look at all this stuff.
And they say, well, that was the old testament.
But in the new, although I hope that no one says that now, I haven't heard the things
that we've said.
But how can you say that, right?
Like look at what this does.
Are we to believe now that God has taken all that away?
from us or maybe, maybe I'm being slightly sarcastic here, we should believe as the
yearly church did and say that this has been fulfilled, transformed, filled to overflowing,
given to us in all of its fullness now with the coming of Christ who says, do this as
my remembrance.
So that's my takeaway, Father.
Yeah, I'm it may not be.
clear immediately how it's related. But you know, Christ says that we're in the church,
the salt of the earth. And if the salt loses its saltiness, you can't make it salty again
if it goes stale. And he says that we're to be the light of the world. And he doesn't
mean to leave a night light on inside the birdhouse in your soul.
I got that one. That's that's direct
that's directed outward, right? And one of the big things we lose when our
Christianity becomes materialist is we lose the priesthood and we lose
sacrifice and we lose worship because those aren't things anymore. Priesthood is
maybe something Christ is the great high priest is doing often heaven.
But sacrifices isn't really a thing we're doing.
And what happens with materialist Christianity every time is it devolves into politics.
If it's conservative materialist Christianity, it devolves into right wing politics.
if it's liberal materialist Christianity
it evolves into liberal politics.
But in both cases, you're using fundamentally material means to try to bring about or enforce
some idea of justice or to create some kind of utopia on Earth through purely physical
means, which means material means means force.
It means force, either the form of direct force and violence or social force, the force
of public shame.
and public will and public sentiment.
Your enemies become the people who disagree with you.
They're the enemy that has to be defeated and destroyed.
And we're trying to do all this without God being involved
because we're doing it without priesthood and we're doing it without worship
and we're doing it without sacrifice.
And so the only thing we can possibly create is hell on earth.
And so the answer to this is to
realize once again who we are.
People who are in the church and people who are outside the church, people who love Christ
and people who hate Christ have the same enemy.
It's not Christ.
They have the same enemy and it's the demonic powers who want to enslave and destroy us.
And we are here as priests.
We are the hope that has been placed in the world for those people outside the church.
We are the ones who, as priests, are able to bring Christ to them and bring them to Christ.
We are the ones who are called and empowered to reconnect them with God,
to bring them into community of which Christ is a member, so that they can come to know us and be communion with us and be in communion with Christ.
That's what can transform the world.
That's what can transform people. That's what can help us all defeat our common enemies
But if we give up if we forsake if we ignore if we give up that role that God has given us and called us to
Then just like Christ said about the salt and about the lamp that gets put under a bushel
There's no hope for the world
Those people aren't going to find that hope the world is not going to be changed.
in any positive way. So the gifts that God has given us of knowledge of
understanding of our own salvation, he's given to us as a deposit that he
expects to bear fruit. He's planted something in us and he's going to want
the harvest from that to be offered to him at some point in the future. And so I
think when we come to understand Israel's worship and how it was directed
outside of itself. It wasn't...
It wasn't just contained in Israel and just Israel concerned with their fellow Israelites and we're going to find salvation and to heck with those people outside. They're all evil of rotten sinners.
That has to transform the way we view our own lives and our own worship and the purpose of all of this in the first place.
Well, that is our show for tonight.
Thank you very much, everyone, for listening.
did not get a chance to call in during the live broadcast.
We would love to hear from you either via email
at Lordofspiritsatationfaith.com
or you can message us at our Lordofspirits Podcast
Facebook page.
We read everything but can't respond everything
and we do save what you send
for possible use in future episodes.
And join us for our live broadcast
on the second and fourth Thursdays of the month
at 7 p.m. Eastern 4 p.m. Pacific.
Like our Facebook page and join our Facebook discussion group
Thank you.
still do that sort of thing.
Leave reviews and ratings, but most importantly,
share this show with a friend whom you know is going to love it.
And consider starting a Lord of Spirits discussion group
at your parish.
Hello everyone from St. Sava in Texas.
And finally be sure to go to ancientfaith.com slash support
and help make sure we and lots of other AFR podcasters
stay on the air.
Thank you very much and may God bless you always.
You've been listening to the Lord of Spirits with Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew
Stephen Damick and Father Stephen De Young, a listener-supported presentation of ancient
faith radio.
And I beheld and I heard the voice of many angels round about the throne and the beasts
and the elders, and the number of them was 10,000 times 10,000 than thousands of thousands,
staying with a loud voice, worthy is the land that was slain.
to receive power and riches and wisdom and strength and honor and glory and blessing.
Revelation chapter 5 verses 11 through 12.