Yeah, yeah. Yeah.
Relied on sort of the love of anti-heroes in Western culture.
Right. So just a technical note, Father Steven, you're kind of cutting in and out.
So there are engineer who is Motik Shukha Trudy. Hello Trudy is going to be sending you
a new link. But I just wanted to talk while we're working on that a little bit about what
you're discussing just from my own experience. You know, when I was a kid, I read a lot of,
You know what we would call
mythology literature. And you know, we've talked about this a little bit in the past on the show, but
this idea that these are just sort of stories, right? And that the modern people often have the sense that ancient mythology is
ancient people who saw stuff that they couldn't
that they couldn't explain. And so they came up with the idea of gods who did things. So like, you know, lightning and thunder or storms or the
ocean moving or whatever and they looked at that and they said, well, that there must be
some kind of force behind that that's making that happen.
And the problem, of course, with that outlook is number one, it doesn't take ancient people
seriously.
And number two, it doesn't account for the complexity of the stories, right?
And especially the similarity of them across different cultures, right?
And...
You know, we're going to be talking about, like you said, that there's this kind of propaganda
from a Christian and ancient Israel point of view that the stories of these ancient gods
is not actually the true story of what really occurs, that it's an attempt to co-opt what
really happened in order to bring people under their subjection to make them think that they're
kind of on the right.
So to speak in worshiping these fallen beings.
You know, so yeah, it's interesting.
And one of the things that we've, you know, if you read the scriptures closely,
you'll note that some of these stories from ancient peoples
and the worship that they engage in intersect at various points with the scripture.
And of course, the one that you see the most often as bail,
probably especially in the Old Testament.
and Bayless mentioned over and over again, but have your
thought about who bail is exactly right and why is bail mentioned so often in the Old Testament?
It's not just that there's this other worship that's going on somewhere, but that this is a being
that they're actually dealing with. So, Father Stephen, do we have your back here yet?
I believe so.
Okay, great.
Okay.
Alright.
Yeah, yeah. Yes, listeners. I was just I was just filling in a little bit, but hopefully that was actually good content.
Yes, so okay, so so let's talk about some of this propaganda, right?
And yeah.
The first of these probably is what's referred to generally by scholars and all of these stories together.
As you find in pretty much every ancient culture, some version of what's called this succession.
myth, which is the bare bones, the idea that there was a we talked before about how there
was the idea of there being a council of gods and then a sort of divine opt-high god and
then a divine son who was the head of the council. We talked about how in Israel that was
Yahweh in both cases, right? So you already have at least vinegaredity into ancient Israel
like religion.
But the idea in most of the other cultures of the ancient world pretty much universally is that there was an original most high god
Who was overthrown at least once by a later god who rose up from among the council by one of his sons in the council
Who overthrew him and took his place? Yeah, the most high god
so
The most common you mentioned bail already, this has
with Bale. The Bale cycle is primarily the story of Bale's insurrection. This happens twice in
Babylonian mythology. It happens twice in Greek mythology, as people may be aware, when
and Kronos castrates his book, Roronos, or Uranus,
and becomes the most high god.
And then Zeus later kills his book.
other chronos and takes us place. So there are actually two successes there. Yeah.
It's a rapolonium mythology. So you have this story of a rebellion, but in every case
in these other nations, that rebellion was successful. Right. Right. And of course, the
version that we are going to see in the Old Testament in the Hebrew scriptures is going
to be converted in that this insurrection is going to have fail.
And now this is the basis for what Milton does in Paradise Lost, but here's the key difference.
By casting it before the creation of the world, there's a basic logical problem.
So you say in a way an angel is a creature.
So let's see tomorrow you decide you're going to overthrow God and become God.
What's your first step?
You get to get an army together.
What's the army going to do?
I don't know, attack some other gods.
Right?
You literally can't attack God.
As a creature.
Yeah.
Right?
You can't like throw things at him.
I mean, like there's not.
Yeah.
What do you?
There's not a way to do that.
Right?
And the key to this is that.
Gregory said in the quote that we...
read a last episode when he said where is God enthroned?
God is enthroned in the minds, the hearts of his creatures.
Right. He's everywhere.
And so if you're going to dethrone the most high God, the true God,
the only way to do that, you can't defrown him in reality.
But you can try to de-thrown him in the hearts and minds of his creatures, but that requires there to be other creatures.
Yeah
So
creation hasn't happened yet then
Yeah, yeah, and and it's interesting just as a as a point that
What did it mean for them to rebel?
when we're talking about the true story, right?
What does it mean for them to rebel?
And
It is in some sense an internal process, right?
Casting him out, so to speak, from their own hearts and minds.
Now, obviously God is everywhere, but so it's not a question of actually creating a space
that God can't be in, because that's not a thing, but rather a space that you're not receiving
him.
That's exactly how human beings do it, too.
I mean, right?
that we de-throw him in our hearts
not in a way that makes us,
so he's no longer present,
cause he's everywhere present,
but in a way that we're no longer accepting him
and receiving him and cooperating with him
and to use new testimonies,
synergizing with him,
instead we're resisting him, right?
And so that's what this means
cast them out from the throne of their hearts.
Right. And you can't attack him, but you can attack your fellow creatures. Right. You
can't destroy him, but you could try to destroy your fellow creatures. And that love of
God and love of neighbor and hatred of God and hatred of neighbor always linked together
in the scriptures all the way through. Yeah. Because you, you, you, if you have wrath
against God or anger against God or rebellion against God, you're going to express that
by taking it out.
on his creatures. And that's exactly what the devil ends up doing. And that's the storyline
that's going on in terms of the devil in Genesis chapter 3. Okay. So much focus in Western religion
is on Adam and Eve, right? And what happens with them and what they did, right? And in a later
episode I'm sure we'll be talking about the
three falls of humanity in Genesis 1 through 11.
Yeah, because there's three falls people.
There are three falls of humanity.
Post, post-Saint Augustine, everything gets kind of pushed
into Adam.
But there's something that happens to Eve,
but there's also something here that happens
to the devil, to the serpent.
and there are sometimes people who want to
to read Genesis 3 a little overly literally and turn them into a talking snake, right?
Yeah.
Say, this is like a Rudyard Kipling just so story, how the snake lost his legs, right?
That's what I have.
Six head legs, but then, oh, this one was bad.
So now they don't have legs.
But that obviously is not, right?
What the scriptures are spending their time talking about.
The word that's used here that's translated so-
in Hebrew and Akash. There's actually a little bit of a play out of words because of course in Hebrew you only write the consonants.
Right. The vowel points, if you read modern Hebrew or read a modern printing of the Hebrew Bible, it has vowel points added and those were added in the medieval period.
So thousands of years after it was written.
But if you take the valid points,
words become much more ambiguous. You just have three consonants. So the word
necache in this case can be a noun being used substantively, being used like a
noun or a snake or it could be a verb or a verbal noun, essentially a part of
Oh, a sneaky.
Well, so if it's a now to be
being serpent, right?
If it's an adjective,
means the shining one. Oh, interesting. If it's a verbal participle, it means the cutting
one or the deceptive one, the deceiver. All three of those ideas, if you don't have
valopoints, it makes it very easy to do a word play where it can mean all three of those
things. Yeah. And this is a feature of Hebrew prose and poetry to use a word in this
Let's go.
of multivalent way to convey all of these things. So in terms of the snake
part, remember that serpents are a class of angel. We talked about the seraphim
last time that seraph is the the Egyptian word for a serpent. And just a moment
I'm going to talk a little bit about a Zecule 28, where this story is told
from another perspective.
And in there, the W.
Foray Fell is referred to
was a guardian cherub. And cherub's had a similar kind of role as a guardian of a divine throne
in the ancient world. But so in Genesis 3, particularly in verse 14 and 15, is that the serpent himself
is cursed by Yahweh. And that curse is important in terms of understanding what's going on here
with the devil.
And what Yahweh says to him in Genesis 3, 14 and 15 is because you've done this,
cursed are you beyond all be Saul creatures.
And beyond all of the animals of the field, on your belly you shall go and dust you shall
eat all the days of your life.
And I'll put enmity between you and the woman and your seed and her seed.
He will bruise your head and you will.
Now that verse 15 is meditation.
on a lot as being sort of an initial statement of the gospel. Right. But that part about going on
your belly and eating dust all the day to your life is the part that gets turned into, oh, well,
he lost his legs. Yeah. Akshit people weren't stupid. Yeah. Yeah. It's not like they,
they, that they snakes were eating dirt. You know, they knew that they saw the meat mice,
Right, dislike we've seen the meat wise.
that they followed that. And so the dust that this is talking about, it's the same word,
because this is in the context of also then Adam and Eve receiving the curse that dust they are
and to dust they shall return. And so the imagery here is of the serpent, the devil,
becoming the Eater of the Dead. See an iconography, Hades depicted this way.
is the sort of serpent with a big wide open mouth, the vouring, the vouring people, the
vouring the dead.
And so this is what's happening here is not just about snakes.
It's about the devil.
This is where he falls.
This is where he's cast down.
And he becomes earth.
And he becomes the Lord of death, right?
He becomes associated with death.
and the word here for
translated ground, passed down to the ground or the earth is
errant in Hebrew, which is also a word that's commonly used
refer to the other.
So the underworld is the devil being made, he's made the
prince of the underworld, he's made the Lord of death.
And we see this reference in the New Testament.
One big example is Hebrews 2.14, which refers to the one who
who holds the power of death.
Yes, right.
That is a devil.
Right.
Which is interesting to put it that way.
Like, it doesn't mean like it's not like, um, and maybe correct me if I'm wrong.
Getting this wrong.
We're not saying that he's the one who gets to decide when people die.
Right.
Yeah.
That's not he has the power to go around and kill whoever he wants.
Right.
Um.
But, but that's, uh, right.
the idea in the curse that's put on that
and Eve, you know, dust you are to dust you will return, right? It's sort of God brought them
from nothing and they're going to go back to being nothing. Yeah. Right. And so essentially the devil
here is being made the Lord of nothing. Right. Is this kingdom of dust and ashes, which is what he
receives. Yeah. And then this this whole idea that, of course, that a lot of our hemnography of
of Pascha that crept in and invades the underworld and takes even that away from him.
doesn't even have that to him. Yeah. Right. When all is said and done. Yeah. And and this
story, the same story gets retold again by the prophet Isaiah and the prophet Ezekiel.
Okay. About the devil. But they both tell it in terms of the stories being told in surrounding
nations surrounding...
surrounding Israel. So they're co-opting what we would call pagan mythology. Right?
Right. They're or correcting it. Right. Saying, here's your story. Right. Here's the truth.
And so for the prophet Isaiah, speaking to Babylon, that takes place in Isaiah 14.
Okay. Do you want to read that section? Yeah.
This is 3 through 21.
Yeah, sure it's kind of long-ish, but let's go ahead and roll through it
I'm looking at the the King James version here
So you know if there's any translation problems. I mean no
And it shall come to pass in the day that the Lord shall give the rest from the sorrow and from thy fear and from the hard bondage
We're in that was made to serve
thou shall take up this proverb against the king of Babylon and say
How hath the oppressor ceased the golden city ceased
The Lord has broken the step.
of the wicked and the scepter of the rulers. He who smought the people in wrath with a continual stroke,
he that ruled the nations in anger is persecuted and none hindrath. The whole earth is at rest and
is quiet. They break forth into singing. Ye the fir trees rejoice at the and the cedars of Lebanon
saying, since thou art laid down, no feller is come up against us. Hell from beneath is moved for the
to meet thee at thy coming. It stireth up the dead for thee, even all the chief ones of the earth.
It is
raised up from their thrones all the kings of the nations. All they shall speak and say
into the art thou also become weak as we, art thou become like unto us. Thy pomp is brought
down to the grave and the noise of thy vials. The worm is spread under thee and the worms cover thee.
How art thou fallen from heaven, O Lucifer, son of the morning? How art thou cut down to the ground,
which dits weak in the nations? For thou is said in thy heart, I will ascend into heaven,
and I will exalt my throne above the stars of God.
I will sit also upon the mount of the congregation in the sides of the north.
I will ascend above the heights of the clouds.
I will be like the most high, yet thou shalt be brought down to hell to the sides of the pit.
They that see thee shall narrowly look upon thee and consider thee saying,
is this the man that made the earth to tremble that did shake kingdoms,
that made the world as a wilderness and destroyed the cities thereof,
that opened not the house of his prisoners, all the kings of the nations,
even all of them lie in glory, everyone in his own house.
but that
How art cast out of thy grave like an abominable branch, and as the raiment of those that are slain thrust through the sword,
that go down to the stones of the pit as a carcass trotten under feet, thou shalt not be joined with them in burial,
because thou hast destroyed thy land, and slain thy people, the seed of evil-doers, shall never be renowned.
Prepare slaughter for his children, for the iniquity of their fathers, that they do not rise nor possess the land,
fill the face of the world with cities.
It's kind of a long passage, but I think it's worth rolling through it, actually.
But yeah, I mean, it's interesting just to read it.
If you didn't know that this is essentially a repeat of the Genesis 3 story, then you
kind of wonder what's going on here when this is talking, what it's talking about, you
know?
Right.
But you have this repeated language of being brought down to the maggots and worms, which
or of course representative-
of death, you know, that he's brought out as you'll lay it on a bag of maggots and worms
in person. And it's this idea of this fall. And of course, probably the most famous part of this is
since you read the King James, it had the name Luke inserted it to it. It's interesting to me how many
Modern Orthodox authors have a doc.
the idea that the devil's NFL was Lucifer.
Okay.
This is actually something St. Jerome came up with.
In the fifth century, D.
Now he's not wrong.
What is actually there in the Hebrew
is the name of this person is Hello Benchekar.
car is son of the morning.
star, which is where that sort of sun of the morning comes from. But hell out in the Hebrew,
most likely is actually a Hebrewization of the name Enlil, who was the primary god of
old Babylon. So the Babylonian Empire who shows up and takes Judah into captivity with
the Nebuchadnezzar, the one we're familiar with in the Old Testament, is actually the Neo-Babalonean
an empire.
Old Babylon, Enlil was the chief of the gods and had been overthrown by Marduk.
And Marduk was at this time the chief god.
So but Enlil had also been the subject of the succession myth.
So Enlil had taken this place as the most high god by force and then was unseated by Marduk.
And so Isaiah is deliberately playing with this story.
Correcting it to say that that no, you know, you you tried to overthrow
Yahweh the true God, but you failed and were cast down to
Toshio while so when when Saint Jerome comes to this and is looking for a name
He actually gets Lucifer from first enoch
Oh interesting
So so this is an importation this is an importation
from first enich that makes its way into the King James version of the Bible.
Yes, yeah, Saint Jerome was a fair fan of first enich to the point of apologizing for it to the point of coming up with an elaborate explanation about Noah taking a copy on the arc with him to explain its provenance.
Wow, but in in first enich the name of a zeal will name of a zeal before he fell was rema-l which means the light bearer of God.
Okay.
But Lucifer is pretty much a direct Latin translation of that.
And so he translates it, Lucifer, son of the morning to bring in the Ben-Shakar, but
he's not really the basis for Lucifer.
He's going for the Rinochic tradition to get that.
That's interesting.
And then we won't read the whole story, but Ezekiel in chapter 28.
tells it again in verses one through ten of that chapter he gives a prophecy
against the Prince of Tyre and if you read it it's very clear he's talking about
the human king and then he gives a prophecy about the king of Tyre who would
outrank him and it's about the king of Tyre that he says that he stood
among the the blazing stones and then talks about him being cast down to the
Underworld.
which is again this same story of sort of a failed insurrection,
attached to Eden, which helps us with the connection to Genesis 3.
But this is also formed around the story of Bale.
Bale likewise, as we mentioned, had this succession myth,
where he overthrew the post-part.
And then in the Bale cycle, after doing that,
he just ended up building his palace there, just of his own accord.
Whereas in his EQL version,
in the correct version he fails.
is cast down into the underworld. And that is sort of the last little he is allowed to have.
Wow. So all right, well, we've gone about half an hour. So we're going to go ahead and take
a break. And when we come back, we are going to talk about the next fall of angels that we want
want to discuss so let's go ahead and go to break.
The Ancient Faith for the Modern World
This is Ancient Faith Radio.
Blessed Memory.
It seemed to me that in this modern life of ours, everything has become so frightfully
materialistic.
There is a very great need of tense figuration of a change of our attitude, our way of thinking,
our way of behaving, our way of hurting ourselves.
Everything needs a new Christianization.
it must become more aware of the Christ within us.
first published in 1981 and long out of print.
The Holy Angels by Mother Alexandra has yet to be surpassed
as a comprehensive and comprehensible account of the nature of the angels
and their role in our salvation. In lay person's terms,
Mother Alexandra presents the essence of everything the church has to teach us
about the angels. Beginning with the Old Testament, continuing through the
New Testament and concluding with the tradition of the church
I see
express in her theology, hemnography, and iconography.
For those who long to become better acquainted
with these holy servants of God
and to understand their role in our lives,
this book is a great place to start.
Available now at store.antientfaith.com.
Again, that is store.antientfaith.com.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits,
Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father
even to young. If you have a question call now at 855-237-2346. That's 855-AF radio.
All right well welcome back. This is the second part of the show and it's where we begin to take
your calls. You can reach us at 855-AF radio. That's 855-237-2346 and you can also send questions
our chat room, but we would especially love to hear your voices. So, you know, just to recap a little bit,
we talked about the fall of the devil becoming the Lord of the dead. And it's interesting to me
that when you look at the biblical narratives, while you do get occasionally this language of being
cast down, the thing that, and I think we'll see this as we proceed through these different
five different events is that what's really happening is actually it
five rebellions or five apostacies even right? You know, there is this language of being cast
down but it's not necessarily just like a moral fall in the sense of like, oh well, I guess that
angel sinned, he's a demon now. You know, right? That's not what we're talking about, is it?
Right. Like it's not that all the feathers fell out of their wings and they turned into bat wings and
and it proves that a tale, yeah.
And as we talked about, there are different types of angels.
And when those angels rebel against their creator, they turn into different types of evil spirits.
That they have a, there are certain commonalities, as we said, that they're going to attack God's creation, chiefly humanity,
and trying to destroy God's creation, chiefly humanity,
out of their aim.
or rebellion toward their creator, but they're not all going to do it the same way.
I'll go ahead and mention here, I think we've mentioned it before, but there's not like a hierarchy.
Right? Like we just talked about the devil. It's not like the devil's the boss.
Yeah, all the other demons, right? And they all work for him and they have some kind of authority
structure. We tend to at least in popular culture turn the
demons and hell into whatever we think is bad. So if you're, if you're John Milton, then
you're a Puritan. It's a kingdom for sure. Right? And he has all his courteers and everything
in this reg structure, this hierarchy. If you're in CS Lewis's day, the worst thing you could
think of is bureaucracy. So it becomes this big bureaucracy full of middle managers and interoffice
memos that's got to be a hellis.
Right.
But the spirits of chaos and lawlessness and destruction, so that hierarchy is a good thing,
so they don't have one.
Right?
They're trying to destroy hierarchy and creation.
Yeah.
So, before we get to this next posthusy that we're going to talk about, we actually have Bob
from North Carolina calling in.
So Bob, are you there?
Can you hear us?
Yes, yes, I mean, welcome Bob. What is your question for us this evening?
I've always wondered what gave Lucifer state and the idea that he would actually be able to conquer
the Supreme Omnipotent being? Where did he get that idea?
All right, well, that's a good question. So father Steven, how does the devil
think that he can actually win this fight.
Right.
Well, that's part of what we were saying before in terms of the sense that if this is a fist
fight, obviously, he doesn't have a chance.
There's too much of a power and disparity here for him to do that.
that in terms of leading humans who are God's creation, leading them to their destruction.
that he can do. So it's not a war of conquest. It's a war of attrition. It's an anger.
We didn't really mention this in terms of the devil, but what the fathers tell us, for example,
I know I've quoted St Andrew of Cessaria of this before, but he said that after the
crew of the devil fell through envy, and that's envy of humanity, because humanity was created
for this destiny in Christ.
right that that angels don't have that the devil didn't have. And so that anger
and resentment led him to try to destroy humanity. And so for him, there's no
way in terms of unseeding God or taking over the earth or avoiding his fate
at the last judgment, even do as much damage as he can in that time spent.
That's why St. Peter says the devil proud.
about like a roaring lion seeking someone to devour, right? He knows this time is short, and so he's trying to do all the damage and destruction that he's creative of his creator.
Yeah, and you know, the thing that I would add that this idea that a demon could overthrow the most high god is pure propaganda.
Like he knows that that's not actually possible.
Right?
It's this is...
this appears in these other myths, but it's not actually a thing that the demons think
that they can accomplish.
So as Father Stephen was saying, that instead they attack us in particular, and I think
that that's a really important point to make, not just in terms of, you know, what does
the devil think he can actually accomplish by doing this, but rather understanding where
we fit into the story.
That, you know, as Father Stephen said, we often look at Genesis and we see it as being a
story about mankind and that is true.
But the truth is that there is another story going on
and that is the story of these angelic rebellions.
And what happens with mankind falling into sin,
we're going to talk about this, obviously a lot more
when we talk about the various falls of mankind.
But what happens is that man is joining in
and existing rebellion.
And that's the rebellion of these demonic powers.
Right? And to think that the fall of everything hinges entirely
on what
Adam and Eve do is not to see the whole story and not even to realize that it's actually
not even chapter one, you know, of the story of rebellion.
You know, that there's an ongoing rebellion and mankind is joining in with it.
And that explains, of course, why it is when we, when we act like demons and rebel against
God, then we become more and more like them.
You know, we're joining their side.
And just to wrap up what I'm saying here, you know, at the beginning of the Orthodox baptismal
service.
There is what is called in Greek the apotus Sikhs and Sindaxis, which means basically the
the desertion and the pledging of allegiance, I guess, the alignment.
And it's where the person says that they're repudialing Satan and everything that he does
and saying, now I align myself with Christ.
So the idea is you're leaving that rebellion and you're joining yourself now with the one
who created you with the one who loves you with the one who wants to.
to make you like himself. So does that make sense Bob?
Yes it does. It seems like basically Satan is pure spite.
Yeah, envy. Envy.
Yep, absolutely.
So yeah.
Well, thank you very much for that call Bob.
Great, I'm glad that answered your question.
All right, so Father Stephen, let's talk about the next apostasy or fall of angelic beings.
Uh,
What do we got next?
What else, you know, is we're taking this litany of bad stuff?
Horrible things.
Well, this one also has a corresponding pagan narrative in the surrounding cultures.
And this is a narrative that we find in things like the Sumerian Kings list and the story
of the Opcalaure, the story of the Seven Sages.
in this video.
and Kings list, and this is true of Sumerian and early
Acadian religion, they believed that this story will tell you
that when humanity was first created, they lived in the
cities of the gods, but then at a certain point the gods
became angry at them and from those cities.
And so humanity had to go and build their own cities.
Right, and we sort of see this in what happens with Kane, right?
Kane goes and builds, builds the first city and he, even the name of this city from these
other stories, we're told that Kane names the city after the son of his son, after his
grandson, Irrad and the most pertaining in belief was that the first city was Eris.
do. It's linguistically the same name. Okay, right. So, and then in the pagan version of the story,
the gods then give kingship to as a gift. The other gods, not the the most high god who threw them out
of the cities. And the way it says is that the kingship comes and is given.
you may notice with both this is when we talked about that the most beginning is always cast as wicked
and evil over against the new gods who have shown up. Yeah right who are entities back
And are now going to do something to favor them, right?
This
narrative as a side note, when you take the pagan narrative and apply the scriptures to it,
rather than seeing scriptures as correcting the pagan narrative, but you end up with,
well there's this Old Testament, most high god who's bad, and then there's this new god who shows
up in the New Testament and takes over. Right. Right. So they've sort of sort of
did it, wedged it in there. But in this comes down from heaven, there's an
area before the flood and then after the flood. And before the flood, that's the
time of the seven sages, the Apkalu, who the first of which comes out of the sea.
And things has an Apkalu, has one of these lesser gods who's advising him. And
because of this advisor.
the king is able to create astrology,
dick, technology, all of these things
based on this knowledge
that he's given from these spirits.
After the flood,
the kings who are listed are said to be
two-thirds of Kalu and one-third human.
So, this is to be hybridized
It's supposed to be hybridized.
Yeah.
I mean, how do you mean two thirds of something that doesn't work out in terms of what we'll
get to that in a second.
But there's a way it works out.
But then based on these stories, it was very common for various cultures to claim as part
of their right of kingship when they able to establish an empire or conquer territory
to claim that they had access.
to these law secrets from before the blood that were imparted by these beings.
The most famous one of those groups is probably the Amuru.
And the most famous Amuru, they came in from the west in Concord, Mesopotamia.
Amuru actually means westerners.
They came from what's now Syria in Concord, Mesopotamia.
And the most famous one of those is probably Hammurabi.
Okay.
Yeah right, yeah the code guy
Right. And these are the same folks who are called amurites in the Torah.
Oh, yeah.
The amurites who they're facing, the amurite kings who are among the ones who they're told to wipe out.
These are the same people who claim to have this knowledge.
So we get a version of this story then 4 through 6.
a correcting of the record or a defeating propaganda, where you see Keynes line laid out,
Keynes found the first city. The major figures in Keynes line who are named, it talks about the
technological innovations that they produced. Yeah, right, right. Weapons of war, all of these things.
So this idea is that yes, these spirits gave technology to man, but it was not to benefit man.
and they were giving man technology.
humanity wasn't ready for. Right. Right. And this, this same story is played out in multiple
other ancient mythologies, right? So, you know, the one that probably most people, most
of our listeners are familiar with is Greek mythology. And you've got the story of Prometheus,
right? Who, who gives fire from the gods to mankind. And but in, of course, in that story,
depicted as
as permeteous kind, you know, it's correct in the sense that permeteous is sort of
rebelling. He's doing something he's not supposed to be doing, but it's presented as
positive. Like look at this wonderful gift that he gave mankind, you know, and but the
problem of course is that, again, it's propaganda, right? This is these demons saying, look
at all the good things that we gave you, you know, why don't you just go ahead and bow down
and worship us. And you think about that like isn't
that the same thing that's happening when Christ is tempted by the devil, that the devil offers
him stuff. Look, look what I'll do for you if you just bow down and worship me. And even
in our own lives, right, there's this promise of being great, being smart, being beautiful,
being popular, being wealthy, being prestigious. If only you would serve whatever it is that
you're being asked to
serve. You know, so it's a trick, right? It's, as you said, it's for their destruction.
Notice who this technology is given to. It's given to Kane, the first murderer and to his,
you know, his descendants. But the problem, of course, is like, you look at the stuff, you're like,
well, what's so wrong with, like iron working and with music and like, what's wrong with that stuff?
Right, and it gets expanded first to get the book of Jubilee's, you know.
to include all kinds of things in terms of pharmaceuticals.
And sorcery means the destruction of the opposite sex.
But even if we're just talking about raw technology,
again, it's not that it's evil anymore
than the tree of knowledge of people in it itself,
but it was wisdom for which humanity wasn't ready
to use it appropriately.
And so it comes to...
And these men as, I'm giving you this knowledge so that you can use it to gain power, to conquer
your neighbors, to set yourself up as a king, to seduce members of the opposite sex.
So you'll have this power and wealth and authority, and that's what humanity uses it for.
Right.
So from the pagan perspective, kingship and these kings are these glorious beings from
the perspective of scripture,
there are these wicked beings who are destroying themselves.
Eddie.
each other and the world around them.
And that culminates in Genesis 6, 1 through 4,
with the story of the sons of God going into the daughters of men
and having these children who are described as Nephilim,
as giants.
And will undoubtedly do a whole episode
just talking about giants.
but oh yeah, there is gonna be a
Giants episode, I know a lot of people are so ready for that and and well you should.
But it's such a big topic.
It's such a big topic.
Yeah.
We, I know we actually had one person that emailed us and said, stop saying you're going to cover
something in a future episode.
But the problem is, it's such a, the stuff we're talking about branches so much that we have
to constantly limit it and say, well, we're not going to go there yet.
You know, eventually we will have to keep.
We have to keep teasing, we have to tease future countries.
That's right, because we want people to come back.
Exactly.
But so for our purposes, for our purposes tonight, right, we get to hit into what this means,
right, like we have angelic beings procreating with humans, right.
And of course, in the pagan stories, we have these people who are two thirds,
find being one third.
human or demigods right? Right right and we see that in like in the Greek
traditions you know Hercules being a pride. Hercules. Yep. These these
definitely these men of renowned Gilgamesh is another one of them. We get a clue
in this sort of exactly what's going on actually in Deuteronomy 3 verse 11.
Okay. In a verse that no one has cross stitched above their door.
I guarantee it.
This is not anybody's life verse.
No, no one has made this a theme for a retreat.
I know.
Even I have not yet, although now I think it is a challenge.
They're like, take it as a challenge now.
But do you know what we've been doing?
Verse 11 describes Aug's bed.
Yeah.
Aug is the king of patient, which we'll talk about more.
He's the last of the refeem, which we'll also talk about.
what we talk about.
about giants. But it gives this
description of this bronze bed
of an usual size. It gives the
measurement and you know, it's
basically a teen foot tall person.
Yeah, yeah, do you mind if I
read this one? I'm looking, I'm
looking, of course, again at the
King James, which for all of its
problems is still probably my
favorite Bible. So, Deuteronomy 311
for only Og King of Bishan
of the remnant of giants.
Behold, his bedstead was a bedstead of iron.
Is it not in roboth of the children of Amon?
Nine qubits was the length thereof
and four qubits, the breadth of it
after the qubit of a man.
So as you said, about 15 feet, right?
Nine qubits is about 15 feet.
I mean, nobody's got a qubit.
You learn their house.
Yeah, yeah.
And the size of a qubit varied the same way.
the size of a foot used to because it was the measurement from the end of your
middle finger to your elbow. Oh, that varies a lot on different size
humans. Right. It was usually the king's cubit, but you know, it's hard to tell
sometimes in the text exactly how big but roughly. And and so basically
first tells us about this giant bed, this giant metal bed, right? And that
And it's on display somewhere where you can go and look at it.
Right, right? Is it not there? Yeah.
Yeah. And people kind of skim over it go, okay, he had a big bed, right?
But here's where this becomes important.
When the Ziggurat of Edmund Nankhi was excavated in Babylon,
they found a bed with exactly these dimensions, a metal bed with exactly these dimensions in the temple.
you
And this bed was a ritual bed that was used for pagan ritual.
There was a time of the year, there was a festival where the king would go into the temple.
He would be entwelt by the spirit of the God of the temple.
And he would fornicate with one of the
temple prostitutes to an
inter-ritual act, a paying a ritual act
that would ensure fertility and
prosperity for the city in the future.
But the future king was often
conceived in this manner.
The idea behind pointing out that this is
Aug's bed is telling us about something about his origin.
and the origin.
giants in general. So a future king conceived in this way would have two fathers, the king
and the god who the king was embodying. And one mother, right, who was the woman in the temple.
And so the king was considered to be a god, the god they were worshiping was considered to be a god.
And the woman was a human.
So you had to wait.
two thirds one third's man and that's how that works. You know, I'm suddenly thinking
of that was what was that movie was it twins was that the film that had two fathers no
I don't know I'm blanking on that anyways, but they're clearly not about Nephilim.
That's the two shows.
Yeah, yeah, my two dads was not better than before.
three minute not not about not believe but now listeners you've got all kinds of great jokes to make that your friends are not going to get it all so enjoy.
Right. And so this is this is what we're talking about. It's this this demonic ritual origin.
to involve spiritual powers and human kings that is producing these quote unquote heroes
of all.
So that's what we're talking about. We're talking about giants in Nephilim in short form, but the spiritual
beings involved in this, then our spiritual beings who are obviously by doing this are entering into
rebellion. Right. Then then punish versus second Peter and then St. Jude's epistle. Yeah.
But you're picking up on things that are already there in Jewish literature preserving these
traditions that yeah so so that's that's the apostasy is leading
man kind of stray by giving him knowledge that he's not ready for that's going to lead him into
destruction. Right. And that culminates in this sort of combination of sexual immorality
and happiness that humans are led into by these spirits. Okay. All right. Well, let's talk about the
third fall or apostasy of demons.
And this one's boy, I'm looking at the notes here and it's just this amazing list.
But yeah, let's talk about that.
So this is, you know, we've got this listed as what the origin of demons, right?
Although like, why would we say that?
Haven't we been talking about demons the whole time?
Like what makes this distinct?
Right.
Well, the origin of the demons that we read about in the synoptic gospels.
Okay, alright, so the demons that we need.
Like, for instance, the the the exorcism that happens with Legion, you know, into the pigs or or what about what about the the the the spirit that's in the the fortune telling woman that St. Paul gets so annoyed at the spirit is that the back.
Yeah, and book of acts and kind of thing that we see in Saul the unclean spirit who comes to trouble King Saul.
Okay. The demonic spirit in the book of Tobit, who appears...
There are these, we've been talking about sort of fallen angelic beings.
And even though there's at least one person who hates when we say this,
we're talking about bodies later.
We mentioned it last week that angels do have a sort of body.
It's just very different than ours.
Yeah.
But there are these demonic spirits and are including who are bodyless.
because they come and put them in the cell or they go
into idols and use idols as body. Right. These bodyless beings. And so the short version
of where they come from is the guys we were just talking about the Nephilim die. And
their spirits leave their bodies. And a portion of them become these spirits. Right. So in
In this case we're talking about...
spiritual beings who have, they fell when they led Manastray, but then there's another,
another event that involves these same,
same beings, right? Is that what you're saying?
These are the spawn, the spiritual spawn.
Oh, gotcha.
Those beings.
Which, okay, so are we talking about actual reproduction or what, when we're talking about the product
of this ritual.
Okay, right. We're talking about the product of the we aren't told how it all works, right? Yeah, okay. There isn't D and there's a DNA or at least knowledge of DNA in the age of world.
Yeah, so we have to sort of take what we have.
And this is sort of put in narrative form, for example, in the book of Jubilee's where when these spirits, you know, the flood wipes out a lot and we read in Scripture that the descendants of Abraham leading up to David White.
up to David White.
the rest of the Nephilim, these giants, and the name
de mastima in the book of Jubilee's go to God to cut a deal
and says sort of similar to what we saw St. Gregory talking about again.
He says, well, if you allow some of us to remain in the world and don't throw us
all into the abyss, right? Which is where the previous
spirits were in prison. It says, if you don't there's any of this, if you let us remain in the world
until the last judgment, we will, we'll afflict the wicked sort of on your behalf. We'll go and
we'll afflict the wicked and you can use that to bring them to repentance. It kind of cut this deal.
We'll never bad people. And so the book of Jubilee's got sort of a gris that used the evil spirit
So the way Saint Gregory talked about, even though they made it for evil, God uses it for
good. But this idea, even though we don't see it explicitly laid out in the scriptures,
is sort of resident all the way through. Why are they unclean spirits? What makes them unclean?
Not evil but unclean. Yeah. Why would they be described that way?
The Torah, when something is unclean, the easiest way to get a unclean is for it to be mixed.
You mix two types of cloth. You plant two different things at the same field.
You mix beaten dairy products.
And so I won't use the word that the Dead Sea Scrolls use for these demons, but it refers to
them being illegitimate in birth. Interesting. And so that idea of their uncleanness, that that's
how they're identified in the Old Testament. And then when they speak in the New Testament,
you know, we see them say to Christ, you know, if you come to trouble us before the time,
Right. We still have the time.
I've left. Yeah, you're coming here to throw us into the abyss now.
We have. Yeah, when is the time?
Right. And so this is this is reflected, right? It lays underneath.
It's part of the tradition that lays underneath the scriptures.
Right. And I think that it's really important to underline at this point.
What? What exactly this has to do with us? Because this is this is I think is
one of the
sort of apostacies that we should pay attention to the most because the truth is is that we do
still have demons in the world. They are still functioning in the world and they are here with God's
permission obviously because if they didn't have her permission, they wouldn't be here.
And as you said, there was this deal struck that they said that they would only afflict the wicked
and God permits them to stay and afflict.
but you know, one of the questions that some people might ask then is like, well, wait a minute.
I'm not one of the wicked and yet I'm having these problems.
You know, I'm being afflicted by a demon.
And I think that the way to understand that is that God of course knows full well
because he created all of us that human repentance does not happen when we are comfortable, right?
right? And it just doesn't. We have
We have kind of no reason to repent if we're comfortable. You know, there has to be a struggle
Right, and so one of the ways that the struggle comes to us is through demonic affliction now the demons have their own agenda
They are in this because they want to draw us away from God and certainly sometimes you see when people are afflicted by demons
They do of their own accord. They they are drawn away from God. They enter into that rebellion. They join in the rebellion but
temptation also is actually valuable to the saint.
So even the righteous person, because he's still, you know, there's still some part of his will that isn't totally aligned with God,
he can use that as an opportunity to repent even more, right?
You know, demonic affliction is an opportunity to repent, and it's not only people that we think of as bad sinners,
but it's all of us. All of us, you know, have this opportunity to repent.
And you and I were talking about this a little bit a few months ago when we were on Father Thomas Sorokas show
ancient faith today
where he asked the question, you know, is the coronavirus a judgment from God, right?
And you know, which is a lot of people are saying that actually it just saw a survey results today.
I think it was from the Pew Research people saying that something like a third of Americans
believe that there's a lesson from God in the virus. And I think probably a lot of them think,
Well God is doing this to us like he's afflicting us with this.
suffering because we did something bad. And that's only kind of partly right. We do need to repent
of our evil, but it's not God who sends out plagues in the sense of like these directly afflicting us.
It's, you know, wherever you see, especially mass suffering like this, there's demonic activity going on.
And we do have an opportunity to repent. We see it over and over again in scripture where
a disaster befalls.
the people of God, whether it's disease or invasion or calamity, you know, earthquakes or whatever.
And it becomes an opportunity for them to repent, so to turn back to God. So I mean, you know, this
is this is one of the ways that we understand evil in the world. You know, if we do not remember
that there are demonic powers out there, then we can think, well, all the evil in the world is either
mankind doing it. And you know, why doesn't God just stop them or even worse? It's God doing
this
to us, right? But we forget that there is this other force out there that is functioning
with God's permission, but he's not attacking us, right? He's allowing them so that we can
repent because he knows that we need it. So I just wanted to kind of add that as a way
of really connecting this directly to our own lives. And I'll be, I'll say this, you know,
As I came to understand this better, I came to see...
it as being liberating actually because a lot of times when bad things happen to good people,
right? There's a big question of theodicy. Why do bad things happen to good people?
People say, well, why, you know, is God mad at me or whatever? But no, I mean, that's
probably not what's going on. There are spiritual forces at work. There are evil spiritual forces at
work, but we have to use them as an opportunity. Suffering is an opportunity, actually. It doesn't
doesn't mean we like.
suffering or seek it out, but it is an opportunity. It is absolutely an opportunity. So I just wanted
to kind of underline that as something that's really directly pertinent to all of us and not just
trying to understand, you know, demonology or whatever. St. Paul can stay of an unrepentant
sinner that he needs to be did over to Satan for the destruction of his body and the salvation of
the soul. Right? Yep.
Yep, I mean that means something.
You know, so.
All right, well, why don't we go to our second break
and we will be back in just a moment.
Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung
will be back in a moment to take your calls
on the second half of the Lord of Spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
That's 855.
A.F. Radio.
Guide to the Three Basic and Primary Disciplines of Orthodox Spirituality.
Through these disciplines, Christ opened for us a path that frees us from the disordered
way of life, who has become normal for many, even though their hearts and minds tell them
otherwise.
Please join me in exploring the Three Legged Stool of Orthodox Spiritual Practice, Prayer,
Fasting Nomsgiving.
Books now available at store.ancientfaith.com.
And the title once again is Toolkit for Spiritual Growth.
I look forward to sharing it with you.
Bless.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits, the Father Andrew Stephen Daymak and Father
Stephen DeYoung.
If you have a question, call now at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF Radio.
Welcome to the third half of our show.
Like you heard the voice of Steve right now.
right there. You can reach us at A55 AF radio. It's A552372346. And before we get to what
we're the last two falls or apostacies of angelic beings, I just wanted to let you guys know
that, you know, normally, of course, we are on the second and fourth Thursdays of the
month at seven o'clock Eastern, four o'clock Pacific. So you're hearing us tonight and
Here's again in two weeks on the 22nd of October, but we have a special
bonus episode on October 29th, it is our Halloween special.
So, you know, tune in for that.
You're gonna find it really fascinating.
It's titled The Real Demons of Halloween.
As you know, we talk about demons a lot,
but we are doing a special bonus episode
on October 29th for Halloween.
I'm not gonna, you know, give too many spoilers for that,
but just wanted to make sure you put that on your calendars
This is a little bit outside.
of our normal schedule. So, all right. So, let's move on to our next apostasy or fall of demons.
And this has to do with one of my favorite accounts in the Old Testament. And that is the Tower of Babel.
Right the Tower of Babel which you know, it's one of the most wonderfully depicted things
I think in Christian art you see these massive massive towers
and it's depicted in lots of different ways.
Like sometimes you get something that looks kind of like
the leaning tariff, pizza, other times, you see something
that looks more like a pyramid.
So what's going on in this one?
Right.
Well, this one also, we have again, a pagan narrative,
right?
A narrative of the other nation has been corrected
by Genesis chapter 11.
And I won't read these, but...
if you really want to nerd out, it's in the public domain online. And that's Plato actually
gives an account of this in two places. In the critis, it's going to be through D and in his
on the laws 7th, 13th, C through E. Okay. And what played out just because what he calls the A
of Cronus, which is this earlier age when Cronus was the most high god and of
course his son Zeus was over the council of gods before things went badly
between them. And in this time Cronus apportioned the world and the cities of
the world to the various gods who are members of
the Council of Gods. Okay. Assigned them to their faces. And Plato says that at first,
they guided them like good and faithful shepherds. And then things changed. Started to demand
sacrifice and appease. And this is not just a Greek thing. Greece was sort of the last
ancient Near Eastern civilization. We're used to thinking of them as the first Western
civilization but in
reality that the last station in Eastern Poland.
And this is paralleled everywhere, where
L. Bale's father appointed the 70 sons of L
to rule over the 70 nations.
This is a commonplace.
And even sociologists will talk about this
and anthropologists of religion.
there's this period of time after the end of the
the Neolithic era where the idea of a most high God becomes very distant. And there are
these sort of lesser gods who then become the object of worship and magic and ritual
and all of these things. This is observable all over the world really. And so it's this
story of this narrative that
that the story of the tower of Bable
is really intended to correct.
And this is another one where we have sort of a just so story
attached to it where we think the problem was
that these ancient humans were so dumb
that they thought if they built a tall enough tower,
they could get to where God was in heaven.
Yeah.
And the biggest problem with that is that God
that comes down and stops them.
So that makes it sound like maybe they could have.
Right.
I think like you've got that stuff, they would have actually built one that tall, which
of course is kind of silly, right?
But the reality is that the tower we're talking about, which was a ziggurat, like a pyramid,
was a man-made mountain.
Right.
You were crafting the mountain of God yourself.
And...
the name Bable of course is related to Babylon, but it's the name for the city and the name
Bable comes from Babili in Babylonian, which means the gate of the gods. Oh interesting.
And this wasn't the gate for humans to get to the gods. This was the gate through which the
God's came. Oh man. That's so the idea was. Wow. Yes. Yeah.
I was just saying, I suddenly think about that movie Stargate.
Yeah, home, man.
Yeah, what you build the gate is an aliens.
Yeah, not aliens.
Not aliens.
I'm not saying it was aliens, but it was demons.
This is not the history of people.
the idea is
that you would build this map when a gate that would bring the God down to dwell on your artificial mountain.
And so once you had him there dwelling particularly in the idol,
or responsible to care for him, but that also gave you the leverage to manipulate him and get him to do what you wanted.
Yeah, right, which is the whole point of idolatry.
Right
And we see, they of course say that they want to ascend to heaven, but what does
St. Paul say? He says, do not ask who will listen. That is to bring God down.
Yeah. Yeah. So he glosses this idea of ascending to heaven as actually attempting to kind of trap
God via idolatry.
Right, the human level.
Yeah.
and this was Yahweh, the most
high God, the true God, the creator of the
faith. And it's not something
would have succeeded. It's just
this is really wicked.
Yeah, this is the worst.
This is a massive rebellion, right?
To attempt to try to control him.
And so what we see is that God says
let us, he speaks to, and says,
and says, let us go.
He says, you want me to come down on, come down.
Right.
And when he comes down, he confuses the languages.
He separates out the nations.
And they go there, they go there, from that one place.
Right.
But this story is returned to in the book of Deuteronomy,
and do it.
on me chapter 32 comes back to this story of the Tower of Babel. And so probably the most
famous place is Duturotomy 32 verse 8, which when the most high gave to the nations their
inheritance when he divided humanity, he fixed the borders of the peoples according to
the number of the sons of God. Yeah, that's an interesting phrase.
Yeah, and that phrase will be different depending on what English translation you're looking at.
Yeah, right.
Because the, what's called the Maseretic text, the Medieval Hebrew text that's the basis
for like the King James version and most English Bibles has sons of Israel there.
Yeah.
Like in the King James, this is children of Israel.
Right.
which sort of makes no sense, because it's a private crime.
Israel. Yeah, because this is this is the nations. Yeah, right. There's 70 nations, right?
And there happened to be 70 sons of L and the divine counsel in the ancient world. Now
the Greek tradition understood with this man because it says when he did it he did it
according to the number of his angels. Right. So they had the idea that the sons of
They disambiguated it. But the sons of God.
God here wasn't talking about people, it was talking about angelic beings.
And when we recovered the Dead Sea Scrolls in the 1960s,
the Deuteronomy Scrolls among the Dead Sea Scrolls, which are of course a thousand years older,
than our previous Hebrew texts, they have sons of God,
and was revealed to be correct.
And that had been kind of covered over by later rabbinic Judaism that was less comfortable
with the phrase.
And so there is a certain school within our more liberal testament studies that wants to see this not as a variation on the ancient story but as the ancient story.
Okay. So they want to say that this is just taking the bail version of the story
and they want to interpret it as saying, well, Israel
believed that Yahweh, the God of Israel, was just the one who was given Israel.
Like he was a lesser member of the council, they must have had some version of the succession.
Yeah, right.
No record of, of course.
But they hypothesized.
Yeah.
The key to understanding that this is not true is if you flip back a little bit to Deuteronomy chapter 4.
Okay, versus 19 and 20.
Great.
Which I have in front of me here.
Okay.
Why don't you go ahead and read it then.
Yeah, yeah.
Okay.
Deuteronomy 4, 19 and 20.
And less thou lift up thine eyes into heaven.
And when thou seeest the sun and the moon and the stars,
even all the host of heaven,
should be driven to worship them and serve them.
Which the Lord thy God have divided unto all nations
under the whole heaven.
But the Lord have taken you and brought you forth
out of the iron furnace, even out of Egypt,
of Egypt.
to be into him a people of inheritance as he are this day.
Right. So we see here very clearly, right, that it's it's
Yahweh the God of Israel who allotted the host of heaven to
the nations, right. And it's also Yahweh the God of Israel who
took Israel for himself. Yes, he's not assigned by someone else.
Right. So that's just within the pages of Deuteronomy, that
ideas refuted. But the idea stands.
that this was done by Yahweh, the Most High God in terms of the nations. So this is a punishment.
This is a punishment in that it's not that the Most High God who was crowned as the other gods,
these other places. And so it was right for them to worship them. This was because they tried to
drag him down.
to the human level and manipulate him, a response and punishment by stepping back away from humanity.
Withdrawing from humanity.
Right.
Which actually is a merciful act, right? Because to be sinful and be in the presence of God
is to have that sin burned, or you know, as you actually had a recent blog post called
death by holiness.
Right.
which is this exact comment-suppt. And so God is stepping back from humanity to give
him a chance to repent, to reform. Because if he stays in contact with them, if he does
come down and stays with them, that's going to be bad because they're sinful. And so
he allots them to these angelic beings. So how does that constitute an apostasy or a
fall on the part of the sons of God, these angels.
Right, well, it's important to emphasize what you just said that the purpose was both to
protect them and the idea was that these angelic beings would serve the same way as the angelic
beings who we talked about who and the moon and the things of nature and the other things
of the creation, they're just assigned to these nations. And St. Paul says, and
17 when St Paul's speaking to pagans, this is what he talks about the most high God who
assigned everyone their place of life and their time of living, right? And that he did
all this so that they would seek after him. So the intent was not that he didn't want
any of the nations except for Israel, but that they were put away for their own good with
the attempt that they would return, that they would come and return to him.
But what happens is described in Deuteronomy 32 the same chapter in verse 17 and
That's
There are different English translations, but a lot of them obscure what's going on here
So they they it's usually translated they sacrifice to demons that were not gods to gods. They had never known
Yeah, to new gods that had come recently whom your father said never dreaded now
because it's contradictory. They sacrificed demons that weren't gods to gods they had never
known. So what are the gods are not? In the King James, it renders it, they sacrificed unto
devils not to God, to gods whom they knew not to knew God. So that's consistent.
That's better, right? Because it says Elohim, right? So the God part is right.
The work for demons here though is also interesting because it's a word that occurs nowhere else in
is the Bible.
It's the word Shedu.
It doesn't occur anywhere else in the Bible,
because it's not actually a Hebrew ending on it.
But Shedu is a Babylonian word.
And Shedu in Babylonian religion was the use of territory.
A territorial spirit.
Yeah.
So this is really saying they said
the territorial spirits, the spirits assigned to that piece of territory to their land.
Not forgot to the most high God.
Right.
And so the apostasy then on the part of these beings is that they receive that worship,
that they say that's a yeah, we'll take that.
Whereas, you know, if you meet an angel of God and you see man, you know, you see a person
attempt about down then like no hey whoa whoa no no get up
Yeah, exactly. We do not do this. And clearly human beings are tempted to do that.
You see a divine being. You're like, oh, better worship. And that's one of the reasons
that the fathers, especially some of the monastic fathers, they basically say that the good
default thing to do, if you see some kind of divine being, is to make the sign of the cross,
I'm trying to get out because an angel will be cool with that.
And if it's a demon, well, that's what you should be doing.
Don't do the thing that you're tempted to do,
just to fall down before them.
You know?
Right.
Yeah.
And so then these fear the demons that St. Paul talks about,
when he talks about demons,
what he says with the nation's sacrifice,
they sacrifice to demons.
When he talks about powers and principalities
that's these things.
Yeah, yeah.
All right. Well, any did you want to say anything else before we take another call on this particular
Apostasy that's four out of five that's four out of five. We're almost done. Okay. Well, we have a call and
This I think is coming from someone whom I know in fact, so we have
Mehigh calling in and me high are you in North Carolina?
Yes, Father Andrew.
I mean, not all in all Carolina.
And you definitely know me.
So, well, it is great to hear from you
and to hear your voice, folks,
this is my wife's Godfather.
So I am really glad to hear from you,
me, Hayat's been a long time.
So what is your comment to your question for us this evening?
Okay, so my question is very simple.
If the evil spirits could interact directly
with the physical world,
there are, of course, they could interact
with humanity, the other...
They could influence people, but there are some indications they could also interact directly
for the evil spirit to speak with evil. He must have created acoustic waves or maybe the
pigs that went over the cliff when the devils went into them. So if that is so, in what measure
and could be safe for instance that disease or...
or something like that,
because it's produced by an evil spirit.
That's very much my question.
All right. Well, that's a good question.
So, Father Steven,
I have some ideas about that.
But Father, why don't you comment on that first?
Well, we have biblical examples of them doing that.
So, for example,
if Job, who we're going to talk about some more here in a minute,
Of course, anything that
it's going to do, they're only doing within God permitting them to do it. But they're
permitted to, the demonic attack on Job includes the collapse of a building on top of his family.
Right. And it includes him getting boils, right. And disease. And it includes these things.
So that seems to make it clear that, yes, that can happen. And of course, there are plenty
of stories in our tradition into the lives of...
saints of of demonic spirits interacting the demon and Tobit kills several people
and and so again within God's restraining there are examples of that that happening.
Yeah and and even stuff that might be a little more subtle to us you know we talked about demons
being involved with plague and certainly in the apocalypse, not to steal some of Earth.
thunder for maybe a later episode everybody, but the Four Horsemen of the Apocalypse definitely
release very physical experiences upon mankind, you know, pestilence and war and death, you know,
and so yeah, there is this direct interaction and certainly people experience these things
sometimes in their own homes, right?
Things being thrown around or shoved.
You're the customer.
that makes it into horror films, I mean that's not unreal, those things are real. Now that doesn't
mean that every single bumpy here in your house is a demon that's you know closing a drawer or something
like that, but it is it is a thing for sure. They can interact directly with the material world.
So does that answer your question, Mihai? Yes, thank you very much. You just mentioned some new
examples and that makes it more clear. Thank you.
God. Well again, good to hear from you and I hope I see you again soon. All right, so we've got one
one more fall or apostasy of demonic beings to discuss today. And this is one that probably
a lot of us know about because I think it's it is mentioned in scripture by Christ himself, right?
But but maybe we didn't think twice about it. I think that this is another event. So so
So, Father Stephen Tick.
us on into this one. This is the fifth and final fall of our five ish falls of angels. This is the
ish. This is the ish. All right, not to be confused with the Hebrew word ish, which is heves
original name, right? Exactly. Yes. So this depends the reason there's an ish. This depends on whether
the devil and Satan are the
same person.
Okay.
Right.
Which many of us may have taken for granted for much of our lives.
These are the same person.
And they may be the same person.
Okay.
Both second temple Jewish tradition and or the tradition.
They are not the same person.
Hmm.
And so...
In fact, this is alluded to by San Andrew of Cesarilla, who I've mentioned before, in terms
of understanding the fathers saw what we're about to talk about in this problem or an issue
at least that needed an explanation.
And there are two possible explanations.
So there's this figure who we encounter in the book of Job who is referred to
to in the book of Job as the Satan.
Okay, right.
The Satan.
And the the is important because in some languages like Greek,
you can put a definite article before someone.
We usually don't do that in English, the finder, Steven,
But in Hebrew you also
has Ha, which is the definite article in Hebrew in front of a name. So that means it's a title.
Right. Okay. The person in Job is not named Satan in the book of Job. He is the Satan.
Okay. And so what? Yeah, the adversary or the enemy, the enemy or the opponent.
Yeah.
comes into the divine council and presents this case against Job.
And this figure, people have probably in Jewish, even later,
rabbinic Jewish tradition, they don't see the Satan as necessarily an evil or part of the
upon diabolical figure necessarily.
Yeah.
He's so classic.
executing attorney for city points,
the SIDS, right?
And so there is already, yeah, it's
a tradition.
So in the tradition between 500 BC and, you know,
the writing of the New Testament in that, in that Judaism,
there's sometimes he's given an angelic form of the name,
like Satana L or Sama L.
Sometimes considered one of the
seven archangels. The geologist had seven before his fall. And so you have this figure. It's
usually seen as being in contest with Saint Michael the Archangel. That Saint Michael
the Archangel is sort of defending Israel and the righteous of God. And satanael is accusing,
or SAMHL is accusing.
the the righteous of God. Right. And this sort of continual back and forth. And of course, St.
Michael has said to have been the archangel of or the guardian angel of Jacob. And Sam
L was the guardian angel of Esau, right? And so this contest has sort of been going on for a long
time. Sam L, his name means means the venom of God or the poison of God. And he's usually identified
as like the angel of death of the past.
over the one who brings the plague in response to sin. And so you can see how that dynamics
plays out. And that dynamic is referred to by St. Jude in Jude. My Satan can test go
over the body of Moses. Yeah. And that's that's a play on this demand dynamic. So you can
easily see how someone can
there.
Okay, well this is
basically another name for the devil, right? Like this, this is the same person. Right? Right.
What causes the issue is largely Luke 10 versus 17 through 20. Okay.
Of you. Yeah. Yeah. I'm going to pull it up here right now. So Luke 10 versus 17 through 20.
And so and the 70 returned against the
70 apostles that Christ had out. The 70 returned again with joy, saying,
Lord, even the devils are subject unto us through thy name. And he said unto them,
I beheld Satan as lightning fall from heaven. Behold, I give unto you power to tread on
serpents and scorpions and over all the power of the enemy, and nothing shall by any means hurt you.
Notwithstanding in this rejoice not that the spirits are subject unto you, but rather rejoice because
your names are written in heaven.
So I saw or as I haven't heard it, I saw Satan fall like lightning.
Yeah. Right. So so it's very clear from the thing has changed here during the Ministry of Christ.
Yeah.
Something has happened.
These are the V Satan.
Right.
That he's he's lost or well, he's no longer given access to divine council or something has happened here.
Just say.
Right.
And we find the same thing in revelance one through nine, where we read.
about Satan being cast down after Christ's birth.
Christ's birth is described.
And then the fall of Satan.
And so.
Right.
You kind of broke all the files.
You kind of broke up there a little bit.
But I think that like a really important point to make here is,
you know, like I remember reading that,
I saw Satan fall like lightning and my first
thought when I recall from when I was a kid is thinking, okay, he's talking about things
that he saw before the creation of the world.
But like you said in Revelation, it talks about this fall that happens after the birth
of Christ.
So it's something current when he's speaking.
And Christ says that because of that, he's giving them this authority over demons.
Right.
Yeah.
And so...
When St Andrew looks at this, he says,
well, wait a second, the fathers
all say that after the creation
of the world, the devil fell through envy.
But now we have this fall in the ministry of Christ.
And if you read Revelation 12, verse 9 in Greek,
it says, you know, the dragon who is the devil
and Satan are cast out or is cast out.
So is it the dragon who is both
the devil and Satan, or is it the dragon who is the devil, one guy and Satan who's this other guy?
It's ambiguous. Yeah. And so the question is, are these two different figures who both fall,
or is this one figure, one person who falls two different times in two different ways?
And St Andrew thinks it's one figure who falls in two different ways.
But there are other places, for example, some of the icons of theophony.
will show instead of the little river gods, they will show, they'll show what looks like a man with wings, like an arch, like a fallen angel down there, and then a dragon.
Oh yeah, I've seen it.
Beings.
Yeah.
Right.
So, there are these elements of tradition where these are separate demonic powers and there
are elements of tradition where they're put together.
into one. Right. And it's not uncommon for all about tonight to be kind of mixed and matched in different texts.
That's part of the order chaos. Right. We shouldn't be surprised that, you know, as you said, lying spirits should be hard to pin down, you know, that they're going to fool us.
You know they're there they're there's
spiritual beings, they have great powers, abilities, they're extremely experienced with
tempting mankind. They're going to appear in the way that makes sense to them to attempt
to tempt us. They're going to function in a way that tries to bring us into their rebellion.
They're not going to come up show up and say, and here's my demonic ID. Here's my picture
on it. It's just a third class.
Right. And which is an interesting contrast to the way that that
A lot of people kind of want to, they want to have this all sorted out.
Right?
And there are whole like spiritual systems, religious systems that lay all these things
out and they try to codify them and so forth.
But they're just not, and this is, these traditions that we have are people who are encountering
these beings and trying to make sense of what it is that they're actually experiencing.
Like this is not speculation.
Right?
Now, this is actual direct experience of human beings
over time saying, I saw this, I encountered this,
this happened.
You know, these are these are these are demonic spirits.
These are different ways in which demonic spirits
are encountered.
I also pay an idolatrous worship in temptation
to commit evil through knowledge that they're not prepared
for through an attempt to displace God
You
their heart and mind and soul. These are all actual experiences that we have human beings
since the beginning of human beings have of spirits of evil who are bent on the destruction
of humanity.
Yeah. Yeah. All right. Well, having said that, we're going to wrap up for tonight. But
before we do that, I just wanted to give you a little bit of preview of what we're going
we talk about next time so two weeks from today on the
22nd of October. We're going to be talking about exactly the opposite of what we've been discussing
this evening. And we'll be talking about the sons of God, what it means to what that title means,
what it means to become sons of God, human beings, become sons of God. And of course,
that word that every Orthodox Christian probably should know, which is theoses. So you may wonder
exactly what all that has to do with all these things we've been discussing. So tune in again,
To
weeks from tonight for that. Father Stephen, did you have any final comments you wanted to make before we wrap up tonight?
Um, just that, um, in relation to our second call, and this is important as a theme, we're going to come back to again and again and again.
The chain of cause and effect moves back and forth between the material and spiritual worlds. They're not separate, there's not a divider, there's not a partition.
But
everything moves back and forth because it is all one creation in one world that includes demons,
demigods and staplers. And staplers. All right, well, don't forget on the 29th of October, we have a
bonus Halloween special episode. So that is our show for today. Thank you very much everyone for
listening if you did not get a chance to call in during the live broadcast.
We would love to hear from you either via email at Lordofspiritsatinchinfaith.com.
You can contact us through the chat room which we had going tonight.
You can also message us at our Lordofspirits podcast Facebook page.
And there is also, by the way, a Facebook group called the Divine Council.
We read everything. We do. We really read everything.
But we can't respond to everything. And we do save what you send for possible use in future episodes.
and join us for our live broadcast on the second and fourth Thursdays of the month at 7pm Eastern 4pm Pacific.
Don't forget to like our Lord of the Spirit podcast Facebook page while you're at it and join the aforementioned group.
Leave a recommendation and then invite your friends.
And if you leave a review on Apple Podcasts on Facebook or wherever you get your podcasts and that raises the visibility of the show and gets more people connected.
And finally be sure to go to the ancient faith.
Thank you, and God bless you.
And I be held and I heard the voice of many angels round about the throne.
And the number of them was 10,000 times 10,000 than thousands of thousands,
saying with a loud voice, worthy is the land that was slain to receive power and riches.
and wisdom, and strength, and honor, and glory, and blessing.
Revelation chapter 5 verses 11 through 12.