He will be a staff for the righteous with which for them to stand and not to fall,
and he will be the light of the nations and the hope of those whose hearts are troubled.
All who dwell on the earth will fall down and worship him,
and they will praise and bless and celebrate with song the Lord of Spirits,
1st denoc, chapter 48, verses 4-5.
The modern world doesn't acknowledge but is nevertheless haunted by spirits,
Angels, demons and saints in our
time many year into break free of the prison of a flat secular materialism to see and to
know reality as it truly is.
What is this spiritual reality like?
How do we engage with it well?
How do we permeate everyday life with spiritual presence?
Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen De Young
post this live Colin show, focused on enchantment in creation.
union of the scene and unseen as made by God.
and experienced by mankind throughout history.
Welcome to the Lord of Spirits.
[♪ Music playing in background,
And normally you would be listening to us live, but
This is actually not being played live and the reason is that father Stephen had funeral services that he needs to attend to.
So if you're listening to this at the normal time, he's doing a funeral right now.
And I might be listening in. I don't know.
But anyway, instead of canceling the episode or moving it or whatever, we decided to pre-record.
So this is a pre-recorded episode.
And even though you will hear the voice of Steve suggesting you call in,
And if you call in, you will not get us in this particular particular
time. Alright, well, this is actually the second part of a two part series on bodies. And so
instead of my usual introductory comments, we're going to do a little recap of our last episode,
just very briefly, and also try to clear up a couple of misconceptions and some questions that we
got about the body of God. And so to begin that, I just want to play a message that we got from Kyle,
and he had a really interesting question.
So...
Let's go ahead and play that.
Father's bless.
In the last episode, you spoke about anthropomorphizing God
and how we can interpret the Bible to be a theoromorphizing
of humans.
The Bible has God showing emotions like anger and wrath.
How are we to interpret that in light of a theoromorphizing
of humans?
Thank you for taking my question.
Alright, well, this obviously connects directly to...
what we were talking about.
And we, I noticed, for instance, in our Facebook group,
hey, everybody join the Facebook group.
That there were some issues with this.
Like, so for instance, one person sent a message saying,
aren't you basically, if you're saying that God has a body,
aren't you just basically saying that God is just
a very big version of us, you know, right?
And I think that what Kyle asked here
is kind of connected to that, not that he's saying that,
but he's trying to mix...
sense of the Bible, for instance, saying that God has emotions. Right? And we made the point
last time about theomorphism versus anthropomorphism. So, Father Stephen, why don't you give a little recap
as exactly what that means and why we are absolutely not saying in any particular, in any way at all,
that the body of God is basically a kind of...
Really big and powerful version of the bodies of human beings.
Yes.
Last time on Lord of Spirits.
Right.
Now we insert a shot of a guy turning a car key and then a long shot of a car exploding or something.
Um, but so, um, nothing really exploded, but we did have these questions.
Yes.
Right.
they're like that exactly exactly what we're talking about.
And so we talked about how and and tried to reiterate that when we're talking about a body in general
from the ancient understanding, the ancient understanding of body
that we're not per se talking about a material object in the world, right? We're talking about
a nexus of powers.
and or potentialities, we'll get into that and or a little more as we go on in this episode.
But we're talking about that.
And so that in some bodies and human bodies and animal bodies, that has a material form.
If we're talking about angels and demons as we're going to, as we always do, but as we're going to later on in this episode,
We're talking
about bodies which are immaterial compared to ours,
but are still created.
Right?
And if we're talking about God's body,
there's zero material aspect to it.
We're talking about his powers.
And I think to directly get to Kyle's question,
first, one of the points we were trying to make
is that when we were criticizing the idea
of anthropomorphism.
in favor of theomorphism is that for example when the scriptures talk about God's face,
someone says they want to see God's face, he doesn't say, don't be silly, I'm not a big human,
I don't have a face. He says you can't see my face and live, if you see my face you'll die
implying he has one, but that's understood within the definition of body that we're talking about
out here in the ink.
world. So it's not a material face. Right. And and and face is this sort of
communication power. Right. Right. And we have communication. Yeah. We know we use the word face.
And it includes what you know what we normally think of as a face like something you could put
makeup on or something. You know, right. But that and when we use that word to refer to God,
that we're not saying that God's face is like our face.
But we're saying that he,
And in fact, in the full way has the ability to communicate and to interface.
There we go, interface, what a great word with human beings with angels, so forth.
So it's interesting.
And I think it's tough because the scriptures do use what we would conceive of as anthropomorphic words.
Right, but that doesn't mean that
you know, for instance, when they say the hand of, you know, the hand of the Lord was upon him or something like that, right?
That there's this gigantic hand that comes out of heaven, you know, with five fingers on it.
It's, it's rather about God connecting with and acting in.
So there is anthropomorphic language, but that's not what's really meant when that language is used.
If that's right.
Am I getting that right?
Yeah.
The idea is we're not attributing this
human quality of having a physical arm to God.
Right?
We're referring to when we talk about God's right arm,
we're talking about his power and might.
Right.
And our human right arm, if we're right handed at least,
which most people were and are,
unless you're a Benjamin.
Your right arm is your strong arm.
It's the arm you used to do things
that require strength index.
So our right arm is sort of a devalued, low grade shadow of our strength is this low grade devalued shadowy version of God's strength.
Yeah, and and and and and we're gonna talk and saying we're gonna talk about this a lot more but but that our strength
Includes a fleshly arm with an elbow and fingers and a wrist and right that's the instrument that we use to
exercise our physical strength. But so when we talk about God's right arm, we're
not just imagining God having an arm. Right? We're referring to something real,
his power, his might. Right? And so the same thing is true when we use this
emotional language for God. Right? We're not saying that God is sort of passive,
you know, and flies into a fit of rage or gets really sad or right.
Bye.
We're not saying he's subject to human emotions, but at the same time those things that we refer to like when we talk about God's wrath
That's referring to something real. Yeah, that's referring to a real
Experience of God that we don't want to have
So it's not just this this oh well these primitive people they thought of God as a giant human and talked about him getting angry
but we know that silly.
Yeah, and so that we just sort of abandoned that right?
No, that was language that was used to point to a reality and me we might choose to point to that reality with different language now
Right, right and and and that is a normal thing that happens
Right in the the the history of the scriptures where you see language change and scripture
You know the most obvious example is the Old Testament most of it and it's original right
original
writings there I go, but you know what I mean?
Is in Hebrew, but then the New Testament is all in Greek
and Greek is not one to one and equivalent to Hebrew. I mean in so many ways
right? No, no two languages are one to one equivalents to each other. Yeah, they can't be even ones even languages that are closely related.
Hebrew and Aramaic aren't one to one. There are words that mean different things in Hebrew and Aramaic. Sometimes subtly, sometimes in a big way.
Yeah, and
And this process of, I mean, this is one of the things that I study a lot, just, you know,
even outside of my, I don't know, is there anything outside of religious theological
pastoral study for me?
I don't know.
But even what might be explicitly kind of that religious stuff is something that's really
interesting to me.
And because no language functions one to one, not just in terms of vocabulary, but in terms
of grammar and the way that the words relate to each other.
That means that we can't get fixated on particular vocabulary terms.
Right? And I'll give a really quick example.
So the seventh ecumenical counsel makes a distinction between two Greek words,
Latria and proskinesis.
And Latria is generally translated in English as worship,
or sometimes you get adoration.
And proskinesis is translated generally in English as veneration.
and that worship belongs only to God and veneration can be given to His
saints into holy objects and so forth. But proskeenacies is used in scripture to refer to worship in God.
Does that mean that the seventh-economic council fathers are pulling a fast one? No, it just means they're using particular words and giving them a technical meaning.
But the truth is that it's not like once that was decided that you can only use those words in those particular ways ever after.
For instance, at the beginning of most of our services,
you get
And you get, oh, come let us worship and fall down before God or king.
Let's set a lot.
Well, in Greek, that's Vephte Proskini-Somen.
They're using Proskini-Sys.
And yet we don't understand it as, oh, come let us venerate God.
It's, let's worship God, right?
So even though this very technical kind of definition was given at the 7th Emanicle Council
to those two words.
don't
It's not like we sat down and revised the scripture based on that or or that we're not allowed to use that earlier meaning or whatever
Context is so so so so important and so you know when when you hear us use particular words
Don't get hung up on the particular word like if you say if we say that God has a body
We don't we do not mean that God has a body in the same way that we have bodies
Right, but but rather that there is this ancient sense
of what a body is
which includes what we think of as bodies,
but is not limited to it.
So yeah, we're not trying to create
a theological dictionary here, you know?
That's not our task at all.
And both of us like Battlestar Galactica,
but we're not Mormons.
Yes, right exactly.
So, yes, yes.
And I love JR Tolkien without being a Roman Catholic.
Yeah.
So yeah, this is important,
a lot of the questions we got.
We're related to well how does this ancient use of the term body relate to
XYZ
Later Greek theological terms like how does this relate to the essence and energies distinction? How does this relate to
nature the term nature feces, right?
How does this relate to hepostosis or person, right?
and
There's a problem there in approach that we need to address.
We've kind of addressed a version of this before, but we need to make it plain.
Those terms used as technical terms the way Orthodox, theologians used them today.
came into existence over the course of the first eight centuries of the church.
Right? They were refined.
by the fathers and refined at the councils using that terminology,
since they were speaking Greek, using that Greek terminology to describe the Holy Trinity,
to describe Christ, to describe these other spiritual realities. And those terms are all good,
and all valid, and all important in terms of Al-Ghosephars, say those are the best way to describe
those realities.
in the Greek language. But the Old Testament in Hebrew and Aramaic and even Greek translation
doesn't use those terms the same way. Neither does the New Testament. And so we have a whole
bunch of people, 19th century German theologians in their ilk, who based on that fact say,
Oh well, the whole idea of the Holy Trinity.
the whole idea of calcedonian Christology,
the whole idea of Christ having two wills developed later.
Yeah, that those ideas, those understandings,
those realities don't pre-exist the language,
the Greek language that was used for them
these later centuries.
So part of what we're doing last episode
and on this show in general
And that I'm always trying to do and stuff out.
this show is show the continuity between you know late Bronze Age Israelites and
eight-century church fathers. Yeah and they're they're pointing at the same
reality. They're coming to know the same God, right? And so the idea of the
Holy Trinity, the idea of Christology, these all pre-exist that that later Greek
language by centuries if not millennia.
Yeah, and so when we're talking about, for example, how body was used in the ancient world
and how it's used in the Old Testament, right, we're talking about here's the terminology
that's used in Scripture to describe these realities.
So that once you understand the terminology Scripture uses, hopefully that'll help you
make those connections, right?
So this that you know, St. Maximus is saying about the will, right?
really the same thing that the solmest is here saying in Hebrew. Right. He's just using
different terms. Right. But they're talking about the same reality. Yeah. And then there's
the issue of reading English translations of both of those texts. Right. Which again are not,
you know, Greek and Hebrew are not one to one and English is not one to with one with either
Greek or Hebrew. It probably has more in common with Greek because there's there both
Indo-European languages.
But still, you know, just because you've read something in translation doesn't mean that
you really, truly got what it is.
Or even maybe you understand that language, maybe you took classes and you understand Hebrew,
that doesn't necessarily mean still that you are automatically going to read it well, you
know.
And this might seem like a big digression, everybody.
But I think it's a really important point.
And because for this particular...
program, the kind of expertise that, you know, in particular,
Father Stephen brings to the table is biblical expertise.
It's going to the way that it gets talked about is going to be
different than someone like, for instance, if we had a
patristic scholar, right?
Now, we're both interacting with the fathers and informed by
the fathers and, you know, the church services, and we're bringing
in as well. But it's not going to be I
in terms of the language, you know, and context is super, super, super important. Right? There are ways,
for instance, I became aware that someone was unhappy that I used the phrase, there is one energy. Well,
you know, referring to God, the context of that makes a big difference, because you can see
the patristic language, one energy language and plurality of energy.
Jesus language, depending on context.
And even that's all just within Greek.
So you can't just pick out a particular phrase and say,
look, gotcha, you're seeing it wrong, whatever.
Right?
And also, it's possible.
I will admit, I'm wrong about things.
And God willing, I'm getting better.
It's OK, right?
It's OK.
I'm happy to be corrected.
And that's a lot of what we're doing here.
So yeah.
Like I said, it seems like a big digression, but I think it's really important, especially because
particularly the last episode got into a lot of stuff that a lot of us have never really thought much about or read much about.
Including me, especially me. So, you know, hang in there everybody. It's going to be okay.
So, all right, well let's continue talking about this question of
a body as being a nexus of powers or potentialities.
you know and so last time we talked about
the body of God, now we're going to begin talking about human bodies. So take us in, Father
Stephen. Right. So less controversially than saying God has one, humans have bodies. Yes,
that should be a surprise to know of. Yes. But it's important that we're still using
that same definition of body for our purposes, right? In the sense that we're not just
talking
about the material body, but we're talking about body in terms of this nexus of powers
and potentialities. And it's really when we start talking about created bodies that the
idea of potentialities enters in. This is another place where we got some questions that
indicated there was some confusion, which means we didn't clarify it enough. And so the
The reason we were talking about powers and potentialities is...
that we were talking about bodies in general.
And if we're talking about this ancient understanding
as applied to God,
so if we're talking about God's body
understood in this ancient sense,
we're just talking about powers.
Yeah, he doesn't, God doesn't grow.
For a meal.
Yeah, and he isn't acted upon,
all of that is true, right?
So we're talking about powers with him.
When we start talking about created bodies though,
There are
created powers, right? But there's also then potentialities because created
things are acted upon, right? And in some cases do change, and etc. etc.
So when humans are created, and this is going to be a little bit of recap too,
because I know we talked about this in a previous episode, but we talked about
how the act of creation as
it's portrayed in Genesis 1 and 2 is in Genesis 1 it's God acting to first in the first
three days of creation set the creation in order so it's moving from chaos to order and
then the second set of three days the fourth, fifth and sixth days that correspond directly
to the previous days, it's filling those spaces he created with life.
Right.
then human beings are created to continue that work, right, for to go out from paradise
the garden that God planted and to set the world in order and fill it with life. And we get
in Genesis 2, the particular story of Adam being pulled apart into Adam and Eve.
And Eve being created in particular, woman being created in particular for this function
of filling the world with life.
And Adam in naming the animals being the one who sets things in order.
So.
But, and even as I say that, I want to also make the point, right, that this isn't saying,
Whoa
Women just feel the world of the live and men just that things that are obviously the whole context of the two being one flesh is that both are participating in the other.
Right. Right.
It's very clear, for example, that while women give birth to children, men participate in the making of children. Right.
Yep. So there's a mutuality there as well.
And so the reason we talked about
about this as in the context of potentialities rather than just powers is that the work that
Adam and Eve are created to do is still God's work.
Right?
They're still, they're continuing God's work.
God is working in and through them to accomplish this.
So for them, it's a potentiality because they're participating in God.
exercising of his powers, right? His works. Right. Right. It's not... They can't be, you know,
to use the philosophical language fully actualized in that because it's God and they're just human beings.
You know, even in this unfallen state, right? Right. Right. They are participating in God's ongoing
work of creation. They're not creating
additional things independently apart from God.
To use one of my beloved Tocinian terms, they are being sub-creators.
They can't make things come into being, but they can take God's existing creation
and reorder it, give it a higher level of order.
But again, as you said, they're not functioning independently.
they're being like God, they're participating in God,
they're doing his work.
Right, to continue the example, when Eve gives birth to her first child, she says,
I have received a son from Yahweh.
Yeah.
Obviously, she and Adam were involved in making the child and biological processes and and and,
but she correctly sees that this new life has come into the world from God.
Yeah.
Even though it turns out to be king.
Right.
Uh...
So that said, and we've already alluded to this, this means we have to shift our paradigm
a little bit in terms of how we understand Eden and how we understand humanity, given
that most of us have grown up in a Western context.
Yeah.
Where my least favorite person to pick on, St. Augustine, because he gets picked on too much.
has kind of influenced our vision and our understanding of these things.
In the way in which he's kind of, well, I'll be fair to him.
We will inevitably be doing a show where we talk about the fact that there are three
falls of humanity. I think we already alluded to that in the fall of the Angels episode.
And what you find in the early fathers is that
They will not deny any of the three.
They'll refer to all three, but they will tend to focus on one event in Genesis 1 through
11 as being the primary event where humanity fell or where sin took hold of humanity.
And so St. Augustine was very much within the mainstream of that in that he picked the
the expulsion from paradise as being the main event in Genesis 1 through 11.
11 and the other one sort of being subsidiary and kind of collapsed some of the elements
of the other two into that first one.
And the problem is he wrote in Latin and not a lot of other people did.
And so Western Christianity from the 5th century on became almost completely beholden to
St. Augustine. Yeah.
And so the more full-orbed understanding
didn't get fully handed down to his successors.
Right, and there's one of the big problems with this, and I mean, I'm not deeply read in
St. Augustine, but one of the big problems with this is that there's at least the way that people
have now kind of received this, is that Adam and Eve in the Garden of Eden, everything is
This is utterly perfect and then it all goes wrong.
that that's the image that most people have of what's happening there. And so not only
is there, as you said, there are these multiple events that occur that kind of constitute
the fall, but also there's the problem of seeing Adam and Eve as being utterly perfect
in an utterly perfect place, right? That neither one of those things is true. Now, the
problem with parsing that, of course, is that we tend to use the word perfect to mean
and sinless, right?
If I do something wrong, I can say,
well,
not perfect. But that's not what perfect means generally, for instance, when the church fathers
use whatever their equivalent term is, usually in Greek, but whatever language they might be writing in,
that in English, we do use this word perfect, I mean sinless, but we also have the sense of
something being perfected. In other words, that it's coming into its full flower, it's coming into
it's full polish, you know, like it's
It's becoming all that it can be, right?
And that's what Adam and Eve and even the world
don't actually have.
They're off to a good start, right?
The world is off to a good start,
but there is this,
it's not just an interruption,
it's also kind of an alteration, right?
And we're gonna talk about that, I know a lot more.
But I think, you know, it's interesting.
I've noticed
this that especially as English speakers appropriate this theology of Adam and Eve being
sinless but not perfect before this fall, less often you get this idea of the world actually
not yet being perfected, that it's kind of incomplete, it's not done yet, so to speak.
And yet these are intimately connected and Adam is the priest of this world, his task,
And he's the...
of this world, his task is to rule it with God's rule, to name it, to order it, you know,
all these things, of course, e-participates in that as well.
It's interesting.
I can't remember was it the last episode where we talked about the idea that Eden was supposed
to have been expanded, right?
I love that.
That's so, I don't know.
That's really, it's inspiring.
It's invigorating because this is our task as well.
Our task is to do the thing that add
failed at, you know, being in Christ. That's our task. But I don't know, maybe I'm getting ahead of
ourselves a little bit here. I'm just excited about these ideas. Well, yeah, and it's in the text,
if we read the text carefully in Genesis, right? God plants a garden in the east in Eden, right? So
that's not the whole world. That's a garden that he puts in a place. Right? And that's the place
where he's going to dwell with humanity. That's what makes it paradise.
And the word paradise in Greek is actually taken over from Persian and refers to a walled garden, right? So it's enclosed.
Which made me, made me really happy when I watched the Good Omen's adaptation on Amazon that they, when they showed Eden, it was walled in. But anyway.
And that's the way we sland outside.
But, well, you know, that's kind of the, isn't that the image that CS Lewis uses?
in the last battle that there's this walled garden as well that you further up and further
in. So there you go. There's one for all you and Arnie Elevers out there.
So and when Adam has created God goes and forms him from the duster ground forms him out
of this sort of chaotic prime matter that's out there and then places him in Eden. Places
him in Paradise. He gets created outside and then picked up and put there. And so there's
this outside area and
When the command is given to Adam and Eve to fill the earth and subdue it, which is that command, right?
The word subdue doesn't just mean put an order in a general sense, like, hey, put all your DVDs in alphabetical order, right?
Which I do because I'm OCD.
It's, it's the word subdue there is actually the word for like conquering a city.
Oh wow.
So it implies like opposition and
and contest and what our German friends call chaos comp, right?
The struggle against chaos, right?
So that's the picture.
So the picture is that the world outside Eden
isn't finished yet in the sense of what God is doing
in Genesis 1.
It's still empty and it's still filled with chaos.
And so Adam and Eve were to go out and expand
and Eden to fill the whole world,
and then, because of their trespass,
they're sent out instead.
But in the same way that the creation
as a whole isn't done, Adam and Eve aren't done.
That's perfect.
The Greek concept of telos, teleology, it's the final,
it's the end, it's the goal,
it's where you arrive at fullness and completion
and a wholeness purpose.
at the end of the growth and change process, right?
That's where you're at.
That's your final form and your power levels over 9,000.
Right?
And that's what it's aiming at.
And so the way Adam and Eve were going to go
from this innocence to this perfection,
to this completion was by participating with God
in bringing the rest of creation toward that perfection.
Yeah, yeah, and a
Crucial element of that a crucial element of that that we're going to talk about more toward the end of this episode is the incarnation of Christ
Which you as I say so you're saying that
the incarnation is not
Plan B
Right the incarnation
Sorry, and so of Canterbury
Thank you very much.
the reason why the God-man is not human sin. So the incarnation is a, of Christ, is a super
lapsarian reality. Yes. Shout out to all the Calvinists I just triggered. It over arches
the concept of the fall, because the
the participation we were just talking about between Adam and even God, right,
finds its fullness and its fulfillment when God becomes man. When God is
made man in the person of Jesus Christ and its Christ who was always going to
bring not just humanity but creation to its fullness, to its tellows, to its
and to its perfect.
through the incarnation. So this is a positive aspect of salvation. This is what we've been talking about
when we've talked about theosis in previous episodes of us becoming sons of God, right?
Christ is the unique son of God. So it's in his image, right? And it's through him that we become
sons of God in that positive sense, right? Which Adam hadn't yet achieved. He was a good person.
Yeah, so salvation isn't...
not just about the forgiveness of sins and the removal of death and the rescue from the
domination by the dark powers, but is actually about this growth, this realization of what
it is that Adam is supposed to be that in if I can say this and maybe maybe corrected
a nuance or whatever, that Christ is what Adam was made for.
that atom becomes
Christ in by nature, right, but that Christ is Adam's
tell us am I am I he putting that well right he becomes like
Christ through grace through participating in the work of God,
he becomes like Christ. Yes Christ is the paradigm. The logos,
if you will, of the whole creation. There we go.
So yeah, so
So there's both, we tend to focus almost entirely, and sorry, St. Augustine, right?
But the West, and it wasn't his fault, it's how he was appropriated. But the West has focused
almost entirely on this negative aspect of salvation as if that's the whole thing. That's the whole
enchilada is taking care of the sin and death problem. That's not the whole enchilada. Those are some
roadblocks that were thrown up.
up on the original road.
Yeah, it's like a child who's ill in a way that prevents him from growing.
So heal the illness, and now he can grow.
Now he can grow to fullness and maturity.
But the fullness and maturity was always the intent in the plan.
So Christ still would have been incarnate for our sakes and accomplished what he accomplished
even without any with zero falls.
Right?
Yeah.
But he wouldn't have died the death on the cross, right?
He wouldn't have those things are to deal with death, sin, etc.
Right?
But the incarnation itself is to accomplish this original purpose in God's creation and
His creative acts.
Yeah.
And sometimes people see the incarnation as being just sort of a necessary condition so
can do the things.
like die on the cross. Like, well, we need, we needed a savior who could do this. And so therefore,
we have one. But it's, but that's the opposite. It's that that he isn't carnit. And, um,
you know, he dies. He suffers. He dies because of who he is because he's taking care of,
as you said, these negative aspects of what has happened. So yeah, yeah. All right. Well,
Well, let's talk then now about...
What does happen to Adam and Eve?
You know, we talked about this a little bit.
We kind of, you know, telegraphed it a touch,
talking about the garments of skin, for instance.
So they eat of the tree of the knowledge of good and evil.
And things change.
So the tree of the knowledge of good and evil itself
is talking about this issue of maturity, right?
Because everywhere else where that phrase,
the knowledge of good and evil, knowing good and evil.
occurs in the Old Testament.
It's referring to maturity, right?
So I'd say a chapter seven, you know,
a child will be born before he is old enough
to choose the good and reject the evil,
this will happen, right?
Before he comes of age, before he reaches maturity.
And so the fathers are all very clear,
and even before that, second type of literature is very clear
that the tree of knowledge of good and evil
is not itself evil.
Yeah.
Right, that it's why it represents a knowledge. Yeah, I would say why would God have put a poisonous tree in the middle of the garden?
Right. Right. Yeah. It's that this was knowledge that they weren't ready for yet. Yeah. This was a level of maturity that they hadn't reached yet
and they were trying to seize it before God knew they were ready for him to give it to them.
But so this this happened and so his commandment to them was was more of a warning
Yeah, right it was not
like I'm going to just arbitrarily set a test for them. You know by saying, Hey, you know
what? You can eat all the other trees. Don't eat this one.
Right. Well, I mean, you know, those of us who are parents, it's the same thing. It's like,
look, you know, you're not ready for that yet. Right. You're not like it's not like I'm
tempting my kids by having a car in the garage and they know where the keys are. Right.
I didn't buy a car in order to send them into ruin.
Right, I mean obviously the analogy isn't totally holding every way but but you know like yes, they
They've seen me start the car they they could probably you know
You know not my toddler, but the three older kids probably could go in there and start the car
Right they could do that. They've seen me do it enough. They've seen my wife do it enough
But we didn't buy the car in order to to send them into ruin, but what we do tell them is there is gonna come a day when you're gonna be ready for this
You know, you're going to have this ability. You're going to have this permission, you know,
and it's going to be fruitful for everybody, God willing. I don't have any drivers just yet,
but maybe you'll need your to away from it. Oh man. But, but you know, I, you know, that's just a
try. I mentioned that just to kind of stay off some people. Obviously, again, the analogy does not
hold in every way. They're like, well, why would God have put that tree there? You know, if you knew
true that Adam and Eve were going to do this.
But it was there because...
was going to be for them.
They were seizing it and he told them don't do that.
He didn't hand them the keys, the car, and see, now this is how it all works.
Now don't go to it.
It wasn't like that.
Right.
And so once, and that's the devil's whole presentation is.
Yes.
If you eat this, you can leapfrog all this hard work stuff.
Right?
You can leapfrog all this subduing and filialing and all that.
You've just become like God right off the bat, right?
Boom.
Here's the easy path, right?
But so once they eat of the tree, they now know good and evil.
And the word no, we tend to intellectualize, right, where we think this doesn't mean
now they could write an ethics textbook.
Right, right.
Like before this they had no concept of misobeying God.
Now they have a copy of the rules.
And now they understand deontology, according to a manual.
That categorical imperative.
Who does though really?
So the verb no, you know, Yadda in Hebrew is the same one that's used at the end of chapter
three to say Adam knew his wife, Eve, and they brought forth a son.
So knowing something is more intimate and more involved than just intellectually having the idea in your head of good and evil.
They now know good and they now know evil.
And so what God says in terms of why they're going to die, the way it's often presented is sort of, you know, God makes this rule.
And he says, if you break this rule, I'm a kill you.
Right.
Like on that day, I'm going to kill you.
And then that causes people all these problems.
they look at it and say, well, wait a minute. He didn't kill them that day. Yeah. Right.
So, but that's not what he said. Right. He said, that day, you will die. And so we see
this kind of deliberation scene with the divine counsel in Genesis 3 after, after this
has happened, after they've come to know good and evil where God says, well, now they're
like us knowing good and evil. What are we going to do about this? If they now go
and eat from the tree of life, they will be immortal.
Right? They will be immortal.
And so that evil that they now know will be immortal.
They'll be like the demons, right? Immortal and evil.
We don't want that. So they need to be cut off from the tree of life.
They need to be expelled from God's presence,
right which will bring about which is immediately
their physical death. Right? There are two kinds of death. Spiritual death is the separation
of the human soul from God. Physical death is the separation of the human soul from the
human body. And body in our material sense. Yeah. Right. Right. So, so they have to be they
have to become be made mortal now so that that evil will not be immortal. Yes. So.
that that evil can die so that they will not live forever in that state as
as Genesis 3 says and so this is the idea that that mortality being subject to
corruption then brings about mutability and mutability brings about the
possibility of repentance. If you can get sick and you can die you can also be
healed and and rest
So in terms of our ancient definition of body, what we're talking about is a lot of the powers that humanity had are weakened
and these new potentialities of being subject to death and corruption and decay, both physical and moral, all of those things now enter into the realm of human potentiality that we're there before.
right that God gives and this is what this is what
the garments of skin are. It's not that God makes some leather outfits for them. It's that
their their bodies change and they gain and lose, you know, as you said, potentialities and powers
and summer weekend. And and that mortality is actually a gift from God and not a punishment
because otherwise we wouldn't crystallize and sin. You know, I'm just kind of restating what you
but I think
It's really important to hammer this home that this is a gift from God so that we would
become mutable.
We could certainly change in the sense of growing, right?
We had that ability to grow and so forth, but not to be acted upon and to be altered, right?
was necessary in order to be able to repent.
Because...
Because that's what repentance is.
It's just this turning back to God and reconnecting with him and so forth.
That, um, and we're going to, we're about to talk about angels in a moment, but, but that death is God's gift to mankind.
So he does not become demon.
And what we do with that gift is up to us.
It's up to us, but it is, it is a gift.
Um, it comes with some problems.
You know.
So, corruptibility is no joke, right?
It's not a walk in the park, but it is the path back to wholeness, to communion with God.
And there's another important distinction we have to make here, especially in terms of
the way flesh is going to be used biblically later, like in the New Testament.
but also in terms of underst-
standing this properly and that's the difference between mortal flesh, right, the mortal body
that Adam and Eve receive and sinful flesh, flesh corrupted by sin that's under the power
of sin. Again, because of poor St. Augustine, who I have to keep pointing to unfortunately,
those two things get collapsed, right, because you get the Western idea of original sin,
and I'm not going to go into the whole argument.
about whether that included guilt for St. Augustine or not anyway. But that corruption is,
that corruptibility is actual depravity. And that's not the way the scriptures present it,
and that's not the way, if you read Second Temple, Jewish literature, the early fathers,
there's a New Testament that's not the way they understand it because...
There are two different figures here who are getting put together. One of them is Adam and one of them is Cain.
The word sin does not occur anywhere in Genesis 3. The Scriptures do not say that Adam and Eve sinned.
They violated a commandment, and the word that's usually used for that is trespass.
Yeah, right.
Trust pass.
Step over the line.
Yeah.
Right.
The line was drawn and you stepped over.
You went over the fence.
But the word sin first appears in Genesis 4 when God is talking to Cain.
And he says, this is after Cain is upset because his offering was rejected and Abel's was accepted.
And God says to him, sin is crouching at your door.
It seeks to master you, but you must master it.
that that presentation of sin is not.
breaking a rule. Yeah. God didn't say, Hey, Kane, you're about to break that no murdering people rule.
Yeah. It's it's,
K, there is this force, right? The verb that is translated usually crouching there is actually a
lone word from a K, oh, that yeah, fun with a K, another, another Semitic language everybody
refers to, yeah, it's basically
the earliest tier of Babylonian language as opposed to Samarian. But that verb that's translated
crouching is a word that was used in a Canadian to describe a particular type of demon that
they thought crawled up out of the underworld through cracks in the ground and sort of stalked
people. So that's the imagery that's being invoked there, that that's what sin is like.
We see this in once you know that and you read.
Romans 5 and what St. Paul says, when he says, sin entered the world through Adam.
He's not saying Adam's the first person who broke a rule.
He's saying sin, this power, this demon that crawled up out of the underworld.
It came into the world through Adam and then it goes after Adam's son.
Yeah.
It ends up winning and it's up conquering Cain and subjecting him.
This is why the fathers talk about Satan's passion.
They make us passive, they act upon us, they take control.
Yeah, it's interesting that there's...
And I don't know, it was not that long ago that this distinction kind of came to me
in my mind finally, that we often pray in the Orthodox tradition for protection from sin.
Right?
And not as much, I mean, there's nothing wrong also to pray.
that God would keep us from sinning, right?
That's also a thing for sure.
But the notion of being protected from sin
that sin is this external thing.
I mean, is it, maybe this is going too far, whatever?
But I mean, is it wrong to say that sin is a demon
or maybe sin is demonic force?
Or I don't know.
I mean, there's almost this personification of sin
going on there in Genesis 4, right?
Well, it's true throughout scripture. This is another one of those places where St. Paul uses words very carefully.
There are only a handful of places in St. Paul's epistles where he uses sins plural.
Right. Almost always he talks about sin
Singular as this force as this power. Yeah. That's that's unleashed in the world and that is trying to dominate us
and master us the same way. Mastered Cain and so Cain is is
In the second-table period in the New Testament.
You see this in first John as one shining example.
Cain is the preeminent sinner, not Adam.
Cain is the sinner.
He reads Josephus, he's the first heretic.
Right?
That gets picked up by a bunch of the anti-Nicene fathers,
that he taught his children after him evil.
Right?
So he's the paradigmatic heretic.
He's the paradigmatic murderer.
He's all of these things.
he's, you know, I mean, Saint John called.
him the son of the devil. And it's that sonship like we've talked about it in past episodes
and being a son of God, that he's his image, his likeness, the one doing his works on earth.
That's what happens through sin. And we have to separate those. So we're going to talk about
the bodily resurrection some more in the second half coming up here.
But...
We see in our iconography, in our hemnography, that we see Adam and Eve being restored,
Adam and Eve being redeemed, humanity being redeemed from death, and from the mortality
that resulted from Adam's transgression.
We don't see the same thing in terms of cane anywhere being redeemed from sin.
Redemption from death is universal for the human race, but that negative aspect
of salvation, taking care of sin and purification is not everyone.
Yeah.
Man.
Alright.
Well, before we go to break, I actually just wanted to read a prayer that actually kind of
summarizes a lot of what we just said.
And so this is a prayer that's said by the priest.
It's called a prayer for one who has suffered long
and who is at the point of death.
And I'm just gonna read it to you.
We don't need to explicate it
because we just explicated everything we're just talking about.
But I'm gonna read it to you
and you can hear everything that we've said
summarized now in this beautiful moment
when a priest is praying over someone
who's in the process of dying.
O Lord our God, who in line in affable wisdom
just create man and his fashion him out of the dust,
adorning him with comeliness.
and splendor as an honorable and heavenly acquisition to the glory and magnificence of the
glory and kingdom, that Thou mightest lead him unto that which is according to the image
and likeness. But in as much as he trespassed the command of Thysat, having accepted the image,
but having preserved it not, and therefore that evil not be immortal out of love for mankind
as God of the fathers by the divine will, that is ordained remission for this, and that this
indestructible.
bond should be severed and dissolved, and that the body thereof would be dissolved from
the elements of which it was fashioned, but that the soul be translated to that place
where it will remain until the general resurrection.
Therefore we pray unto thee the unoriginate and immortal Father, and unto thine only
be gotten sun, and unto thine most holy spirit, that thou wilt release from the body unto
rest, in treating also out of thine ineffable goodness forgiveness, if he in any way, whether
of knowledge or ignorance has offended that good
or as under the ban of a priest, or as embittered his parents, or as broken a vow, or as fallen into demonic delusion, or shameful magic, because of the malice of an evil demon.
Ye, O Master, Lord God, harken unto me thy sinful and unworthy servant in this hour, and release thy servant from this unendurable sickness, and the bitter infirmity that has taken a cold of him, and give him rest, where the souls of the righteous abide.
for thou art the repose of our souls and bodies, and unto thee do we send up glory to the Father
and to the Son and to the Holy Spirit.
now and ever, not to eat as of eat as a men.
Father Andrew Stephen Daymak and Father Stephen DeYoung
will be back in a moment to take your calls
on the next part of the Lord of Spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF radio.
You have that RV that blared out a warning,
that some type of an explosion.
The pollution was coming.
It happened on Christmas Day tonight that powerful hurricane Zeta is slamming into Louisiana
at 110 miles per hour.
It's moving at breakneck speeds, firefighters rarely see, exploding across the Sierra
National Forest.
This Sunday assault on democracy.
To slow this spread of the coronavirus, as you can see, we are heading in the wrong direction
and we are heading there very fast.
In these uncertain times, it is...
It's difficult to know who to trust and where to turn for guidance on the issues of the
day.
How does one nurture and maintain an orthodox mindset in the midst of what seems at times,
like crisis after crisis?
We are the gentle and discerning voices that speak reason and hope in a way that cuts
through the cacophony of panic and unrest that surrounds us everywhere.
you are feeling lost and overwhelmed in this age of turmoil or like your orthodontic
faith no longer pertains to contemporary society and its challenges. One place you can go for
refreshment, renewal, and just plain good sense is ancient faith radio. As Orthodox Christians,
we don't oppose medicine. We see the wonders of such progress as a sign of the higher faculties of
man. Even the image of God which allows us to think higher thoughts, to create, to inform, and even
to build. So God decided
that there had to be a world with holy costs, with tsunamis, with murders of children,
with all these horrible, horrible things. And when we hear them all, what comes to the
mind of a believer is first of all, thanks be to God that this is not the final word.
Our struggle to live according to God's ultimate and original plan is a journey to reclaim
our true nature. Restore communion with...
With God and ultimately returned all of radiation to the state God had originally intended.
Ancient Faith Radio, your home for Orthodox teaching, Orthodox music, and reliable cultural
insight from an Orthodox perspective.
Thanks for listening and thanks so much for your support.
We're back now.
with the Lord of Spirits, the Father Andrew Stephen Damick, and Father Stephen DeYoung.
If you have a question, call now at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF Radio.
All right, welcome back. This is the second part of our show.
Normally, we begin to take your calls, but as we mentioned earlier, this is not a live show.
show this is pre
recorded. So we talked about human bodies and what happens to human bodies, especially after
all the things that occur in Eden and the time after that and so forth. But what about angels?
What about their bodies? We talked about that a little bit and so to start us off, I just wanted to
play this pair of questions from our friend Father Fautius in Texas.
Hi, this is Father Fautius Avant and I'm very sorry but I actually have two questions and I hope
that's not cheating.
St. John of Damascus in his exact exposition of the Orthodox faith says that angels cannot
repent on account of their incorporeal nature, and yet he further clarifies that it is only
the deity which is truly immaterial and incorporeal.
I do not see in this necessarily a contradiction to the understanding that Yahweh and the
angels can be said to have bodies if we are speaking of a nexus of potential.
as has been mentioned. I do however wonder what it is about the angels immortality which prevents them from repenting.
And secondly, how do unclean spirits interact with the world around them as they are deprived of the faculties of a body?
Thank you so much. God bless you abundantly.
So what about that? Well, that's what we're about to talk about actually. So it's good that you ask father fortius
Yeah, I mean, I think the way for us to get into this is to talk about angels and their bodies.
And especially to mention, you know, we got a little bit of pushback in our Facebook group,
saying, well, doesn't the church teach that angels are bodyless? We call them the bodyless
powers over and over again. How can you guys possibly say that they have bodies? And of course,
to that, we will answer, well, St. Paul says that they have bodies. So, I mean, you can't go wrong
by simply quoting St Paul, right? So...
Let's talk about that a little bit then.
Right. And not only St. Paul, but numerous fathers, I mean, St. John of Damascus is a notable one.
Yep.
Explain, you know, that that apparent disjunction of the church using the language of bodyless and then
St. Paul saying they have bodies by saying that their bodyless compared to us.
Yes, it's a relative term.
right and when they say bodyless compared to us, they're not saying.
They're not using body there in the sense that we've been talking about it in this ancient sense.
So, they're not saying that angels are powerless compared to us, or they're unable to interact
with God or humans or the world, they're less able than we are. They mean it in the sense of
physicality and materiality. Yeah.
Compared to us, they are, they are immaterial.
and lack tangibility, right?
But they are not utterly intangible
and utterly immaterial because they're created beings.
They're not God.
Yeah, and I seem to recall that
is it St. John Damascus who says
that they are circumscribed,
meaning that there's a,
for lack of a better phrase,
space that they exist in,
or that they're not limitless.
to be truly infinite.
Yes, right.
They're not infinite.
They're limited, they're finite.
We are too, although in very different ways.
So they have bodies, but they're not material bodies
in the sense that we have materiality to our bodies, right?
And that's an important point.
So they are bodyless, but again,
again, it's just like we said at the very beginning,
Like you can't get hung up on a particular word.
right? What does someone mean by the word? That's the important thing. When we say that angels
have bodies, we're not saying that they have corpses if they were to die or something like that.
That's not what we're saying. There are arms and legs and fingers and toes, hair and eyeballs and
so forth. That's not what we're saying. So yeah, so well, you know, if you don't mind, I'm going to
read actually what St. Paul says about this so we can talk about this passage. And so this is from
1 Corinthians chapter 5.
He's continuing on from a little bit longer discourse here where he's talking about bodies
and the resurrection and all this kind of stuff.
The soul chapter is really fascinating and interesting.
And as you have pointed out many times, pivotal.
So starting with verse 38, and I'm reading here from the New King James, but God gives
it a body as He pleases and to each seed its own body.
All flesh is not the same flesh, but there is one kind of flesh of men, another flesh
of animals.
another a fish and another birds. There are also celestial bodies and terrestrial bodies,
but the glory of the celestial is one and the glory of the terrestrial is another. There
is one glory of the sun, another glory of the moon, and another glory of the stars for
one star differs from another star in glory. So I can imagine the immediate objection now
to this is when he's talking about celestial body.
days. Doesn't he just mean rocks floating in space and balls of gas that are on fire?
You know, right? It's some are some are brighter than others, right? That's what the glory
is talking about. Yeah. Yeah. So no. No. Yeah. It's the short answer. So the slightly
longer answer is in the Greek, both that list, the sun, the moon, the stars, the way they're
talked about and
And the list in the passage you just read of the different types of animals is reproduced
word for word essentially from the Greek of Deuteronomy chapter four.
And that's a text that we've cited a bunch in the past.
Right.
It's right.
Deuteronomy four and 19 especially, right, where God says don't give worship to the heavenly
you know, when you look up at the moon in the stars and all the host of heaven, it says there, don't worship them and serve them.
Right. Who?
Who God has allotted to the other nations? Right. Right. So we've talked about that connected to Deuteronomy 32 verse 8.
So St Paul very clearly he isn't just accidentally
reproducing those two lists and exactly the same.
order, right? That's that's deliberate. So say Paul is thinking of Deuteronomy for
here. And so he's very clearly referring to angels. And so what it means that the bodies
of angels in this has differ from one another in glory is what we talked about in our previous
episode when we talked about the quote unquote ranks of angels, right? That different angelic
beings right their vast
cosmic intelligence is they have different purposes, different roles, different jobs as it were,
that they fulfill. And so they receive, being created beings, they receive powers, abilities,
potentialities related to that role that they're going to serve. Right. And so they in that sense
participate in God's power and His grace to those
different extents and so their glory differs based on that role.
So Paul clearly has them in the same continuum of human beings and animals in terms of bodies,
but it's especially important that he's talking about angels here because as we're going
to talk about in a little bit once we're done talking about angels, he's going to use this
This idea of angelic bodies and celestial bodies when he starts talking about...
human bodies in the resurrection and some of how they're different.
But sticking with angels for now.
One thing at a time.
This applies to the second part of Father Fodius' question or his second question, depending
on how we want to diagram his sentences.
The second part is talking about demons.
And so...
When we talked about the five-ish falls of the angels, we talked about how there are different
things in the category of demon, different types of beings. And so the demons who are fallen
in jealous beings, the gods of the nations who are demons, powers and principalities who are demons,
the demons responsible
for making the Nephilim, right, a misleading humanity, the devil, they have bodies. They have
angelic bodies. The exception to that would be the dead Nephilim themselves who we've talked
about, the dead giants, the spirits of the dead giants being dead. Their bodies went into the ground
and big.
composed and they now are in a different sense bodyless, the sense that they've been deprived
of their body. And those are the demons that we see in the synoptic gospels and in the
writings of the fathers and stories from their lives who come and ind well, both idols and
come and possess humans.
And use those as their bodies.
in order to interact with the world and do what they do.
Yeah, although it should be noted that it's not a real union, right?
Right.
You know, if they inhabit an idol or even possess a human being,
those physical objects do not become truly theirs.
They just sort of temporarily kind of make use of them.
You know?
Right.
We got a kind of an odd question I recall this in the group where
or someone essentially kind of wondered,
if someone, if one of these disembodied Nephilim
inhabit a person, you know, possess a living human being,
what does that kind of say about that human being
and all this kind of stuff?
It's like, well, it's not, you know,
that body doesn't become their body, you know?
It's almost like, I don't know, a suit of clothes, right?
It's not your body, you're just kind of clothed in it.
I don't know if that's the right word.
to use. But, you know, I could, I could wear a hazmat suit, right, and use that to interact
with the world. But it's not, and it moves when I move it. But it's not me, you know.
It's just like a body. We have a bunch of examples of this, of this
synoptic gospels. I mean, Legion is an example of this. Yes, right, right. Right. So, I mean,
they can be driven out. Yeah, yeah, they could be, they could be driven out again. Now, the one
possible and this is going to be a big t
But the one possible slightly different scenario
Would be in the case of vampires, but we'll talk about that in a future episode. Yeah, there we go
Yeah, we should do a whole episode that's sort of vampires where we'll
Zombies yeah
Yes
Maybe our next Halloween special that's where we'll go there we go
So but we'll see when we get to that but
So, yes.
That's how they then interact with the world
is through possessing, right?
Taking possession.
I mean, we use the term possession all the time,
but that's what it is.
It's taking possession.
They're squatting, right?
Taking possession of somebody in the material world.
And this also, probably the question
that I think we've gotten the most
since this show started.
has been about why demons can't repent.
Yeah, right.
And even we got a recent question in the group.
Someone was like someone was telling a relative I think about this.
And the relative was like, well, that's not fair.
You know, why doesn't God provide them the means of repentance as well?
You know, why can't angels fall in angels demons?
Why can they not repent?
Can't they just change their minds?
Don't they see?
how horrible it is to be a demon.
You know, like, don't they see how fun?
Yeah, like I would love to get back
to the divine council guys, come on,
is this really forever?
So yeah, well, what about that?
Cause it's actually relevant to us, to us,
to us human beings, but let's talk about it
from an angelic point of view first.
Right, and as much as we can.
I suppose it is a noble quality
they have
sympathy for the devil. And to quote a great Armenian, I cry when angels deserve to die.
But that would probably went right over your head. I know.
It did. But there's someone out there.
There's someone out there who that just landed with it a big way.
Said this, your cards and letters telling us if it was you.
So we've already touched on a couple elements of this.
Like.
we touched on the idea that human mortality is what provides for repentance, right?
That our mortal bodies are particularly suited to allow for repentance.
And I think back in the Five-Eished Falls episode, again, we referenced at least the idea
that one of the reasons why God provided this way of repentance for humans is because,
Because if he didn't...
essentially the evil spiritual powers would have won. Right. That was their goal was to
confound God's plan in Christ and the incarnation was to destroy humanity. Right. Yeah.
And we could say here, by the way, that this idea that angels can't repent because they
don't have mortal bodies. Again, we're not making this up. This is straight out of St.
of Damascus, he has a section about angels, right? And he explicitly says...
here and and St. John Damascus is not a speculative theologian. He's a
catechist right? He is teaching the basics, the core stuff right? Right and what
he's received from previous fathers. Yeah, yeah, he's he's not making it up
either. Yeah. Right. So what this all comes down to, ultimately, is what is it like to be a bat?
a bat. A bat. Yes. Like a bat.
Oh, I gave flying rodents. Yes. A flying rodent.
So this is not a vampire thing. Is it? No. No. No. We're not going back to the vampire thing. Yes.
Don't get excited. Don't get too excited.
What is it like to be a vampire is a whole other thing? No. Yeah.
So I was told that the world is a vampire.
Yeah, yeah, set to dream. Yeah. Yeah.
See, I can make pop culture references too.
You can.
And since we're, that's particularly inappropriate.
Since we're answering father-photias, it's quite,
but so what does it like to be a bat is the title of a famous among 12 nerds philosophical
essay by a philosopher named Nagel who's probably the preeminent contemporary writer and philosophy.
Here's why it's important.
What he talks about in that is the fact that if we want to sit and discuss the question,
what is it like to be a bat?
What we're doing in trying to imagine that is we're essentially imagining our brain
in a bat body, right?
It's like, what would it be like if my consciousness was inside a bat body, like a
which turned me into a bat?
It was still me.
And I had all my memories and thoughts.
and everything, but now I'm a bat.
Which isn't what it's like to be a bat.
Yeah.
That's what it's like to be a human consciousness
trapped in a bat body, which is a different thing.
And so we don't know and we can't know what it's like
to sense the air traveling around our wings while we're
in flight, right?
Or experiencing the world through reflected sound,
the way a bat does.
that the
the a bat's consciousness is structured totally differently than ours. Right? And so we don't have a
window into what it's like to be a bat. We only have a window into human consciousness. So why is
this important for angels? Well, if we can't understand what it's like to be a bat,
yeah, we can't understand what it's like to be a vast cosmic intelligence. Right. And I just
I just looked this up by the way and
What is it like to be a bat is in fact a Wikipedia article?
So it actually has a nice little summary about the picture.
Yeah, there's actually a Wikipedia article called,
what is it like to be a bat?
So there it is.
And there's even a picture for bat.
And there's a picture of Dr. Nagle.
And we're talking here about the structure of consciousness.
And here's why that's important.
It means we don't understand how an angelic being
experience is reality.
Yeah.
We don't understand how they experience things like time
and space, right?
Because, you know, for example,
we don't have like with archangel Gabriel
comes to the Theotokos to tell her
she's going to bear a sun, right?
It's not told like, well, he leaves heaven
and then he has like 93 million mile trip, right?
to get to earth to get to
right? The thing of Tocos is, right, to tell her. He's not like traversing space like that.
And we can't... Well, what is the maximum flight velocity of an angel, right? Like...
Yes. We understand that lately that these are silly questions.
You mean an African or a European angel?
Right. Exactly. Well, they're coming to help with the election. I've just given
to understand by a certain profit, but HL is coming from Africa and from...
So we got political, I know.
But the, so we understand that that's a silly question,
but it's equally a silly question for us to try to understand
how angels experience time.
We still preeminent, since I've said so many,
like quasi negative things about them,
I'll say something super positive now about St. Augustine.
St. Augustine's understanding of human consciousness of time
in books.
ten and eleven of the confessions. Is the greatest work on that subject ever read?
And I can pretty much prove that because even phenomenologists like Husserl and Heidegger
basically just cribbed from it when they talked about human understanding of time.
All right. They just basically stole from it. But that is again, that's talking about how humans
experience time and memory and change right yeah and all of
understand all of our understanding of time and change is intimately related to our mortality.
Right. Our mutability. Right. Those all factor in. So what it means to talk about
angels and demons, you know, before and after they fell and quote unquote when they fell
from their perspective, not from our perspective.
right because some of these events co-us inside in with events on earth and so we can talk about from our human perspective
well here's what was going on on earth related to the fall of this being. Yeah but that's not from the angels perspective. Right. Right. That's from our perspective, the perspective of human history and human memory.
So a lot of these questions are
Ultimately unanswerable.
Yeah. Right.
In terms of what we say, well, isn't an angel in hell?
Isn't he sorry?
Doesn't he want to go back to heaven?
Right.
That's our brain, our consciousness in an angel body.
Yeah.
Right.
That's not what it's like to be an angel.
Yeah.
And I think, you know, you and I privately talk often
about what's called the Dunning Kruger effect.
Right.
Usually when we see people
making, embarrassing themselves. But the Dunning Kruger effect is when you don't even know what you don't
know, right? And the less you know about something, the more you think you understand it.
Yeah, right. Right. And, you know, I mean, just from an experience of probably all of us have had,
you know, watching a kid think that he knows everything there is to know about whatever,
and then horribly do something horribly...
wrong, right? You know, really a big mistake. And the problem is that we don't even know
how we would begin to know what it's like to be an angel. Right? Like, you don't even know
where to begin the problem. Even the concept that a problem has a beginning is a human concept.
but we can't conceive of another way of conceiving.
All right, we don't even know it.
it means for them to conceive, to think.
And this causes theological problems too, right?
Like, you know, we've talked, for instance,
about the heresy of universalism.
It's, universalism is predicated upon these kinds of
assumptions that human consciousness
is what kind of really rules the universe.
It's kind of the way it comes down to being
or the way that every sentient being really functions,
you know that our present
fallen human consciousness to boot right right right and I mean and this has this has enormous pastoral
implications to right um you know someone might say well I have a tendency towards what's something
that the church says is sinful well I that's just who I am I was just born this way whatever it might be
that's like well but we're we're in a fallen state so yes I am maybe I am born this way but that
But that doesn't mean that that...
That's how God made me or that I have to stay that way or whatever it might be or that
I can't, that I'm just subject to it, you know, that I must accept that, right?
You know, it's, it's, we need, we need a lot of more humility, theologically speaking
and, and pastoral speaking and, and just in terms of our own kind of psychology, like
just because I feel something over and over again and I can't imagine not feeling it.
And I don't mean just, you know, things that we think of.
of his sinful tendencies, but even just habits of the mind, right?
If we have that problem where we can't even imagine being different, then how much more
is an issue for us to try to figure out, you know, what it's like to be an angel and
what it means for an angel to repent or not repent or whatever.
So yeah, I mean this is huge.
This is, again, this is not just, you know, as we've said in the past, not just nerdy giant
stuff.
The angel stuff like this
actually comes down to kind of where we are, you know.
Right.
And how much more ridiculous is it for us to try to
psychologist God,
or psychologist Christ?
And this works in all kinds of insidious ways,
not necessarily perfidious, but
where people talk about, you know,
God planning.
things. Yeah. Like God sat down at some point in time and then planned the future or talk
about what was Jesus thinking when this happened? It's like, what? You know, like, well, he's
God. So you can't fathom it, right? We can't know what it's like to be God. We can't
even know what it's like to be other created things.
Yeah.
Let alone not created.
Okay, so related to that, and probably,
now that you've heard all that, everybody,
you could probably answer this for yourselves,
but still, let's go ahead and ask it.
You know, okay, so God gives mankind mortality,
altering human bodies in order to, for that to be,
you know, and that's what happens.
That makes us capable of repentance.
What would it be like when, if he did that for angels?
Why doesn't he do that for, you know, the fallen angels?
What does it give them?
mortality. And you know, one of the questions that came to my mind is like, well, would we
really want materially embodied demons walking around on this earth? Would that be a good idea?
What would happen? And I recall in our, in our, you know, a pre-show discussion, you kind
said, well, we sort of did. Right? This is part where everybody gets excited.
Giants. Exactly. Are basically that, right? I mean, they're not exactly that. But they are. They're embodied, materially embodied, demonized beings.
And did they repented?
Bullied demonized humans.
Yeah.
Yeah. Did they repent?
No. They super didn't.
The flood came.
You know, they didn't repent.
repent, or God sent Israel to wipe them out because they had to just go.
you know, it had to be over.
So yeah, it, it, it, it, it, yeah.
And again, and I mean, we could fall back and say,
well, God knows what he's doing.
How can we question God?
Which I think is a good answer actually.
I mean, that's what God kind of says to Job when Job says,
well, what about blah, blah, blah?
He's like, well, were you there when I made the world?
Right?
Yeah.
It's not like it's an unbiblical answer to say that.
But there's more to it than that.
There's more to it than that.
And I think, I think a lot of it is just simply that
It's predicated upon this idea that
that we don't know what it means to be an angel.
So even though we sort of try to imagine
what it might be for them to repent,
we just, it's not a problem
that we can even think about correctly
to say nothing about solve
and to say nothing about judging God.
Like, why don't you make this truth instead?
You know?
Because again, we have to work with
what actually God has revealed to us,
not what we want it to have met.
Right.
And apophaticism, which is what this basically is,
is not just a punt. It's not just like, yeah, I don't know, right? Or, you know, yeah,
you found a flaw in my logic, so I'm just going to paper it over by appealing to mystery,
right? That's not what I have. Appafaticism is realistic humility about what humans are
capable of knowing and understanding and what they're not. And understanding that if you try to
come to an understanding of something that you by nature cannot understand, you're going to
to at best a deformed understanding. And it was just total total imagination and fiction. Right?
Yep. So now let's get back to some catafaticism. Okay.
Welcome back to things we can say. Yeah. Welcome back to things we can say everybody.
So all right, well, yeah, back to first Corinthians 15 then.
Yeah, and the immediately succeeding verses.
in which St. Paul is talking about specifically about our bodies, human bodies in the resurrection,
whether the resurrection takes place and our soul is reunited with our body. Our life is brought
back into our body to animate it again. Right. Yeah. So he had just said, look there's different
kinds of bodies. There's celestial bodies, there's terrestrial bodies, there's different kinds of
terrestrial bodies. There's different kinds of celestial bodies. And then he begins with so
also is the resurrection of the
the dead, right? We're not going to read this whole passage to you, but but what we're
looking at, if you want to open it up, everybody is 1 Corinthians chapter 15 verses 42 through
54. So we're going to kind of summarize that and and say what's he polishing here? So so what
is he saying? What is this? What is this about? Yeah, it will be coming back here in our pre-Posca
episode, by the way. We got to keep the tees is coming. Yeah, there you go. Keep everybody
coming back for more. The first one's free.
So what St. Paul talks about here is he uses the language of the mortal being clothed with immortality.
Yeah.
Right. Of our bodies being sowed in the ground, buried in weakness but rising in strength.
Right.
Right. And and that language he's using, again, makes sense if you if you understand this ancient concept of the body.
because the transition that happened at the expulsion from
paradise is powers becoming weakened. These potentialities, these passive
potentialities coming into play, right? And those are the things that St. Paul
is calling weakness. Those are the things that St. Paul is noting when he talks
about mortal bodies and mortal flesh, right? And then that gets clothed upon
with immortality that rises in strength, meaning those powers are reinvigorated,
Right and and those passive potentialities are sort of
of eclipsed and removed. Death has sort of served its purpose, the purpose for which we just
talked about. God had granted it to humanity in the first place. That purpose has now been
served. So now it's done away with, right? And it's done away with by making humans no longer
subject to it. Right. Right. And we should point out that this redemption of human nature
happens to its it's huge.
nature itself. So that means that all human beings are going to rise from the dead. Resurrection
is not a reward for the righteous. It's something that's going to happen to all of us, absolutely
all of us. We will be raised incorruptible. And that's how St. John Chrysostom in his
Pascal homily can say not one dead remains in the grave.
He's not just talking about some group of people. It's it's everybody. And now he's speaking
eschatologically when he speaks there because he's obviously in the fourth or fifth century,
whenever you're speaking, the general resurrection had not occurred yet. Justice has not occurred
yet for us. But but right, it's universal. It's universal. Right. And John 528, 29 famously,
Christ says the day is coming when all those who are in the tombs will hear the voice of the
the Son of Man and those who here shall live.
Right.
those who have done good into the resurrection of life,
those who have done evil to the resurrection
of condemnation.
But everyone experiences this resurrection,
everyone receives this new body.
Yep.
This new human body.
So in a sense, this is a reversal of what happens
at the expulsion from Paradise, but it's not just that.
Yeah.
Yeah, this is
intriguing to me because I don't know, I guess for most, you know, most of my life, I thought,
okay, we're going to get, finally get back to where we were in paradise and can kind of
get back on track and continue on, you know, have that life again. But we can't,
like we can't say, well, it's all water under the bridge now. Something has happened, which is
all of these things we've been talking about, all of human history, all of these,
these falls, all of our sins.
all of all of this has occurred that even individual human history, my history,
right, it's not going to be erased in the resurrection. It's not gone, right?
Right. So what else is happening here? Right. So humanity is now in a different
position than it was at the time of the expulsion from Paradise where Adam was
was innocent and was at the beginning of the story.
But humanity has now...
through the incarnation of Christ, this positive work that was always intended to
happen has taken place. So the adoption as sons of God that we've talked about in
so many previous episodes, this has now taken place in Christ. Humanity has been
brought to a maturity that it didn't have originally. And so when we receive
the resurrection body, it's not only just reversing that, taking us back to this
of innocence, but it's now being confirmed in what we've become. And that is for good and for ill.
That's where that resurrection of condemnation comes in. Yeah. Right. Because looking at it
negatively, right, all of humanity would have ended up like the demons immortal and wicked,
if not for mortality. But the unrepentant, that is where they still end up. After losing
this window that God has given for repentance,
this life in this world that he's given us for repentance.
And then on the positive side, humanity has now
been united to God in the person of Jesus Christ,
permanently and forever.
So again, since I wanna try and balance out the things
I've said about St. Augustine, right?
St. Augustine, the one him he wrote,
his ode to the Possible candle famously
has a
Latin refers to Adam and Eve's transgression as phalix culpa.
Yes.
Sometimes translated, oh happy fault.
Yeah.
In English.
Right.
And the reason it's happy is because of the redemption it produced.
Yeah.
Right.
So he's saying Augustin is even delighting in the fact that this, that the devil intended
for evil.
Even this Christ has now turned to good for humanity.
Right.
And I think, for instance, about the fact that the resurrected Christ still bore on,
visibly, on his body, the marks of the Passion, his suffering is part of who he is.
I mean, if I can put it that way, I'm not trying to lay out any complicated Christology here.
But it's clear that it's not, it's not E-
It's not erased. It's not erased. That it's there. And it's, you know, his wounds are life-giving now, right?
You know, thus, Felix Kulpa, right? These, these, that, man meant it for evil, but God has turned it to good.
And it's interesting that the Scripture puts it that way and not man meant it for evil and God erased it.
Right. Right. That the thing that was meant for evil has become now good.
now good. That tombs, tombs,
of scenes can be healing rather than destruction and decay and so forth, right?
Relics, you know, all of this stuff.
Yeah, so this, this, there's both the positive piece and the negative piece, but this positive
piece is why St. Paul over and over again and our reading of St. Paul's Soteriology is a mess
because of a lot of western stuff.
go into a tyraine against it again.
I've done plenty of those.
But because we've lost this positive part,
again and again and again,
St. Paul not only talks about repenting of sin, right?
Knock it off with the sinning guys, right?
I mean, that's definitely important, right?
And being healed of the effects of our sin
is definitely important.
But equally important to St. Paul
and in some epistles more important
is him again and again calling the people
in
the communities he's writing to, to come to maturity, to push toward perfection, to be
zealous for good works, to participate in the work of God in the world and be transformed
in a positive way, not just in getting rid of sin.
This is a part of our salvation, right?
And it's part of that original plan that we kind of lose sight of and forget about,
the picture we get at the end of the book of Revelation.
of the new heavens of the new earth, right?
There's no temple and that includes no Eden
because the whole cosmos is the place where God lives now.
That original goal has been accomplished.
The whole cosmos, the whole universe is now Eden.
It's now the place where God dwells,
is now in perfect order, is now filled with life, right?
That's been accomplished at the end.
But we're in the process of...
of accomplishing it now.
And that is part and parcel of our salvation.
Just as Adam and Eve were going to come to maturity
and be transformed themselves by continuing the work
of God and participating in it.
Same with us.
That's how Saint Paul sees salvation.
Amazing.
And you know, I don't know that we've made it explicit yet,
but just to say this also,
because I think it's important, you know,
that passage from John chapter five
about the resurrection of life and the resurrection
kind of neat.
or sometimes it's translated as a judgment or even damnation, that because our bodies will
no longer be subject to mortality, then that means that repentance is not a thing. It's not
possible after, it's not possible not only after death, but it's not possible after the
the resurrection either.
Right.
And when we say repentance is not possible, right, it's important.
not to say I apologize this because again, this is a person in a state other than our present human consciousness.
But not just that.
We're not saying that there are all these poor people in hell or however you want to talk about it.
Usually the people who are opposed to this will conjure up some kind of fiery hell of torment,
which it ever will do an episode that's not what hell is.
But anyway, it's not what Hades is.
That they're there and they're suffering horribly and they really want to repent, but they get told up not too late
Right now you miss your window
stores closed, right
That's not what we mean by it's not possible to repent
It's not possible to repent meaning in their will
They don't desire to repent
Right, there is no transformation that takes place
self-motivatedly.
Yeah, there's no regret. They don't have the capability of regret.
Anyone who and hopefully it will be few, you know, very, very few,
other than the demons themselves,
anyone in that state of condemnation is going to be there
hating God with every fiber of their being.
Right. Right. Which then
I just wanted to loop back to a question. I don't think we addressed directly, but we get all the time.
which is...
given that there's multiple points at which angels fall,
as depicted in a scripture, could that still happen?
And if not why,
like it's the Archangel Michael kind of changes mind
about serving God or, you know.
Right, well, that's again assuming that angels
experience time the way we do, like on a parallel track, right?
Yeah.
So I guess, you know, we talk about five-ish falls of angels,
that
That's from our point of view.
I seem to recall, I don't know if it's St. Maximus,
or if he was talking about, yeah, I think it might have been
St. Maximus.
I talked about the fallen angels falling as they come into being,
which of course makes no sense from our kind of temporal point of view,
but seems to attempt to sort of solve some of this issue,
you know, so to speak.
But I think the whole point of talking about five-ish falls of angels
say, look, the scripture depicts these things kind of connecting with our time in whatever
way that that happens at four or maybe five different points, you know, at least five
events that we can point to. And maybe there's other events that we're not aware of, right?
Right. I mean, that's, I'm just speculating here, but.
Or maybe from their perspective, it's not an event. Right. I mean, yeah. Yeah. Maybe
event is a human thing.
There are five historical events that relate to this spiritual reality.
Yeah.
And this connects with this question of the resurrection of the dead because, again,
it's this problem of perspective.
I don't know what it's going to be like when I'm raised from the dead.
What, how will I think?
How will I perceive?
How will I function?
How will I act, you know?
And that's really all important to keep in mind for so many reasons, not just because
This is kind of interesting.
whether angels could still fall.
But also, when I think about, I don't know,
there's sometimes people will say things like, well,
okay, if you go in the ground and you decompose,
your molecules are gonna make their way through the ground.
And if they fertilize some piece of grass
that's eaten by a cow and then the cow is eaten by a person,
Does he then have your molecule and is the reservoir?
and get really work on you. I mean, I'm reminded of there's a whole passage from Hamlet that kind of
talks about this, about a worm eating the guts of a king and then the worm being used as bait by a
beggar who eats the fish. But again, we're talking about a rearrangement of matter itself on the way
that it works, at least as it relates to human beings.
You know, the
idea that I think the problem is is sometimes we think, okay,
in the resurrection, we're going to basically be exactly what we are
now, except faster, stronger, better, you know, super humans,
basically. But but no, right.
All you can eat pros and yogurt.
You go to the good place. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah.
Yeah. Lamest afterlife ever.
And that's so, I mean, a really fascinating, interesting show.
But but but but heaven there is is awful. It's lame.
Yeah, yeah, and you know, St. Paul says the body is
sewn in corruption and raising in corruption.
It's not the same thing.
And even like, there's the image of the seed.
Like you think about a seed, it's this little thing.
And you put it in the ground and what comes out
looks nothing like it.
Yeah, you know, it doesn't function like it,
it doesn't look like it, it doesn't smell like it,
it doesn't taste like, it's just completely different.
And yet it is the seed.
It's the same.
He will be his team.
He will be his team, he will be his team.
Yeah, it's the same living entity.
Yeah.
Cool stuff.
All right.
Well, why don't we go ahead and go to a break
and then we'll come back for the third half of our show.
Father Andrew Stephen Daymak and Father Stephen DeYoung
will be back in a moment to take your calls
on the next part of the Lord of Spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
That's 855 AF Radio.
Hello, Alisa, a bella-titch of everyday orthodox.
Well, hi there, Bobbi Maddox, station manager of Anxion Faith Radio.
Hey, so I wanted to talk to you about creating a promo for the great lineup of family-related
programming currently available at AncientFate.com.
Ah, cool.
You know, there are actually a lot of resources on the site for orthodox families of all
shapes and sizes.
Including a few that you've had a hand in.
That is true.
I'm talking, of course, about tending the garden of our hearts, which you record with
Christine.
and that features weekly meditations for families with stories about the saints,
scripture readings, and lessons designed to open up conversation
and to enrich the little church of the home.
And then there's the podcast, Raising Saints, in which you offer tools to equip adults
to share the Orthodox Christian faith with children.
Elmiad Alisa, what else does AFR provide with regard to the family?
Well, let's see, you mentioned Christina, and she's also the woman behind Let Us Attend,
which is a podcast that paraphrases the Sunday Gospel for younger and older children,
and uh...
Don't forget about family matters in which the Center for Family Care, which is a Ministry
of the Greek Orthodox Archdiocese, nurtures and empowers families, helping them navigate
the joys and challenges of life.
And of course, Annalisa Boyd has her own podcast called The Ascetic Lives of Mothers, that serves
as an encouragement for mamas parenting children through all their different ages and stages.
That's five podcasts right there, Bobby.
And now there's a six.
Really?
Yeah, I'm very happy to announce the debut of all these things with Hannah Vasquez.
Hannah is a wife and-
a 4 with one on the way who offers encouragement and inspiration as well as practical tips to mothers as they navigate the
Responsibilities with all these things home-making childcare food preparation etc
We're trying to stay focused on seeking the kingdom. Wow. That's a lot of family content and it definitely deserves a promo
So when should we record it? We just did. I guess we did didn't wait. So are we done here? Yep. Thank you, Elizabeth Yeltsich. So long Bobby Maddox
We're
Back now with the Lord of Spirits,
the Father Andrew Stephen Damick,
and Father Stephen DeYoung.
If you have a question, call now at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF radio.
Welcome back everybody.
This is now the third half of the Lord of Spirits.
And like I said earlier, this is a pre-recorded episode.
So don't call in.
we're not live tonight. God willing, we'll be back live next time. Again, we're on the second and fourth Thursdays of the month at 7 p.m. Eastern 4 p.m. Pacific.
So all right, well, we've just talked about the bodily resurrection.
Let's bring it to the the full final conclusion here and talk about our Lord Jesus Christ, who is the man.
You know, he is he is he is of the
human right he is he is the the new Adam right all of that right and so of
course since we teased the end of the last episode with this Christ have two
bodies we're now going to talk about that at the very end of this episode
exactly because that's how we roll around these parts we're glad you stayed with
this is whole time, everybody.
So, um, so if we're going to talk about body in...
this ancient sense, right? We're talking about powers and potentialities. So as God, Christ,
the divine logos, the word of God, the second person of the Holy Trinity, possesses all of the powers
of the divine nature. Right. Right. So, and we talked about last time how one of the primary ways
in the second temple period and an ancient Israelite religion of
of Unders.
standing the second person of the Holy Trinity was as the embodied Yahweh.
Right. Because he appears to people and I mean we talked about this last time.
Right. And interacts with people and speaks with people face to face.
And right.
Yeah.
So in the incarnation, right.
Christ takes our shared human nature
he takes upon himself all of the powers associated with humanity, right? So using body in that ancient
sense, you could say, right, you confuse everyone, but you could say that Christ has two bodies in
that sense, and you'd basically be referring to a concept very similar to talking about Christ
having two natures divided and human.
But...
There are places where, if you read the Fathers closely,
St. John of Damascus does this fairly frequently,
but other Fathers too, when they're talking
about the incarnation, they'll refer to Christ's human nature
as his human body.
And they're not being appolinarians
like we talked about last time.
Right, they're not saying that he's,
yeah, this material, two arms, two legs in a head
with, you know,
the soul extracted and God in there in place.
Right. Instead, right? That's yeah.
Not what the fathers are saying. They clearly reject that view.
So when they use that terminology that way, they're using body not to refer to
Christ's material human body, which he certainly had. But they're using human body in that
ancient sense to refer to a concept more that includes his whole human nature. All of his powers
as human will, as human energy, all of those things can be covered.
by this ancient sense of the word body. And so sometimes the fathers will use the term body that way.
And so if you're reading one of those texts talking about the incarnation,
don't be confused what it says that when it talks about Christ's human body and his human body
being created, it's not just talking about the physical body, it's talking about Christ's humanity
in total. Yeah okay.
Okay, so I kind of have a question and don't remember if we even talked about this pre-show or not,
but in thinking about this, then Christ takes on human nature. He takes on a human body
with all of that means. When he's, you know, prior to his death and resurrection, he's walking around,
he's material, right? He takes on materiality. Right. He takes on its limitations. He
and you know, we're gonna talk about him taking on this
voluntarily and so forth.
So, and then he rises from the dead,
he sends it to heaven, he sits down
with the right hand of the father.
Is it right to say that he's still material in this way
if materiality is, so okay, maybe that might need
to back him and say this, is materiality,
is it only a sort of manifestation
of the kind of mortality that we have now,
or what's going on there, right?
So human body's changed.
after what happens in Eden and become mortal,
we're Adam and Eve material,
or they were material but in a different way.
I mean, you know, you know, you know,
you know, you see I'm getting angry.
They're material but in a different way.
In a different way.
Right.
And just as our resurrection bodies
will be material in a different way.
And we see this with Christ's resurrected body
in the scriptures, right?
He talked about flesh and bone.
They could touch him.
He still has flesh and bone.
You know, each of Thomas could,
We're not told whether he did or...
not, but I like the Caravaggio painting. So we'll say he did put his hand in in Christ's side and
in the holes of the nails. Yeah, most orthodox icons, so I'm actually making contact. Yeah.
So, um, so yeah, all that's true. It eats, right? All of that's true, right? But at the same time,
he could just appear in a locked room. Uh, he can, you know, uh, cross vast distances without, you
You know, running.
Right, it's not like Christ turns invisible and then goes running over to the road of Emmaus, right?
Right. He's just he's there, right?
And he's there. There's a so he's still he's clearly still material, but he's clearly material in a different way
Yeah, right and and yeah, if if we don't understand that
You could get into some really goofy stuff with your doctorate of the Eucharist for example
Yeah, yeah, right like I'm looking I'm looking
Lutherans in Calvinist. Oh, you're
debate. Yeah. Well, let's talk
about, I mean, I don't know, maybe we'll
get to that. But yeah, I mean, I think
we should talk about that because we
say it's the body of, I mean, we use
this phrase body of Christ not only to
refer to what we would normally think
of as the person of Christ, but, but the
church and the Eucharist, right? So
what's, I mean, what's going on there?
Why?
And what's
The sense is the Eucharist, the body of Christ,
according to this kind of language.
Yeah, both.
This is a porcaneolos dose situation.
Why not both?
Yeah.
That the Eucharist is both Christ's body,
in the sense of being his body,
and in our soon to be forthcoming episodes on sacrifice,
will be talking.
about this. And his blood, which is the fact that his blood is involved very clearly means
that that sense is real. Because blood is not used the way we've been talking about body.
But it is also true that the Eucharist is the body of Christ in this sense, in the sense that
The Eucharist and all of the material sacraments,
and all the sacraments have these material elements,
are the instruments through which Christ's power
enters into the world to transform us,
to change us the way he acts upon us.
Right? This is what we mean when we say God's grace,
his energies, his working in the world
is mediated through sacramentality, right?
Through the mysteries.
We mean that Christ works through the
So there they're also his body in this ancient sense. Yeah, the Eucharist is also his body in this ancient sense
Yeah, so yeah, so both I was more going after you know
the Calvinists arguing that
It can't be Christ's body in the Eucharist because his body is in heaven at the right hand of God like that's a place
Yeah, right where it's located and then and then the Lutherans
essentially arguing. So it's hard to pin them down in with an under. But yeah, and using
this. But if you say consubstantial, then you know, or yeah, consubstantiation, like,
no, no, no, no, using this weird incarnational analogy that is definitely not orthodox, that
somehow like Christ takes a third nature of bread or something, like it's hypothetically
united to him instead of incarnation. It's in panation. Yeah. So anyway, enough picking
on Protesters.
But that whole debate kind of
Does it make a lot of sense if we understand Christ's body in this biblical sense that we derive from St. Paul on the resurrection body and of Christ's resurrection appearances in the Gospels
That whole Eucharistic debate kind of doesn't make a whole lot of sense
Yeah
Right, I think it's a it's an attempt to to take these kinds of
Aristotelian categories of things and what makes a thing a thing.
and apply it to the God man.
I can't believe I even said this sentence.
But you know what I mean?
Right, right.
Yeah.
And it wasn't the Protestants who did that first.
We'll spread the blamber out to everybody in the West
for forgetting that all mixed up.
And confusing everyone.
How many of our listeners have we alienated in the last?
Probably a lot.
Three seconds.
There are friends that I'm just saying.
We do love them.
I'm just saying they're confused.
And it's not their fault they're confused.
Like they have this historical trajectory
has led them to a confusing place.
So, yeah, it's not blame worthy that they're confused.
Yes.
So, but the other key thing, and the people I'm going to bash a little now, I don't even
consider Protestants, is that when Christ is incarnate and he takes on human nature and
he takes on these human powers, he's taking on something else.
is not.
getting rid of or substituting anything.
Yeah, right. Okay, so I've heard this view and it's, you know, there's that word
Kenosis, right, or Kenosis is sometimes getting angstized. The self-emptying of
God, you know, in Christ, and I've even heard it as, you know, he set aside being
God so he could be man for a while or something like that.
which is just, I mean, awful.
Yeah, right.
It's to use that wonderful phrase.
It's not even wrong.
It's so incoherent.
It's not even incorrect.
Yeah.
It's frackedally wrong.
Yeah, right.
Meaning the whole thing is wrong.
And if you zoom in on any particular part of it,
it is just as wrong as the whole thing is wrong.
Right.
Yeah.
So, yeah.
Right, so that is not the idea at all.
This is why the fathers were so clear that Christ becomes man without change or alteration.
Yeah.
He's still fully gone, all that it needs to be gone.
He has added to himself human powers, right?
The human nature, right?
The human body in this ancient sense, which includes human body in the modern sense, right?
He's added that.
And so the limitations that Christ takes upon Himself are each and always He takes them upon Himself voluntarily.
Yeah.
right? I
like, now it's my time to die.
I'm gonna go do it.
And it's not suicidal, but it's voluntary.
He's conquering death.
Death is not, he's not a victim in the sense of like,
okay, well, I'm gonna let them overpower me.
And it's illustrated in scripture.
I can't remember who I read that explicated this,
but I just thought it was such an amazing piece
of attention to a really important detail
where it says that he bows his head
and then gives up the spirit in that order, which is exactly the opposite order of the way most of us die, which is that we die, and then we slump over because, you know, we don't have any control of our bodies anymore.
He's in control, he bows his head, and then gives up his spirit.
It's the moment that he himself dies as his choice.
You know, it's not that the Roman successfully killed him.
Right. Right.
Right, yeah, that's a-
especially if he's in St. John's gospel over and over and over again, there are all these times where they try to kill Jesus during his ministry
and it doesn't say, but Jesus was clever and escaped.
Right?
Yeah.
It says, but they could not kill him because it wasn't his time yet.
And then that gets sort of summed up by Christ himself saying, no one takes my life from me.
I am able to lay it down and I am able to take it up again.
So Christ chooses
to die. He's not even subject to death, let alone any of the other things. So Christ chooses
to become tired. He chooses to become hungry. He chooses to undertake what are called by
the Father's, the blameless passions. The things we suffer that aren't the result of the
direct result of us being sinners and our domination by sin.
Yeah, yeah, and you know, it's when a human being is
taken hold of by circumstances and then suffers it
valiantly and
without complaining and maybe even self-sacrificing. That for us is extremely admirable.
You see someone taken prisoner and tortured and killed or whatever, which happens over and
over again with the martyrs. And yet Christ is the Lord of glory at every moment, in his whole life,
his passion and his death. He could call down 10 legions of angels. He could, with a thought,
make them all dissolve faster than Thanos can snap his fingers.
I don't know. How do you even conceive of that? That he is so in control and chooses it all.
It's very, very delivered in his part.
You know, we add...
someone who's caught up by circumstances and bears them up well, he's not even caught up by circumstances.
Right? We can't say, you know, well, they did it to him, but you know, he, look at what he did.
It's way beyond that. It's a choice every moment that that that he enters into death in order to save
us from death and he chooses it. It wasn't just a last desperate kind of attempt, right? It's his
His choice, he enters into it.
very, very deliberately.
And there's no point in which he loses control ever, ever,
through that the whole timeline, not ever.
Right.
And this isn't something that we can construct a good enough
series of philosophical categories
to understand and explain.
This is an incredible mystery that we write hymns and poetry
and sing and pray and stand in awe at.
I mean, that's what Holy Week is.
It's a-
a protracted period of standing in awe of this before it,
not trying to explain or comprehend it.
Yeah.
Well, let's, I think maybe a good place to,
I mean, we've already talked about this a little bit,
but maybe we can meditate on this as our place to kind of wrap up.
The church is the body of Christ.
What does that mean?
To understand this, you have to understand body in this ancient sense that we've been talking about this whole time.
That when St. Paul talks about some people being
God's eyes and some people being his feet and some people being his hands, right?
This isn't just to randomly
talk about body parts or do it do an analogy.
He means it in this sense, right? So that
the way in which
people in this world experience being seen and known by God is by being seen and
known by us. The way in which the world hears Christ's voice is when the church
speaks. The way in which people Christ feeds the hungry, right, close the naked,
right we we sit back in our modern
world and we look at poverty and hunger and disease and these horrible things happen in the world
and we have the gall to say why doesn't God do something about this? This is a philosophical problem
of the opposite. Why doesn't God sent someone? He sent you buddy. God sent someone. It's you sitting
got your couch watching the Sally Strothers commercial right like that's a
deep cut right here's the one
you're the one who's supposed to be doing something about this, right? And you're not.
That's what St. Paul means. There's an urgency to St. Paul saying that.
That not only do we each need to fulfill, God has given us the gifts to do what he's called each of us to do,
are a small part of that.
And it's critically important that we not only each do it,
but that we all cooperate together as one whole.
whole body, right, to do this work together and to get it done in the world. And there are,
there are no substitutes for direct action. And I'm going to be only slightly political now,
fair warning. This is true across the board, right? So going and voting for someone who says he's
is going to do something to help poor
people is not fulfilling God's calling to you to help those in need. And going and voting
for someone who says they're maybe going to somehow ban abortion is not fulfilling God's
call on you to go and help mothers who are pregnant and who are in distress and need
help. Right. There's not a substitute for direct action. There's not a substitute. There's
that's something we can do.
to fulfill what God wants other than doing what God wants in the world.
Yeah. So I have some final thoughts and then you can give your thoughts.
Sure.
You know, so for these last couple episodes we've been talking about concepts that are really
difficult because they're so different from the way we usually think. Right. We tend
think of bodies as objects as a material thing.
And then again, this is the podcast of, hey, it's not just a metaphor.
So when we hear phrases like the body of Christ, whether it means the Eucharist or the church,
or we think about the resurrection, right, we think about what happens to Adam and Eve,
we think about angels, like all of these things.
If we just have a concept of bodies as objects, then it's...
It's an atomized theology, right? It's just, here's a thing, here's a thing, here's a thing.
And it tends towards kind of the magical and the talismanic, if I can say so, right?
Like, here's a thing that's charged with superpowers, right? But if we understand that
God in Christ is making use of us, especially the church, that we are his body. We are his
is nexus of
powers to use that kind of language, then it utterly
vivifies the Christian life in a radically different way.
You know, we've talked for instance about living an
ecstasystic life, you know, casting out demons.
Well, it's not because I have a power of being an
ecstasyst.
It's because Christ's mission is casting out his enemies
the demons.
And I can participate in that or not.
I can become, I can become
truly his body in that sense or not. It's all voluntary. You know, I have a choice.
And what that means is that the thing that you do listener, whatever it is, you sit
a prayer this morning for someone, you gave something that you didn't have to give. You
helped someone with something that they needed help with.
whatever it is you did, when you did that, you were participating in the very power and
action and love the body of God Himself.
You know, it's not enough for us to just sort of say, God is everywhere and he's watching
the things I do and like the divine Santa Claus making a list and checking it twice.
I hope I get in it.
the end, it's so much more than that. It's so, so much more. He is present now in this
room where you are and he's acting and he's acting through you. You have become, you know,
St. John Chrysostom talks about the priest at one point. He says, Christ is the priest and
the one that we call a priest, the president, he gives his voice in his hands and he participates
price priesthood. So my prayer is as you have listened to these two episodes and probably
had your mind blown ten or twelve times which would be exactly half the number that I
had maybe, that you would, again, not just say wow, I learned some interesting ancient
concepts today and so forth, but that this would
to vivify your life in Christ.
Christ, that you would understand it's not a metaphor. The church is the body of Christ.
He is present with us. He's in our midst. He's working in our midst. It's just like it
says at the beginning of the Acts, the Apostles, you know, where St. Luke says, in the former
treatise, you know, when he's talking about his gospel text, I wrote about all the things
that Jesus began to do and say.
which means that what happens the book of acts is Jesus continuing to do all of those things.
And it's not just the book of acts, it's not just for second, third, fourth, fifth century Christianity,
it's now. It's now as well. Christ is acting. He is healing his world. He is drawing all men to
himself. He is forgiving sins. He is healing, you know? He is doing all those things. And so our
task is to
join in and be faithful and remain faithful.
And when we fall over to get back up
and return to faithfulness and keep going forward,
always with our eyes on that final day,
when Christ is going to come to judge the living
and the dead, and we will see Him as He is.
What I have to say is not unrelated.
We got a question by email.
in which someone asked us how this relates to St. Paul teaching that our body is the temple
of the Holy Spirit.
And we kind of brushed over, I mean there's so much related to this, we couldn't go into
detail on everything.
That St. John, both in his gospel and in the apocalypse in the book of Revelation, says
that Christ's body, Christ's
humanity, right, is the temple, is the new temple. And how that relates to then our bodies
being the temple of the Holy Spirit and how that works, right, because we may think about
that as well, our body is sort of a physical space and the Holy Spirit lives inside it, right?
And obviously if you push on that even gently, it gets kind of ridiculous, like we've got
internal organs in there.
right? Obviously that's not that's not that kind of literal spatial kind of sense.
The presence of God in the temple is what made it the temple. His body being there as we talked
about in the previous episode, temples the place where God's body is. And so the same is true
with Christ. Christ's body is God's body. But say
Paul is saying the same thing when he says that our body is the temple of the Holy Spirit.
He's saying that our body is and is to be God's body.
That's why in that same context, he can say to someone, how can you go and join the members
of Christ to a prostitute?
We may take that primarily in the negative sense, which, and St. Paul clearly means that
negative sense, but it's also true in the positive sense over and over again in our
our liturgy and the divine liturgy we offer our cell
and our whole lives and each other to Christ.
St. Paul says, we offer ourselves as living sacrifices.
We offer our bodies to God as instruments for him to use.
And we're making a commitment and we're making a promise when we do that.
That we are not going to use our bodies, our powers, our abilities, our gifts.
We're not going to use those as a means to gratify ourselves,
Let's see...
to seek pleasure for ourselves, but we're going to give them to him to do his work.
The Christian religion is not an immaterial or ghostly religion. It is not about sitting in your house
and purely repenting and contemplative prayer. It is not about avoiding the outside world and
than avoiding others.
Even...
our great monastics who have done that, have only done that for a certain period of time.
And then have shared what God has done in them with others. So we work out our salvation every day
in the material world through our bodies by showing love, showing compassion, doing good,
cultivating life, putting things in order and establishing justice and
decency and good in the world every day. That's not an add on. That's not something that's
good to do in addition to our salvation. That's not a sign that we're really saved. That
is the stuff of our salvation because that is the stuff of our transformation. That's how
we grow. That's how we change. That's how we come to know Christ, Lord, deeply. That's
That's how we become sons of God.
And that's how we reach that maturity and
completion and perfection that God created us to seek after and by His grace to attain.
And that's what we've got for today. Thank you very much everyone for listening. If your
question didn't get a chance to be addressed during this broadcast, we would love to hear
from you either via email at Lordofspiritsatheanchandfaith.com or you can message us at our Lord of Spirits
podcast Facebook page we read everything.
but we cannot respond to everything, unfortunately.
And we do say what you said for possible use in future episodes.
Join us for our live broadcasts on the second and fourth Thursdays of the month at 7 p.m.
Eastern 4 p.m. Pacific, like our Facebook page and join our Facebook discussion room.
Leave reviews and ratings, but most importantly, share this show with a friend whom you know
is going to love it.
And finally be sure to go to ancientfaith.com slash support and help make sure we
and a lot of other AFR podcasters stay on the air.
Thank you very much and God bless you.
You've been listening to the Lord of Spirits
with Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew Stephen Daymak
and Father Stephen DeYoung,
a listener-supported presentation of ancient faith radio.
and I be held.
And I heard the voice of many angels round about the throne
and the beasts and the elders.
And the number of them was 10,000 times 10,000
and thousands of thousands,
saying with a loud voice, worthy as the land
that was slain to receive power and riches and wisdom
and strength and honor and glory and blessing.
Revelation chapter 5 verses 11 through 12.