He will be a staff for the righteous with which for them to stand and not to fall.
And he will be the light of the nations and the hope of those whose hearts are troubled.
All who dwell on the earth will fall down and worship him, and they will praise and bless,
and celebrate with song the Lord of Spirits.
1st denoc, chapter 48, verses 4-5.
The modern world doesn't acknowledge, but is nevertheless haunted by spirits,
Angels, demons and saints in our
time many year into break free of the prison of a flat secular materialism to see
and to know reality as it truly is. What is this spiritual reality like? How do we
engage with it well? How do we permeate every day life with spiritual presence?
Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew Stephen Damick, and Father Stephen De Young
host this live Colin show focused on enchantment in creation. The union of the
seen and unseen as made by God.
and experienced by mankind throughout history.
Welcome to the Lord of Spirits.
Welcome to the Lord of Spirits Podcast.
I am Father Andrew Stephen Damick in Emeas, Pennsylvania.
And with me is my co-host, Father Stephen D'Young in Lafayette, Louisiana.
And if you are listening to us live, you can call in at 855-AF radio.
that's 855237234c
and we're going to get your calls in the second part of today's show, God willing.
So every year Christians argue about Halloween.
Is it participation of the occult,
cavorting with demons that we should be running away from,
or is it harmless dressing up and candy?
Some more traditionally minded say it's not about demons,
it's about the feast of all states.
And some non-Christians will say that their fall holiday of silence
spelled S-A-M-H-I-H-A-I-N, is greatly misunderstood at what's been maybe co-opted by Christians
or slandered by them or others.
One thing is for sure, people have opinions about Halloween.
We say that Halloween really is about demons.
And for those who have been listening to this program since we premiered in September,
that will not surprise you in the least.
it would surprise our long-time listeners even less to learn.
that we say we're okay with running right toward those demons.
Now, we very likely have a whole lot of new listeners
tuning in right now who have never heard one episode
of the Lord of Spirits podcast before tonight.
If that's you and if our assertion that Halloween
is about demons gets you mad
or if our willingness to be involved with demons
gets you mad before you tune out,
at least listen to the first part of the show
because this is almost certainly not going to be
what you think.
So to help get...
all of you new listeners a sense of what our deal here is on this show. I'm not going to tell
you to go back and listen to our first four episodes before this one. Although if you're listening
to this recorded why don't you just pause and go back and listen to those first. You should
definitely check them out either way. But I'm going to ask my co-host Father Stephen to give you a
very quick summary of what exactly this program is about. So Father Stephen, let's give a quick
orientation for all of our new listeners. Sure so...
What we're about here is recovering a sense of the full orbred reality of the universe
that we live in. The cosmos that we live in includes not only material reality,
which we're very comfortable with, but spiritual reality which we as contemporary
modern people are not comfortable with if we even believe it exists.
And the truth is that when you look at ancient people,
whether we're talking about ancient pagans
or we're talking about ancient Israelites
or we're talking about Second Temple Judaism
or we're talking about early Christianity,
they all based on their own experience
of spiritual reality,
had a shared understanding of the contours of that reality,
of the geography of that reality,
of the inhabitants of that reality.
And along the way over the last five centuries or so give or take, our culture, our Western culture has sort of made a bargain.
And that bargain was to trade away that ancient spiritual wisdom and to trade it for an ever-deepening and ever more technologically applied understanding of the material world.
We gave up our spiritual understanding to gain a greater scientific and technological and material.
understanding of that element of the world around us. And that's created while
people are maybe aware of it, you know, maybe starting in the 60s, they know about
the Beatles or somebody going to yogis and people dabbling in Buddhism and
the rise of new age spirituality and various forms of reconstructed neo-paganism.
It goes back much farther than that. I mean you can go to Emerson, we go well back
back into the 18.
in the 19th century, where Western people realizing this gap have tried to reach out to other
non-Western traditions to try to recover that spiritual wisdom and that spiritual sense.
And that's not just true in the world in general, it's true of Christianity.
Along the way, Christianity decided to trade its inheritance for a mess of potage, essentially.
and uh
sidelined that spiritual inheritance in order to become modern people.
And so what we're really about in this show is about taking the journey back into the ground of Christianity,
back into the understanding of this spiritual reality that our fathers and forefathers had,
and that we gave up to try to recover it, not giving up any of the technology or
understanding of the
material world we have now, but adding to it that spiritual wisdom that otherwise might
have been lost, that will allow us to navigate our modern contemporary material and technological
world more successfully with that spiritual wisdom.
Okay.
Well, just to lay out a few ground rules of sorts for this particular episode, I just want
policy. Our purpose tonight is not what
probably a lot of people think that this episode is about. It's not to say where Halloween
really comes from so that we can kind of slap down a label of okay or forbidden on the thing.
Why? Why are we not addressing that? Well, it's because there are a lot of things going by the name
of Halloween. The name itself is Christian and origin, actually, in a short for all Hallows Eve,
That is the evening before all Saints Day, which is a holiday that celebrated on November.
in the Western Christian churches, but in the early summer by most Orthodox Christians like us,
it moves around a little bit for us, and it's always on a Sunday.
And there was actually, at one point in history, even a May 13th date for all saints,
all saints as a few celebrated all over the Christian world in various ways.
But Halloween is a name that for a lot of people just means dressing up in costumes
and collecting candy from the neighbors with accompanying spooky parties and decorations.
and themes. For some people it means getting together and using Ouija boards to divine information
from spirits. Others might hold a salience, trying to summon spirits directly. Others might celebrate
a modern reconstruction of the ancient Celtic pagan Sauen, a celebration for which we have no
manuals from pre-Christian times which means that modern reconstructions are reconstructions.
So, for as many people who celebrate Sallin, you can get that many...
variations on what it's really supposed to be and what it means. Identifying where all
of those things come from is not the purpose of our program tonight. And what we are going
to talk about tonight is what people actually do and what those things they do, rituals,
what they actually accomplish. And of course, that's going to include some history. And
of course, we'll also be speaking from an unabashedly Orthodox Christian point of view because
That's who we are. We're not gonna make any apologies about that
But in order for any of that to make any sense, we first have to begin with the spiritual landscape.
As we've been talking about for the past four episodes of this show, there are indeed spiritual beings in the world, aside from the Holy Trinity.
There are angels, there are demons, and the demons were angels who rebelled against God, and the primary way that they rebelled was by accepting worship that should be given to God alone.
and they're still in rebellion.
So that's the basic conflict.
So let's go back to the earliest interactions of human beings with those rebels.
How did ancient people understand these beings that they worshipped?
So let's begin.
And Father Stephen, I know you have in our notes here
we're going to begin actually talking about the way that pagans understood
the gods whom they interacted with, which again from a Christian point of view
and we've covered this in previous episodes.
These gods, the pagans worshiped are fallen angels also known as demons.
So let's talk about the way that pagans understood their gods.
So why don't you go ahead and begin for us, Father?
Sure.
And the reason it's important to start here and to address this is because we're used to
thinking about if we ever think about Greek religion or Roman religion or Babylonian religion
or Celtic religion.
and pick your culture's original religious beliefs,
we're used to thinking about that in terms of mythology.
Right.
So we've got, here's our list of gods, right?
And they're sort of like the Justice League.
There's like the guy who runs real fast
and there's the guy who throws the lightning bolts, right?
And we're approaching it in that way.
And that of course is not how the people experienced
and approached their religious life
who actually lived this in the ancient world, right?
They didn't view it as obviously not as fictional characters or as characters at all.
These were spirits who they experienced and are acted with.
And so, right.
I've got a couple of quotes from Plato that I'm going to read to kind of summarize this.
This is how Plato is an Athenian in the classical period.
So this is sort of our peak of high-great culture we could say.
how he understood where the gods came from and their relationship to the people of particular cities and nations
and their relationship to the earth and the ground in those places, the physical space and physical territory.
Yeah, right, the geography.
Yeah, and so the first of these is from his dialogue, Critius,
And if you want to look this up later, this is line
109 B and C if you want to fully nerd out like I do. But otherwise here's what Plato says,
in the days of old the gods had the whole earth distributed among them by allotment.
There was no quarreling, but you cannot rightly suppose that the gods did not know what was
proper for each of them to have, or knowing this, that they would seek to procure for themselves
by contention that which more properly belong to others.
They all have
them by just appointment, obtained what they wanted, and people their own districts, and
when they had people them they tended us their nurslings and possessions as shepherds,
ten their flocks, accepting only that they did not use blows or bodily force as shepherds
do, but governed us like pilots from the stem of the vessel, which is an easy way of guiding
animals, holding our souls by the rudder of persuasion according to their own pleasure.
Did they guide all mortal creatures?
No different gods.
had their allotments in different places, which they set in order,
Hephaestus and Athenii, who were brother and sister,
and sprang from the same father, having a common nature,
being united also in the love of philosophy and art,
both obtained as their common portion in this land,
meaning Athens, which was naturally adapted
for wisdom in virtue, and there they implanted brave children
of the soil and put into their minds the order of government.
Their names are preserved, but their actions have disappeared
by reason of the discusing.
destruction of those who received the tradition and the laps of ages.
For when there were any survivors of, as I've already said, they were men who dwelt in
the mountains, and they were ignorant of the art of writing, and it hurt only the names
of the chiefs of the land, but very little about their actions.
The names they were willing enough to give to their children, but the virtues and the
laws of their predecessors, they knew only by obscure traditions, and as they themselves
and their children, lacked for many generations the necessities of life, they directed their
Thank you.
attention to the supply of their wants, and of them they converse to the neglect of
events that had happened in times long past. From mythology and the inquiry into antiquity
are first introduced into cities when they begin to have leisure, and when they see that
the necessities of life have already been provided but not before.
Right. So Plato was saying that all of the gods had assigned to them, right? The gods
and the counsel of the gods had assigned to them these different.
places in different territories, a Festus and Athenian had Athens and it's
surrounding a sign to them and they brought forth the people of Athens from the
soil of Athens. So there was a connection for Plato and these other ancient
peoples between themselves and the soil that they came out of and themselves
and their gods. Right, right. They believed had been assigned to them. Yeah and I
And I mean, it's kind of a long passage, right?
But I think it's a really interesting point to make that here is an ancient pagan
describing exactly his understanding of what the pagan landscape looked like, right, that these gods live in various
territories. I mean they're territorial and they interact frequently with the people that worship them and
and provide for them and so forth.
You know that essentially everybody just has their con-
of their local deity. And of course, he paints, I mean, it's a pretty happy picture of what,
you know, as he says, of course, he's saying, this is just way at the beginning, he starts
up by saying there was no quarreling. And you have to kind of say, well, you know, yet,
right? Because, you know, supposedly they reach territorial and they just sort of hung out
in their, their particular territory. And, and I think it's notable that this is contrary
to the way that...
Modern people tend to look at ancient paganism that they basically say well, you know pagans just sort of
They saw things they couldn't explain so they they figured maybe there's some kind of divine being behind that
But here's an ancient pagan saying no, this is what we
This is what's going on in our experience, you know
This is this is what what what you know he understands
pagan life to be like right so okay
right and I go ahead it's a it's a it's a
to emphasize, as you mentioned, the second part of that quote, that Plato sees that there was this
period where these gentle shepherds, right after they were assigned, but something has changed,
something has happened, something has been lost. And the bit about the mountains there,
I mean, I didn't want to make the quote even longer, but Plato's really talking about the flood.
He's talking about the sinking of Atlantis. And so the only people who survive were sort of these
rustics who lived on high mountains.
So he attributes that to the place where sort of these things were lost
Because he understands that those same gods behave differently now. Yeah
Yeah, so okay
Well, do we want to I mean I see we've got more here kind of talking about about this ancient pagan
view
Well, let me summarize it instead of yeah, yeah, let's summarize that yeah, so
And if someone does want to look it up and read it.
again if you want to fully nerd out.
This is from Plays on the Laws, line 713c through e.
I'm using the universal line numbers because that way I don't
have to worry about what translation you might pick up.
So basically in this section, he repeats essentially a lot
of what we just read.
But the important additional part here
that he identifies Kronos, the father of Zeus, as the
one who did the allotment.
So there is a, for, for play to hear in that early age,
there was this most high God, was Kronos,
the Sun's Zeus presided in the council of the gods.
And of course, in a previous episode,
talked about what's called the succession myth
that Zeus, you know,
kills Kronos and takes over.
But the pattern here, this is a pattern that,
I'm using this as representative of
every you can find this in every form of pagan religion on earth that there is
the study of a most high god who is above you know the decalmbal gods and who
did who did this allotting and the separation and gave places they're assigned
deities to govern them. Right, right. So, alright, well
Let's then talk about the biblical version of this.
And we talked about this a bit in our previous episode,
which was about the five-ish falls of angels,
and that's the Tower of Babel.
So I'm not going to read this to you,
but this is in Deuteronomy 32,
and also Deuteronomy, is that four, chapter four?
Right, your enemy 32-8 says that when the most
tied, divided in the nations, he numbered them according to the sons of God.
Right.
So it has Yahweh, the most high God, being the one who assigns these angelic
beings to go through the nations.
Right.
So what happens at Babel is that mankind attempts to worship the one true God
by means of idolatry.
And God says, no, that's not going to be.
and he withdraws and
He scatters the nations from one thing and he withdraws himself so that mankind's wickedness will not destroy him in the presence of God
and
Lots the nations to these various angelic beings and so this is where you get you know Plato talking about well early on
You know the gods were everything was great, you know
There was no quarreling and so forth everything was great
But then something changed and from the biblical Christian point of view
what changes is that the gods begin to accept
for themselves, right? So that these angels fall by means of setting themselves up as
gods to be worshipped. And so there is this alteration in the way that human being
experience the gods that is these angels who become fallen angels, or as we would call
them demons. And by the way, just a word about that word, demon, okay? Now, when we use
the word demon we have this idea of a of an
evil, dark, horrible spirit. And you know, we should. But in the ancient world,
demon or daemon just meant kind of a spirit, right? Even Socrates claimed that a
daemon spoke to him and that's where he got his wisdom from. And obviously he wasn't saying
that was a bad thing that he was in league with demons as we might put it now. Right? So when we talk
about demons, this is the word actually in the ancient world just simply means a spiritual being of
of some kind, but eventually in
in the Christian context it becomes very negative, but it's neutral in the ancient world.
Right? But these demons, these fallen angels, these gods, begin to accept worship and they
begin to oppress mankind. And it's in that act in particular that they are rebelling against
Yahweh the most high God who created all of them and who appointed them to govern the
Nations and so this sets up
a conflict, right? Now from the pagan point of view, the gods are all fighting with each other.
From the Christian point of view, these fallen angels are rebelling against the one true God,
and that's the origin of this conflict. So obviously there's two different takes on what's going on.
As Christians, we're taking the Christian take. Like we're not going to, you know, apologize for accepting that as being the truth, right?
Right?
So, but I know that, you know, Father Stephen, in some of your research here, you have a really
interesting passage from actually an anthropologist who, if I remember correctly, this anthropologist
is not even particularly any kind of religious person himself. He's just sort of analyzing
the ancient world and its religion, right? And I thought this was an interesting, another
interesting angle on exactly the same narrative that we're talking about of early on. These,
these divine beings governing
and doing so in a way that seems peaceful and good,
and then there's this change that happens.
So why don't you go ahead and tell us about this passage
that you found in some of your research
from an anthropologist.
Right, so this is from, and I'll give the reference again
for people who want to nerd.
It's Andrew Lang's book, The Managing of Religion.
So this is a religious anthropology text.
Now this is from pages 281 and 282.
And he's talking about the transition from the worship of a Most High God to the worship
of a whole series of lesser gods and sort of the dying away of direct worship of that
Most High God in pretty much essentially all pagan cultures as a historical event that
happens in their religious development.
So it says the moral creator in no need of gifts and opposed to lust and mischief
Will not help men with love spells or with malevolent sending of disease by witchcraft
Will not favor one man above his neighbor or one tribe above its rivals and a reward for sacrifice which he's not except
Or was constrained by charms which do not touch his own evidence
Ghosts and ghost gods on the other hand in
In mid-a food and blood, a rate of spells and buying charms.
are a corrupt but to man a useful constituency. Man being what he is, man was certain to go
a horing after practically useful ghouls, ghosts, gossgas and fashas, which he could keep
in his wallet or metastas bag. For these he was sure in the long run, first to elect
his idea of a creator.
Next perhaps to reckon him is only one if the-
highest of venal rabble of spirit or gitties and to sacrifice to him as to them. This is exactly what happened.
Right. So the most high god, the reason he becomes sort of irrelevant to worshipers is that he
doesn't need anything. He's not going to be swayed by it. Right. So there's no deal they can make.
Right. So I'm not the judge of all the earth through right. You know, and you know, god is as the
your pesto it says it is not delight.
in the blood of bulls and goats. Well, if I want to get someone to follow love with me,
or if I want to curse my enemy, or if I want to get somebody on my side so that I can defeat my
neighboring tribe in war, there's nothing I could do with the most high God. But if we have our own
God and they have theirs, well, maybe I can bribe theirs into coming over to our side and letting
us land, or maybe I can get this or that spirit of the woods.
to do what I want in terms of making this person fall in love with me or a person this person.
And so it becomes sort of more pragmatically useful to shift one's devotion and attention to
these gods with whom you think you might be able to set up a quote or a quote of some sort.
Yeah. Yeah. And it's interesting, you know, I think often people think about religions
as being basically e-
Right? Well everyone has different views and everyone worships in their own way and they're all basically trying to accomplish the same thing.
But like what this anthropologist is basically saying is like, no, if your deity doesn't need anything from you, then that is a different kind of religion than one that needs you somehow. Right?
Because one where you can make deals with him and get whatever it is you want from him.
Because precisely because you're doing particular things then that creates a different kind of morality
It certainly creates a different kind of worship, right?
Whereas a deity that's above everything and doesn't need anything and is outside of everything
He can command universal
Loyalty right he can set universal moral principles
That are good because they're good right not you know and because he himself is the definition of the good
Right, so one of the-
things that this points out, you know, and it's going to become clear why we're why we're
sitting things up this way when we're talking about Halloween, okay, so just bear with us.
You know, one of the things that this points out is that the one true God, the most high
God, is a very different kind of being than these gods that are being worshipped by ancient
pagan peoples, right? That from the Christian point of view, start out as angels governing
on behalf of God the nations and then fall because they be...
to receive worship and become wicked and rebellious and of course you know fighting with one another.
You know it's a very different kind of thing. So you know like sometimes the atheist will say to
the Christian well the only difference between me and you is that I just believe in one fewer God
than you do. You know say well Christians just don't believe in other gods they just believe in
their one God but from you know what we if you listen to this show you'll know that that we believe
that there are multiple
but only one is worthy of worship,
and not only is he the only one worthy of worship,
he's quite different from the rest, right?
Who among the gods is like unto Thou, O Lord, right?
We see that kind of thing over and over again in scriptures.
So before we go to break,
which we're gonna go to in just a minute here,
let's, I wanted to read a passage here
that is from Galatians chapter four, okay?
And this is
Just following on what we're just talking about where there is this slavery that happens
between mankind and these various gods that they begin to worship and all of these vicious
animal sacrifices and even human sacrifice, right?
And there's this, the morality of the ancient world is about the strong dominating the
weak.
No one in those days when this came to be would have said that all people are valuable.
Right? There is no sense that everybody has created equal?
Swear.
There's where we're talking about
organism, the veganism.
Yeah.
Genism can be a kind of experience.
Okay. All right.
We're going to go ahead and take a break.
We're having some sound issues with with Father Stephen there,
but we will be back in just a minute.
Here is Mother Alexandra of Blessed Memory.
It seemed to me that in this modern life of ours everything has become so frightfully
methodistic.
There is a very great need of transfiguration of a change of our attitude, of our way of thinking,
our way of behaving, our way of holding ourselves.
means a new Christianization that must become more aware.
of the Christ within us.
First published in 1981 and long out of print,
the Holy Angels by Mother Alexandra has yet to be surpassed
as a comprehensive and comprehensible
account of the nature of the angels and their role in our salvation.
In lay person's terms,
Mother Alexandra presents the essence of everything
the church has to teach us about the angels,
beginning with the Old Testament,
you going through the new testament and concl-
including with the tradition of the church as expressed in her theology,
hemnography and iconography.
For those who long to become better acquainted with these holy servants of God
and to understand their role in our lives, this book is a great place to start.
Available now at store.AncientFaith.com.
Again, that is store.AncientFaith.com.
Hi, this is Father Evan Armitas.
priest at St. Spirit on Greek Orthodox Church in Luland, Colorado, and the host of the
ancient faith radio Sunday night call and show Orthodoxy live.
I am pleased to announce today the release of my first book for ancient faith publishing,
titled, Toolkit for Spiritual Growth, a Practual Guide to Prayer of Fasting and Omsgiving.
It seeks to provide a guide to the three basic and primary disciplines of Orthodox spirituality.
Through these disciplines, Christ opened for us a path that frees us from the disordered
way of life has become...
normal for many, even though their hearts and minds tell them otherwise.
Please join me in exploring the Three-Legged Stool of Orthodox Spiritual Practice, Prayer
Fasting Nomsgiving.
Books now available at store.enginefaith.com.
And the title once again is Toolkit for Spiritual Growth.
I look forward to sharing it with you.
God bless.
Now available on Ancient Faith Publishing, the Shield of Selmic Prayer, Refo...
collections on translating, interpreting, and praying the Psalter.
In this posthumous collection of poet and teacher Donald Cheehan's reflections on
Psalms and Salt McPrayer, called from his journals and teaching notes,
you will find two quite different kinds of writing working in tandem,
poetic and personal journaling by a man of faith, a scholar, a linguist,
and in the deepest sense of a teacher.
alongside scholarly linguistic and poetic analysis.
by a man steeped in poetry who thought like a poet.
Here's what Father Stephen Freeman has to say on the walk.
In the spiritual life, two things are essential,
what we do and how we do it.
And this wonderful collection of the late Donald Sheen's thoughts
on the Psalms, we see both.
He takes us into what the Psalms are in depth,
that is the Word of God,
but he also demonstrates time
and again how those deaths shaped his life in the world in which he lives. Thus we are given two
things, the Word of God, and the life in which the Word has given shape. It's a path we all should walk.
the father Andrew Stephen Damick and father Stephen DeYoung.
If you have a question, call now at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF radio.
All right, well, we're back.
We got father Stephen switched over to another audio source there, thank God.
Although I hear your dog in the background there, father Stephen.
Is that one of your dogs?
One of them...
probably was making his presence known.
Yeah, okay.
So we were just talking about, you know, morality, especially in the ancient world that
resulted from the way that these fallen angels, these fallen gods interacted with human beings,
right?
And did you want anything else to that before we talk about this little passage from
Galatians chapter four?
Yeah, well, I'm not sure when exactly I got cut out, but I was just attempting to make
the point that...
that when you look at the nature of the gods who are being worshipped with whom these
quid proclos were being formed and you have, for example, Zeus, when you believe that the
god who presides over the council of the gods is essentially a serial rapist.
Right. And that's what he is. And if there's anybody who needed to be me too, it was Zeus.
Yeah.
And what does that do to shape your view of manhood
and masculinity in your culture?
And when your view of womanhood is shaped around his wife,
Hera, who is constantly being abused and aggrieved,
and then taking vengeance in her anger and jealousy.
And the actual guy from Greek religion
who had her children taken from her.
So just bring forth monsters.
to take violent revenge.
What view of womanhood does that give to your culture?
And so while we're talking about ancient paganism
and not the modern stripe, the result of that
is as we saw historically brutal caste system slavery,
that's the cost of sort of this quid pro quo that
was set up with these spirits.
get them to do these vindictive and petty things that the worshipers wanted them to do.
Yep.
Yeah.
So, I mean, again, religions are not all the same.
They don't have the same effect on people, theology matters, what your worshiping matters.
You become like what you worship, right?
And because that that deity becomes part of your community and you become
part of its community, right? So that leads us then to Galatians chapter four, verses
three, and then also we're going to bracket it with verse nine, which reads like this,
in the same way we also, when we were children, were enslaved to the elementary principles
of the world. Listen to that, we are enslaved to the elementary principles of the world.
But now that you have come to know God or rather to be known by God, how can you turn
back against the weak.
and worthless elementary principles of the world who slaves you want to be once more.
So see Paul is saying there, if you've been listening to everything we've just been saying,
is look, back in the day, you were enslaved to these false gods. You know, they were associated with
the, as he calls them, the elementary principles of the world. I mean, that's what he's talking about.
He doesn't mean that you're enslaved to, you know, carbon and oxygen and, you know, that's not
what the element
principles of the world is, they don't think in those terms.
He's talking about spiritual beings.
And then he's saying now that you know the one true God, why would you want to go back
there?
Why would you want to be subject to them again?
Again, we're talking about this conflict that comes about because of the fall of these
angelic beings, becoming demons, becoming the gods of pagans.
Okay, so that's the basic setup for the spiritual landscape that we're talking about.
And it's what's really important when we're talking about Halloween.
You're still, I mean, some of you are probably on the edge of your seats.
Like when are they going to actually talk about Halloween episode?
But the truth is that we're so used to thinking about religion and about rituals and about
customs and practice.
in ways that kind of assume that most of the world is not spiritual or for some people, it's not at all.
So we have to kind of reconstruct, at least within our minds, the way that the world really is, the way that the world is depicted by the scriptures, the way the world is depicted in the tradition of the Orthodox Church.
So just again, bear with us, but because it takes, you know, I myself had to kind of go through some of this process and sort of...
unlearn the things that I had learned and you know, you know, relearn to learn a new way of
looking at the world which actually is the old way in a lot of ways. So, right. And the last
thing I think we should say about this, and I'm going to let you say it, Father Stephen, is you
know that there's a difference between, and you kind of alluded to this a little earlier, but there's
a difference between the way that ancient pagans described what their experience was with their gods,
and the way that modern people...
who describe themselves as pagans or neo-pagans do.
So what's the difference there between those things?
Right, and this is important because
your wicking neighbor down the road
is not doing any human sacrifices
and does not believe in a brutally oppressive caste system.
Right.
Does not believe that women are subhuman.
none of those, none of those things.
is true of that, right? So in a way, right, in a way, you can almost describe modern neopagonism,
these reconstructed paganisms as sort of Protestant paganism. And I mean that in the sense that it's a
reconstruction not just trying to go back to that rather dark world of actual ancient paganism,
Bye.
taking elements of it but formed along the lines of a general sort of
northern European cultural sensibility and morality, which is the same kind of
cultural factors that have influenced a lot of northern European and American
Protestantism. Yeah, yeah. And so yeah, we're not accusing any of those people of
any of these things that I just talked about happen.
of the ancient world. Yeah, right. Exactly. There's a big difference between that kind of religion
and what it is that people are practicing now. Right. So before we move on, I'd like to take a call.
And so we have Jacob calling from Chicago. Jacob, can you can you hear me? Yes, Father, I can.
All right. Well, Jacob, welcome to the Lord of Spirits Halloween special episode.
So what's your question or comment, Jacob?
Thanks.
much my question is and I'll try to be as quick as possible and as big as possible.
When you as a believer or a North of the X Christian have an experience where you have felt
like an evil presence as strong as you or as you are, specifically when you're alone
or in an evening time, like for example a dream and something like that happens, what
What does that mean and what would you do in
response. So for example, I actually had a personal experience recently where I woke up in the middle of the night and I had a terrible dream. It was pretty evil and I felt that presence around me still.
So I went, I went to my, you know, my prayer corner and I read the Vespers, but it wasn't even until I got to the creed where I started to feel better.
feel better and then it it it
lifted and I'm like, okay, I'm
normal now. It's 145 in the
morning. I can go back to sleep.
But it's just it struck me and I think there's meaning behind it. There's a reason, you know,
God obviously allows these things to happen. And they're rare and distinct. But the reason I'm
asking is because, you know, my father has had similar experiences and he's not North at Oxygen,
but he's interested. So I'm just kind of curious as to what, you know, what this kind of,
of what you take on this one thing.
So you're having, let me see if I can summarize what you're saying.
There's a sense of an evil presence in dreams, right?
Is that right?
Yeah, correct.
And then wake you.
That character.
Yeah, and how do you understand that?
You know, part of the difficulty, of course, in responding
to stuff like that is that it's hard to speak generally
about specific.
experiences, right? So like I can't say for instance that there is definitely a demon
affecting you or your you said it was your father. Is that was that right? That's correct. Yeah
But but certainly that is possible, right? I can say that generally speaking that it is possible
That that is the case
so
you know the you know the thing to do about that
that of course is that if, you know, as a Christian,
or as an Orthodox Christian, to make this under the cross
and to pray for God's protection, you know,
and you know, as an Orthodox Christian,
you can anoint yourself with holy water
and, you know, any negative experience that we have
should be an opportunity for repentance for us.
And this kind of underlines actually beautifully,
the difference between the Orthodox Christian
understanding of repentance and maybe some other
Christians understanding a repentance that for the Orthodox Christian repentance is not only I did
something bad and therefore I need to make up for it, right, or samsari or whatever, but rather it's
moving towards Christ, it's becoming more like Christ, right? So, you know, I can repent even if I've
I've not done anything particular bad.
And why?
Because I'm not perfect yet.
Right?
I'm.
not completely like Christ yet. So repentance is to move towards him to turn towards him again.
So even if there's not some specific evil deed I've committed. And so even when a righteous
person experiences suffering, whether it's directly from demonic affliction or something else,
he uses that for repentance. In other words, he uses to become even more like Christ, even though
know his righteous, he can become more righteous.
So for orthodox...
Christians, we have a lot of tools for this. Other Christians may not have the same kind of understanding,
but certainly they could use that disturbance as a way to draw near to God,
even if they're the only way that they're doing is maybe to ask for his protection or for his
love or for his healing. So I don't know, Father Stephen, did you want to add anything to that?
that? Well, just in the general
sense that again, we obviously
can't go into
this particular case, but it is said in our Orthodox evening prayers that we ask for protection
from the fantasies of Satan which come in the night. And that's talking about dreams.
Right.
So the key is that if you're in Christ there's not a demon out there that you need to be afraid
of.
Right.
and
Well, being sort of beings of chaos and destruction is trying so fear and confusion and this sort of thing.
So being afraid of is the exact opposite of what you should do.
And those prayers, even if they don't take away whatever particular dream experience it is,
will help you again to become more confident in not giving into that kind of
of fear and confusion that it's trying to sow.
Yeah.
Does that make sense to you there, Jacob?
It makes perfect sense.
Awesome.
I felt like that was the way that what we were going to,
that was kind of the conclusion that we were going to get at.
I mean, I think that's really encouraging.
And so thank you so much, Father.
Yep.
Absolutely.
Thank you for calling, Jacob.
All right.
Well, let's continue on in what we're talking about.
So we've
set up this basic kind of conflict between the false gods, the fallen angels, and God and his righteous ones on the other side.
And obviously this is a problem that needs to be solved, and the one to do that is Yahweh the Most High God.
So let's talk about that.
Father Steven, I see that you've got here something from one of our favorite songs, which is Psalm 82.
I think you're going to hear about Psalm 82, maybe on every episode.
I don't know, every episode here.
But yeah, it's talks on many, too.
This is such an important Psalm people.
So if you've got your Bible, open it up and take a look at Psalm 82.
Yeah, so at least at least or Psalm 81 if you're using an Orthodox study by.
Yeah, okay.
Yeah, sure.
Yeah, so this, you know, building off of what we read in Galatians, right?
St. Paul's whole take on paganism when he's talking to pagans.
You can go to act 17 and the after.
in the area of apagus, which I know is a passage near and dear to Father Andrew's heart.
Oh, yes, absolutely.
Well, Paul's approach is that most high God who you haven't known and who you haven't
been known by, as he says in Galatians, is now coming to take you back.
Right.
Not that he tossed you aside, right?
St. Paul is clear about that too.
He never tossed you aside.
Right.
wanted you back, but now he is taking you back.
And so that action of taking back the people of the nations who were sometimes translated
in English as Gentiles is related to an event that's prophesied in the Old Testament.
And that event based on Psalm 82 or 81, if you're in the Orthodox study Bible with the Greek
numbering, is called the death of the gods.
So, death of gods.
but yes, so I'll just read the whole thing because
made you to is not long. Right. God has taken his place in the council of the gods. In the midst of
the gods, he holds judgment. How long will you judge unjustly and show partiality to the wicked?
Give justice to the weak and to the fatherless. Maintain the right of the afflicted and the bestitude.
Rescue the weak and the needy. Deliver them from the hand of the wicked. They have neither knowledge
for understanding they walk about in darkness.
All the foundations of the earth are shaken.
I said, you are God's sons of the most high, all of you.
Nevertheless, like men you shall die and fall like any prince.
A rhizogad judge the earth for you shall inherit all the nations.
So this is describing a scene in which Yahweh, the God of Israel,
who presides in the counsel of the gods, the sons of God, right?
right? These these diviner angelic beings come.
into their midst and he renders judgment because he assigned something to them. And that's
the basis of this judgment. And what is that to represent the cause of the orphan in
the widow, right? To care for the weak and the poor, right? To be that kind of gentle shepherd
that Plato was describing.
Yeah, right. Right. The gods as they were. Yeah. Right. And that's not who they've been.
Right as we were just
talking about. That's not who they've been for all the nations to whom they were assigned.
And so they're getting killed. That's the true God is killing them, is driving them out.
Right. And he is taking back as an inheritance to himself. He is taking back those nations and
and those peoples to whom he had assigned them.
Yeah.
After rendering judgment against them.
Right, right.
Yeah, so it's, this is, and hopefully this blows some people's minds here a little bit,
because it blew my mind when I realized it.
This is, in fact, what the whole Bible is about.
Right, would you agree with me on that?
Yes, yeah, overall.
Yeah, yeah, not every single verse, but it's what's going on in the Bible.
and for what?
Christens, it's what's going on as Christians that God is taking back what
belongs to Him and we belong to Him. We belong to Him. That's what it means for us
to be saved, saved from what? Saved from this malevolent,
domineering, oppressing influence of these fallen angels who rebelled
against him. And you know that the last
part of that Psalm, a rhizogod judged the earth for you shall inherit all the nations. As
Orthodox Christians, we sing that on Holy Saturday, and Holy Saturday being the day before
Pascar Easter, on which we believe we ritually connect with the resurrection of Christ, a rhizogod
and judge. So he's he's arising from death and laying down judgment on these fallen gods. Right.
And this is why we are able to be saved from that's where being saved from we're not just being saved from kind of a personal
Moral failing the personal moral failings come as a result of cooperation with these beings
You know whether you know it or not every time you stand you're cooperating with them
Just as every time you do something good and holy you're cooperating with the one true God with Yahweh
so
Like I said that blew my mind when I first
realize like wait, there is a war on, and I'm caught in the crossfire here. Right?
Right. And I don't want to go too far down the Greek nerd rabbit hole, but in case some people
we actually sing the whole song because we do the other verses of the song as
stacera, as verses in between that last verse that we sing as a chorus. Right. Saturday.
Yeah.
But some people may think, well,
Okay, yeah, it says arise.
Right, that's not about Jesus rising from the dead, right?
You'll get that, right?
So, and so just to briefly mention that the verb there,
Anastee in Greek, in the Greek version of this song,
is a different verb that's then what's used
in the New Testament to talk about Christ rising from the dead.
which is usually a year old.
A.E.R.O. is the word that says Christ rises from the dead.
Right.
So this is literally to stand up again to like to take a stand, right, to judge.
Okay?
So when you see an icon for Holy Saturday of the Heroine of Hell, or when Saint Paul refers
to not to Christ rising but to the resurrection, the Anastasis, he's not just talking about
about Christ rising.
from the dead, he's saying that Christ rising from the dead is the inostasis.
It is this judgment.
Yeah.
It is this event.
Right.
So this isn't just sort of an analogy or, hey, here's a word that's similar.
Right?
Yeah.
This is a theological point that the New Testament makes.
It's Christ coming into His judgment.
just standing up to judge the fallen gods.
And you know, we got a couple, a couple more lines from the Old Testament from Isaiah 24, 21, which basically says the same thing in that day Yahweh will punish the host of heaven in the heavens and the kings of the earth on the earth.
Obviously that's not talking about the angels that are obedient. Why would he do that to them?
This is talking of the host of heaven. He's so it's clearly identifying that these are fallen angels, right?
right, the kings of the earth on the earth, that these are the rulers over the earth.
the spiritual rulers over there. It's not just, it's not talking about
presidents and politicians and, you know, princes and kings in that sense. This is,
this is a spiritual war that's on. And then, you know, also then as we begin to
sing not just on Holy Saturday, but on Posca itself, on Easter itself, Psalm 68,
one of my favorite hymns, let God arise and let his enemies be scattered and let
them that hate him flee from before his face. It's such a stunning thing to say
And
And you know, like who are the enemies that are being scattered?
These are not like unbelievers.
These are not members of other religions.
These are, you know, that's not what it's talking about.
It's talking about these rebellious angelic beings,
you know, the demons.
That's those are the enemies of God.
That's such an important thing, important point to make.
And I just want to pause in a second
and really emphasize this because sometimes Christians,
and even Orthodox Christians too,
We're no better about...
this, we act like the enemies of God are other people. They are not. They are not. Now,
they may sometimes act in a way to oppose themselves to God if they cooperate with the
enemies of God, but they are not the enemies of God. The enemies of God are these angelic
beings who from a bold declared war on him by taking from him what belonged to him, namely
worship and humanity, right? That they...
they rebel, they are the enemies of God. So a God arise and let us enemies be scattered,
let them hate him flee from before his face. That's what happens when Jesus rises from the
dead. Right? There is this conflict. There is not peaceful coexistence. Right? It is a war.
It's not like, well, you know, you know, it's doous wants to be worshipped over here, then we'll
let him do that. God is absolutely not accepting that. You know, there is a war on.
Absolutely, there's a war.
Anyway, I just wanted to emphasize that
because I think it's a really, really important point.
And it kind of, I don't know, it loosens us up
to not have to be hateful to other people,
even if they are absolutely opposed to us.
We don't have to, they're not the enemies of God.
They might be enslaved to the enemies of God,
but you don't treat your enemies slave badly
because of the way he's being enslaved, you know?
Right?
So I just wanted to kind of double down on that.
I think it was a really, really important point.
Right.
Yeah, yeah.
That's the attitude of God Himself toward these people.
Right.
God doesn't say you filthy pagans, you can go to hell with the demons you worship.
No.
Right.
The whole thing.
Christ becomes man, suffers and dies and rises again in order to set those people.
to set those
people free and bring them back to their creator because their creator loves them.
Yeah. Right. So yeah, God does not hate those people. Yeah.
He is trying to redeem them. And so it's also important that once again these beings,
who God assigned to govern the nations who he assigned and created and assigned to
to govern.
the aspects of the physical and material creation, these angelic beings, it's not that God needed them.
Like he couldn't handle it all.
Right.
No, it's his love.
It's his love having them participate in it.
Right.
He loves them.
And so he shares his rule and his authority and his creation with them.
But so when Christ arises in victory, right, when the inocencies happens
and these gods get killed.
that leaves a bunch of job openings.
Well, there you go.
All right.
So on that note then, let's go ahead and take another break.
And when we come back, we will talk about those job openings.
We'll get to Halloween.
It's about Halloween, I promise.
All right, let's go to the right.
How you could apply for those job openings.
There you go.
Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung
will be back in a moment to take your calls on the second half
of the Lord of Spirits.
Give them a call.
855-237-2346. That's 855-AF radio.
All these things, a new podcast from Ancient Faith Radio, in which Hannah Vask has offers encouragement and inspiration,
as well as practical tips to mothers as they navigate their responsibilities with all these things,
these things.
Homemaking, childcare, food,
separation, etc., while trying to stay focused on seeking the kingdom.
Being an Orthodox Christian in this world is hard and mothering is hard.
Combine it's a lot to navigate and discern.
I want to help be a guide for you in your journey toward the Kingdom of God.
That is the heart behind this podcast.
All these things, seeking the Kingdom of God as an Orthodox Christian mother,
Available now on ancientface.com slash
podcasts.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits, the father Andrew
Stephen Damick and father Stephen DeYoung.
If you have a question, call now at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF radio.
Come back everybody.
So when we completed our last segment,
Father Stephen put out a job at.
advertisement. Well, we're just sort of like headhunters over here. We're just letting
people know that there are some positions available because the Heavenly hosts are a bit depleted
as a result of the rebellion of these fallen angels. So what do you mean by that, Father
Stephen? Well, God's love hasn't changed and has desired to
share his creation and his rule and his authority and his
eternal divine life with his creations has changed. And so
there is this now this room. There's this space, right, for
for others to come in. And so what we find very quickly in
the New Testament is that a lot of the terminology that's
used to describe.
these angelic beings in the, what we call the Old Testament,
in the Hebrew Bible, starts right off the bat,
getting applied to humans in who are in Christ.
Right.
And so we talked about some of that language,
the sons of God language that was used
for these angelic leaders and authorities.
But probably the even more common one.
is the word that's translated as saints, right?
The which literally means both in Hebrew and in Greek holy ones.
Right.
So before we elaborate on that too much, I wanted to take a call from Myla.
I'm not sure if it's Milo or Milo, it's spelled M-Y-L-A, so...
Mila are you there? Can you hear me?
Mila are you on the other end of the line there?
All right, well, I'm not sure where Mila is but my note says that Mila asked is
Mila are you there? Yes, are you there?
What's your what's your question Mila?
All right, well, my understanding is that Mila is one of our young people.
Okay.
Okay. Well, Mila's question in my notes is, she asked, is Satan an angel? Is Satan an angel?
So the end, yeah, go ahead, go ahead, Father.
Well, the answer to that is he was.
was exactly right. He rebounds so he lost that job.
right? He didn't do what he was supposed to do, Mila, and so Satan was an angel, and he
rebelled against God who gave him that task of being an angel, and now he serves
himself. So he was, but he lost it because he was bad, and he permanently left,
left it behind. So Mila, I'm not sure if you can hear us, but I hope that answers
your question.
All right, well, I'm not sure we actually got her on the line, but I hope we answered
a question there.
So, all right, we'll talk about the saints, right?
And we've talked about this a lot in previous episodes, okay?
Especially the previous one, the immediately previous one, that the saints are the holy
ones of God.
And initially, in the Old Testament, that term applies to the obedient angels, right?
You know, obedience servants and we've talked about the various ranks of angels
and so forth. So if you want to know about that, you have to go back to those previous episodes.
But obviously, you know, God, it's not as you said, God is not that God is incapable of
fighting this war himself or of taking care of the universe himself. He's capable, but it's his love
that wants other beings to participate in this. And so this is given initially to the heavenly
hosts, right? But then, as we heard, as we've heard several times on this show, that is opened
than to human beings, that God is drawing in human beings to become part of the heavenly
host as well. Does that mean that we become a different species, Father Stephen?
No. No.
Yes, sure, it's not about becoming angels is kind of technically correct, because as we've
talked about before Angel is sort of a job description.
Yeah, right. Angel is pure.
messenger, that's what you do. So, it is said, humans can become angels and a human can
serve as the messenger of God. But in the sense of we don't cease to be a human person
in God this new job. And this new role and these new gifts, the adoption as sons that
we talked about last time being made a holy
one does not change the one, right? A holy man is still a man who is just now holy.
Because he's filled with the presence of God who changes the way that he exists and gives
him frankly abilities that he may not have otherwise had.
Right. And so he shares in God's holiness. And I'm not going to read all this in the notes,
But just one representative passage from the Old Testament.
this term holy ones is used in the same kind of way we've we've been talking is
in Psalm 89 verse five and verse seven let the heavens praise your wonders so
Yahweh your faithfulness and the assembly of the holy ones in the council of the
holy ones God is greatly feared is more awesome than all who surround him yeah and
I didn't read the whole song but it's very clear in the summit's talking about
in the heavens. So this isn't talking about holy people on earth.
worth yet, right? Because they're not up this guy. Right. And then I'm not going to definitely
not going to read all these. But if you talk about the word that we translate saints,
right? Holy ones being applied to humans in the New Testament. I listed probably two
dozen verse references just from St Paul. Yeah, we can't list those off. But yeah, it's
over and over again. Basically, this word that this phrase that's used, well, it's a
single word in Greek anyway. I don't know if he doesn't hear.
as well, but yes, you know, that gets used in for human beings. This word that's
for angels, for God's holy ones gets applied to human beings. So yeah, and then you
know, one of the things that's fascinating to me, for instance, is that there are
these other references in the New Testament, such as in Revelation chapter 20,
where you've got these these elders, these 24 elders, and there's references to
a third of the stars falling from heaven.
And what does that have to do with anything?
Well, as we've talked about before,
the stars are associated closely with divine beings,
and we know that a number of these divine beings
rebel against God.
And so that is appropriate then
to describe them as falling from heaven.
And there is this traditional number of 70 or 72 nations,
right?
And so.
72 elders.
72 elders of Israel.
Right.
And so if you allow.
eliminate a third of those than what the number you get is 24.
And what do you know?
There are 24 elders, human beings, redeemed human beings,
in the book of Revelation that surround the throne of God
and offer up prayer and worship to him
and the prayers of the saints, as it says,
they're in the scripture, right?
So there is why the number 24,
they're not saying that only 24 people get saved.
It's not what that means.
It is a symbolic third.
You know what I mean?
In other words, the point is not that only a certain number of people can be redeemed,
it's that the fallen angels leave the space open, like you said.
There's kind of, there's some openings.
Position is being advertised.
Human beings take the place of these fallen divine beings and do the service that they do.
So they replace.
They absolutely replace.
these fallen beings.
So.
And you have in Revelation 20 verse four,
you have the souls of the martyrs,
those who are slain for Christ,
which come alive and rule and reign with Christ.
He shares his rule and his reign in authority with them.
We've referenced this before, but Matthew 1928,
where Christ says to his disciples,
You'll sit on 12 thrones and judge the 12.
tribes of Israel, right? That's an ongoing thing. They're going to rule over the 12 tribes
of Israel. And just isn't a side. When he said that, Judas was one of the 12 standing there.
Judas did not get that throne. Sorry Calvinists. There's a slot in a job. Anyway, maybe we'll explain
that joke sometime in the future, but yeah.
All right. So you see, you see,
that sometimes I think we have weird views of the life of the world to come of eternal life.
Right? We think, well, some people think, oh, we're going to be up sitting on a cloud
playing a hard-hanging out with angels. Or they just think it's going to be like an earthly
paradise and just everything's going to be wonderful.
Yeah, yeah, like a, like a resort.
a resort where everything sparkles.
I never had the vacation, right?
And you're gonna, but that's not the picture.
The picture is that we're going to be part of God's counsel
and we're gonna be administering and ruling and reigning
over his creation.
Right.
We have jobs to do.
You know it.
Yeah.
So we had a caller in earlier and it looks like he came off the line
but we had a call from Gary.
And...
Gary asked quite outright, Gary from Texas.
He asked outright, should we even celebrate Halloween?
So I'm mentioning Gary, yeah, right exactly.
I'm mentioning Gary's call here.
So I'm sorry, Gary, if you dropped off,
I hope you're still listening.
I'm mentioning Gary's call here because this is the point now
where having stood up all of that.
I mean, I think it's really important, right?
Having set up all of that, now we're gonna actually
talk about this, okay?
So not only are human beings being invited
to divine counsel to assist God in blessing the earth, in serving as messengers, and doing
all these beautiful, positive things. But they are also being recruited into an army.
And I think, I mean, we should make a note of this. I think that we should do an episode
just on the service of baptism, right?
Which just dedicated a whole episode to
baptism, I do. Yeah, yeah. Yeah. If you look, but I'm just going to mention it here close,
here briefly. Okay. So if you look at the service of baptism in the Orthodox Church, and I can't
speak for other traditions, but if you look at the service of baptism in the Orthodox Church as
I celebrated in the Byzantine right, you know, it mentions demons and foul spirits and aerial
phantoms over and over and dragons over and over again. And it's not only is there at the beginning
an exorcism.
of these foul spirits from this person, an exorcism of these spirits from the water that they're about to be baptized in,
but then there are also prayers specifically asking that they be assigned to guardian angel,
and specifically asking that they be equipped to fight against these spirits.
Right? If you, if you ever go to North of the North of the Dachshmah service, you will hear what I'm talking about.
about. This person is being recruited into an army and given his armor and weapon.
to fight against evil spirits, to fight in this war that is going on.
It's not a metaphor, not a metaphor, and again, we're not talking about peaceful coexistence,
but again, I should say we do peacefully coexist with our fellow human beings, but we do
not peacefully coexist with demons.
We give them everything we've got.
And you know, if you've been watching our Lord of Spirits podcast, Facebook page over
last week. You'll have seen that we post
to the couple of images of saints,
you know, taking hammers.
There's a famous one of Saint Marina
or Margaret of Antioch,
hammering a demon in the head.
And then there was another one of Saint Nikita St. The Goth,
also taking hold of a demon and giving him what for.
And that's because they're doing exactly
what they were baptized to do, right?
This is our task.
If you, you know, as baptized Christians,
not only are demons exorcized from us,
like get out this
belongs to Christ, but also you're being given weapons and armor to engage in this battle.
It's not just a nice sort of initiation into church membership, it's not just a nice thing that we do
when, you know, with kids. Baptism is about recruiting recruitment into an army, into an army.
So, so this, this is what Halloween in the traditional Christian understanding is for.
That's what it's for.
Okay?
Now, I know that there's a lot of things, and I said this at the beginning, there's a lot of things that people do that go by the name of Halloween.
But from the Orthodox Christian point of view, there is, and particularly this feast of all saints, there is a purpose for this feast, and it's not just to say all of these saints aren't they great?
Isn't so nice we have scenes you know like look at these really wonderfully
people. No, no, no, no, no, no. This is this is a military parade. Okay. That is what all
saints is. It's a military parade and it's also, you know, lining up the troops to get them to go
and do battle. All right. Well, let's let's talk about this, Father Steven. Now, yeah, now,
and I hope that all of you who followed us all the way to this.
So understand why it took everything we just said in order to begin to say this.
We can't just start out, like if someone tuned in saying, now are they going to tell
me if I can go trick or treating?
That's not the point of this at all.
But welcome now.
Welcome to the Halloween episode.
All right.
Take us further in, Father Steve.
Well, we've just been saying, we've just been talking about this battle that sort of happened
with the death of the God.
that happened with the death and resurrection of Christ.
But if you've read the military history
and to all the dads out there, I know you have,
you know that the decisive battle
isn't the end of the war.
Right.
D. Day was not the end of World War II,
it was the beginning of the end of World War II.
Mm.
Right.
And so in the same way, Christ victory that he won,
that is
the decisive battle, but there's still battles, there are still battles to be fought before
this war fully comes to an end. And so the gospel, what the gospel is, what the word
gospel frankly means is the report, the report of a military victory. And so what we proclaim
when we go and we evangelize is we're proclaiming the victory that Christ has won this decisive
and we're recruiting people for the final push.
Yeah.
We're announcing to the people who have been liberated by Christ that they're now liberated
and encouraging them to now take up arms against their former oppressors.
And this is what happens.
You were talking about baptism.
When you get to the very end of the gospel of Matthew, this is the send off at the end of
the gospel of Matthew Christ.
into heaven is the great commission where he says all authority in heaven and on earth
has been given to me. So Christ has taken it back from these spiritual powers who abused
it. And he says, therefore, because that's true, go and make disciples of all nations.
Now you can go out to those nations.
Yeah, it's interesting. Think about that phrase, the great commission. I think we should
think about that more in military terms.
You're being commissioned as officers as soldiers. That's what's happening
Yeah, yeah, therefore go out and baptize all nations. So yes, so so related to each oh go ahead go ahead
Teach them all that I have commanded you. Yeah, give them their orders. Yep. Yep train them
Right. Yeah, so related to what you said about turning away from those false spirits and
joining this army. We have Brett who has been very patient.
waiting on the line from Indiana who called in almost at the beginning of the show and he's been
waiting the whole time. So Brett, this is your opportunity. Welcome to the Lord of Spheres podcast.
Hey father, how are you guys doing? Great. Great to hear from you. What's your question
in your comment, Brett? So my question is, if somebody was a former Neo-Pagan
participated in various pagan rituals offered by patients to pagan gods,
How are they?
spiritually recover from that and write themselves on a path of orthodox Christianity.
That's a great question. Excellent question. Well, I would say number one, be baptized.
Number one, be baptized, right? Because I think about everything we just said that baptism is and does.
Right? But there's more I think that they can be done. So, Father Stephen, what would you add to that?
you know to repent and be baptized.
What else?
Right.
Well, at the very beginning of the Orthodox baptismal service, there's a change of allegiance.
Yeah, exactly.
Right.
Where you reject your former allegiance, and actually, at least symbolically, hopefully,
they don't do this literally if it's inside the church building, but spit on the devil.
Or in my understanding, the more ancient ritual is simply an exhaling, a breathing out.
which is an exorcistic act. Yeah. Yeah.
Yeah.
To, you know, from him and then and then pledging their allegiance to to Christ.
So you are when a person who has been in this kind of slavery is then brought into Christ,
set free from that to live a new and different life.
life. And this is where St. Paul's
metaphors are aimed. That that
person who was a slave before that
person who did whatever they did.
That person is now dead. And a
new person has come to life.
Yeah. A new person who is
characterized by all of these
things we've been saying who is
a son of God who is a holy one
of God. All of these things are
true of them and will be
please.
true of them, as they follow Christ.
So, this is an absolute setting free,
and I think someone who's been in that kind of background,
who then comes to Christ, I think they experience that very
literally in the way that a lot of other people who may come
into the church from some other kind of background,
or some other church background, may not experience it quite
so literally as liberation.
Yeah.
I think one of the biggest things to understand
is that there is the switching of loyalties
and that Christian faith is Christian faithfulness.
So if you're, it's really obvious
if you're a pagan in the ancient world,
you stop going to the temple of Zeus or Athena or Aries
and offering sacrifices and eating them.
And now you go only to the temple of the one true God,
where again there is a sacrifice that is offered
and you eat it, right?
but that same thing applies.
to a modern neo pagan. Stop worshiping, you stop worshiping those other
guys, you stop doing that thing, right? Now there might be feelings and you know
and and all of that kind of thoughts and so forth that still have to be
wrestled with. But the key thing to do is to the faithfulness to go and to worship
Yahweh and to you know to do to to make prayers to him every day. You know it is
about this continually going back. Just like for instance if you...
If someone commits adultery, they have to turn away from that paramour and turn back to their spouse and only go towards the spouse.
That's what's going on.
And then doing that then gradually builds the love and the trust and the oneness.
Right? Does that make sense, Brett?
Yes, there it does.
Excellent.
All right.
All right, well, let's go ahead, Father.
What last little note?
No.
And this is particularly intense if you're talking to someone.
who's still in an environment where essentially ancient paganism still applies. If you're talking
to someone from India or Southeast Asia or or Sub-Saharan Africa who's in that kind of situation and who
is coming now to Christ, often they'll be afraid that the Spirit they've been worshiping,
the God they've been worshiping is going to kill them if they do. This idea of a quid pro quo and
when having made bargains and deals is very real.
and experiential.
And so that's setting free from that, the deliverance from that, and the salvation that comes
in Christ and the protection that then comes from Christ against those powers is also very
real for them.
Right.
And maybe something to add is that while someone who is going from paganism or something
like that into Orthodox Christianity, that baptism is the obvious door for them to walk through,
It's possible we're talking sometimes maybe about Christians.
who fall into that and then come back from apostasy from Christ. And it depends kind of on what
they did while they were away and where they were maybe before that. But still, there are ways to
receive that person and exorcistic acts that can be done with them, right? So I hope that helps.
It's not an easy thing to do with thoughts. You know, you might still have thoughts that are
connected to your
form a way of life, but the key is to fight against them and to be faithful to Christ, right?
Okay, so we're going to talk now about some of those specific ways that Christians
see in do battle, and what exactly that has to do with Halloween. But I have to say,
Father Stephen, I was super intrigued by an example you gave that is in December,
rather than October, November because
I thought this is a cool way of getting into this thing about Halloween in particular.
And that's because, so, you know, in the Christian calendar, December 6th is the Feast of
St. Nicholas, you know, who's the beloved Santa Claus, you know, but but an actually an
ancient Christian saint, a bishop in what is now Turkey, and one of the most popular saints
in the world, probably the best known saint in the world after the Virgin Mary maybe.
But there is this tradition amongst Germanic peoples in northern Europe.
of something the night before.
So what is that, Father Steven?
The eve of Satan.
Well, I believe the way I broke it to you was,
I messaged you and said,
hey, what do you know about Krampus Noct.
Right, Krampus Noct.
I know.
As soon as I saw that, I'm like,
nothing but the name is really bringing me in.
Yeah.
Krampus.
So, noct of course is German for night or evening.
Right.
So the night of cramp it.
So this is the eve of St. Nicholas Day as it's celebrated in
Kampus is primarily Austria, Germany, the German lands, but there are sort of
variations of this in the Netherlands or my ancestors are from and in other
other Germanic countries, but
Crampus is who is now labeled as a demon
was a demon in the other sense before the coming of Christianity to the Germanic lands.
Right. He was a local god and a forest god, right? Yes. He was a a pagan forest spirit who was
worshiped worshiped by the people there. Yep. And in current practice,
This campus is at St. Nicholas Day, that he is enslaved and overpowered by
Nicholas. Again, we're not talking peaceful coexistence here. Right. And St. Nicholas
sort of overpowers him and enslaves him and takes control of him. What sort of allows
him to afflict the wicked, right? The people who have been bad, especially the children
who have been bad over the past year are, in a lot of cases, it's being beaten with
birch rods. I think we have birch rods are the worst things to be beaten with, but apparently
they are.
And you know, when we're talking about this, of course, for fans of the office, that comedy TV show from NBC, which takes place actually just north of where I live, not too far up in Scranton.
There is a character on their name Dwight who introduces one Christmas a figure named Belschnickle
and if I'm not mistaken, Belschnickle is essentially a very similar kind of figure.
right? But there's, but what's interesting is that some of the, you know, we've got this
naughty and nice idea with Santa Claus. And Belch Nickel has this kind of naughty and nice,
although the way that Dwight puts it is, have you been admirable or impish?
Admiral or impish? But if you've been impish, he beats you with the, as you said, what is it,
Birchrods? Yes. Yeah. Well, the, the impish is actually very, very kind of tough because,
in all of these traditions, cramp it.
or black Peter, as he's called in the Netherlands,
or Belch Nigo, are assisted by these assistants
who, Krampus' assistants are imps.
Yeah.
So, yeah.
And some little Kramp-I.
So, what's happening with these customs?
And sometimes people put on costumes
and they dress up as Krampus,
and they, you know, get dragged along
by a St. Nicholas figure, right?
They've been enslaved.
The point of this is its rich...
participation in the defeat of demonic beings, you know, so that we essentially can do the same kind of thing connected with these Christian feast days.
Right. Right. And so having painted that picture now, we can understand where some of the customs surrounding Halloween come from.
Now again, people have a lot of opinions and you can find a gazillion websites out
they're telling you the quote unquote truth about Halloween. But a lot of what's going on in Halloween
is exactly this kind of mocking and defeat of death and of demonic beings. That's part of what's
happening. And even in the Orthodox Church, so the Orthodox Church, I sometimes will say happy
Halloween to that Saturday before all saints, which is usually in June, and people kind of laugh
nervously like wise father Andrew
saying happy Halloween in June. But the reason is that, right, you know, the
Feast of all Saints in the Orthodox Church, for instance, it has this him.
I'm just going to read a part of it. This is from Vespers of all Saints. So Vespers
of all Saints would literally be Halloween in the Orthodox Church. It's the
night before all Saints, the night before all Hallows, okay? So it includes
this hymn. It's talking, it's speaking to the saints. Indeed, you have...
fulfilled the sayings of the Savior for through ye, through you the gates of
Hades open against the church have been closed and your shed blood dried up
the libations of idols and having nourished the perfection of believers through
your slaughter, you dazzled the incorporeals, that's the angels, standing
before Christ, wearing your crowns, wherefore intercede ye ceaselessly with him
for our souls. In other words, it says that the saints ended the worship of
idols ended the worship of these gods and that they obey.
the things of Christ and they even amaze the angels, right? And they stand before Christ
wearing their crowns and they intercede with Christ just as the angels the angelic beings do with us.
So again, it's about this defeat by demonic powers, you know, the saints defeating the demonic
powers and we participate in that. Now, we don't participate just by like dressing up and doing
these things where you see St. Nicholas, you know, with with crampus being dragged.
after him in a chain, that's not the only thing.
It's not only this sort of costume act, right?
We also defeat the demons in a lot of other ways.
We talked about, of course, baptism.
In January, in the Orthodox Church,
we have our homes, our churches,
and our homes and anywhere else
that the priest has led in blessed.
Right, the priest comes in with holy water
throws it around.
everywhere. This is an exorcistic act. It's an exorcistic act. And I just want to add here, I know I'm
kind of on a roll here, but I just want to add that when we do these, these are all the same act.
It's about driving out and defeating demons, okay. When we do these things, it's because this is
real, there is a war on. Now, if you understand that, that's the case, then it would never be the case
that as like I was a pastor for 11 years and I would occasionally have people say
No, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, not that.
You know, let's just wait,
let's just do the house buzzing next year.
You know, I just,
it's just not, I can't get it clean
or it's just not a convenient time
or whatever, whatever, whatever.
Like, so you're saying,
let's just go ahead and delay driving out
the demons for a year.
Like, are you really okay with that?
Like if you understand that's what's happening,
then you would never just make it a,
oh well, let's, you know,
let's, we could take care of that later, right?
And, but if you think about it,
then also your prayers at home,
Like, like no, today...
We're not gonna just say, you know, well tomorrow we will, you know, we'll drive out demons from our home.
You know, like it doesn't just change the whole way you understand what the Christian life is about.
I said in one of our places online. I said, you know, every house is haunted.
You know, change my mind. Well, you're not gonna change my mind. Every house is haunted. Every place is haunted.
because these evil forces are present in every place and it's our
our job as Christians to go and to drive them out.
And that's why I was kind of so frustrated
when we started talking about this episode,
when like there was one person,
even just the other day,
who was kind of demanding of me on Twitter,
like, well, do you bless your parishioners
to go trick or treating?
Do you take your children out trick or treat?
Like, that's what they wanted to talk about.
And I'm like, you know what?
If that's what you think that is really important,
God bless you, but it's super not.
You know like you know, really
Really, I mean, for the record, my kids don't go trick or treating, but that's not because,
I believe that collecting candy from your neighbors is participation in an occult ritual.
It's because it's just kind of too gruesome out there on the streets on that night for me to want
my kids. I mean, I have small kids. That's really what it comes down to for us. So, I don't know,
that's kind of a monologue. But...
Yeah, so well to re-oriented this a little yes
not that I disagree with anything you just said.
Oh, thank God.
And being honest, actually, we're gonna go to break here
just a second, but yeah, go ahead and say what you're gonna say.
So to be honest, in terms of how the early Christians
saw what they were doing, right?
Christ has accomplished D-Day, right?
The victory has happened, right?
The war is effectively over.
But that doesn't mean it's over.
Now he sends out his disciples
and they send out their disciples
and they send out their disciples into the world
in order to route the enemy, to chase him down,
right, to push him out of every stronghold
and every place that he has.
As that happens, as that happens,
our fathers in the faith come into Europe.
They come into pagan Europe.
And when they come to pagan Europe, they find these people who just like the pagan Roman
centuries before are enslaved by these demonic spirits.
And so they come and they proclaim the victory of Christ, they bring these people over, they
free.
And then the rap that you hear all over the place, the rap that you hear all over the
places that well the Christian
were basically, you know, selling AMway. They're basically recruiting.
Right. It's not this spiritual warfare, but they're just recruiting. And so they decided it
would be easier for them to get pagan recruits if they let them keep. Right. And they'll even try
to attribute this to the letter that St. Gregory the Deologist, St. Gregory the Great, the Bishop of
of Rome, sent to St. Augustine, the one in England, not the one in here.
like, oh, well, this will just make it easier for them.
Yeah.
That's a complete misread of what happened and of that letter.
Right.
Here's what actually happened.
That first generation of pagans experienced, just like we've been saying, being set free by Christ,
having their lives transformed and being set free.
And the defeat of those demonic towers who had enslaved them.
and so, and so the church
in her wisdom says, future generations need to celebrate this liberation. They need to
celebrate and ritually participate themselves in the defeat of those powers that enslaved
them, in their freedom from that bondage and that slavery. And it is an a way just like
the Jewish Passover.
Yep.
In which Yahweh judges.
is the gods of Egypt. That's what he says he's about to do.
Judges the gods of Egypt frees his people.
That generation experienced it literally.
Future generations experienced by ritual participation
in eating the Passover.
And so these holidays like Krampus Noct,
like all Hallows Eve,
all of these are essentially
little European Passover's
where if properly understood.
Right? If you don't forget about the All Saints part and just go trick or treating for
Halloween. If you don't, you know, forget who St. Nicholas was and just have a really
metal winter celebration in your campus outfit with the chains. Right? Or you don't do that.
You could experience that freedom that your ancestors experienced.
Yeah. Yeah. And the men of the Saints came and as I said in the speech, these spirits had
set them free.
And the mistake that some people
make is they essentially go join the other side again. Like that's what like
we do boards and sances and and that kind of thing are about. They're they're
taking it they're they're they're they're reversing it for themselves. They're
going back to Egypt and being enslaved by those gods again. Right. And that's
exactly what St. Paul said is we read in Galatians. Why do you want to go back now in
slavery? Exactly. Exactly. All right. Well, we are going to go now for our final
break and then
When we come back, we are going to take your questions
and then we are going to wrap up.
So we'll see you back in just a minute.
Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung
will be back in a moment to take your calls
on the second half of the Lord of Spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF radio.
Hi, this is Father Evan Armitoss, priest at St. Spirit on Greek Orthodox Church in Lulang, Colorado.
In the host of the Ancient Faith Radio, Sunday Night Call and Show, Orthodoxy Live,
I am pleased to announce today the release of my first book for Ancient Faith Publishing.
Title, Toolkit for Spiritual Growth, a practical guide to prayer fasting and arms giving.
It seeks to provide a guide to the three basic and primary disciplines of Orthodox spirituality.
Through these disciplines Christ opened for us a path.
that frees us from the disordered way of life has become normal for many, even though their
hearts and minds tell them otherwise.
Please join me in exploring the three-legged stool of Orthodox spiritual practice, prayer,
fasting, and non-sgiving.
Books now available at store.ancientfaith.com.
And the title once again is Toolkit for Spiritual Grove.
I look forward to sharing it with you.
God bless.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits, the Father-Andre Steven.
and Father Stephen DeYoung.
If you have a question, call now at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF radio.
Welcome back, everybody.
Now for the final segment of our special mega
Mando bonus Halloween episode.
And I just...
The fourth half.
Yeah, the fourth half of this show, exactly.
You know, and the initial concept...
of this show, it was good of this show where we first started.
It was that the idea was to be about an hour long.
We've never gone just an hour, but that's okay.
We know you love it.
And I should also say,
I've heard sometimes people say,
like, why do you guys laugh when you're talking about demons
and stuff?
It's not because we think they're a joke,
like that they don't exist or they don't matter.
It's really, I mean, if I could just put it this way,
it's kind of the joy of battle, honestly, right?
It really kind of is.
So.
We are very serious about all this. Okay. It's alright. Well, we've got a call
from Anthony who is calling from West Virginia. So Anthony, can you hear me?
Anthony, are you there? All right
God bless you. Welcome to Lord of Spirits. I'm glad you finally got through after waiting on the line for an hour
Okay, here is I was just listening to the podcast and
Um, so there wasn't any time wasted.
Thank God.
So sorry, I'm a little out of breath.
I had to take the dog out and I was hoping I couldn't miss the call.
Oh, you made it.
I did just barely.
I got back in just as you were saying my name actually.
Oh man.
Okay.
Well, what's your question or comment there, Anthony?
So my question, sorry, it's not very Halloween related.
Bye.
In the book of Tobit, toward the beginning there you meet Sarah and she has this demon that
it's been a little while since I read the book so I can't remember exactly the phrase but I feel like it says something like the demon is in love with her.
But he's definitely attached himself to her in some way and you know she's like tormented by this demon for quite a while
until Tobias comes in.
does the whole incense thing that the St.
Rothfiles told them to do with decision, everything.
So the question is, what is that relationship that the demon
thinks?
Like, what is he getting out of that relationship
with being attached to Sarah?
And how often does that sort of thing happen?
Is that a common thing?
Yeah.
All right.
Well, Father Steven, I'm going to let you take that one,
because I think you'd probably know this a lot better
than I do.
Yeah.
Okay. So yeah, and in fact, in fact that demon in the book of Tobit is like murdering all
of her suitors. Right. In the book of Tobit. Yeah, so the reality is that this kind of paganism,
this kind of demonoletry, right? Demon worship is a relationship, not a religion, right?
Yep, in a lot of ways.
that quid pro, what we've been calling a quid pro core,
these agreements entered into, that's a real thing.
The bondage and slavery we're talking about
is a real personal thing, right?
It's not just, sometimes I think when we say that,
people taking bondage metaphorically,
like we're talking about bad ideas or something,
that are making you depressed
or not achieve your full potential.
That's not what we're talking about.
We're talking about literal slavery.
oppression. And so usually when you have that kind of demonic activity, and it's not always
spelled out in the Bible, like we don't find out how Legion got into that man, what exactly
he did. But it's not that people, you know, very pious people who are seeking to follow
Christ are walking down the street one day at Sunlady, they get demon-fossessed.
Yeah.
Right. This is something that takes place over time through a series of interactions
and trade-offs and relationships and then...
point people really all
slaves and bonded and attached
to this kind of spirit. And it's
not a pleasant thing, right?
It may seem that way at the
beginning, because otherwise
no one would do it. But once
you're down that road, it is
oppressive. And you are
tormented as she was in
in Tobit. And you long to be
free of it. And this is the
experience I was talking about
with some some people you'll
Some people you'll find
in India or in Southeast Asia, in Sub-Saharan Africa, where they think that if they try to break
this connection, now they'll, the demon will kill them.
You know, the spirit will kill them or the god they've been wishing will murder them,
or their family or something. And so this is power that a person has given to that spirit.
right important point. Yeah, and then and then the you know the thrust.
of course, of Tobit is that, you know, Tobias comes and St. Rafael comes and
set her free. Set her free from it. And I won't go further than that in terms of
connections to baptism and other things that take place there and the cleansing
of his sets. But I've got Bible studies on Tobit somewhere that you can listen to.
There you go. So does that help? Does that help Anthony?
It does, but if I can.
to clarify this story in
and to that is we kind of
only are getting the last
half of that story.
There must have been
something before there for
Hertz invite that sort of
thing is what you said.
Right.
Yep.
All right. Well, thank you very
much for that Anthony.
We're going to take one more
call.
So Linda, you are our final
caller.
So Linda from Georgia.
Can you hear me?
Yes.
Yes, I can.
hear you father. All right Linda what is your question or comment welcome to
the Lord of Spirits. Well thank you for taking my call. I'm a history buff and I
have listened to you both before. I was looking at something the other night of
history magazine that I subscribed to on Medieval History and it actually
mentioned and it was the day of the feast day of Saint Dmitrius the great
martyr and it was actually talking
about Demetrius and how he has celebrated at least in some countries, it's with the change
of the seasons around this time.
And I guess in ancient times it had to do with the wrapping up of the military campaigns
for the summer and fall, winter was coming.
And then I started thinking about the name Demetrius.
I thought wait, didn't need her, the Greek goddess and the changing of
with her, the whole story about her daughter Persephone being abducted, winter, spring coming.
And so I started thinking about, you know, if you look at some of our saints, if you scratch
just below the surface, there's a connection there, I say with paganism.
I'm trying not to do it.
I mean, I'll close it off.
I think I know what you're saying, Linda, and I would say...
And I'm sure Father will have a bunch of things add to this.
But I would say that, you know, just like
Krampus, Noct or Halloween or any of these other things,
this is not a connection in the sense of like, well,
pagans are doing this thing and we want to try to recruit them
and so let's give them instead of, instead of Demeter,
we're going to give them Saint Demetrius.
Yeah, we're going to invent a saint who, wow,
has a name that's very similar and we'll kind of, you know,
Do you see that?
some of the same kind of things, and about there'll be Christian versions. That's not what's happening.
There is a deliberate defeat, right, of those spiritual beings by the saints, right?
So, Saint Dmitrius now is clearly the person whom God has assigned to the city of the Svaniki
in Greece as its protector. And on his feast day, I mean, he's a real person, like he's not a story.
They take out his actual relics, his actual body.
which I visited and venerated actually a couple of years ago,
they take out his body and they carry it in procession
around Thessaloniki as an act of exorcism and protection.
Again, this is not just sort of adapting in something pagan.
This is about stomping on something pagan, right?
It's very deliberate and Dmitrius is a real martyr
who was put to death in the early years of the church
And now is the spiritual...
the city of the Soneke, which is why they love him there so much.
So, I don't know, Father Stephen, do you want to add anything to that?
Well, yeah, with names, we have to sort of always take into account the fact that a lot
of these early Christian saints and martyrs were converts to Christianity, and so they
would have been given pagan names by their parents.
Yep.
I mean, Saint Dionysius theoreopogite would be exhibit A, who's named after the God Dionysus,
right?
But we have we have saints with pretty much every
taken God name. There is. There's even a state. There's even a state
Plato. Yep. Was was named after the philosopher. But then became a Christian and
you know became a saint. So we can't read too much into the names. Plus I mean
if I want to really nerd out, the mysteries of Demeter were centered at
Corinth rather than that that's the le deke. But that's the le deke had a spirit
that was worshipped under the name Afra Daiti,
that dominated it.
And through his victorious martyrdom,
St. Demetrius defeated her and booted her out,
and took her place as the person in Christ's administration
who is sharing in his role and reign over
the city of Thessaloniki and became its patron.
So, and this is a really good segue
into what we're gonna talk about on the next show in two weeks.
Yes.
So you're tracking with us,
They're trying with us there in Georgia.
And it's not just a storm that tracked from Louisiana through Georgia.
Yeah.
Well, it was just a connection that I kind of saw.
And they talked about in that article, Demetrius even writing a horse and that's writing
into the otherworldly, I guess, aspects of things.
And then I thought about Demetrius Saturday with the commemoration of the dead and all of
this stuff around this time at Halloween.
So thank you.
Welcome.
Welcome. Well, thank you very much everyone for calling.
We just want to take a minute to give some summary marks.
And I'm going to ask my co-host, Father Steven,
to go first.
Yeah, I think the core of what we've
wanted to get across and talk about tonight
is that, contrary to what sometimes our Protestant friends
we'll say about the traditional Christian view of...
of the saints where they'll say,
oh, well, this is a pastiche for paganism.
They're just sort of replacing the pagan gods
in popular worship.
Then it's just sort of this shift of ideas,
and at the veneration of the saints
must just be worshiped the same way
that the pagan gods were worshiped.
Over against that, we're saying that the replacement
of the pagan gods by the saints
is not an intellectual flip
or some kind of change of doc.
But is a historical event that happened in history, just as surely as any other historical
event, the battles in World War II that I mentioned.
It is just as real as those that Saint Demetrius replaced the spirit that was worshipped as
Aphrodite.
This was played.
And just as the angelic beings to whom God assigned governance over his creation.
the sort of vice-regions were not to be worshiped, but they were to serve and to guide and to
shepherd people to the true and living God, the Holy Trinity, in the same way, the saints now,
those righteous men and women who have gone before us who have been adopted as sons of God,
who have become holy ones of God in part of God's divine counsel, are now governing the earth,
and they are not worshiped, but they assist God in bringing
a
us to him and to the true worship of the most high God, the Holy Trinity.
Well, for my closing comment, I wanted to expand a little bit on something I said earlier.
I talked about having the priest come to your home to bless it in January, which we in
the Orthodox Church do, connection with the Feast of theophanie, the baptism of Christ.
Theophony, of course.
you see in many Theophany icons Christ stepping on dragons in the water or sometimes water gods or sometimes both
You know, this is his defeat of those spiritual beings right and
We participate in that by being baptized but by also taking that holy water and spreading it throughout creation including in our homes
Everywhere that we can outdoors indoors or ever
ever.
Because you know the thing that Father Stephen was just describing the saints
defeating these
Demonic powers
That's what we're supposed to be doing ourselves. That is our job
That is our commission
Right, it's not this Christianity is not a spectator sport
Right, we are here to trample upon the the
the false powers, the demons, the fallen angels.
And if you understand that that's what the Christian life is, right?
When you say your prayers in the morning and at night, when you say prayers over the things
that you eat, when you have the priest come to your home to bless it, when you are baptized
and your children are baptized, when you come to church and receive the very bottom blood
of Christ into yourself, when you turn away from the sins that are participation in the
works of the evil one.
When you do any of those things, you are driving out the influence of these foul spirits.
And they are as afraid of it as they are the mightiest of scenes because you're not invoking
your own power.
It's not your power.
You are invoking the power of Christ and His cross.
And when they see that sign of the cross, they flee.
Some people ask, what do you do if you encounter a demon?
What do you do if you encounter the feeling of an evil presence?
What do you do?
There's a lot of things you can do.
All the things I just mentioned, but in the moment, especially, you make this side of the cross,
and you give praise and worship to Christ, because that is the worship that they have attempted to steal for themselves,
and they cannot stand to be in the presence of the worship of the one who is worthy of worship.
There is only one worthy of worship, and that is Jesus Christ, our one and true God.
And so my prayer is that, you know, whatever...
Remember it is that you and your wisdom choose to do related to this American celebration
of Halloween, but more importantly, all of the other things that we do as Christians
that you do it in an exorcistic way, that you are there to do battle with these real
demons, understanding that that is the Christian life.
You have been recruited into an army and so get out there and fight.
You're not alone.
not alone you have the power of Christ if you are faithful to Him.
and you invoke him continuously.
So thank you so much everybody for joining us
for this special episode of The Lord of Spirits.
That is our show for today.
If you didn't get a chance to call in
during the live broadcast, we'd love to hear from you
either via email at Lordofspiritsatinchandfate.com
or you can message us at our Lord of Spirits podcast
Facebook page.
We read everything, but we can respond to everything
Go.
we get a whole lot and we do
save what you send for possible
use in future episodes.
Join us for a lot of broadcasts
on the second and fourth Thursdays
of the month at 7 p.m. Eastern 4 p.m.
Pacific. Don't forget to like our
Lord of Spirits podcast Facebook
page. Join our Facebook group and
while you're at it, leave a
recommendation and invite your friends.
And if you leave a review on Apple
podcasts, Facebook or wherever you
get your podcasts, then that raises
the visibility of this show and
gets more people connected.
And finally, be sure to go to www.engserfake.com-support
and help make sure we and lots of other AFR podcasters stay on the air.
Thank you and may God bless you and the angels in Saint Stan beside you.
You've been listening to the Lord of Spirits with Orthodox Christian priests,
Father Andrew Stephen Damick, and Father Stephen DeYoung,
a listener supported presentation of ancient faith.
video.
And I be held and I heard the voice of many angels round about the throne and the beasts
and the elders, and the number of them was 10,000 times 10,000, and thousands of thousands
seeing with a loud voice worthy as the land that was slain to receive power and riches
and wisdom and strength and honor and glory and blessing.
Revelation chapter 5 verses 11 through 12.