He will be a staff for the righteous with which for them to stand and not to fall, and
he will be the light of the nations and the hope of those whose hearts are troubled.
All who dwell on the earth will fall down and worship him, and they will praise and bless
and celebrate with song the Lord of Spirits, 1st denoc, chapter 48, verses 4-5.
The modern world doesn't acknowledge, but is nevertheless haunted by spirits, angels,
demons, and saints.
In our time, many year into break free of the prison of a flat, secular materialism, to
see and to know reality as it truly is.
What is this spiritual reality like?
How do we engage with it well?
How do we permeate everyday life with spiritual presence?
Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew Stephen Damick,
and Father Stephen De Young,
host this live Colin show,
focused on enchantment in creation,
the union of the scene and unseen as made by God,
and experienced by mankind throughout history.
Welcome to the Lord of Spirits.
Welcome back to the Lord of Spirits podcast.
I am Father Andrew Stephen Damick in Emeas, Pennsylvania,
and my co-host Father Stephen De Young
with me from Lafayette, Louisiana. So unlike most of our episodes, this one, like the previous one,
actually is pre-recorded because when this one airs, Father Stephen is going to be at a retreat,
last time I was at a retreat. So if you call, you're not going to get anyone on the other end,
but we should be back again live in the future. As you hear this, I will be in Tennessee,
the Greenest State in the land of the free. Well, it is Monster Month here on the Lord of
Spirits Podcast and we're going to be focusing on Biblical and other monsters for both of our episodes here in October.
For tonight's episode we're going to be talking about gigantic
demonic monsters like Leviathan and Behemoth,
but also some assorted and related spiritual beasts that we see in apocalyptic biblical texts.
First though, Leviathan. I think the question that most people would probably start with is this,
is the Bible saying that there is some kind of gigantic sea dragon swimming around
in the ocean. Yes, yes. I knew it. So yeah, I mean was I remember watching the
movie The Abyss and I was like okay I know it's gonna be here at some point
there's a gotta be it but no there was no dragon. Yeah, no, no there yeah you
We kind of get that in Pacific Rim a little bit.
I mean, they're technically dragons, Kaiju, close enough.
So yeah, so we're going to be talking about Leviathan, this particular sea monster here
in the first half.
And so we're going to be talking a little bit about him or her.
And we will be also sort of disambiguating from other sea monsters as we go.
Right.
There's a lot of things crawling down under there.
Lots of Oak critters.
Yeah.
So the one we're talking about Leviathan is Leviathan is the sort of standard English
translation of the Hebrew Luyetan, which the actual
Semitic root, right, if you know a little bit about any of the Semitic languages,
they all have a trilateral root, they have three consonants that are sort of the root
of the word. And it's L-T-N equivalent in this case. So you get Lotan in some
places in some dialects.
You, Ugrinic, you have Littanu.
Though that comes at the end of a big,
long academic argument about how to correctly pronounce
the Ugrinic version of the name.
Because that's what we do for fun.
Yeah, and we don't have any, you know,
Ugrinic people around to let us know
how it's supposed to be.
How they would say it.
But everyone now has settled upon Littanu
for the agreement.
And all of those, what they sort of mean
is the twisting one or the riving one.
And that is obviously a vocative of a sort of sea serpent
type of creature.
Right.
Yeah.
And you know, I mean, I was going to say,
and that's connected.
I mean, there's a lot of sort of serpentine imagery
from the ancient world that emphasizes this idea,
which is connected with being twisted in the way
that you talk, being a liar,
it brings up Genesis 3, the serpent in the garden.
So the idea of being twisty and being a serpent
and being shifty and evil, this is totally a thing.
But we're not talking about all of those images together,
but this particular one.
And not even every, as you said, every kind of snake in the water,
but this particular one, right?
Yeah, who is sort of emblematic of that, right?
That is its emblematic feature.
So like when we say liturgically, oh, good one,
we're not just saying, like, ah, he's pretty good, right?
Yeah.
We're saying, you know, this is the one who is truly good, right?
And same kind of idea here.
This is the one that is truly twisting and riving and subtle and slippery.
The twisted one of those things, right?
Right. Right. Yeah.
Okay.
So to help us to help us begin to disambiguate exactly what we're talking about, we
actually, even though this this episode is pre-recorded, we are going to quote,
take some calls, but they're all pre-recorded calls.
So we have one and this was submitted by Steve who has this relevant thing to say.
Greetings, fathers. This is Steve from Grand Rapids, Michigan. First, I just wanted to say thank you for the show.
I've been curious about and have felt drawn to orthodoxy for many years, but this podcast finally let the fire in me to actually go and
participate. So thank you for that. My question is about Yam, the Hebrew word for C. I took some biblical Hebrew way back in the day at a very liberal
liberal arts college. The professor loved to try and scandalize the students by pointing out all the places
modern translations demythologized the text. I never quite had enough of a
grid for how to deal with his critiques, but thanks to this podcast and also
shout out to Jonathan Pigeot as well, I now feel like I do. One of my
professor's favorite examples was what he called Yam the Seagod. It seems that
anytime the text would say the word Yam, he'd wink and eye and kind of chuckle
to himself. So I'm curious about the connection between Yam, the word for C, and
and more explicit references to Leviathan and Bechemis.
Is every reference to the sea a reference on some level to these lesser gods?
Thanks. Love the show.
All right, so okay. So he mentions Yom.
Yom has been mentioned on this podcast before.
What's the deal? How does Yom relate to?
Is every reference to the sea a reference to the God of the sea?
Yom or in, you know, how does this connect to Leviathan?
Right. And despite spelling, Yam has no connection to sweet potatoes.
Yes, disappointing. Also disappointing. Yeah. Y.A.M. Yam.
So he is right that Yam, the word that's just used for the C, is also the word for this sort of primordial.
What is in the bail cycle the previous most high god this chaos force?
Yeah
But that I mean that's that's common right in the ancient Near East right?
Sure is just the word for Sun and it's also the Sun God right?
I mean, gosh is moon and moon God and you know and as we've emphasized before on on this show
You know, Hades is the place and the God who rules it or you know hell
in Germanic mythology. So I mean you could understand why someone might think, okay, every time this word is mentioned, is it supposed to be a voking this notion of the God who rules it or is in it?
Right. And this brings us back to the concept that we kind of broached last time about the way
epistosis is used to describe ancient gods in general. Right. We're most used to that.
So before you freak out about me using it this way here, go back and listen to the last
episode if you haven't. Yeah, please. Because there are continuities and discontinuities with
how it gets used by the church fathers in terms of the doctrine of the Holy Trinity
and how it's used when we're talking about ancient gods.
It's not completely different, but there are significant differences.
So, and when we're talking about pagan gods, probably the key word we need to remember
in terms of that is the idea of embodiment.
the idea of something serving as sort of a body or a localization or an instantiation
of that spirit.
Yeah, so if you're in the water on some level, you're interacting with Yom from the point
of view of, you know, Semitic paganism, right?
Right, in the sea, right.
Yeah, yeah.
And so, if they're going, they didn't really go out to sea.
They said they're pretty close to the land at this point in history.
Yeah, they're both going to go too far.
Yeah.
But, yes, so if you're a pagan and you're doing this, you're going to be offering before
you go your sacrifices and your rituals related to dag on slash Poseidon slash Yam, slash
whomever, right?
To sort of try to be friendly, make friends, right?
So that when you're out there, then you'll be safe.
And not to go, we're not going to go down this rabbit trail, but this is sort of what's
at play when Jonah gets caught in the storm at sea and all the pagans are praying to their
gods.
Right.
To try and figure out, like, hey, try yours.
Which one did we make angry?
That's so, but so this, what we would call the material C, right, the Mediterranean is
what we're really talking about in this case.
They would say that is an embodiment of Yom, the same way, you know, the Egyptians would
see the solar disk in the sky as one embodiment of Ray. And so when in Egypt when the worship of
Amun as such the solar disk itself as such sort of comes to the four later on, it's still often
referred to as Amun Ray in the text. It's not they don't see it as a different God they see it as
where we're worshiping this particular localization
or instantiation of that spirit.
Right.
So all of that said, this that gets us to the relationship
between Yom and Litanu to stick with the ugaritic language
and names.
So in their understanding, Yom has a whole bunch of dragons.
Right. Who are sort of one of the ways in which he sort of projects his will and activity
into the world. And so they sort of represent, you could use the word, hypostasis, they
represent different sort of aspects of Yom as they go out into into the world. And so
L'Itano in particular or Leviathan sort of represented his destructive power.
So would they power like his might?
Would they make reference then to L'Itano Yam or I don't know what order they would put it in?
But they would yeah, yeah, yeah.
It would be like it would be a possessive Yam's L'Itano.
Okay, gotcha.
The way we would talk about Bob's strength.
Right.
Because that Bob, he's a tough guy.
So, we're not sure where he's worshipped, but somewhere.
Oh, there's a cult of Bob, I'm sure.
So, until this is why this sort of comes up, of course, in the first big struggle in
the bail cycle is bail versus YAHB, right, in his sort of revolution of the gods against
the previous most high god. And so in the process of him defeating YAHB, he defeats
Litanic. He defeats Leviathan. Right. Right. He overcome his power and his might. Right,
so you break him down a piece at a time. Right. You've got to defeat all the foot soldiers
before you go up against the boss at the end of the level.
Right. Right. Yeah. Yom is the end boss. Yeah. But there's also it's a little different
than that in that Yom isn't seen as totally separate. Yes. Right. So to defeat all of these
dragons. Yeah. To defeat all of these dragons is to defeat Yom. Right. Right. So yeah.
So it's a little yeah. There's a little subtlety to it. But um, and this is this is lost by
the way on most folks like the professor we just heard about, right, who tend to look
at, you know, ancient quote unquote mythology through the clash of the Titans lens of, you
know, Zeus yelling release the crack in, right? Like, but these are just these creatures
and these beings and stuff and they basically, we've talked about this before several times,
they should pay against, there's these primitive screw heads
who don't know anything.
Yeah, right.
Right, I mean, I think it's worth revisiting
this question, because I mean, I started out
with this sort of idea, is there a dragon in the water?
I can, in the abyss, they go down there,
and there is not that they're looking for one,
but that there isn't something there,
or just like, you know,
or they had diving.
Yeah, yeah, or Yuri Gagarin goes up in a space
and says, I didn't see any god there.
And that's one of the problems is there's this sort of materialist reading of ancient religion
which looks at these beings and says, well, I just, you know, the way I conceive of, you know,
Zeus, whoever is basically just a big human that's really powerful or whatever. And I didn't see
any of that, so there must not be any Zeus, you know. Or, you know, I, we took a submarine down into
into the water and we didn't see any dragon there, so there must not be one. But even though
that's the imagery that's used in ancient paganism depicts these things, you know, as images,
right? As something you can see or describe or look at, that's not the way that people actually
interacted with the idea. It's not like they went out there and they're like, oh, I bet there's a
see serpent down there. Look, look, I can see it. You know, there's, it's, it's, it's rather that
there's the experience that they have of it. And then this is the kind of language that they use
to describe it because it's kind of indescribable. Right. Right. And they looked at the sea and
the sea is in motion. Storms come off of the sea. The sea swallows people up and kills them.
Right? Boats go out to see it never come back. Right? And
in their understanding, which is not an unsophisticated understanding for something to act for something to do things,
it has to be animated by a spirit. Right. Right. Right. Things that aren't animated by a spirit don't do things. Right. Right.
Other than maybe decompose in the case of a dead body. Right. But but decomposing. Right. Like the sea seems to hold
together. Yeah, well, it's funny even in modern materialist views of these things, we still have,
like we don't call it that, but we still have these notion of kind of animating spirits, like gravity.
Right, it's this forest that's acting all the time and moves things. But, you know, well, I can't
see it, you can't, you know, like it's interesting, like there still is this idea, or even things like,
like cosmic rays or radiation or all these things
that have these effects that we and we can measure them,
but they're not visible, right?
So it's just really,
in some ways a kind of alternative take
on exactly the same kinds of things
that ancient people are talking about.
Right, right.
It's just a question of what level of consciousness
you have described to these things, right?
There are scientists and philosophers of mind today who are starting to
ascribe consciousness to things like the Earth.
Yeah.
So, and welcome back everybody.
Yeah, it's not.
It's not, well, it was poo-pooed for a long time because of the completely
materialist approach to things.
People are now coming back around.
Yeah.
and say, oh, well, yeah, maybe in some places,
they phrase to things in an unsophisticated way.
But there's an important insight many times to be had here.
Yeah, so this assumption of, again, our 19th century
German friends, that everything just evolves,
that it's all progress, and everything
starts out primitive, it's stupid,
and then culminates in 19th century Germany,
one sort of through line,
maybe with a little hiccup for the dark ages,
but unquote dark ages.
But other than that, it's onward and upward,
just is being abandoned now, we get it.
It was dumb.
So this understanding,
we were just using the Ugritic terms and names,
but you find parallels to this understanding
all over the place in the ancient in the ancient Near East, right?
So we have these very early seals and inscriptions that show Hadad or Hadad,
or Hadad, depending on the conversation.
But Hadad, this is not HADDAD.
Yeah, which means blacksmith in Arabic at least.
I'm not sure about other sorts of languages.
Right, this is HDD, or the consonants.
Right.
And this was the storm god in ancient Syria
that was roughly parallel to bail in what's now Lebanon,
Phoenicia.
And we have these inscriptions and these seals of Haddad
defeating a serpent, the succession myth,
Marduk is sort of the actor.
And part of that is defeating Tiamat,
whose other Semitic name is Tahome,
which is the word for Abyss.
So Tiamat, this dragon, is seen as the Abyss
in the same way that Leviathan or Latanu
is related to Yom, who Marduk defeats.
Marduk heads up when he defeats Tiamat, he makes the world out of her carcass and her blood
drips and becomes humans.
So that's an enchanting tale for your kids about how the world came to be.
And then we even see in Egypt, we see in inscriptions and seals these depictions of Horace,
who was the sort of Falcon Headed God, the God associated in that early period with the
Pharaoh defeating Sowebac, who was the God of the Nile, Sowebac had a crocodile head.
So this is Falcon Head Guy versus Crocodile Head Guy, if you're showing it to small kids.
That's how they will describe it.
I'll say, Felgin, I say, bird hit guy to be fair.
And then this even, because as we've said before, Greece is not really the first Western
civilization.
They're the last ancient, or Eastern civilization.
Starting in the sixth century in Greece, we start getting imagery of the Hydra.
Right.
which gets defeated by Hercules, although Hercules is not exactly...
He's not the thunder god. I mean, he's related, you know, he's the son of Zeus, right?
If I recall, yeah, I'm not banking on that. Yeah, yeah.
So he's really...
And a human woman.
Yeah, right, exactly. He's a demigod.
And then, you know, you even get, you even get then...
Although, it mutates further as you get further out, I think.
Like you get Thor and Jormengonder, but Jormengonder is the midguard serpent,
sort of the world serpent, which we're going to talk about in just a second as to why this is a little
little bit different. Not yeah, not exactly the same thing, but there is this notion
for whatever reason of a thunder god versus a serpent that seems to keep getting popping up
over and over again in various kinds of mythology. Right, and there is
with Hercules, the connection's a little more tenuous, but he is sort of the rejected illegitimate son
who has to sort of earn his place among the gods. So it's not a true succession myth, he doesn't go
and kill Zeus, but there is sort of a, there are elements there that we connect it. And we also have,
Now going even further back, going way way back to the long ago time.
In Sumeria, we have depictions.
There's not a depiction of a God or someone else defeating it,
but there are depictions of the seven headed serpents that generally have horns on their head.
Yeah.
So we don't see somebody beating it up, but the idea of this creature,
because the seven heads and the horns are our typical parts of the way Lafayette and
Lottana is depicted. That depiction of such a creature goes all the way back into
ancient Sumeria. So this is the idea of this creature Lafayette has been around sort of as long
as human civilization has been around as far as we could tell. And then they had various figures
and they're understanding defeating it, but that means they saw it as sort of the primordial threat
that someone needs to defeat. Someone needs to overcome in order to establish order or create the
world or both. Right. But let's not get too far ahead of ourselves. Yeah. So and it's worth noting that
the one of the frequent sort of epithets right we talked about Halivai and and Latanu and
and Lothan means sort of the twisting one.
But one of the titles that gets applied
to Leviathan over and over again,
both in Ugritic texts and in the Old Testament
in particular in Isaiah is the fugitive serpent.
That gets translated in weird ways
sometimes in English translations
though the fleeing serpent or the serpent who runs away.
And that makes for some really weird reading in English because you have somebody, you know,
God beating up the serpent that runs away and that doesn't sound very heroic or impressive.
He was trying to run away like seriously.
But it means it's more the idea of a fugitive.
That's what fugitive means actually.
Yeah, I mean, it's fleeing literally.
Somebody who runs away.
Yeah.
So it's not incorrect.
It's just not really capturing the idea.
Right.
Well, what's going on and that I didn't kill my wife kind of thing. Yeah, yeah, I don't care
so
That in Hebrew is
Nakash Akalatone
And
Nakash that word that's translated that's the word of the two that's translated serpent
Is the word that's used that's translated as serpent in Genesis
Genesis 3.
Right.
Nakash.
So there is a connection between the devil as depicted in Genesis and this creature.
Yeah, right. Right. Right.
So there is a sort of a direct connection there.
Yeah, and I thought, you know, the temptation is, you know, since we have sort of modern post-enlightenment brains,
brains. We're like, okay, is that, are you saying that this is the devil? Like this is this spirit,
this is this creature, you know, but like, that's just kind of not the way that these, that ancient
myth and its texts actually work. You know, it's not a taxonomy. Right. Right. Yeah. Well,
at its end, like we were talking about before, it's like asking, is Yom Leviathan? Yes or no.
And the answer is yes and no. Yeah, right, right often.
So so is Leviathan the devil?
Yes and no
So
As we mentioned we have to kind of disambiguate a little
Yes
Not not herbs of not every not every snake down in the depths is the same snake
right. So there's some diversity in this. We can, there's a tendency when we get on to something
like this, right. We're like, oh, the vi that all this is interesting. There's all these parallels.
There's, there's a temptation sometimes to go a little crazy, right? Therefore, every snake,
every dragon, every crocodile, every, everything, every lizard is, is Leviathan now. Right. And we have
have to disambiguate a little, right?
They're not all the same.
There's some nuance there that you'll miss
if you just try to lump everything together.
This is why the ways where Joseph Campbell goes horribly wrong.
Oh, is this where he goes horribly wrong?
Yes.
No, this is the problem with his methodology
that produces all of the other problems with Joseph Campbell.
Yeah, everything becomes about everything.
Right.
It's that you just ignore all of the nuance
in particularities in order to lump as many things as possible into the same.
Yeah, which is a total problem, especially for the kind of not very studied approach
to ancient religion that some people take.
Like, oh look, here's a God that seems to die and then comes back.
Well, that must just mean that Jesus is just a rip off from some whatever, whatever.
You know, like, okay, actually the differences are really important here.
Yeah, yeah.
So yeah, so you get Joseph Campbell saying Hercules and Christ and Luke Skywalker are the same person and it's like
No
Is that is that Joseph Campbell and his George Lucas apostasis?
Yes
Yes, sorry
You could watch the old PBS documentary. He literally says that yes, right
So yeah, so we have to take into account not only the continuity's but also the discontinuities right so
One of the most common ones that gets mixed with Leviathan is
the
Uruburus
imagery
The serpent or the serpent that it circles the world the snake eating its own tail right the
And that
That is actually an ancient thing. Yeah
Yeah, that symbolism, but that symbolism occurs
alongside the sort of Leviathan, K. O. C. Monster imagery.
It's not another function of the same imagery.
Right, because this serpent, like, and you know,
in Norse mythology, you've got the midgard serpent, right?
This serpent is a binding sort of force
that kind of holds everything together versus, you know,
which if it comes on loose, that's where you get earthquakes and, you know,
Ragnarok. Yeah. We don't want that.
You know, whereas Leviathan is destructive force, it's aimed at ripping things apart.
And, you know, it's, you know, the storms and the sea and, you know, that,
that kind of stuff. Right. It's chaos and death and darkness and that kind of
stuff. Right. So that needs that's a separate thing. Right. In Egypt, something
interesting sort of happens with a poffis. A poffis starts out in earlier
periods of part of the the story surrounding Ray the sun god is that what we
would describe as the sunset is Ray entering the underworld to do battle with a
poffis who is this serpent being the serpent monster, right? So it's very easy to
quickly jump on that and say, aha, so see this is another, right, it's the God
battling Leviathan thing. But in this early period the
the Apophis monster is not associated with the sea in any way. Right? Each of
has a coastline with the Mediterranean. Yeah. But Apophis is not associated with
the sea because the sun didn't set into the sea if you're Egyptian. Hmm. The
sunset into the desert. And so Apophis is more associated with the darkness of
the sky between the stars, right? The sun, Ray, drives out that darkness, right? At sunrise
every day, right? So at night, that darkness briefly becomes somewhat ascendant and then
right, is defeated again in the morning. So that's how sort of originally works. But ancient
people jumped to conclusions too. They're not all perfect geniuses that have a little
the stuff worked out.
Right.
Some of them pulled the Joseph Campbell move.
So during the Hicksoss period,
Semitic peoples, who the Egyptians called Azeatics,
invaded and took over Egypt.
And they brought with them their own stories and traditions
and understandings of things.
So you get these Semitic stories related to bail and latanu,
right, Haddad and the serpent, right,
all of these things now come into Egypt
and this sort of assimilation takes place.
And so after the Hicksaw period,
you get depictions of set,
who have set killing a crocodile.
Right. And we can see this is on one hand parallel to the earlier Egyptian
imagery of Horus defeating Sobek, the crocodile god.
Yeah.
But on the other hand, sat being a god associated with death has sort of assimilated
part of the Catholic Bale tradition.
Hmm. Right. And so he's sort of replaced Horus in this
in killing a crocodile. So a poffis starts out disambiguated from Leviathan and then sort of gets
pulled in later on to that Leviathan tradition once it comes to Egypt.
And I mean, and relatedly, you know, set is like he has storms and disorder and violence and that kind
thing associated with him. Right yeah yeah. Yeah. So and yeah, and of course, Ray is going into the
underworld to fight a a a a a a a a the original Egyptian thing. So it just kind of gets pushed together
and takes this new form. And then finally, we have to just say big UA Leviathan from Rahav.
Rahav is another name for a sea monster, a sea serpent. It's also described as a
tonning, which is the Hebrew word for dragon. It's also described in Uberian
sources as a fugitive serpent, right, as the fugitive serpent. But the book of
So Job, for example, mentions Rahav and Louis Yatain, Leviathan separately, distinguishes
the two.
And so this is because, as we mentioned, Yom had several dragons.
L'Hatanu and Rahav are sort of two different dragons.
They're both associated with Yom, but they're not always necessarily the same critter.
Yeah.
And, you know, point of interest.
This is the same name as the Harlet Rahab who lets the people of Israel into Jericho.
Right?
Yes.
Yeah.
So not that we're saying she is a dragon of yom.
No.
She just has this name.
She was a legit pagan though before.
Yeah, clearly.
Before becoming part of Israel.
Yeah.
She had her pagan street cred.
All sorted out.
Right, so with that sort of definition and disambiguation done, we're going to go to the
places where Lafayette has mentioned in the Old Testament directly talked about.
And so we're not going through the order they were written or even the order they appear
in your Bible, there's a method to our madness. Trust us. We're going to start with Psalm 74.
So Psalm 74, before we get to the part about Leviathan, which starts in verse 12, just to sort of set
the context, verses 1 through 11 are sort of a lament. This is a Psalm that's written during the exile
in Babylon, and the temple has been destroyed, and so there's sort of a lament for those 11 verses of
the defeat of Judah, the destruction of the temple, and how Judah's been laid low.
Right. And then there's this turn in verse 12, thus, you know, the first word then being yet.
Right? After all this bad stuff has happened. So I'm just going to read verses 12 through 17,
so you can hear where this turn then goes. Yet God, my king, is from before the ages. He has worked
salvation in the midst of the earth. You split yam by your might. You broke the heads of the
the dragons on the waters.
You crushed the heads of Leviathan.
You gave him his food for the Ethiopians.
You split open springs and brooks.
You dried up ever flowing streams.
Yours is the day.
Yours also the night.
You have established the heavenly lights and the sun.
You have fixed all the boundaries of the earth.
You have made summer and winter."
So I mean this is cool because first there's a lament about the destruction that's happened
in Israel. And then it's yet God is the king from before the ages. He's the one who works
salvation. Then you get this description of him defeating Yom and Leviathan, feeding Leviathan
to the Ethiopians, and then talking about sending the earth in order. There's split open
springs of Brooks, you drive up over flowing streams. And then the day and the night, the seasons,
the bounds of the earth, right?
So it's this notion that God is not just the conquer
of these beings, but is also the creator
the one who sets things in order.
Right, right, there's this move.
And so this is, well, first we should say,
just in case somebody just opened their Bible
and did the Ethiopians.
Yeah.
That's, so the Hebrew there literally has
those who live in the wilderness.
Yes, those are the ones who get to eat Leviathan.
But I think it's the Greek, the Greek Old Testament
that has the Ethiopians.
It identifies the Ethiopians as the ones
who live in the wilderness.
Right, and the point of that identification
is for a lot of people in the Mediterranean,
Ethiopia is the ends of the earth.
Right, that's the super far away place
that is on the margins of everything.
Right.
And for more about that, listen to some of the stuff.
The conversations that Jonathan Pezo has had with Richard Rowan,
where they talk about Ethiopia.
Yeah.
And so interestingly here, notice that the salvation that God
wrought in the midst of the earth here
is the creation of the world.
And the way the creation of the world is described
is the defeat of Yom and Yom, the defeat of chaos,
and then the putting in order, right?
We get the language from the days of creation.
You fixed all the batteries of the earth,
years as the day, years as the night,
and made the heavenly lights of the sun, right?
And so this way of phrasing it is deliberately sort of,
as we've talked about many times before,
taking the claims that the big and nations made about bail
and ascribing them instead to Yahweh.
No, it's Yahweh who did this, right?
Not Bale, not Marduk,
even though it's slaves in Babylon right now.
Not anyone else, right?
Yeah, and again, a useful point to note is
there's no struggle, God just splits.
Yum, it just breaks the heads of the dragon.
There's not like, and there was a pitched battle
where he had to, it was really touch and go for a while.
It never is with God.
He simply commands.
And it's done, just boom, it's a single act.
Right, yeah.
And that split language is also kind of a reference
to separating the waters above from the waters below.
Those are two different dragons in the Obavalonian stories
with Marduk.
So over against what is befallen Israel
was before Judah in this case Israel is already gone. What is the
default Judah is remember this is who God is and what he has
done. And a brief note we're going to be developing this more
later on in the episode. But this all think about Leviathan being
fed to Ethiopians. Right. This feeding thing. This is also an
imagery of this sort of order. So if you go out hunting and you go and hunt down a wild beast,
a wild beast out in the wilderness is an image of chaos. But if you go out and you hunt it and you
kill it and you bring it back and you prepare it and you cook it, you have now placed it in order
and it's now providing sustenance and life. Yeah. And it's also worth noting for those who
have been to the services for Theophany or been to an Orthodox baptism in the
Byzantine tradition. These texts are used at Theophany in the blessing of
waters and at baptism at the blessing of waters. Associating this defeat of
sea monsters with the purification of the world that happens when Christ is
baptized and then also with the purification that happens when a Christian is
baptized. Right. And it also describes the movement that happens when water is blessed. Right.
Right. That water within the fallen creation becomes like the sea. It becomes this destructive
force of flooding, of drowning, of all of these things. But when it's taken and it's blessed,
either by Christ's physical presence in it, or by us at the great blessing of the waters,
it is transformed into something that's for sustenance and purification and healing, right?
And so that same kind of move is happening, right? And we're participating in it in those
liturgical services. And then, of course, this Psalm ends in verses 22 and 23 with an opportunity
for you to plug your book. I need with an important call. It turns out that the phrase
arise oh God appears in multiple places in the Bible. And I mean, it's super relevant.
Versus 22 and 23, arise oh God, defend your cause. Remember how the foolish scoff at you all the day
do not forget the clamor of your foes, the uproar of those who rise against you which goes up continually.
So there's this notion then that having earlier in the Psalm said, this is our God, this is what he did.
It's essentially saying
Would you do this again? It's calling upon him to do it again come up against these same foes, you know
Right, yeah, honesty is again the arise from which we get anastasis
right right
so
That then is a good segue into another place where Leviathan is mentioned.
And that's in Isaiah chapter 27.
And this is right at the beginning.
And it begins with in that day, that day being the day of Yahweh, the day of the Lord.
Right. Okay. So verses one through three in that day, Yahweh with his heart and great and strong sword will punish Leviathan, the fugitive serpent.
fugitive serpent, Leviathan the twisting serpent, and he will slay the dragon that is in the sea.
In that day a pleasant vineyard, sing of it, I yaw way emits keeper every moment, I water it.
And again, there's this connection of defeating a serpent, and then there's a vineyard,
you know, the cultivated nurtured land.
Right.
And so this is rather than going back to the past,
this is projected toward the future of Yahweh defeating
Leviathan in the future.
And then we have this paradise imagery
of this watered garden, this watered vineyard
that's going to be reestablished.
So what does that mean?
Well, when we put these two things together,
we understand, right? Well, if Leviathan got its heads crushed and got fed to Ethiopians
back at the creation, and how are their Ethiopians around at the creation? Anyway, then how,
how can Leviathan still be around? Well, the answer is in that movement and that a rhizogad.
Leviathan is still around and is lurking behind is the spirit, the force that's animating
the enemies of God, like the Babylonians.
Right.
And the others who are oppressing Israel.
And then this gets the other place where,
going back to Psalm 74 for just a second,
I didn't want to spoil.
That verse 12 of Psalm 74,
yet God by King is from before the ages,
he has worked salvation in the midst of the earth.
The place where you may have,
if your Orthodox or attending an Orthodox church,
heard that recently, was that the feast of the cross?
Yeah, it's everywhere in him is related to the cross.
Last month.
And so you will get a lot of sort of
leymaux explanations of that,
that he's worked salvation in the midst of the earth.
Well, that means that, you know,
they thought Jerusalem was in the center of the world.
So that's what they say, Jesus died in the middle of the earth.
in Middle-Earth.
And not in Middle-Earth.
I knew you were going to try to go there.
Not Midgard, not Midgard.
Yes.
It's not always the same podcast.
So it is being a different podcast.
So what this is saying, right, again, when you get a verse quoted, even if it's just one
verse being sung in liturgy that's supposed to call your mind back to the whole context.
What that saying is that what happens on the cross when Christ is crucified is that
second battle against Leviathan, in which Leviathan is defeated in the new creation
begins.
Yeah.
So, it's not why it's quoted there.
It's not about a geographic location.
about the whole creation at once,
that it affects everything.
It's about creation, not about a spot on the map.
Right, yeah.
And the crucifixion is not Christ temporarily losing,
but he's gonna have a comeback three days later.
No, no, it's the cross.
Yeah.
is Christ splitting Yaman to and crushing the heads of Lafayette then.
Right. Yeah, I mean, there's, it's interesting to me that if you understand the underworld,
you, according to ancient myth, then there is both this sense of a kind of cavern beneath the
world and then also a notion of plunging into the depths of the ocean. Right. And, you know,
When we usually think of the harrowing of how,
then we, I don't know, and frankly,
most iconography depicts the kind of cavern.
I have an awesome icon here in my studio,
thanks to some very generous people,
that depicts exactly this.
Although it's interesting, it's kind of both
because you see the souls of the departed
being swallowed up by what looks like a big serpent.
But still, you've got that and then also cave.
But then also the underworld is understood as being underwater at the same time.
And so you get sort of the Jonah imagery of being down in the depths of the sea at the same time.
And so I mean, that's kind of all going on at the same time here.
Right, right.
And so those are the two sort of most interesting perhaps references that give us this picture
of the cosmic significance of Leviathan.
But there are also some other sort of appearances.
And some of them have a little different character
in the testament.
Yeah.
So there's sort of a cursory mention in Amos 9, verse 3,
where it's just Leviathan is the serpent
at the bottom of the sea.
It's going to bite people.
Something interesting to say about that.
But I mean, that's what it is.
Yeah.
I mean, it just literally says in that verse,
If you try to hide from the sight of God at the bottom of the sea,
then the serpent will bite you.
That's basically what it is.
Yeah.
So the one we probably hear the most, again,
if you go to Vespers in an Orthodox church,
and I'm going to use the liturgical English,
anti-Ochean translation we're probably used to hearing.
So your experience may vary in translation,
but Psalm 104 or 103 in the Greek numbering that's read
at the beginning of the verse,
Leviathan whom thou hast made to support therein
is how it's usually translated referring to the sea.
So you have the sea and then God makes Leviathan
to sort of flip around and play in the water.
Yeah, yeah. It's how it comes off.
Yeah, right. You get this image that God made this beast
and you know, go play.
No, but that's not what's going on here.
Right.
Because you can equally translate it, Leviathan whom thou hast made to play with him, to
sport with him.
Right?
The idea being that God plays with Leviathan.
Leviathan is like his pet, like his dog, right, or like his cat, who he plays with.
Now that seems to be a striking contrast.
Yes, with what we were just talking about with Leviathan.
Right.
But the way that these two things come together is this notion of almost domestication or
muscling or control, you know.
Right.
Yeah.
And when we get into the last place where Leviathan has talked about, the Job that kind
of comes together.
So Job actually talks about Leviathan in two places.
The first place is kind of a cursory reference again.
And that's a Job 3 verse 8.
Talks about those skilled in raising up Leviathan, which
is kind of ominous.
Yeah.
I mean, as we might picture, could Tulu sort of, you know,
yes, or release the Kraken.
Yes.
Right.
So this is referring to sorcery.
This is what it's referring to is magic,
and not good magic, not friendly magic.
And so the form that this seems,
what this seems to be referring to directly
is we have these things from ancient Israel
and ancient Judah that are called incantation bolts.
We have them from their neighbors, too.
This is something they got from their neighbors.
This is something they were supposed to be doing.
And they're called incantation bowls because they're sort of pottery bowls and then around
the like in a circle around the sometimes the outer ring, sometimes an inner ring, sometimes
both if it's a long inscription, they'll have these sort of spell incantations.
Now, I mean, what they use is to kind of like mix up ingredients to make magical stuff,
potions and such.
It's hard to tell.
Yeah.
We just know that, right, we know that in some cases,
they would, you could turn it and read it.
We know in some cases where there were curses, right?
They would read the curse and then smash it.
The symbol is a being kind of obvious.
You're right, right.
You're putting a curse on someone.
And so the idea here is that raising up Leviathan
is not getting your summoning circle
and calling, you know, Cthulhu or Nari,
the Arleitho type into the world.
It's the ideas that you're sort of sticking Leviathan,
you're sending chaos and destruction after somebody.
Yeah.
It's not a question.
It incursing them.
Yes, it's a bad thing to do.
Don't try this at home.
Yeah.
Or anywhere.
Definitely not at church.
So.
Right.
But sort of the main extended place
where we hear about Leviathan in the book of Job,
runs from Job 40, verse 25 to 41, verse 26.
And Leviathan is described in terms
that are obviously reminiscent in many places
of a crocodile.
And so you'll get folks of a materialist bent
sort of often of a sort of,
we need to take everything literally bent,
who will try to say, oh well, this passage of Job
is just describing a crocodile.
Because crocodiles are big and scary,
but it's a fire, fire breathing crocodile.
And they don't do that.
That was hard to take literally.
So you say, I'm gonna take it literally
and say it's a crocodile,
but the fire breathing part is figured out.
Right.
Right. Right.
But yeah, good luck with that.
Yeah, and then this connects then with the idea
that Leviathan can be a pet, right?
How does that work?
What's going on?
And so the place where the crocodile is coming in
is we've seen like with the Horace-Sobak imagery
in Egypt where this sort of chaos was
is depicted as a crocodile.
That's where crocodile elements are coming
into Job's description.
But we also have an early Iron Age Palestine,
which would be the period of the judges roughly.
We have these seals that show a humanoid figure.
It's just an image.
So we don't know if that's supposed to be a god
or a who is controlling two crocodiles.
Has them on either leashes or hooks in their mouth
or something.
And in the academic world,
this guy is called the crocodile master,
which really sounds like a golden age, you know,
DC hero.
Yes.
Well, villain, excuse me.
A villain, yeah.
A Batman villain.
Yeah.
A villain, the crocodile master.
The crocodile master.
So, but that's just because we don't know who he's supposed
to be.
Right.
The economics column.
But it's a symbol of sort of some being
that has power or control over the forces of chaos and evil,
right?
Right.
Is able to sort of dominate them and control them.
And so this is where this connects
into this idea of Leviathan being,
or Liyaton being in some sense,
Yahweh the God of Israel's pet under his control.
Right, right.
And I mean, if this seems really too weird,
I mean, like, I'll just give a,
I'll just give an example from my own personal experience.
So most people in our culture are from the other people owning dogs and dogs are pets.
Dogs are nice.
And that's why it horrifies us when we hear that people in the far east like to eat them.
Like, don't eat them.
But when I was quite young, I used to deliver newspapers on the island of Guam.
Guam has a lot of totally undeveloped jungle area and in a lot of that undeveloped jungle
area are the descendants largely of people's pets.
So there are wild dogs on go.
At least there were back when I lived there in the late 80s.
I don't know if that's still the case.
But there are wild dogs that are running packs and do awful things.
And I would encounter them sometimes when I was out there at 4 in the morning delivering
newspapers in my neighborhood.
And boy, are they, I mean, they look the same basically as your, the, the pets that people
have in their houses, although they're often, you know, mangy and gross, but they are their
personalities are vicious and chaotic and, you know, and really destructive, right? And so
the idea of taking a wild vicious animal like that and, you know, controlling it and turning into
a different kind of thing, that's a really great example of that. I mean, you know, hardly ever
run across a wild dog in the United States. You just run across people's pets, but boy dogs
on their own, they are, they are KS monsters, that's for sure.
Right, and this, this imagery is critically important to understanding how the old testament
looks at what we today call the question of the Odyssey.
And the relationship between God and the evil and chaos and destruction in the world.
So in paganism, as we saw, when we started talking about Leviathan, there's this idea
of sort of equal opposition, right, that there are forces of order and forces of chaos,
and they're sort of continuously at war, right?
And for now, order has the upper hand, but that order is always threatened by chaos coming
back in.
And so there's this constant vigilance.
And usually, I shouldn't say usually, often in these myth cycles, there's some point in
the future where chaos comes back and wins.
Yeah, right.
Like some kind of ragnarok.
Ragnarok.
Exactly.
That's the one I wanted to mention.
So there's this kind of equal ultimacy of these two forces, right?
You don't have that in the Old Testament.
You have something very different.
There is nothing equal and opposite to Yahweh.
Everything that is Yahweh created, right?
And so that is what creates the question of the Odyssey.
You don't have the question of the Odyssey.
If it's just like, well, Ray's doing the best he can.
He's sweating a puff.
It's every bloody night.
What do you want from him?
Yeah.
Right?
Right.
Yeah.
You don't ask, like, why does evil exist, Ray?
You know what?
No, I do.
All right.
It's obvious, right?
He's working.
He's sweating.
So the picture we get, and we get this over and over again
in different ways.
And we'll talk about this again when we cover other topics.
Because there are depictions of other gods of plague
gods of trouble that are parallel to this and connected to the forehorses of the apocalypse,
right, for example, in the prophets. But what we see over and over again is this imagery of
God having control over these things in the sense that he can then use them. They are in some
sense forced against their will to be his servants. We've talked about this with demons in general.
right. Right. This idea, this imagery that's made very explicit in the book of Jubiles, that
that God allows a certain number of demons, a certain amount of leash in the world,
in order to torment the wicked in order to bring them to repentance. Yeah, it's the idea of
the left hand of God. Right. And St. Paul, you know, this is what he picks up on that truck
about turning someone over to Satan for the salvation of their soul through the destruction
of their body, right? That's what he's alluding to is that understanding. That's why there
are these troubles to try to bring us to repentance, right? To try to bring us to salvation.
So God doesn't just, Yahweh the God of Israel doesn't just defeat chaos or hold chaos at
Bay, right? But he actually grabs a hold of chaos and uses even it to bring about order, to
bring about good, right? He seizes the force of evil and makes them bring about good despite
themselves. Yeah, he harnesses it. Yeah. Right. All right, well, that is the first half of this
episode and we're going to be right back after a short break. Father Andrew Stephen Daymak and
and Father Stephen DeYoung will be back in a moment
to take your calls on the next part
of the Lord of Spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF radio.
The Lord of Spirits, the Father Andrew Stephen Daymak
and Father Stephen DeYoung.
If you have a question, call now at 855-237-2346.
That's 855 AF radio.
Welcome to the second half.
Normally we would start taking your calls here but despite what the voice of Steve just said
this is in fact a pre-recorded episode so we're not receiving any calls.
Don't call the number no one's home.
Well someone, what if they call it and someone does answer?
I'm not sure what would happen actually.
I don't think anyone will be able to.
It's a risk. You could roll the dice. It's possible. I mean, it's true. I mean, you could call. I mean, who did that?
Hopefully, Trudy is taking the night off or something, you know. Maybe maybe the call would end up coming from inside your own house.
That says that we did get this message from Chris.
Hi, fathers. So my question is actually about these demonic feats,
and I guess I've been thinking about it in relation to Christ putting all things under
His feet.
So my question is actually two parts.
Do you think we could say that when Christ put all things under His feet that He did in
fact do the mash, He did the monster mash?
And also, if so, do you think it actually was a graveyard smash?
That's it, thank you.
So given everything we just said, I think the answer is pretty clearly yes on both counts.
My answer is wah wah.
But I'm ch.
Thank you for that, Chris.
It is a good observation you are making.
All right, so, okay, we've talked about Leviathan and being the monster mashed.
Indeed, it was a graveyard smash since it's about the destruction of heady and so forth.
So okay, we're also going to be talking about behemoth.
So what's that all about?
This is a very different kind of image.
Yes, yeah, this is not just another name for the same thing.
Right.
This is a whole separate tradition.
And behemoth is also like Leviathan is a transliteration of Louis Yattain.
Heemoth is a transliteration of Bahaimote.
And Bahaimote, unlike Luyitan,
is a much more commonly used word
because Bahaimah, which is the noun in the singular,
means cow, okay, literally.
And it's also sometimes used more generally
just to mean beast as in beasts of the field.
Okay.
And so yeah, that's a relatively common word.
And then being a feminine, because it's cow,
being a feminine noun, grammatically feminine,
the plural of that is behemoth.
So yes, you heard that right.
grammatically, behemoth is feminine plural.
Right.
But there are places where this feminine plural noun
takes masculine singular pronouns.
That's why we talk about behemoth as a thing,
and as things.
Right.
Creature, right.
Not as things.
And so this plural is what we call an intensive plural.
Right. So probably the first place people might go is to think of, okay,
is this like the royal we or as they call it, the plural of majesty,
right, which is sort of a similar concept, right?
But it's not just it's not just a plural that refers to a singular thing.
In that case, it's a plural that refers to royalty or
although you also have the editorial we,
as we have ever seen.
But yeah, it's not the plural of majesty,
it's an intensive plural.
It's, yeah.
So what does that mean?
This is really a brief digression to respond to pedantry.
Yes.
We don't have any pedants to listen to this podcast,
though I'm sure none.
No, not a one.
Only the people who make it.
Yeah, right.
So oftentimes, right, we're usually
not talking about behemoth when this comes up.
We're usually talking about the word Elohim, which
is another plural that takes masculine singular pronouns
in the Hebrew Old Testament sometimes.
Yeah, often, because it's being used to refer to God.
It's used to refer to Yahweh, but it's in the plural.
And so oftentimes the way that's explained.
Some folks will try to bring the Trinity into that.
There's a way you can do that that semi-valid,
but frankly, no one is ever going to be convinced by it,
because there's another available option.
And usually when that other option is being explained,
Usually people refer to the royal we that you were just referring to right we are not amused right so
And this idea that oh well this is this is this royal thing being applied to God because he's God right and
Most times when that gets brought up
You will have someone show up and say well, there's not a plural of majesty in Hebrew
Right is that true?
That is true. There it is. There is not technically speaking. Technically speaking. That is a correct, unactually technically.
But it's being used for pedantry because
when people giving them the benefit of the doubt, people who know what they're talking about,
when they use this example to explain to an English speaker why Elohim is plural, they're using it as an analogy.
Right? So the plural of majesty in English is a structure like the intensive plural in Hebrew.
But it's not the same thing. Right. We don't have an intensive plural in English.
Yeah, I think the closest we get is, and this is purely colloquial spoken English, is sometimes when we want,
sometimes we will repeat a word in order to achieve the same effect.
So in this case, I might disambiguate between, okay, I'm talking about a God or
I'm talking about God, God. We sometimes do that.
There's a lift that happens in pitch when you do the first one and then as
as the kind of modifier for the second.
I think that's the closest thing we have in English,
but it only, I think it only really exists
in spoken English.
You don't really see that written anywhere.
Right, I mean, the closest thing in written English
would be capitalizing thing.
Yeah, right, right.
Right, turning it into a proper noun
instead of a general noun.
Yeah.
Right, but so what actually is going on
with the intensive plural in Hebrew
is that, so for example, with Elohim,
It's sort of like, this is God of God.
This is God with a capital G.
This is the great God, right?
This is the God, right?
Which is why in Greek you get, oh, theos, the God.
You get the article, you get the article at it, right?
To convey that same kind of idea.
So that's why it's called the intensive plural.
It intensifies the thing.
So the same thing is happening with Bahaimot,
the reason it's plural, even though it's taking
masculine singular pronouns is that this is the beast of beasts, right?
This is the beast.
This is the great beast.
Hey, yes, the super beast.
This is, right?
This is the beast, right?
The beast to end all beasts.
Right.
That's, that's the idea, right?
That's the idea.
And that's why behemoth gets turned into a proper noun,
translated into a proper noun and capitalized, right?
The way Leviathan is.
So, we don't have the related cognate words
related to cattle directly used to name behemoth,
the way we have like Lothan and Lutano and Lutat.
But we do have parallels
outside of the Old Testament for this idea, right, that this is connected to.
And probably the closest one, and I'll just go ahead and say it now.
We're going to be speaking delicately throughout this half of the program about something.
Parents with Behemoth.
Parents just better.
We will be doing our best to speak delicately.
Yeah.
So the biggest and main parallel that we have from neighbors,
again comes out of the Ugaritic tradition.
This shouldn't be surprising, right?
These are Israel's neighbors.
And bail worship is what keeps intruding down into Israel
throughout its history.
So there is this figure Bill El-Teeck.
Say that again.
Sorry.
You just like glottals.
Yeah.
This is, that translated is Ells' calf, a Teeck.
And Ell is a male's father.
Right.
So he has this calf, David Teek, also sometimes called Arshu in the texts.
And this is a sort of version of bail.
Elsewhere he sometimes referred to as bull bail or a catholic bail that we mentioned before
in terms of set being assimilated to set in sort of under underworldly bail.
Yes.
So.
Yeah, and so we talked about how Leviathan is from the earth, from the sea.
This bullet scene is being sort of from the earth.
And when we see that, we assume that means like came up out of the ground, sort of, right?
Because the Hebrew word arits that usually gets translated earth is also a word that's used
a lot to refer to the underworld. This is what's going on in Genesis 3 also by the way with
the serpent is going to crawl along the earth. It's talking about the underworld being thrown
down to the underworld, not being thrown down to the ground, but the underworld. That's that
that catholic element again.
And so Bull Bale is again that hypostasis idea.
This is an aspect.
This is a localization and instantiation of Bale.
That's associated with his power and particularly masculine
power and virility.
It's the delicacy.
Talking about some of this stuff.
And so the primary sort of appearance of bullbale in myth
is bullbale in the underworld
in which he three times engages with a heifer,
in sheol in the underworld as a sort of bringing fertility
out of death.
This is a transition from winter to spring thing.
And this was celebrated annually
in Ugarit and in Phoenicia,
ritually, with a fertility ritual
that involved engaging human priests engaging with cattle.
and priests engaging with cattle.
Right.
That's as delicate as I could do it.
Okay.
Let the listener understand who's an adult.
So,
Inc. paganism beautiful.
and this figure of bullbale of Arshu
is described in another ugeritic source
in which the goddess Anat is speaking,
and bragging about all the cool stuff she's done.
She talks about having defeated the seven headed dragon,
the twisting serpent, right, Lattano,
and having defeated Arshu.
So in the pagan, Ugranic sources also,
there's sort of this parallel between Behimeth and Lafayette,
emerging.
They're not only drawn together as we're gonna see
in a minute in the Old Testament.
We also see this kind of figure in the bowl of heaven in the epic of Gilgamesh,
where you have this bowl figure that is precious to the gods and usually to a male god in
particular because it represents his virility and masculine power, his Austin Powers Mojo,
So, right, et cetera.
And this even sort of makes it appearance
with Zeus and Europa and that kind of thing.
And also with the Minotaur in Greek stories,
because again, Greece is the last ancient very certain civilization.
And sort of brings some of these things into their final form.
So that brings us to then the Bible.
And behemoth shows up in the Bible less,
at least directly, in the Old Testament,
than Leviathan does.
There are only two places,
and the second place is a little contested,
but I think I have a good argument for it.
Okay.
So, but the first place is uncontested,
and the first place is in Job,
chapter 40 verses 15 through 24 in the Hebrew 10 through 19 in the Greek. You may notice from that verse reference that
that's right before
Leviathan is talked about the he myth has talked about so there's sort of brought together and paired here in the same way that they're paired in the
Eucharitic texts these two figures. Okay. All right, so I'm gonna read this from Job 40
Behold, behemoth, who I made as I made you, he eats grass like an ox, behold his strength
as in his loins and his power in the muscles of his stomach.
He makes his tail stiff like a cedar, the sinews of his thighs are knit together.
His bones are tubes of bronze, his limbs like bars of iron.
He is the first of the works of God, let he who made him bring near his sword.
the mountains yield food for him, were all the wild beasts play. Under the lotus plants
he lies in the shelter of the reeds and in the marsh. For his shade, the lotus trees
cover him, the willows of the brooks surround him. Behold, if the river is turbulent, he
is not frightened. He is confident, though Jordan rushes against his mouth, can someone
take him by his eyes or pierce his nose to capture him. And I'll just say here, there's
There's a reference at the beginning to behemoths power in terms of virility.
So the bit about the tale is actually referring to something else.
But that's just the way that often some English translations treat it.
So again, yeah.
Delacacy.
Let the reader understand.
Yes.
Right.
And so here, right, just like, you know, there's people who try to do the crocodile thing, the
tireless route with Leviathan.
They're people who try to say this is a hippo.
Yeah, right.
That's a beast of beast is a hippo.
I don't know that there are a lot of hippos in the Jordan.
I don't know that hippos are renowned for being
really placid in rushing water.
I don't think either of those things are true, frankly,
but OK.
OK.
Right.
Clearly not.
So this is, this is me.
And we see there's these images of virility, of power.
But then also the marsh stuff, the river stuff,
the Jordan stuff, this is associating him with the word
river.
There's literally Nahar.
Remember in the Bale story, Yom's sort of prince,
his sort of right hand man is Nahar, River.
Yeah, right.
And so this is connecting Bohemoth again with Yom,
with this chaos, these chaos forces,
that similar kind of idea.
And so if we see Leviathan,
as we've said this before on the show,
but it's worth saying again,
if we see Leviathan as sort of toxic femininity,
behemoth is toxic masculinity,
the sort of conquering tyrannical force.
Yeah.
So, and just as with the vibe of going imagery,
going back to Sumer, if you set the way back machine,
go back to our first episode where we're talking about sacrifices
and the Neolithic era, the bold decorations also go all the way back,
as far as we can tell in human civilization,
the same kind of connection with these forces.
So the second place where I'm going to argue,
Behemoth shows up, is in Isaiah chapter 30 verses 6 and 7.
Now, is this the DeYoungStandard translation?
Or all of these translations, or the DeYoungStandard translation?
Yes.
At any time you hear a translation on this show
and you go and look it up somewhere, it doesn't match.
That's because I've filled with it.
Right.
corrected it. You may disagree with me if I butchered it. Right? Fair enough. But it's my mind.
I've corrected it. It's okay to disagree, everybody. It's okay. Yeah. Right. Okay. So Isaiah,
chapter 30, verses 6 and 7, an oracle against the behemoth of the south, through a land of trouble
and anguish, from whence come the lioness and the lion, the viper and the flying serif, they carry their
their riches on the backs of Donkeys and their treasures on the humps of camels to a people
that cannot profit them. Egypt's help is worthless and empty. Therefore, I have called her Rahav
who sits still. So what's going on with that?
So the way this is typically translated in English is they'll say it's an oracle against
the beasts of the negative or the beasts of the desert.
Yeah, the negative, which is a particular desert,
but it just means south, right?
Right, negative is also the word for south.
That's why they call that desert that.
It was the desert to the south, right?
Yeah, it's the southern desert.
Really is what that means.
Pretty uncreative name for the desert, but there it is.
So, right, so, yeah.
And so what that would mean is,
if you read versus one through five,
they're talking about Egypt.
And verse 7 again mentions Egypt, right?
So it's talking about, right?
The Assyrians are coming, they're coming after Israel
and the temptation for Israel is going to be,
we need to go and make some kind of treat you
with Egypt, this other great power, earthly power,
to defend us against the Assyrians.
Forget the whole repenting and letting Yahweh protect us,
we need to go and kind of deal with the Egyptians
because they have chariots.
Yeah. So, and I say, and yeah, way by means of Isaiah saying, uh-uh, that's not going to work,
right? That's just going to bring about your destruction, right? Because Egypt is
correct. River, I delivered you out of Egypt, right? I defeated the Egyptian gods. There's nothing
for you there, right? So that's what he's clearly, yeah. I was going to say, I mean, this is, I
mean, this is a theme in a lot of the scriptures, which is, you know, revenge is mind, say at the Lord,
You know, like it's the whole the kind of king that they want.
We talked about this, right?
When they when they talked about the kind of king that they wanted in Saul to be a king who's
going to defeat their enemies and go and, you know, make war the way that they want to make
war, right?
Not trusting in God to do this, but instead, you know, building up an army and making treaties
and functioning just like any of the nations around them do.
Right.
And so that's very clearly what one through five is about yeah, Isaiah 31 through five
So then if we go by this other translation then all of a sudden God decides to denounce animals that live in the desert
Yeah, I mean ESV it's called it says an oracle on the beasts of the Nudgef
Which doesn't it?
Right, so why is God denouncing these animals and then when we get the list of animals
right? We got lioness and lion, okay, Viper, okay Viper's out in the desert. And then the way
it's usually translated is flying flaming serpents. Right? Which that doesn't sound natural. Yes. Yeah.
So I translated that by just translating the word that's there. Yeah, Sarah, which I mean
flying Sarah. Right. Because so the reason why it makes sense to translate it that way and why
this would be associated with Egypt is like this is this well again first this is the Egyptian term for
these throne guardians who are depicted in serpentine fashion but as I think we've mentioned on the
podcast before if you think about that headdress that Pharaoh wears it makes them look like a cobra
which what is a cobra it's a snake with with wings you know so to speak right so there's there's
There's the sort of symbol of Egypt is this
Seraphic image.
Right, this is, you know, look at this thing,
it's a lion, right?
So we've got lions and serpents, right?
These are the symbols of Egyptian power, right?
Right, and that's what it's referring to.
Because it's hard to imagine a bunch of lions and lionesses
and snakes, even flying flaming snakes,
carrying their riches on donkeys and camels.
Right.
So like literally the normal translation of this
makes no sense.
I mean, it's, it's make a great,
a great Rudyard Kipling story.
Right.
And so,
right, if you translate verse six the way I did,
an oracle gets the behemoth of the South
calling Egypt the behemoth of the South.
The Tyrant.
Egypt with behemoth, right? And then this is about a serif, right? These are the symbols of their power.
They the Egyptians put their riches on the backs of donkeys and their treasures on the Humps of
Camels when they're doing trade, right? To a people that cannot profit them, right? So their efforts are
futile, right? Their trade efforts are futile. And then lo and behold, in verse 7, it then makes sense
to say Egypt's help is worthless and empty. Right. Therefore, I have called it Rahav.
And now we refer to Rahav. We refer to this Seamonster, this other chaos monster,
who's still, which is the opposite of its power. Who yeah, who is inactive.
Right. They may seem like this powerful beast, but they're not doing anything.
Yeah, right. So this is the other and we see here what's what's important about this one is that
the reason we spent all this time about with me quibbling about the translation of being a penitent
myself is that this shows us the same way we saw Leviathan kind of lurking behind an animating
the enemies of God. This shows us behemoth and brahav also behemoth lurking behind
right and animating these these nations these enemies of God.
And that's going to be really important where we get to the third half.
Which shows then why Israel wanting to deal with this with Egypt by what we might
think of as conventional military and diplomatic means why that's a few
tile act on their part because no no no this is actually a spiritual conflict.
You know you must have God on your side. You can't just go off and
do this on your own. One does not simply walk into Cairo or Alexandria.
Cairo. Sorry. Excuse me. I was being a little, a little anacronistic there.
Even Alexandria is anacronistic. This is Isaiah, bro.
Oh yeah. This is 8th century BC. So what's, I mean, so what's the capital?
Memphis. Memphis, my friend. I'm sorry. Okay.
All right. Well, look, the Bible can be anacronistic. It can refer to Babylon when Babylon is no one
your bias. Okay. Okay. Yeah. Nice try. Actually. Okay. Thank you. So. So, uh, and now to sort of round
this out, right, um, to catch us up to because when we get to the third half, we're going to move to
the new testament. Um, so, uh, we got, we got a lot of interesting reactions. So we, shall we say,
to the title of this episode.
Yes, Leviathan was a noob.
It was a noob for dinner.
Yeah, this idea of chowing down on Leviathan.
And actually, we're talking about chown down on Leviathan
and behemoth.
Yes, right.
So yeah, it's dinner time with both of them.
That dead joke is beneath me.
So you're going to have to make it.
Oh yes, he's Father Steve is reading from the script, right?
Yes, it's the surf in turf.
You're welcome.
Yes.
So, right.
So, what's going to happen is that as we move
through Second Temple Judaism and into early Christianity,
there's one more piece to the puzzle
in terms of how the traditions surrounding
behemoth and Leviathan are going to develop. And that piece comes in Ezekiel, which is
also obviously exilic, written in the Babylonian exile, Ezekiel 39 verses 17 through 20. And
this is describing the fate of Gog and Magog, these nations that are the enemies of God,
and who we now know who's animating them from the other texts.
Right.
Okay, so this is Ezekiel 39 and 17 through 20.
As for you, son of man, thus says the Yahweh God, speak to the birds of all kinds and to
all of the beasts of the field, assemble and come, gather from all around to the sacrificial
feast that I am preparing for you, a great sacrificial feast in the mountains of Israel,
and you will eat flesh and drink blood.
You will eat the flesh of the mighty and drink the blood of the princes of the earth, of
of rams, of lambs, and of goats, of bulls, all of them fat beasts of Bashan, and you will
eat the fat until you are full and drink blood until you are drunk at the sacrificial feast
that I am preparing for you, and you will be filled at my table with horses and charioteers
with mighty men and all kinds of warriors declares Yahweh God.
Right.
So and notice that hopefully by now people notice that reference to Pashan, home of
Og, home of the dead Refaim, home of Mount Herman, gateway to the underworld.
So again, we have that imagery that we saw with Leviathan in the psalm, right, at the
creation of giving as food to the creation, the carcasses and blood of the defeated enemies
of God.
And that's sort of the prophecy of the fate of these enemies.
And so when we get into that second temple Jewish literature, and early Christian literature,
And first, Enoch 60 versus 7 through 9, there's this reference to Behemoth and Leviathan
and Leviathan as a female figure, Behemoth as a male figure, despite language gender,
being opposite.
And Leviathan is in the abyss, right, the Tahome, right, that we saw as connected to Tiamat.
And Behemoth is in the desert of Dundayan, which is not a Tolkien place.
Not Duna Dyanarabit.
It sounds like one place.
Right.
Duna Dyanarabit.
Yes.
But the importance of that desert is that desert is said to be east of Eden.
Yeah.
That's the Cane homeland where he builds his city, the Cane civilization.
Right.
that behemoth and bold imagery is associated with the cities. Right? So you have chaos in the abyss
and you have this, chaos in the cities motivating these nations. And then in four Ezra and again,
you should read four Ezra. If you're from a Slavic Orthodox tradition, it's in your Bible.
4.6 vs. 49-52. This scribes that Leviathan and Behemoth were created on the fifth day
and were separated. Behemoth was put on the land on the earth and Leviathan was put in the sea
until the end times when they come forth to be eaten.
Yeah. Right. And what's for dinner? Yeah. Second Baruch, sometimes called the second apocalypse
of Baruch 29 verse 4, in its description of the Messianic Age, the Age with the Messiah
Reigns, Leviathan Behimeth get eaten by the Remnant, the Remnant who has been purified
by judgment that Leviathan be with the merge and they get eaten by them. And then finally,
you get a similar kind of imagery in the apocalypse of Abraham 21 verse 4. This is just about
Leviathan, but Leviathan is sort of lurking in the sea behind the scenes, like behind
current events until the end times when the emerges.
Yeah, so the point being that all of this imagery that's in the Old Testament that we also find in a lot of pagan sources as well
continues on into the Second Temple period and there's this remarkable, you know
similarity between what's with what said you know the notion that
Leviathan and behemoth of these demonic forces it work in the world Leviathan associate with chaos behemoth with sort of tyranny and
And they're kind of underneath everything.
Like there's a sort of a primal sensibility to them, right?
Versus a lot of the kind of demonic beings that are described as kind of going from one place
to another and that kind of thing.
And that they're going to be eaten at the end of time, you know.
And in the case of, you know, Second Brooke, this notion that they're going to be eaten specifically
by the remnant who've been faithful to God.
It's really interesting how everything, there is this sense that all of these sources
are functioning within the same world.
They're not like cribbing notes from each other.
It's just this is the tradition that people believe in.
I mean, there's different takes, you know, pagan versus Israelite, but the basic kind
of facts are essentially the same.
Right.
And this is bringing us right up to the period of the New Testament being written, where
all of this is going to sort of come to a final flower in terms of the Christian appropriation
of it.
And we will talk about that in the third half.
And so right now we're going to go ahead and take our second break.
We'll be right back.
Father Andrew Stephen Daymak and Father Stephen DeYoung will be back in a moment to take your
calls on the next part of the Lord of Spirits. Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF Radio.
Big in Heaven, a collection of short stories available now on the Ancient Faith Bookstore.
Sometimes poignant, sometimes funny, sometimes heartbreaking, sometimes convicting.
These stories of life in an inner city immigrant orthodox parish are guaranteed to shake your assumptions and make you see your life and faith in a new way.
They are not for the faint of heart, but they are very much for all who want to embrace the truth more fully.
And you didn't have to ask Roscoeva for help, cleaning, polishing, carrying, in or out.
Any work in the church, the woman was a stalled, a tovadesh, you could count on.
No one knew her suffering.
They never bothered to look into her eyes.
It surprised me that most of the church folks at St. Alexander, the whirling dervish parish,
didn't even know her name.
It wasn't anything they thought about.
To find this book and others like it, you can go to store.enchantfaith.com.
Again, that is store.enchantfaith.com.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits, the Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father
Stephen DeYoung.
If you have a question, call now at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF Radio.
Welcome to the third half.
Again, just quick reminder, we do love you, voice of Steve,
but your own pre-recorded voice does not know
that this is a pre-recorded episode.
So we're not taking any calls, but that said,
we did get this message from Nathan.
This is Nathan Margaret Aves calling from Baton Rouge, Louisiana.
And my question is in regards to the beast out of the sea
and the beast out of the earth referenced
in the Book of Revelation,
in growing up in the Protestant world.
I was commonly taught that the B.
study of the sea was identified as the anti-Christ.
And that the B.
study of the Earth was identified as the false prophet.
However, in reading the book of Revelation,
and along with studying Father Stephen the Young's blog,
and listening to this podcast, it seems to me
that given what we see in our world today
in the deification of American civil religion
in particular in liberal democracy
in general around the world, that the B.
out of the sea is rather a world system that is anti-Christ, but not necessarily an individual
or a person. And that the beast out of the earth is in fact what we would call an anti-Christ,
or the world or the devil's replacement of Christ in the form of a goat. I will be curious to hear
your perspective on this given the fact that we do see this proliferation of the liberal democracy
around the world and we see its ultimate bankruptcy in the liberal teachings that are proliferated
with it. Thank you. Okay, so a lot going on there. We are going to talk about the beasts out of
the sea and out of the earth here in the third half. So this is kind of what we're doing.
Right. And I think just to clarify, because especially the way political words are used,
and even the word politics is used in the United States today.
Everything's super ambiguous
because everybody uses words different ways.
I'm going to interpret what he's talking about
with liberal democracy and liberal teachings
to refer to sort of the whole liberal tradition,
like John Locke, right?
Like, and on, like the modern political idea
of liberal democracy, not like liberals the way they're
talked about in American politics.
Right, right.
So from that perspective, pretty much all of America,
just about all of American politics,
the other fridges is somewhere in the liberal democracy
category, right, and Western Europe, and yeah.
We don't have a hereditary absolute monarchy we have.
Right, for example, yeah.
OK, so to understand the beast out of the sea in the Earth,
We have to go back to Daniel first, right?
Right.
That's really the topic of this whole episode.
Is the beast out of the light of the sea.
So of course, we're going to talk about it at the very end.
Of the episode, as is our want.
But so, right.
So we need to pick up the first place where beasts like this
appear is in Daniel chapter seven.
We've talked about Daniel chapter seven a couple of times
before.
But in those couple of times we've talked about it, we focused on mainly verses 9 through 14,
which is the enthronement of the Son of Man with the ancient days. We've talked a lot about that.
Yeah, on our ascension episode particularly, we focused on that.
Right, and this is the rest of that chapter. Right, so verses 1 through 8,
and verses 15 through 28, which deal with some beasts. Right, so this is what's before the
the enthromant of the Sonomand and then afterwards the interpretation of that vision which culminates
with that enthromant. So what we get in Daniel 7, 1 through 8 is this vision that Daniel has of
these four beasts, all of whom come up out of the sea. So if everybody is paying attention in the
the first two halves before we come to our third half,
they know that as soon as you hear beast from the sea,
you should be thinking Leviathan.
Right, right, right.
And so, but we have this succession,
the four don't come out all at once, right?
They come out one at a time.
And so each of these is gonna be connected
in some way to Leviathan.
So the first one of these,
and well, and we'll go ahead and say,
as we already saw Leviathan
as a motivating spirit sort of lies behind these national enemies, these armies, etc, that
are opposed to Yahweh that got in Israel and the people of Israel.
Yeah.
And so that's very much a tantamilier.
So these are sort of monsters that are emerging as sort of instantiations of Leviathan.
Okay.
particular, particular instantiations of Lafayette.
And there's a connection.
I don't want to go down this rabbit trail,
but just to let people know I'm aware of it,
just because we don't have this episode to be five hours long.
I know there's a connection here to Typhon and Gaia
and the Titans, but we're not going
to go down that road right now, maybe at a later point.
Yeah.
So I'm interested already.
I don't know what they're doing.
Yeah, sorry, everybody.
another time. So the first one that emerges is this lion with wings. Okay, a chair. And, right,
a chair. And this may particularly, right, if you're familiar with Babylonian sort of iconography
and a Syrian too for that matter. But Babylonian, you've seen those things that look kind of like a
of inks, right? It's got a lion body and wings and then it's got like a human head.
Yeah, with usually like some kind of a crown, a kind of more of a vertical sort of crown than
the Egyptian version, which has the sort of ferronic headdress on it.
Right. And it's usually got the sort of, it's said of the sort of tacked on pharaoh beard,
which was a fake beard. It's got sort of the big curly ring right here, right? The Babylonian.
Right? And so when we read about a winged lion that's given the mind of a man, right, we could pretty clearly see
this is referring to Babylon at the Babylonian Empire under whose dominion
Daniel was living in exile. Right. Right. So the first sort of instantiation of Leviathan is the Babylonian Empire.
Then the next beast that comes out of the sea is this bear that's sort of listing or
limping to one side who has three ribs in his mouth.
And this is a depiction that's referencing the Persian Empire.
Okay.
Why isn't limping?
What's that all about?
Well because it's technically the mediocre Persian Empire.
Okay.
the beads were sort of the junior partners.
No, okay.
Right.
And you got the ribs, the beads are getting thrown
away.
So you're willing to make that dad joke,
but not just her foot shirt.
Yes, I'm willing to do that.
I draw the line somewhere.
Maybe not where anyone else would, but somewhere.
And then the third beast that emerges
is described as a leopard who has four wings
and four heads.
And the leopard is a reference to Alexander the Great.
So Greece.
And then after Alexander's death,
you end up with the four kingdoms, the Diadokie,
the successors formed the four sort of states
when they carve up what was his empire.
And then finally, the fourth beast emerges.
This beast is described as being like any animal.
It's just sort of terrible and horrible.
It has iron teeth and ten horns
and there's three more horns
and then those horns get cut out of there's little horn
and a little horn is talking trash.
Which, that's just, that's just eerie and weird.
You know, yeah.
Yeah.
I mean, not that it's all not weird,
but you know what I'm saying?
This little horn, I think it's described as having
face of a man, right or something like that?
Yeah, well, and it's, yeah, the horn does.
Yeah, the horn has eyes in a mouth.
Yeah.
And so the little horn, the horns are kings.
The little horn is sort of one of this one king
in particular, who is particularly blasphemous and evil.
Now, you may be wondering, am I just pulling a Jack van
MP here and saying, well, this represents this,
this represents that.
So this is really secure that this is what it's talking about.
Okay.
This is a parallel to the other vision Daniel has where he sees the statue made of the different
metals that points to the same four empires with bronze and iron.
There's even some of the same imagery.
And this is so obvious and so clear that this vision is why a whole host of modern secular
scholars don't believe Daniel could have been written during Daniel's lifetime.
Because of course they don't believe in actual prophecy.
So there's no way he could have been this spot on.
Yeah, it's sort of so on the nose that that yeah, it's not vague enough for quote unquote
real prophecy, right, for them to buy it, right? So yeah, so that's how secure this is,
like that's how clear it is that that's what this is talking about. And so the the enthronement
of the Son of Man, then that we've talked about before, that part of the vision in 9 through 14,
accompanies, you know, this final beast with the horn-talking trash gets defeated and killed,
and we're told that the dominion is taken away from the beasts and given to the son of man,
but they continue to live for a long time. They're sort of still around.
Yeah, right. An interesting useful point. Right, and the mark of this horn is it sort of makes war
against the holy ones. And that's usually translated as saints here, which is a valid translation
of holy ones, but usually what we associate with the New Testament, right? And can give
the wrong idea, right? We think the saints, oh, it's talking about persecuting Christians.
Well, this is the book of Daniel. So this is primarily talking about that there is this,
What they're seeing is this persecution by empires,
the Babylonian empire,
persecuting Daniel and his friends,
that we see throughout the Book of Daniel.
And then the Persians,
also in the Book of Daniel,
and then the Greeks that we see in First and Second Maccabees,
and then the Romans.
So that's this sort of visible material part,
is this persecution, but what lies behind that
is this spiritual warfare.
Yeah, this concept of, you know, in heaven as on earth,
you know, or put it the other way, you know,
on earth as in heaven, that there is a war going on,
on all levels of the creation,
both the material visible and the invisible,
you know, heavenly reality at the same time.
Right, right.
And sort of at the culmination of the interpretation,
talking about the Son of Man,
just to add to this in verse 27,
it says that his kingdom shall be an everlasting kingdom
and all dominions shall serve in Obey him.
Dominions being sort of beings,
that's that rank of angels.
Right.
Right, who have authority over the nations.
So the dominions, the spirits behind these powers
ultimately are going to have to submit to Christ as well
at the end of the long time.
Right, and I mean, this is the exact theme
that the Lord is referencing right before the ascension.
All authority on heaven and earth has been given to me,
go there for and make disciples of all nations.
Right.
Rome didn't suddenly disappear
and stop persecuting Christians.
Right, right.
There's, you know, Christ is ruling in the midst
of his enemies.
I had someone really actually asked me recently,
they're like, how can you say that Christ
has defeated the demons when things are as bad
as they are right now?
And it's like, well, if you understand
what the pagan world was like,
and then how the whole world changed
with the coming of Christ,
then you begin to see that what we're looking at
is no longer demons in charge.
Rather, this is demons on the run,
and they're looting and burning as they go.
They don't run things anymore.
the way that they once did.
But they're still causing a lot of trouble
as they're being routed.
Right.
So all that's set up.
Now we can finally get to Revelation 13.
Okay.
Right.
And these two beasts.
And these two beasts emerge in Revelation 13.
And both of them are said to have the power
that we've already seen the dragon in chapter 12, the devil.
And these two beasts who emerge in chapter 13
have the power of the dragon.
And if we're talking about the power of the devil,
according to St. Paul's epistle to the Hebrews,
that's death.
Yeah.
Right.
Violence death.
We see this, again, this chaos idea,
it's two beasts.
One beast emerges from the sea and one from the earth,
from the arts, from the underworld.
And so it's very clear now that we've read these things,
if you read the Second Temple, early Christian literature,
leading up to this, this is Leviathan from the sea
and behemoth.
This is not now a representative of them,
but this is them.
And so they're sort of the paradigmatic beasts.
These are the forces that animate the various
and stanchions, the various aspects that we see in the material world.
This is now exposing. Remember, that's what's being revealed. Apocalypse, right?
Revelation, this is what's being revealed. The demons behind the curtains, so to speak,
are now stepping out. Right. We're going to reveal what's behind these things you're seeing
and experiencing in the material world, the spiritual reality behind it.
So this is important because just like there's a tendency to play pin the tail on the Antichrist.
Someone out there is creating a game right now called Pin the Tail of the Antichrist.
I'm going to be standing it to us.
Yes.
And they'll have photos of various figures in world history,
Napoleon Hitler, Juan Carlos King of Spain,
pick one.
So when we see these beast of pig, we just
saw the beast in Daniel referring to these specific empires
that emerged in sequence.
He was giving us Daniel.
This is what are several places where the book of Daniel
and its visions gives us the timeline
of when the Messiah is gonna be born.
And people had figured that out in the first century.
That's why there were so many people showing up
in the first century claiming to be the Messiah.
Because not just the actual Messiah, but fake ones.
Yeah, because Rome was on the scene.
Right, and they were reading the book of Daniel
and going, oh yeah, now's the time
when this is supposed to happen, right?
So people managed to be a little narcissistic,
managed to convince themselves they were in.
So there's been a tendency then to apply that same kind of reading to what we get in Revelation 13.
To treat this not as being the revelation of the power behind all of it throughout history,
but to view it as being a particular one.
I see, I see.
So the story continues.
Right.
Right, and so amongst our Protestant friends, for example, you will have people who are
preterists who want to say that all of this prophecy has already been fulfilled, or at
least most of it.
And they will say, well, okay, these beasts are talking about the Roman Empire.
It's a specific empire, it's the Roman Empire, that's in the past.
And conversely, among our Protestant friends,
particularly among people who are of a pre-millennial bent,
but even some who are of an omelennial or other bent
in terms of how they see the end times,
they will see this as, this is talking about
some particular future,
kind of empire or oppressor.
Yeah, I remember when, you know, in the 1980s,
growing up in churches that were very much of that kind,
And often it was taken from just from the future to now.
So in other words, so this is about, you know,
the big one at the time was the Soviet Union.
This is about the Soviet Union, which means
at the end of the world is coming like any day now, you know.
Right, yeah, yeah.
Yeah, this is so this is some future thing.
And now here it is, right?
Yeah.
I think, you know, and, you know,
America in particular has this millennianism in its, you know, in its soup.
And it's a religious soup.
You know, people have been looking for the end of the world over and over again.
And I think this is one of the things that why a lot of people get super,
super anxious about what they see bad things happening in the world is like,
this is the end.
This is the precursor to that.
You know, or this is, this is, it's as arrived.
You know, like there's this, there's this sense.
Often I think not really realizing what's actually going on in these scriptural passages.
You know, like, you know, the answer to the question, are we living in the end times is yes, and we've been living in the end times for 2,000 years.
At least, you know, this is still these last days. Are these the last last last last days? I don't know about that. We don't know.
Yeah, right, we don't know.
Right, we don't know. And this goes back further. It's not just the US. This is yeah. Yeah. I just this starts around
1,000 AD. Yeah, right because there were people looking at
Revelation 20 and saying oh, well this period where Christ reigns in the midst of his enemies is gonna last a thousand years
Well, we must be about on it right? It's a thousand AD. Yeah
And you know, and that's not to make light of evil things happening in the world
but just to say that the the sort of prophetic narrative that sometimes is pushed is
is a bit of a stretch, you know, in terms of what the scripture actually is saying.
Right. And so there's there was medieval apocalypticism surrounding the crusades.
You see it in the Reformation. Oh yeah.
Tons of it. You see it with Jonathan Edwards. You see it with Sir Isaac Newton.
You see it with all this is World War One. This is just a thing. Yeah. Yeah. Napoleon.
Yeah, yeah. So, um, and what we're going to see though, as now we get into the, into the text,
is that again, this is talking about the animated experience themselves. These are the paradigmatic
beasts that lie behind not one of those, but all of those. Right? So in one way, I'm not saying all
those people were wrong. In one way, I'm saying they were all right. Just not in the way they think.
right? Just out of the way they think. That there is this force behind all of
that. And so when they look at something in their world happening and they
point to that and say, see a connection to these beasts in Revelation, there is a
connection. Yes. Right. But but it's not that that's taught making a prediction.
And now that prediction is happening in front of you. Right. Right. That's the
extra step. So we see that right away when we get into the beast from the sea
and the way he's described in Revelation 13,
because we're told he has seven heads, that's Leviathan.
Right, Leviathan is the seven headed serpent,
and he's coming out of the sea,
and that there are 10 horns on each head.
Those 10 horns, remember the fourth beast.
In Daniel.
In Daniel had the 10 horns.
And then when you look at the description of him,
He's got leopard parts and bear parts and lion parts, right? And this isn't saying he's man bear pig. This is
he's a combination of all four beasts in Daniel, right? Right? And Leviathan, right? And
there are on the heads, there are these blasphemous names and titles.
This is a reference to a phenomenon that happened in the Roman Empire, but not just in the Roman Empire.
This happened in pretty much all of the empires from Daniel and going forward where the individual emperor, the ruler, would take to himself these titles.
So you look at the Seljukid monarchs who ruled over the area that included Palestine, including Judea.
You have Antiochus Sotair, the Savior.
You have Antiochus the fourth epiphanies,
the manifestation of a God.
Or I mean a gust has called himself Savior of the world.
Savior of the world, son of God.
The Lord.
These are all titles that these emperors took.
And we're going to talk more about that in a little bit.
So we see this is bundling all of this together. This isn't talking about what in particular, but bundling it all together
and
it's even
refers to
the fact that
that what this represents this spirit this force is is being worshipped over against not just God himself but against
it's set up against the divine counsel, the kingdom,
and the dominion of God on earth.
Yeah, I mean, in Revelation 13, it says,
you know, this beast, it opened its mouth
to utter blasphemies against God,
blaspheming his name and his dwelling.
That is, those who dwell in heaven
also was allowed to make war on the saints
and to conquer them.
So there's this, you know, a kingdom against the kingdom
God and all the holy ones who are dwelling within it. Right. And notice also though that
language, it was allowed. Even as terrible as this is, it's on a leash, Leviathan, still on a leash.
And this idea of this kind of animating spirit that starts all the way back with Cain building
that first city and goes to the tower of Babel and goes through all of these human empires,
right? This is sort of the core insight of what St. Augustine picks up on in City of God. When
he talks about the City of God over against, right, the City of Man. Right, right, right. The City of
Man starts with Cain building that city. And it's worth noting that St. Augustine saw even the Christian
Roman Empire that was collapsing in the West around him as part of the city of man.
This is a separate thing.
So that brings us to the beast from the earth. So then we have the second beast,
the beast from the earth at Revelation chapter 13. And it's described as having horns like a lamb,
but speaking like the dragon.
Right? So this is, as our color pointed out,
this is an antichrist depiction.
Yeah, it looks like a lamb, the Messiah,
but talks like the Messiah.
Like the devil.
Right.
So but it's speaking the devil's words, not gods.
Remember St. John wrote Revelation.
Remember what St. John says over and over again in his gospel, right?
Christ says, I speak the words of my father who is in heaven. I do the works of my father who is in heaven, right?
So this guy may look like a lamb, but he's speaking the words and doing the deeds of his father who is the devil in this case.
This figure and what he does is he gets people to worship the beast from the sea and
and through the beast from the sea, the dragon, the devil, ultimately, right, himself.
So this is a religious leader and a religious system, right, that is then tied to an
a function of this sort of world system that is animated by the first beast.
I mean, it's essentially a kind of state religion, right?
That's this, you know, it's state Satanism, so to speak.
Right.
A civil religion, which does not appear to be Satanism.
Yeah, right.
It appears to be something else.
Yes, it appears to be something else.
Looks like a limb.
Yeah.
And so, right, so these are these two beasts,
behemoth and Leviathan and how these two spirits are functioning, how they're revealed to be functioning behind the scenes.
Not just in St. John's Day, he's making clear, but before that, and after that, until the end.
And then in Revelation 19, verses 17 through 21,
St. John describes what happens to these beasts at the end.
And spoiler alert, it's going to be a beast feast.
Yes.
Yeah, okay.
So here's what it, here's Revelation 19, 17 to 21.
Then I saw an angel standing in the sun, and with a loud voice, he called to all the birds
that fly directly overhead, come, gather for the great supper of God, to eat the flesh of
kings, the flesh of captains, the flesh of mighty men, the flesh of horses and their riders,
and the flesh of all men, both free and slave, both small and great.
And I saw the beast, and the kings of the earth, with their armies gathered to make war
against him, who was sitting on the horse and against his army.
And the beast was captured, and with it the false prophet, who in its presence had done
the signs by which he deceived those who had received the mark of the beast, and those
who worshipped its image.
These two were thrown alive into the lake of fire that burns with sulfur, and the rest
were slain by the sword that came from the mouth of him who was sitting on the horse, and
all the birds were gorge with their flesh.
So I mean, this is the same scene right out of Ezekiel chapter 39, right?
Right.
And so those forces of chaos and evil and destruction are turned into nourishment for the creation.
And so it's not just order defeats chaos, it's God brings order out of chaos, good out
of evil, life out of death, right, in this, in this imagery.
And so to narrow our focus down a little, right, because we talked about this being, right,
there's clearly symbolism about Rome here, right?
This is clearly the spirit, the beast from the sea is clearly the spirit animating Rome.
The beast from the earth is clearly animating Roman religion, right?
Because people literally worship Rome and worship the emperor, right?
But there's also this particular anti-Christ element, right?
And just like there is a particular reference in St. John's Day for Empire,
There's a particular reference in St. John's day for who the emperor is,
who was also the pontifex Maximus,
who was also the high priest of the Roman religion.
Right, and that was Nero.
That's Nero, yes.
So, just like we talked about with the empires,
the same thing applies to the Antichrist.
In fact, if you go to 1 John, again, written by the same author,
Say, John says, you have heard that an antichrist will come and already antichrists plural have a risen.
Yeah. Right. So he's not denying that there will be one final antichrist. Right. And just like there will be one final empire because Christ is going to return and there will be one presumably at that point. That'll be the last one.
But that doesn't mean that it's just to this figure of the future.
Yeah, right.
This is a really important point.
A lot of times when we're playing pin the tail in the Antichrist,
we ignore the fact that it's plural, that there's been a bunch.
And then we can become, even if you recognize that,
then you might become obsessed, well, like, okay, is this the final one?
And the truth is it's, you know, sort of anti-Christ and empires all the way down.
This force keeps animating things all the way down.
It's always with us, right?
It's always going to be the context in which the people of God are called to be faithful.
Right, right. And so again, you know,
Somebody wants to say, you know Napoleon was an antichrist.
Okay.
Sure.
Hitler Stalin.
Yeah.
Lenin.
Okay.
Right.
Mao.
Yeah.
You know, it's not just a question of finding this one.
Right.
This is, this is, we're having a type revealed to us.
And Nero is sort of emblematic of this.
for St. John's Day. He's the one who's sort of in front of St. John. And the particular element that sort of, there are a few elements that cement this.
Two main ones and then a secondary one. The first main one is this imagery of the beast having this wound that was healed, this mortal wound that was healed.
And this is a connection to what's come down to us
as the named the Nero Redevis myth.
It's just mean.
Nero come back to life.
Yeah, I'll have again.
Yeah.
So Nero, of course, committed suicide back in the,
I believe, 68, 80, 68.
And I won't get into all the current scholarly arguments about the fire and everything.
But anyway, Nero died by suicide.
But almost immediately there were rumors and this kind of thing that he wasn't really dead.
Right.
That he had fake the suicide or he was injured but not really dead.
and he'd gone off to Asia Minor, not coincidentally. This is where St. John is writing to, the seven
churches he addresses Revelation to are all in Asia Minor in the place where folks thought Nero might
be hiding out to come back. So according to St. Irenaeus of Leon, who I have no reason as a church
to doubt on this since he was the spiritual grandson of St. John. St. John's
revelation, he had his vision circa AD 95, second year of
demotion. So we have evidence from before that of the existence of this
belief. And one of the primary places we have that is in deocrystallum, no
relation to St. John. Yes, that's not a last name. It just means golden mouth. Right. So,
it's a good speaker. A title for somebody who is good with rhetoric. But,
Dio Chris Estom was a Roman pagan. His discourse 21 on beauty that was written circa 88. So
seven years before St. John had his vision. He talks about there about this hope that
that Nero would return and sort of return the empire
to its glory days.
We have in the Similene oracles, four and five,
Tacitus' histories, two eight and Sutonius, 57.
They all talk about in later Roman history,
pseudo-Nero's, who people who show up in Rome
or other major Roman cities claiming to be Nero.
Yeah, back from the dead to try to get a throne
or get a following or start a revolution, right?
So this was ingrained enough in people
that you could try to pull that, right?
This sort of story was firmly embedded.
And this lasts all the way up to say to Guston
to St. Augustine in the city of God that we mentioned earlier in 2019-3.
So this is the 5th century in North Africa, the Western Roman Empire, the Christian Roman
Empire, as the Western part is collapsing.
He tells us that at that time there were pagans who were going around holding out hope and
saying that Nero would return and save the Western Empire.
And there were Christians who also believed it.
There were Christians who said,
Nero is going to come back and he's going to be the Antichrist.
He's going to be the final Antichrist.
So they were doing that even in the fifth century.
So that's how embedded this was.
Nero as sort of this prototypical Antichrist figure.
And Nero, the relationship between Nero and this figure
Revelation 13 is just embedded in Roman Christianity, not just here. But again, Neuro is the type
of this. It's not saying, Oh, Neuro was it. So don't worry about that whole antichrist thing
anymore.
The one and only he's sorry, pretterious. So there's also, so this is this kind of secondary
argument, I don't want to go down this rabbit hole. I think it's kind of a weak
argument, frankly, but in Revelation 17 verses 10 through 11, there's these seven
kings and people try to link them up to seven Roman Emperor, the first seven Roman
Emperor's and there's some shenanigans there. I don't think we need to try and do
that. But more importantly, we get the mark of the B's name at the end of chapter
13 which is either the 666 that everybody's familiar with or in the oldest manuscripts we have
of Revelation 616 and that's not a contradiction or a problem because if you do what's called
Gammatria. What's Gammatria, Father Stephen? I know that I'll explain this to Father Andrew.
I know most of our listeners engage in Gabbatria on an almost daily basis.
Gabbatria was a way of, well in Hebrew, they didn't have numerals, right, or Greek for
that matter.
Yeah, they just use letters.
Right, they just use letters.
And so that lends itself to a system in which you can kind of swap out letters for
numbers and then add them up and do things both to put things in code or to do
esoteric stuff with like the text of the Bible sort of quasi-numerological
magical stuff but also just kind of simple encoding and stuff but so the
language should realize that 13th surrounding this number that it's the
numbers the name of a man right I mean say John is very deliberately going
let the reader understand. You know what I'm saying?
No, it's not a wing saying no more.
Right. Right. So in order to do Gammatria with a name or a word or a sentence in a language other
than Hebrew, you have to transliterate it into Hebrew. Right. Because it's all about Hebrew letters
and numbers. And so if you take Nero's title in Greek, Nero and Kaisar, of course,
it's doing Hebrew, you just have the consonants. And you add that up, you get 666. If you take
his title in Latin and translate it into Hebrew. You get Nero Kaisar, which adds up to
616. So they're both encoding the same thing using the same methods. It's just which source
language they're going into Hebrew from.
So this is the same John saying,
you know, the emblematic person I'm talking about is Nero.
That's right. Yes.
But again, this is emblematic.
Right. So yes, I know Ronald Wilson Reagan.
There are six letters in each name.
Oh man.
But he was not the anti Christ.
I'm going to go out on the limb here.
At least not the final one.
You're right.
There's some people in South America who might think he was one of them.
Bung, that's he was not, right, that's not what this is going for.
So, where does this bring? Well, okay. We're talking about these spiritual forces,
the Hemath and Leviathan, and the way they express themselves in our world is by being the
spirits that lie behind empire, that lie behind this whole concept of empire. And there's a fundamental
difference between the idea of a tribe or a nation or a people or a cultural group and
an empire. Yes. Yeah. One, you know, the first is an actual shared life based, you know,
in the earlier stages on families, right? But empire is about taking your values, ideology,
way of life on the road and making other people follow it.
You know, it's through violence and death.
Yeah, exactly.
The power of the dragon.
It's totalitarian, it's expansive,
it's aggressive, it's conquering,
which is the opposite of the gospel,
which is a universal way of life,
but it's spread not through force,
but through persuasion,
through and through martyrdom, frankly. Right. And it takes these different forms as the gospel comes to different tribes and nations and peoples.
Right. It doesn't come and dominate them and seek to eradicate them.
The race is entities. Yeah. Yeah.
Yeah.
And so, so this also always, I mean, in the ancient world, there was no real separation, but there's always a religious dimension to empire.
There is always a sort of imperial religion.
Even in an empire like the Soviet Empire that ostensibly was atheistic, there was functionally
civil religion.
You look at the Arab conquest and immediately after the Arab conquest you find Islam rising
up.
There is always the Persian Empire, it was the official Zoroastrian religion.
And again, all of these are enforced.
And often the state itself, the empire itself, the emperor himself is worshipped as a God,
as part of this.
Both Caesar was a God and animated by a divine force.
And there was the God Roma.
Yeah.
was worship. And so we can see how that language about the beast from the sea, right, that there is this kingdom of God and administration of God over the world.
And instead one chooses and one therefore worships and serves this imperial administration, which is not simply an imperial human administration, but is animated by these hostile spiritual forces of chaos.
forces of chaos at evil.
Yeah, and it sets itself up as in competition
with the gospel because it also is a totalizing
totalitarian force.
But it's, you know, it's force, right?
And, you know, what God sets up again is not about
smashing people into worshiping him.
You know, it's given in humility and again with martyrdom.
Right. And a major part of what happens as the religious function of empire is the creation
of founding myths, the rewriting of history, the rewriting of the story of the world, the
rewriting of the story of culture, and sort of a preeminent example of this is the beginning
of the Roman Empire under Augustus. So Augustus becomes the first Roman Empire, Octavian
and becomes Augustus, and he has Virgil
write the new history of the world,
which culminates in Augustus.
And he has Ovid go and collect all the disparate traditions
of all the tribes and nations and peoples
and forge them together into one collective story,
one sort of monoculture, one ruling culture.
And so the Greeks get their actual culture
displaced by a Romanized version of Greek culture.
You get the Egyptians, their culture,
replaced with a Romanized version of Egyptian culture.
And of course the Greeks and then the Romans
try to do that with Judea.
And that's what triggers the Jewish revolts.
Is their refusal to allow their culture
to be Hellenized and then Romanized?
because the base of their culture is coming from the Torah,
right, and they choose that instead.
But the Greeks of the Romans can't help but try to force compliance.
Right. And reinforce in violence.
And that's the whole ethos of empire.
Right. And that's, and that's why it's not just sort of
computational whatever. That's why it's anti-Christ.
It sets itself up as not just against Christ,
but instead of Christ.
It's doing a parody, so to speak, of what the kingdom of God is actually about.
Like, you know, the kingdom of God Christianizes cultures.
It doesn't suppress them.
It doesn't replace them.
It Christianizes them in a way that's healing for mankind and not destructive.
Right?
You know, the kingdom of God does bring all cultures together under its influence and rule
and so forth.
but not by force, not by conquest on the human level.
There is certainly a spiritual conquest going on, right?
But it's not about making people mandatory, you know, do the will of God.
Right.
Well, let's say some things to wrap up and kind of give us a way forward.
At the end of this episode about Leviathan,
Beheeman the Beasts out of the sea and the earth.
To me, the big question is,
now that we've seen the way that the world on a macro level operates,
what do we do as Christians or as people who maybe want to become Christians?
How do we live the right way?
Well, I think it's pretty clear that we don't try to beat them
their own game. We don't try to win by acting like the anti-Christ empires and leaders. That
is not the way. It's not the way, right? And the reason why that's not the way is not just
because that's bad, but because that is fundamentally telling a different story about what the world
is. I mean, we saw, we heard just now about how Augustus has to rewrite the history of the
world in order to justify his rule. That's the false story. That's not the real
story. That's not the story that we are actually in. That is a lie being told
by these demonic forces, right, and a lie about the creation of an ultimate
empire, right? The story that is the story of Christ is the story that number
Number one begins, as we know, with the fallen rebellion of certain spiritual powers and
then their dragging mankind into their rebellion.
And so then the story of Christ, his rescue of us from that slavery, from being dominated
by these dark powers and behaving like them and becoming like them.
That's the story and that the kingdom of God is coming and now is.
And so then what is the response to the coming of the Kingdom of God?
Well, we see it right there at the Gospels.
Repent.
Repent for the Kingdom of God as it hint.
The scripture throughout its text is always correcting the takes that paganism is offering.
It's always saying, no, no, no, this is the real story.
This is what's actually happening.
And frankly, the narrative that the scripture offers is much more coherent and takes account
of everything in the world in a way that none of these other stories actually do.
If you look at them close enough, you'll always see the cracks.
You'll always see that it doesn't really work out.
There's something false.
There's some lie down at the bottom of them.
The Bible is always correcting these stories and saying, no, this is the truth.
And if we understand that we're in that story and we understand that the people that we
should be emulating are our Lord who doesn't come wielding a sword to strike down human
beings, but he comes and offers himself to die.
He does strike down his enemies.
His enemies are the dark powers, but he dies for us.
man kind that he's offering himself for so that we can benefit from that so that we can be rescued
from that slavery, right? When we see that we're supposed to be like the Lord and then we look at the
way the saints are like the Lord, again offering themselves, again martyrdom, humility, this is the way,
this is completely different than the way that the Leviathan, behemoth systems work. It's not about
destruction and domination and tyranny and so forth, it's about love. When we see that
then we see exactly how we're supposed to live. We see how we can be faithful in the midst
of this. You know, one of the themes that's really kind of intriguing in a lot of this
discussion is this theme that we see, as we titled it, Leviathan, it's What's For Dinner,
that chaos can serve order, that chaos can literally be served to two order as food, as
nourishment. And I think that's one of the things that we're called to His Christians,
is even as we live in the midst of a world that is animated by these dark demonic powers,
we can take what's around us and turn it to good. Man meant it for evil because he was
inspired by demons to make it evil, but God turns it to good. And so we are called to participate
and God's works in this world.
And that's one of them is to take what is evil
and to turn it to good.
And so we can take what we see around us,
even the stories that we see around us,
even pagan stories, right?
But even the stuff that's happening around us
right at this moment, we can take that
and turn it to what is good, right?
By interpreting it, by critiquing it, right?
By seeing how sometimes in surprising
unusual ways, things that are dark and tragic can be turned to beauty and
towards hope for the future and towards life and love, sacrifice, all these things.
So yes, there is an eschatological reality in which Leviathan is going to be
cut up and served to the people in the wilderness. But there's also a present
reality in which we can do the same thing, in which we can take the Leviathanic, if I
may say, cultures that we live in and use them for the service of Christ's gospel, for his
kingdom, for the rescuing of mankind from these dark demonic forces.
So I've loved having this conversation.
I think it's one of the most interesting and intriguing ones we've had so far.
And that's my takeaway, Father.
So I'm not on social media.
So I'm going to go ahead and get myself canceled.
Who knows how long it'll even take me to find out about it.
Yeah.
So I was going to say today, but this has been going on for a while.
but there's been another flare up of it today.
There are a lot of folks,
you can find them on the internet,
you can find them in all kinds of media
who are very concerned that,
and I know we have listeners in other countries,
but I'm in the United States.
Very concerned that the United States
or the Western world,
whenever we wanna say that is,
or the liberal democratic tradition,
as we heard it expressed by our caller,
that that is about to collapse into something else,
something more like empire, something more like tyranny,
the kind of thing we've been describing
is being motivated by Behimeth and Leviathan.
And if you're a person who's worried about that,
I have bad news for you.
It happened about 50 years ago.
So if you do even a casual sort of study
of history and really dig into it,
the British Empire was the Empire.
It really died in World War I,
but it was kind of coughing up blood a little
and still until World War II.
And then after World War II, frankly,
the British handed the baton to the United States of America
to become the new empire.
And as always happens at the beginning of that,
everything looks good.
The Roman Empire headed a suspicious beginning.
Alexander's conquest headed a suspicious beginning.
But since then, it has taken its course,
and now that's where we are.
The world now is either dominated by the United States
of America militarily and or dominated by our culture.
Our movies, our television, with all
of the elements of our media.
That's our main production.
We don't build actual objects anymore.
We make culture and send that culture
with all the sex, violence, blasphemy,
and everything else that we Christians criticize about it
all over the world to indoctrinate the world in consumerism
and all of those good things.
So it's not about sitting and worrying about whether
and when we're gonna be in that situation,
we are in that situation.
Christians have pretty much always been in that situation.
Either they lived in the headquarters of that empire
or they lived someplace where that empire
was a threatening presence.
So question then is, well, what do we do about it?
Is this just hopeless?
Do we just sort of brace ourselves for incoming martyrdom?
Is there nothing we can do except pray that our suffering
is not prolonged?
There's a lot more we can do than that.
But to do that, we have to come back
to real Christianity, what Christianity actually is.
What do I mean by that?
We live in a society.
All societies have a base,
and that base is grounded in sort of material realities.
Then built on that reality,
that base, that foundation of reality,
you have a superstructure,
and that superstructure is all the cultural elements
that we think about.
And they're supported by that base,
they feed back into that base,
they promote and they serve that base.
And for the entirety of the modern period,
I'll be blunt, the entirety of the modern period
in the West and even in a lot of Orthodox countries,
Christianity has not been part of the base of our society.
It's been part of the superstructure.
It's been serving the material realities
of various empires and cultures and civilizations.
I can give lots of examples, right?
Christians lined up to defend King Leopold killing
10 million people in the Congo
to turn it into a rubber farm.
One closer to home for folks in the United States of America,
when slavery became a material necessity
in order to continue the cotton and sugar harvest,
in the plantation system, all of a sudden Christians found Bible verses supporting the enslavement
of Africans, and all of the horrible and brutal violence afflicted upon them. Christianity
served what was necessary for the culture. That's not actually Christianity. That's the
beast from the earth. That's Antichrist. When Christianity distorts itself and contorts itself
to fit its culture, to serve its needs, to serve the ruler of that culture.
That is a twisting and a perversion of Christianity.
Real Christianity, and I know I'm disagreeing with someone publicly on this, but real Christianity
is revolutionary in the truest sense.
Because real Christianity has the power to transform the base.
real Christianity has the ability to change reality by changing people.
Real Christianity is the only thing on earth, the gospel is the only thing on earth that
can transform humanity.
Not just an individual human doing morally better, but transform who and what we are to be
more like Christ.
meaning we can change that base.
This has happened once before in history.
This happened with the Roman Empire.
St. Paul set out to convert the Roman Emperor to Christianity.
That was his goal. That's why he went to Rome.
He says so a couple of times in the Book of Acts.
That didn't happen during his earthly life.
That happened with Constantine.
When St. Constantine became a Christian, the base, which supported the entire culture of
the Roman Empire changed.
And so there were any number of elements of Roman culture that were no longer supported
by that base, and it crumbled.
The Roman view of sexuality crumbled.
The Roman view of men and women crumbled.
the Roman pagan religion crumbled,
the Roman view of humanity as being stratified,
as people who are more and less human, crumbled.
And all those elements of Roman culture,
which were good and positive, and godly,
were all reinforced and strengthened
by the transformation of that base.
So, we have the power through the gospel to change the fundamental reality of our society
and our culture.
But that doesn't start by us going and trying to convert the president of our country.
That doesn't start there.
Not that that's a bad thing to do.
That doesn't start by us trying to convert other civil authorities.
starts with us converting ourselves. That starts with us discovering true Christianity
again and being transformed. Not using Christianity in our own lives to shore up and defend the
things that we already believe or want to be true or the way of life that we want to live,
but instead being transformed by it. I'll be blunt, if you've become a Christian or
or you've joined the Orthodox Church
and become an Orthodox Christian,
and it hasn't changed how you eat,
how you dress, how you act in your family,
how you do your job at work,
how you apportion your time,
how you look at and treat and handle your finances.
If any of those things are untouched,
you have not converted to Christianity.
You've started to.
That's good. It's good to start, right? But you haven't finished.
The revolution has to start in a transformation of your own life.
And when your own life is transformed,
when the basic principles of your life,
the things that your life is built upon change,
and all of the parts that don't need to be there that are sinful and corrupt,
crumble away, and all of the good parts that were created and put there by God are reinforced,
That will put you in the position then to go out and start changing those around you
and ultimately to transform our culture, our communities, our nations, our tribes.
That's where it changes. That's where it starts.
So bad news, we're living in an empire too.
Good news. We've seen once before that our fathers in the faith, our fellow Christians,
were able to completely transform it and defeat it through Christ.
And we can do the same thing.
If number one, we're willing to stop worrying about whether it's an empire not and being afraid.
And number two, if we're willing to begin with ourselves and be radically transformed in a revolutionary way.
and then go out and with the gospel, not with force and violence, bring revolution to our society.
Amen. Well, that is our so for today. Thank you very much for listening. If you didn't get a chance
to call in during a live broadcast, we'd still love to hear from you either via email at Lordofspiritsatainchantfaith.com
or you can message us at our Lordofspirits podcast, Facebook page. We do read everything but we can't
respond everything. We do save some of what you send for possible use in future episodes.
And join us for our live broadcast on the second and fourth Thursdays of the month at 7pm Eastern 4pm
Pacific. If you are on Facebook, you can like our page and join our discussion group, leave reviews
and ratings everywhere, but most importantly, please share this show with a friend whom you know
is going to love it and or benefit from it. And or just needs a cure for insomnia.
That's fine too.
And finally be sure to go to ancientfaith.com
Stroke Support and help make sure we and lots of other AFR
podcasters stay on the earth.
And please buy my new book, Aruzo God, and also Father
Steven's book, which came out earlier this year,
Religion of the Apostles at store.inchantfaith.com.
Thank you, good night.
God bless you all.
You've been listening to the Lord of Spirits
With Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung,
a listener supported presentation of ancient faith radio.
And I beheld, and I heard the voice of many angels round about the throne, and the beasts,
and the elders, and the number of them was 10,000 times 10,000, and thousands of thousands,
saying with a loud voice, worthy is the land that was slain to receive power, and riches,
wisdom and strength and honor and glory and blessing.
Revelation chapter 5 verses 11 through 12.