He will be a staff for the righteous, with which for them to stand and not to fall,
and he will be the light of the nations and the hope of those whose hearts are troubled.
All who dwell on the earth will fall down and worship him,
and they will praise and bless and celebrate with song the Lord of Spirits,
1st denoc, chapter 48, verses 4-5.
The modern world doesn't acknowledge but is nevertheless haunted by spirits, angels, demons, and saints.
In our time, many year into break free of the prison of a flat, secular materialism,
to see and to know reality as it truly is.
What is this spiritual reality like?
How do we engage with it well?
How do we permeate everyday life with spiritual presence?
Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen De Young,
host this live Colin show, focused on enchantment in creation,
the union of the scene and unseen as made by God and experienced by mankind throughout history.
Welcome to the Lord of Spirits.
Welcome back to the Lord of Spirits podcast.
I'm Father Andrew Stephen Damick in Emmaus, Pennsylvania,
and my co-host Father Stephen De Young is with me from Lafayette, Louisiana.
So unlike most of our episodes, this one actually is pre-recorded, we're not live.
Because when this actually does air, I'm going to be participating in the ancient faith ministries
and staff retreat.
So if you were to call right now, you're not going to get anyone on the other end.
But we should be back again live in the future.
In this episode, right now, we're talking to you from the past.
It's right, we're time-traveling voices.
It's like a message in a bottle thrown into the airways.
Right, so this message for this episode is that we're going to be looking at the mysterious figure of Melchizedek.
So Abram, who is going to be later called Abraham, meets him in Genesis chapter 14.
Melchizedek gets mentioned again in Psalm 110,
and then he shows up one more time in the epistle to the Hebrews in its meditation on the priesthood.
But I mean, who is this guy?
And why does Hebrews link him to Christ?
Is he some kind of pre-New Testament appearance of the Son of God?
What's going on here, you know?
So we get to start, and we're going to focus on his appearance first in Genesis 14.
But we're going to need a little bit of contextual backstory.
So what's going on here, Father Stephen?
What happens right before Abraham actually meets Melchizedek?
Right, and this isn't some arcane lore.
Or under Tharcana, you can find this by reading the previous verses.
Yes, right.
A lot of times, you know, we're like, okay,
well, let's talk about Melchizedek.
Well, so we look at we do a search in Bible Gateway, right?
Melchizedek.
Oh, okay, so we read, we read Genesis 14 verses 18 through 20,
which is where he appears, and don't read what comes before that,
what comes after that.
Yeah, I mean, in this case, no archeological dig required.
Just read your Bible.
Yes, you don't need to know eukeritic.
You don't need any of that.
So before these verses, well, first maybe we should read these verses.
Okay, yeah, let's read those verses just to remind everyone of the context.
Yeah, okay.
So this is Genesis 14 verses 18 through 20.
Then Melchizedek, king of Salem, brought out bread and wine
because he was a priest for God most high.
So he blessed him, saying, blessed is Abraham by God most high,
possessor of heaven and earth.
And blessed be God most high, who has delivered your enemies into your hand.
Then he, that is Abram, gave to him a tithe of everything.
And that's it.
Yes, that is it.
There are further conversations that Abram has right after this,
but Melchizedek is just gone at that point, he just disappears.
And he sort of comes out of nowhere and disappears into nowhere.
And St. Paul's epistle to the Hebrews comments on this fact,
but we'll get to that later on.
So in terms of the context, we'll start with what comes before this.
Right.
Because of course, this begins with a then.
Right?
So he's doing this, Melchizedek shows up with the bread and the wine for a reason.
And so what we have at the beginning of Genesis chapter 14
is a description of the war of the five kings,
which sounds like something in Tolkien.
I mean, but this is actually a battle of five armies.
Not really, it's just two armies, but yeah.
Wow.
And so what's set up is that sort of our main figure at this time
is this fellow Ketterlay Omer,
sometimes pronounced Ketterlay Omer by kids in Sunday school,
and then leading to cheese jokes, but Ketterlay Omer,
who is labeled here as an Ilomite king,
his name is from Kenor and LeHomer,
which means servant of LeHomer, who is an Ilomite goddess.
Okay.
So this fella is a pagan, but if you remember our last episode,
you know, Abram lives at the end of the war three period,
the Ilomites are expanding their territory at this time.
Okay.
And they're the ones who ultimately end the war three period when they capture war.
But so the Ilomites are expanding,
and what we're reading about in Genesis 14 is them expanding into Palestine,
into Canaan, and its environs.
They're moving in that direction.
And so he, and he has a number of Ilomite kings who are vassals of his,
whose forces are with him as they're expanding and subjecting the city states of that region
to vassalhood and to send tribute to the growing Ilomite territory.
He counters resistance, several of these cities, including Sodom and Gomorrah,
decide that they want to resist and throw off the shackles of Header LeHomer.
Now when we read about the expansion at the beginning of Genesis 14,
the people who Header LeHomer is taking out and displacing
as he expands into Canaan, are a list of people who we should probably be familiar with already
because we've quoted Deuteronomy two a whole bunch of times on this podcast.
It's the Gurghazites and the Hiveites and the Meme and the Amalakites, right?
It's all the giant clans that Keter LeHomer and his Ilomite armies,
remember these are Mesopotamians, like Abraham, like Abram,
are coming in and displacing them and taking their territory.
So when Sodom and Gomorrah and the other cities of the plain decide they want to throw off at Rebellion's Header LeHomer,
they're siding with the Amalakites and the other giant clans against the Mesopotamians.
And interestingly, Genesis 14 names the names Keter LeHomer and his vassals who are on his side.
It does not name the kings on the other side.
So what's that all about?
The five kings who attack them are just the king of Sodom, the king of Gomorrah, the king of right.
Yeah, I mean, I see, for instance, in Genesis 14, five, this explicit reference to Keter LeHomer and the kings who were with them came and defeated the Reffaites, the Refaim.
Yeah, and the Zuzim.
This is literally a list of giant clans here who he came and defeated.
But then when it gets to the kings, the five kings, we're going to try to overthrow them.
It's just the king of this city, the king of that city, the king of this other city.
Their names are unimportant.
Because they're the bad guys.
In fact, the king of Sodom actually is going to, after the milk is in a passage, have a conversation with Abram.
And he's not named there either.
He's just the king of Sodom.
Right.
The guy who happened to be king of Sodom at that point, because he's not important.
So, remember, these are priests kings who probably set themselves up as God kings.
Which means they're receiving worship.
And in the place where Abram is living, these people are considered divine beings.
It's sort of immensely powerful and important.
And the biblical text doesn't even bother to record their names.
Yes.
May their names be blocked out.
So, it's not even there.
So, when they rise up, they're essentially siding with those conquered giant clans.
Because even now, even at this level in Genesis, just as we're going to see is the Torah continues,
there are your run-of-the-mill pagans and that there are giant clans.
Right.
And pagans are people who have become deluded, who are now being held captive to these spiritual powers,
who they worshipped, and who that gave them power and control over them.
Whereas, the giant clans are the ones who are participating in sort of demonic sexual immorality, human sacrifice, cannibalism.
Like, they're the extreme end.
Right.
And there's this distinction made sort of even here.
So, your run-of-the-mill Mesopotamian pagan is still better than a giant clan.
Right.
At least gets mentioned by name.
Yes.
And he could be used by God to render judgment against those giant clans for their actions.
Right.
So, because he's on the right side, Hitler Leomur and his vassals wipe out make pretty quick work of the five cities of the plain and their kings and go and plunder them.
And plundering doesn't just mean we take all their gold and silver and all their nice stuff.
It also means we take a bunch of their people to be slaves.
Yeah.
And one of those people who gets taken as a slave is Abram's nephew Lot.
Right.
Because he's hanging out in Zoar, which is one of the cities he just got conquered.
And which is near Sodom.
Right.
Every time we see Lot, he's moved closer and closer to Sodom.
Until when Sodom is going to be destroyed, he's actually living in town.
But so he's already in that area.
So he gets taken to be a slave.
So Abram is not siding with the king of Sodom.
Right.
He doesn't go into the battle in the first place, but he is going to rescue his nephew Lot.
Who's a member of his family?
Who's been taken captive by the by the Elonites.
And so to do that, he goes and gathers together 318 fighting men.
He's made some agreements with some people near the land he's living on.
Those agreements would have been about who uses what water and how much for their crops and things.
And he's living outside of the city, outside of civilization.
And he gathers together 318 fighting men to go and pursue the Elonite armies to try to overtake them and get a hold of Lot and and set them free.
If you are Orthodox and you have heard this story, it was probably a Vespers.
Right.
This probably before a feast of the Holy Fathers.
Yeah, exactly.
Like, especially the feast of the First Echemical Council.
But any of that chemical councils, you know, it's the point where the reader stumbles over the name Keterley Omer,
which sometimes has a G inserted into it somewhere.
You know, between the A and the O, that's actually correct.
Yeah, look, go more.
Yes.
Yeah.
Right.
There's an eye in there.
It's a long story.
Right.
So, I mean, my sense of the reason why that would be done.
Like, there's this kind of fast, I've heard this, you know, this fast, I'll explain which as well.
Look, there's 318 people in this, in this little rescue operation.
And while there, there were 318 Holy Fathers at the First Echemical Council, you know.
And I kind of want to like.
Which is true.
Yeah.
Although, I have to wonder.
Sometimes it's like, is this a little bit of a chicken egg issue?
Like, do we say there were 318 because we're modeling it?
But anyway, I mean, it doesn't super, super, super matter.
But the, the, the understanding that I would have is the reason why this reading is chosen for the feast of these Fathers is essentially to say that they're engaging in the same kinds of spiritual battles by virtue of what they're doing in those councils.
As was happening this specifically spiritual warfare because it's warfare against demonized, you know, cannibals and so forth, you know, giant clans.
Is my take on that? Is that, is that right?
Right. It's the same kind of rescue operation.
Yeah.
Right.
I mean, and just like lot isn't innocent, right?
The person who falls into heresy, the church isn't innocent in it, right?
They're involved.
Yeah.
Following after the, the heresy arc or probably after the heresy.
But from the perspective of the church, just like lot got a little too close and now he's been taken captive.
It needs to be rescued.
That's what happens to people in the church with heresy.
And so what the Fathers are doing is not trying to impose their power and impose their will impose their views on the whole church, you know, through this act of force at the at the councils.
They're trying to rescue people who have been taken captive by the doctrines of demons.
Yeah.
Right. And bring them back and set them free.
So yeah, that's, that's the, I think the comparison that's going on there.
Cool.
And yeah, the 318 big is just a, you know, subpoint.
Interesting subpoint.
Yeah.
I mean, right.
I mean, I've heard, you know, I've read, you know, the people say, okay, we don't really have a full list of all the bishops who are at the first
medical council.
You know, the tradition is that was 318.
We don't really know how many were there.
And, you know, I don't know, from my point of view, it doesn't really matter exactly how many were there.
Whether there were exactly 318.
And so wow, what an amazing coincidence.
Or whether we, we assign that number because it connects back to this lot rescue operation.
To me, it doesn't matter really.
You know, either way it works.
Yeah.
This also, this also should change our view of April a little bit.
I think sometimes we've grown up with the kids Bible story books.
So we think he's just this kindly old man.
Right.
You know, who, who sort of lives in a tent with a bunch of sheep.
But he's just this really the like he just went to war with professional military of one of the great powers of his day.
And one with like a rag tag militia he put together.
So the first 18, as it were.
Yes.
I love it when a plan comes to you.
So, yeah.
So he's, he's, and this is, you know, at, you know, age 80, you know, 85.
So he hasn't come along yet.
This is still before.
He's a, right.
He's a force to be reckoned with.
So, yeah.
So that, that comes before.
So it is after this victory and the recovery of lot that verse 18 says that Melchizedek, the king of Salem, shows up with the bread and the wine and gives this blessing.
So then immediately after that.
Right.
Sort of the conclusion of the overarching story is that what, when Abram did this, he not only recovered lot, but he recovered a bunch of other people who were being taken as slaves.
Because they didn't have lots separate.
Right.
Where.
And he also recovered a lot of stuff, a lot of the gold and silver and other valuable stuff, you know, in the process.
And so the king of Sodom shows up and says, Hey, thanks for getting back my stuff.
I'll cut you in for part of it.
It's sort of a bounty, right?
Finders fee or a reward.
Right.
I dropped my wallet in the Walmart parking lot.
You found it.
Hey, here's 20 bucks for being honest and returning it to me.
Right.
And Abram says, nope.
Abram says, I don't want any of your stuff.
Right.
And so we see already here for shadowing, right, of this stuff from Sodom and Gomorrah in the cities of the plane.
This stuff that belongs to the giant clans, is it just sort of neutral stuff?
Right.
You say it's just gold or silver or whatever.
It's just objects, right?
Melt it down.
Makes up the else out of it.
Right.
Even if it's a gold idol, melt it down and make something else out of it.
Yeah.
I mean, we should, we should underline that this is a deeply weird thing to do in the ancient world.
Yes.
You defeat somebody.
You take their stuff.
Like that is, like no one would ever leave it aside.
Like it's just, that would be a stupid, stupid thing to do.
And it might even, it might even threaten your survival.
Like you, you take the stuff that you win on a radar and a battle or whatever,
because that's going to be useful for you.
Why would you ever leave it?
Right.
But here you have Abram saying, no, this is all yours, King of Sodom.
Take it.
Yeah.
And he does say, you know, during the, during the trip, some of his fighting men had to eat something.
And so they ate some of the stuff that they retrieved.
Yeah.
Right.
He said, that's sufficient.
Whatever they ate.
That's our cut.
Right.
That's verse 24.
Yeah.
But so he wants none of it.
Right.
And that's because these objects, the material, right, has been tainted and is connected to.
So it's, it's the same reason why you're going to see Israel commanded not to take the plunder from the giant clans.
Yeah.
Right.
If, if someone attacks Israel, according to the, the laws of war and to neuronomy,
if someone attacks Israel, and Israel defends itself and Israel wins,
they could take those people's stuff.
Right.
But not the giant clans.
Not their stuff.
Their stuff has to be destroyed.
Right.
And this is, again, just underlines that Abram has been called out by God, not to participate in the civilizations around him.
And especially then, not the giant clans, because they are the worst.
Yeah.
I mean, Sodom and Gomorrah and the cities of the plane here end up shortly here after it.
Genesis being portrayed as worse.
Right.
The giant clans.
Yeah.
The giant clans get to go on longer than they do.
God takes out Sodom and Gomorrah directly.
So, yeah.
So, and not very long after this.
So that's, that's sort of the overarching context.
So it's, it's in, in the middle of this story that.
Melchizedek shows up.
Right.
And it's interesting.
If you look at the chapter, right, you get the story about the victory from the war.
And, you know, they grab, they grab hold of lot.
They rescue him.
They make the trip back.
They take, they bring back all the stolen property.
And then, you know, the end of the chapter is Abram having the conversation with the king of Sodom.
And then suddenly, boom.
Verse 17.
I'm sorry, verse 18.
Melchizedek just shows up.
It seems like, so says the king of Sodom went out to meet Abram.
And then, and then Melchizedek just shows up with bread and wine.
Like in the middle of this meeting.
I mean, that's, that's how it looks.
You know, as I'm reading this.
Yeah.
And as this interaction with Abram and then disappears and then Abram goes.
Then sees the king of Sodom.
Once again, he's gotten demoted as less important.
Right.
And it's interesting to look at just how this kind of works out in the text.
Like, if this is a kind of, like it's so disconnected from the rest of the text.
Like, there's nothing about those few verses, the Melchizedek verses,
that seem to connect to anything else around them, right?
At least on the face of it.
And so, you know, you might suggest, oh, well, this is some kind of, you know, interpolation or something like that.
Like, well, this is badly done.
If it's an interpolation because it says an Abraham.
Abraham met the king of Sodom and the other kings.
Oh, and then Melchizedek showed up.
Okay, and then Abraham had this conversation with the king of Sodom, you know.
Like, it doesn't, it's not a really, it doesn't make sense as an interpolation.
Right.
Yeah.
You end up with the weird thing that you end up with with most modern source critical method,
to divide up the text and try and reproduce the editorial process,
where you at once have someone who's a literary genius in a complete bumbler,
like at the same time.
Right.
Yeah.
Whatever, whatever looks amazing things,
amazing literary things with the text, but like left all these scenes showing.
Yeah.
Like, he couldn't smooth them over at all.
And no one noticed that after him.
Yeah.
It's really obvious about everything he did.
So, well, what, what, what then sort of is going on and what, what does connect this?
Well, we're told right off the bat that Melchizedek and there really should be,
we're not used to it, but there really should be a hyphen in the middle of his name.
Melchizedek.
Yeah.
TZ.
So, we're told that he's the king of a city.
Right.
So, so that's one connection because we've got a whole bunch of kings of cities here.
And he's the king of a city.
So, that's kind of a vague, vague connection, at least.
Yeah.
Salem is what it's usually given in most English Bibles.
He's the king of Salem.
Right.
And, and sometimes people want to try to turn Salem into Shalom and try to do,
he's the king of peace or something.
And you could, you could do sort of allegorical things with that.
We'll talk about that in a second, but originally the material level.
This is referring to a city that we're all familiar with from later in the Bible.
Hmm.
Jerusalem.
Right.
Because the city of Jerusalem, the name Jerusalem is derived from Ulu Shalim.
Okay.
Which also has a hyphen in it.
Yeah.
Take that apart for us.
So, Uru Shalim is the Akkadian name for, for that city state.
And it has two pieces.
There's a hyphen in there.
The first part is Uru, which you may recognize from like Uru and Uru.
That's a Sumerian word that has come over into Akkadian.
That means city or settlement.
Okay.
And then Shalim is Akkadian.
God.
Okay.
So it is the city of Shalim.
Yeah.
The city or settlement of Shalim.
Right.
And that's why you get it referred to as just Salim or Shalim.
Just like here in Pennsylvania, we have Pittsburgh.
The Berg part means, you know, a city or a fortified area.
And William Pitt is the divinized God that is worshiped in Pittsburgh.
No, probably not.
But.
Sorry.
St. Peter's a Berg might work better.
Yeah.
There you go.
Sorry.
I just need a little interpensalvania cattiness since I'm on Eastern Pennsylvania.
Right.
Yeah.
And so that, that Uru.
Sumerian word actually then makes its way through Akkadian being loaned into Akkadian makes its way into.
This is just a language nerd fun fact into Northwest Semitic dialects, which would be like Hebrew, Aramaic,
Ugaritic, as the word Yeru, which means a foundation.
It is used in the Bible to be a foundation.
But so that's the city that he's the king of.
Right.
And his name means the melky.
Melk is from melak, right, which means king in Hebrew.
And the E there, the melky, the E is a first person possessive.
So it's my king.
Okay.
Melky is my king.
And then Sedeck, right, is a word that means justice.
But it's also the name of a God.
Who could have guessed that?
Right.
Yeah.
And so yeah, for those maybe familiar with like Arabic, for instance, there's Malik, right, which again means king.
And then even the word melkite, reference people involved connected with the the Imperium, you know, with the empire, right.
So all these words are connected.
So when you look at that melky at the beginning of Melkisadek, that's this route.
That's that king route.
So yeah, my king, my king is Sedeck.
Right.
And so there are ways to try to get around this referring to a pagan god.
Yeah.
Okay.
That people try to do.
But there are a bunch of problems with them.
The biggest one is the name of the next king of Jerusalem, who we see, which is in the book of Joshua, the next one who's named.
And his name is Adonid Sedeck.
Yeah, which would be my lord is.
Yeah.
Right.
Which suggests there's this cult of Sedeck there.
And, you know, they keep getting to be worshiped.
Right.
And Sedeck is, is the main god who's, who's worshiped, particularly what's he start getting into the Jebusite period at that city.
And so here's, here's where we're going to have a conversation.
Right.
Because you described as being a priest of God most high.
Yeah.
Well, well, before we get to that.
Gotta explain who Sedeck is.
Right.
Okay.
And we feel like our listeners are old enough now for us to have this talk.
Sit down and have this talk.
This is what I've been a little leery of because it's not that someone might.
Someone on the internet will take this and run in all kinds of weird directions with it.
And we're just interpreting it by.
Nope.
No press is bad press.
I don't know.
Yeah.
So.
But here we go.
Okay.
Here we go.
So.
If you've read religion of the apostles or other things I've written.
Right.
I've talked about how.
And we've talked about on the show before.
How.
The Israelites and and Judeans of the second temple period.
Already had the idea that their God was more than one person.
Right.
At least two.
What we would what we would now call trinitarianism.
Right.
A version of that or the beginnings of that or the form of that without that particular language yet.
So.
The reason they were able to have that kind of idea in the ancient world is that pretty much everyone in the ancient world had a similar idea.
Not the same, but similar.
There's continuities and discontinuities.
But in the ancient world they believed that all the pagans will just start to pay the pagans believe that there are any given got pagan God could have a whole bunch of different bodies.
Right.
A whole bunch of different localizations.
And this is where I and this is something that we've we've occasionally gotten questions about.
This is where the notion that the sun moon the stars are bodies of gods.
That's a pagan idea.
Right.
Whereas the the you know the Israel idea about that is that they are two separate created things that the one takes care of the other.
Those are not stars identical to stars and stars are not the bodies of angels.
That's a pagan notion.
But that angels are assigned to take care of stars and the association is so close that the scriptures have no problem kind of referring to stars as angels and angels of stars.
But there's still this understanding that they are two separate things.
Whereas the pagan version is that these are bodies of gods.
Right.
So for example, you can have a sun god.
And you believe that he is on top of a mountain somewhere in the council of the gods.
And he's the actual sun in this guy.
And he's in the local temple to the sun god inside the image, the idol there.
Right.
And he's the king.
Yeah.
All months.
Those are all bodies of his.
And he doesn't have to like leave one to use it.
Right.
Like the sun doesn't disappear from the sky when you're doing a ritual at the sun temple.
Meaning that the spirit isn't like hopping from one body to the next.
Right.
You know, they all exist at the same time.
And the word that's used uniformly by scholars to talk about this is to say that any given localization of one of those gods.
We also see this like with the Greek gods.
Like there's Zuzbo energies.
There's Zeus of a certain place.
Right.
Or Bale of a certain place.
And they'll be depicted looking very different.
For example, right.
The word for these different bodies and these different localizations is hypostasis.
What?
Don't freak out.
No.
That's the word that's used.
So the idea that a given god could have multiple hypostasis is a universal idea in the ancient world.
Right.
Now did that's the point of continuity.
Yeah.
But did pagans mean by that the same thing that we mean by it when we refer to others in Holy Spirit.
And the answer here is all the not exactly.
No.
That's just.
Okay.
So that's the continuity.
The continuity is the idea that one god can be the same god but have multiple hypostasis.
Right.
At the same time that are all him or her.
Here's the discontinuity.
Okay.
There are a list of discontinuities.
Right.
So in the pagan world, huge discontinuity.
And you'll notice as we go through these that a lot of the Old Testament commandments about worship and a lot of the things that Yahweh the god of Israel says to his prophets are going to be trying to accentuate these differences.
Yeah.
Right.
Because the temptation is always going to be for the Israelites to think the way their neighbors and other ancient people do.
So here's the big first discontinuity.
For the pagans, you can make a body for the god.
Right.
You could go and craft an idol.
You could craft an image.
You could perform the opening of the nostrils ritual or whatever parallel ritual is practicing your place.
And now that is a body of the god.
Is it now connected to it?
Right.
Not a thing.
No, you cannot do that.
Yeah.
And thus the constant references to he does not dwell in things made by hands.
Right.
And he even asked to then go beyond that to they're like, well, okay, well, we can't make an image and put them there.
But maybe we can make a building and put them there.
And that's why he has to keep telling them with the temple.
I am not bound by your building.
Right.
We'll use it.
But I'm not in that.
Yeah, I'm not bound by it anyway.
The building itself is not in it, which is me.
So that's a major discontinuity.
Right.
In the pagan idea, relatedly, those hypostases can come into existence and go out of existence.
Hmm.
They're not eternal.
Right.
They're not eternal and you can make them.
So there's potentially infinite numbers of them.
Right.
And potentially not at all.
Whereas Yahweh the God of Israel has revealed himself in three, only three exactly three hypostases, which are eternal.
Yeah.
And you think about this from a kind of, I don't know, spiritual, logistical point of view.
If you're a demon and you want to deceive mankind, you know, potentially infinite hypostases is the way to go.
Because how many opportunities would that be?
You know, like, you know, I want to be everywhere.
Because that's what a demon kind of needs in order to be everywhere.
His numerous, numerous bodies that he can inhabit and interact with people through.
Right.
So like, it makes sense.
Not that I'm saying I know what it is to be a fallen angel.
I don't.
I don't even know what it is.
I don't even know what it's like to be the guy in the office next to my studio.
He seems nice though.
But, but, but, you know, just at least what I imagine might be the case.
It seems, you know, good strategy to have as many idols and hypostases as possible for a demon.
Connect on a local level with as many, you know, people that he can try to do as possible.
Right. Right.
And, and once you understand this, it makes sense of a whole bunch of things.
Right.
So for example, the golden calves in the Old Testament, all of them.
Right. Both when Aaron makes the one and when Jeroboam makes the golden calves.
Right.
It's not like, OK, I now made this idol.
We're going to now worship this object.
In both cases, they pointed them and say, this is Yahweh.
Right.
You're God who brought you out of Egypt.
Yeah.
Right.
So they're trying to craft a body.
They're trying to craft a hypostasis for Yahweh.
They got a Israel to confine him and locate him.
Right.
Which, I mean, without this understanding of this notion of hypostasis from the ancient world,
that action looks just royally stupid.
Like, wait, we were brought out by the God of all, you know, the most high God.
And look, I made this, this, you know, this golden calf.
This is your God.
Like that, if you don't understand that that's what's going on, that just looks really stupid.
And you know, maybe one crazy person would have come up with that.
But why would all those Israelites then fall for it?
Oh, yes.
Oh, yeah, right.
That's our God, sure.
You know, because it plugged into their preexisting experience of what spiritual life is about,
and how you connect with the God.
Right.
And so that laid out.
So, so to put a fine point on it, I know this won't be the part anyone quotes.
Right.
Yahweh, the God of Israel, has eternally existed as the most high God in three hypostases.
Father, Son, and Holy Spirit, that's it.
There's no more.
They didn't come into being.
They're not going to go out of being.
That's it.
Right.
That's in contrast to sort of the demonic parody of it.
Which is infinite changing and malleable and the pagan thing.
So that established.
Why did we go into that now of all times?
Right.
Why did we risk everything?
To make.
To make the point that this Zedek, right?
This God is a hypostasis of Shemesh.
Okay.
So remind us who Shemesh is, Father Stephen.
Shemesh.
Isn't he the one that stands in his name, doctor?
Yes.
Actually, he is the pagan God who Samson was named after.
Suspiciously, despite him having been promised as, you always chose it.
Anyway, someone might make something out of that.
But Shemesh, in addition to being the northwest of an awkward for the Sun,
is also the Sun God.
Okay.
And there were, there were a few other hypostases of Shemesh,
but Shemesh is one of the main ones.
And so you will sometimes find him referred to as just Zedek.
Sometimes he's referred to as Shemesh Zedekah, right?
Where it's, it's the Zedekah that that second word is telling you the name of the,
the hypostasis, like Zeus bow energies.
Right.
That language, this is a decide that we won't go into now,
but may at some point in the future.
This Zedekah language is picked up by the prophets.
That's the son of righteousness language that gets applied to Yahweh,
the God of Israel, specifically to Christ, is actually a repurposing of that pagan language,
sort of in the same way that the Bale's cloud rider language gets taken over
and given to Yahweh is the true.
The real cloud rider.
True most I got.
Yeah.
Right.
So, this is, this is a particular form.
We've talked about, about justice before, right?
Justice is the, the right relation between things.
Right.
And so the idea here is that this particular hypostasis of Shemesh
is the son as he establishes order upon, upon the earth.
Right.
That's a son of, son of justice, son of righteousness.
And so there's, there's, there's more about this,
the fact that he's worshiped in, in Jerusalem,
in the Old Testament when, when you look closely.
So, we'll bring up again, Deuteronomy 4 verse 19,
that the sun and moon and stars were some of the divine beings to whom the nations were assigned
at Bable.
But then more specifically,
first Kings 11 verses 4 through 8 talks about the judgment
that comes against Solomon, David's son,
for having built all these pagan shrines
and set up all these pagan altars in and around Jerusalem.
And there are a few details given.
Nothing specifically having to do with Shemesh.
But when you go to Second Kings 23 verse 11,
we get to the second righteous king of Judah.
There's not a lot of them.
And that's King Josiah,
who is the other king.
When you see the, the traditional icon of the inostasis of the resurrection,
right, the harrowing of Hades,
on the one side there's the prophets,
and then on the other side there's the Kings.
And the kings you always have are David and Josiah.
And then sometimes you see some other crowns in the background,
or there's some kind of non-descript guys.
There's hard to find righteous kings in the Old Testament.
Or in general.
But Josiah is,
yeah, there aren't a lot of Byzantine emperors who are saints.
Yeah.
That's true.
So, but one of the things that made Josiah so righteous
is that he went and destroyed all of those shrines.
Yeah.
Just paying the shrines that it aroused Jerusalem,
many of which had been there since the time of Solomon.
Right, right.
And so then the references given in Second Kings 23 11,
you know, speaking about Josiah,
he removed the horses that the kings of Judah
had dedicated to Shemish at the entrance of the temple of Yahweh
by the chamber of Nathan Melek, the Chamberlain,
which was in the temple precincts,
and he burned the chariots of Shemish with fire.
So that's, you know, letting us know then who these, you know,
like so we were told that Solomon set up these pagan shrines.
And here's Josiah.
It actually is identifying then who the shrines are two.
It's Shemish who, you know, was this locally worshiped God?
Right.
Who had been the pagan god of that city.
So people have asked about sort of a pagan creep, right?
Like, can these fallen powers,
what's their ousted kind of start creeping back in?
Well, this is an example.
Right.
David had taken the city from the Jebusites and purified it,
dedicated it to Yahweh, the God of Israel.
Right.
Made the plan so that Solomon could build a temple there.
So that God would be on Mount Zion.
That's the place where Yahweh, the God of Israel,
chose to place his name.
And oh, here comes Shemish sneaking back in.
Yeah.
This is actual syncretism where you're worshiping multiple beings.
You know, this is not the same as the way that pagan imagery
and stories and stuff get used by ancient Israel
and by the church in which there's not actually worshiping
opera to these other beings, but rather there's a sense
that their story gets kind of included in the Christian story
in some way.
You know, that's the difference.
I mean, this to me is a really important point, actually,
because sometimes when people, when Christians talk about paganism a lot,
or even, for instance, as I like to do,
read pagan mythology, right, the accusation can be one of syncretism
because suddenly you're including these stories and these beings
and so forth and what you're talking about what you're doing.
But that is not the same thing as actually setting up shrines
and altars to them and worshiping them.
That's actual syncretism, right?
It's one thing to say, these things fit into our story
in the following ways.
It's another thing entirely to say,
not only do they fit in their story, but here,
let's go ahead and offer sacrifice to them.
Let's go ahead and go into communion with them.
That's not the same thing.
Right.
Very different things, right?
And this is full on, right?
They have constructed, right?
So Shemesh, this is common iconography for all sun deities
in the ancient world pretty much.
From Shemesh here in Canaan to Helios later,
that, right, the sun god rides through the sky of this chariot.
Yeah, right.
Right, with horses.
So based on what Josiah destroys,
they had a full on sculpted horses,
constructed chariot, idol of Shemesh
in the temple courts in Jerusalem for hundreds of years.
So many yikes.
Yes, yeah.
And now note, this is according to the Bible.
I just want to make this point again,
because people who are old testament scholars
who have devoted their life to studying this text
will still do these kind of insane documentaries
that I have to watch through a bitter terrible compulsion
where they will say,
well, according to the Bible, Israel was monotheistic.
So first of all,
thank you for playing on that one.
But, and then say,
but we found in the archaeology
all these pagan shrines and amulets and stuff.
Ha, busted.
Yeah, and it's like,
well, if you actually read the Bible,
the Bible said you would find all that stuff.
Yeah.
So how many, how long is it between Solomon and Josiah?
Solomon setting these things up and then Josiah purifying them out?
A couple of hundred years.
Yeah.
Man.
Not.
Yeah, so this is most of Judah's history.
Right, right.
There's active pages of going out of the temple.
Yeah.
So this is, there is it really,
and the closest thing you get to a gold age
is like the 40 years of David's reign.
Right, right.
So okay.
And even that, David has his problems.
He does.
But fortunately, he repents.
Yeah, so I mean,
so all of this combined together, then,
you get a guy showing up,
this priest king,
whose name means,
my king is Zedic,
this apostasy of Shemists, the sun god.
And he rules over a city named Shalim,
Urushalim, you know,
which is another,
another pagan name.
And then, you know,
you later get these references to Shemish being worshiped there
in the courts of Yahweh's temple.
Why is Melchizedek not a pagan god king, priest?
Like everything about him says that he should be,
except for this line,
it says that he's not,
that he's a priest of the most high god.
Well, that's why he appears in three verses
and it says over at God most high,
God most high, God most high.
God most high.
He's a priest of God most high.
Right.
Because anyone in the ancient world
reading that first sentence,
a guy named Melchizedek,
right,
is the king of Urushalim,
that's a pagan, right?
He's, he's just as pagan,
is Kenner Leuomer and everybody else.
Right.
Literally every single,
of these three verses,
every single one has the phrase
most high god or God most high.
And every single one,
you know?
Yeah.
Over and over.
So, that's why they keep saying it over and over.
Because it's sort of like,
I know what you're thinking,
but no.
I know it.
Of course, he didn't name himself.
Right.
He would have been named by his father,
right, whose heir he was.
Right.
And he didn't name the city.
City already had a name when he showed up
and became king.
So, what this is trying to tell us
over and over again is that,
like we saw with Abram in chapter 12,
and his quote unquote,
call, which isn't really a call.
Melchizedek here is another one of those people,
apparently there's at least two.
Right.
And presumably more out there in the world,
even this far after the Tower of Babel,
who are still worshipping the most high god
and not worshipping these lesser divine beings,
these fallen demonic beings,
even though they've,
he like Abram is living in a city and a culture
and Abram even his father, right,
in a family likely
that are all involved in this,
this paganism, right,
who have all fallen into this kind of worship.
Here's one more guy who has,
who has kept himself pure,
and he comes out and he finds Abram.
Right.
Now, I mean, we should underline,
there's no indication in the scripture
that there are any nations or tribes
who have retained the worship of Yahweh.
We just have...
As a whole, right.
Exactly.
We just have these individuals that are mentioned.
And I don't know, potentially families.
I mean, certainly Abram's family becomes,
you know, is that kind of family, you know,
with him and his children and stuff.
But, yeah, there's no...
Because, I mean, this is what question we sometimes get.
Like, did all of the principalities
who govern the nations really fall?
Like, well, there's literally no indication
that any of them didn't.
You know, that's why God makes a new nation for Himself,
starting with Abram.
Right. Right.
But there are...
These individuals, right.
And, yeah.
And just like with Abram,
you would assume in Ur, right.
You'd assume he's not.
Right.
And the same thing with...
with Malkin's in it, right.
So,
what's the significance of that?
Well, Abram has just won this battle.
Right.
And it's really
as...
as Abram is going to indicate,
it's really Yahweh who won the battle for Him.
Right.
Because it's not just that Abram's a military genius.
So, him and his Ragtag group of 318 people
could beat one of the most powerful Arbis
in the world at the time.
Right.
And rest you take all this stuff.
It's that Yahweh was on his side.
Right.
And so,
what you would expect to happen after that
would be
a thank offering.
Hmm. Right. Right.
To the God. Right.
After the victory.
Which normally would involve
like in the pagan context,
you would have offered
some of the tribute that was taken.
Right.
So, some of that wealth
would have been in like flocks and herds and stuff.
So, you would have sacrificed some of that,
depending on how pagan you were.
Maybe some of the people,
some of the slaves,
some of the captured
enemy military,
right, as human sacrifices.
But there would have been a sacrifice afterwards.
Right. Right.
Because you don't have to be grateful
when you're worshipping pagan gods,
because they're pretty fickle.
They'll turn out you're pretty fast.
Right. Right. Right. Right.
But so, so.
Well,
Kinsedeck comes out and finds Abram
for this purpose. Right.
To offer the the thank offering. Right.
Which in this case is bread and wine.
It's a thank offering meaning
it's a Eucharist as it were. Right. Right. Right.
But the why does he bring bread and wine?
Well, remember,
Abram wants nothing to do
with any of the spoils.
The spoils are all tainted.
That means you can't offer them to God either. Right. Right.
He doesn't want them either. Right.
That's what gets solid to trouble later.
Remember that's excuse.
He seizes the amulacite's livestock
that he was supposed to kill.
And he says, oh no,
I was going to offer it as a sacrifice.
Yeah, sure I was. Yeah.
So, but here's the guy
that Abram can actually worship with
because they worship the same God. Right.
Right. Yeah. Right.
And when Abram takes an oath in Genesis 1422
so right after this,
he's talking to the king of Sodom.
It says, takes an oath that he's not taking any of the tribute.
He says,
I have lifted my hand to Yahweh,
God most high,
the possessor of heaven and earth. Right.
Which is he's mimicking Melchizedek's language,
who said,
blessed is Abram by God most high possessor of heaven and earth. Right. Right.
I'm with that guy. That's what he's saying.
But adding,
yeah, adding the name Yahweh.
Yeah.
Just to make it clear,
that's the most I got we're talking about.
And that possessor of heaven and earth is not coincidental.
That those territories don't really belong
to those gods who are over them right now.
That it's not he's,
that we're not saying,
oh, yeah,
there's a whole bunch of gods,
but Yahweh's the best one,
or he's the toughest one. Right.
He's the bestest one.
It's he's in a whole different category.
He possesses everything that is.
Everything that is really belongs to him. Right.
Which is not something that any pagans ever said about their gods
that I can recall.
Right.
Any authority,
the other ones have is delegated to them.
Yeah. Right. Right.
Even what pagans themselves say about their gods is limited.
Right. Right.
There's, there's not competing omnipotent gods.
No one else is saying that about their god. Right.
There's, there's mind can beat up yours.
There's not mind is omnipotent and created all the others.
Yeah. Right.
From nothing and assign them their places. Right.
Right. Okay. So, so I wanted to, I wanted to bring up this question
that I know custom times comes up with regards to Melchizedek.
Because of the, the apparent,
I mean, we've just explained why this is not the case,
but, but the apparent sort of sudden appearance in the middle
of an irrelevant, you know,
it's narrative, not actually true.
But, and, and then the, you know, the Jesus priest,
he's offering bread and wine, wow, that's eucharistic.
Some people say, oh, is, is, is this Jesus?
You know, is this, is this the son of God showing up,
you know, in the guise of a priest king from the local city?
Right.
I thought it would be useful just to take a couple minutes and say
why the answer to that is no.
You know, so certainly the angel of the Lord, right?
The angel of the Lord, the word of the Lord,
shows up a bunch of times in the Old Testament.
But there's all kinds of ways that that's talked about.
And ways that this text lets you know that that is Yahweh,
the God of Israel.
And none of that happens here with, with Melchizedek, right?
For instance, you know, Abram does not offer sacrifices to this man,
right? That's usually, that's one of the things that often happens
when the word of the Lord shows up.
You know, there's not, he's not called, he's not called Yahweh, right?
He's not, there's no language specifically identifying him as being God.
You know, there's not, it's not a vision.
You know, all of these ways that tend to indicate that someone is encountering
the angel of the Lord are not happening in this case.
There's no indication that this is anything but a human person who's coming out
and, you know, worships the same God as Abram and is the king of this nearby city.
Probably a pagan city, weirdly enough.
And his family clearly was pagan, given his name.
But somehow he worships the one true God.
We don't know why.
Like there's no, there's no context for why he is a worshiper of Yahweh.
We just simply do not know.
But there's also no indication of the text that this is the angel of the Lord.
Like all the, the markers that you would normally look for.
None of those are, are here.
Right, right.
And, and two chapters before Yahweh just talks to Abram.
And he says, I will bless you.
I bless you.
And I will do this first person.
Yeah.
Why would Melchizedek say, you know, you're blessed by my other hippostasis.
Like that doesn't make any sense if that's what's going on.
Right.
And the chapter after this, Yahweh comes with two angels that he eats with him.
So, there's a pattern here that this is in the middle of it.
It doesn't match that pattern.
Right.
So, this is a different, this is a person.
And, and as you mentioned, he doesn't sacrifice.
So, he does tithe to him.
Yes.
Right.
But that's something you do to a priest who's a representative.
That's not offering a sacrifice.
Right.
And he teased from his own.
Again, that's a part of a thank offering.
Yeah.
Thanks for got through the, the priest who is acting as an icon or an image as we've talked about before.
Right.
Okay.
So, before we take a break at the end of our first half here, there's a few things in this scene that actually kind of set up some other big issues for the future in scripture.
Why don't we just kind of quickly go over them?
Yeah.
So, what we get, we get a little bit of the very first seeds of what we call, talked about is remnant theology in the episode on St. John the Forerunner.
Right.
This idea that starting, that, that really starts with the prophet Elijah.
But you get the seeds of it here that even though in this case in Genesis, a few chapters before this at the Tower of Babel, God has sort of just had to distance himself from sinful humanity that he hasn't abandoned humanity.
Right.
And it's not just Abram.
There's also Melchizedek.
So, there are these people who are still faithful.
Yeah.
There's the O.A.
Faithful, the Most High God.
Yeah.
Scattered here and there.
And they may not know that they all exist.
Right.
But they're out there who are still faithful.
We also get from this whole story, this pattern of doing battle with the giant clans with the spiritual evil.
And then victory and then the emergence of a king to offer sacrifice.
So that pattern is going to play out sort of throughout the Old Testament and into the New Testament ways you could probably immediately see.
And we see within the figure of Melchizedek, someone who is not a pagan who is uniting the roles of king and priest in his person.
And so he's going to become sort of archetypal for the, you know, the Venn diagram overlap of king and priest, theologically in the Old Testament.
Right.
Okay.
Well, we're going to go ahead and take a break and we will be right back with more.
Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung will be back in a moment to take your calls on the next part of the Lord of Spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF radio.
Hi, this is John Maddox.
You know when you support 8 of Spirits, the Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung.
If you have a question, call now at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF radio.
Welcome back.
This is the second half of the show.
Now normally we would start taking your calls here.
But despite what the voice of Steve just said, this is a pre-recorded episode.
So we're not going to be receiving any calls for this one.
If you call the number, no one's going to be home.
I can, I could do a funny voice and ask you easy questions.
Very good.
That'd be fun.
Hello.
Hello from Afi-
Do a whole, whole Phil Hendry thing.
Yeah.
I can just grab someone from the hall here in the tower of podcasts to get to see what they
have to say.
That would be fun, wouldn't it?
Yeah.
Okay, well we just finished up talking about Melchizedx appearance in Genesis 14.
And now we want to actually connect to one of the themes that we talked about in the last
episode where we talked about Abraham, but then we also talked about Isaac in particular.
And how Isaac is this singular seed, this unique son of Abraham.
And then as, you know, as we mentioned, so go listen to that episode first if you haven't
listened to it yet.
Okay.
As we mentioned.
Welcome back.
Yeah.
Welcome back everybody from doing that.
Thank you.
And the Christ is that seed.
He is the seed, you know, the unique son, right, of the father who is the one who fulfills
all these things.
So, yeah.
So we're going to connect actually this, you know, this question of who is Melchizedx with
that.
So pretty cool.
Wait, what?
Actually, yes.
So, all right, help us out here, father, because that's probably not obvious to most people.
Not to me, for sure.
Right.
So well, we talked about how Melchizedx becomes where we left off in the first half.
How he becomes sort of the co-location theologically, the Old Testament of King and Priest.
Right.
And we talked, as you mentioned last time about this idea that in addition to seed plural
and this multiplication language that's used in the promises to Abraham, there's also the promise of this
unique singular seed, this unique singular son.
And as anybody with even sort of a passing familiarity with the Bible and or Christianity or even Judaism probably knows,
that idea of a single descendant of Abraham who's sort of unique and special becomes sort of alloyed
with the idea of kingship in the form of the Messiah, right?
Mashiach, the anointed one or Christos, the anointed one in Greek.
And so really what we're going to be talking about this second half is sort of how that happens.
Right.
So we see this image here early on in the story of Abraham of a faithful king who is also a faithful priest that there is one somewhere, right?
That's a thing that exists.
And that's the first image of that that we get in the scriptures is Melchizedek.
He's the first king who gets any kind of overall positive mention.
And so now how does that kingship get connected to this singular person?
And we talked about last time how in St. Paul makes this point in Romans 9 that you see the singleness first reflected in the line of Abraham
that there is an individual line that is going to lead to this all to its seat.
So it's Isaac and not Ishmael who's in that line.
And that's why as we talked about last time Isaac becomes sort of the icon for that ultimate chosen unique son.
But then it also goes to the next generation, right?
It's Jacob not Esau, right?
The St. Paul points out.
But it then continues after that, right?
And after you get through Jacob or Israel, you now have 12 kids with four different women.
Where it spreads out even more and these become fathers of the 12 tribes of Israel.
And so when the time comes that Jacob or Israel is dying, he's on his deathbed, he gives what is now called his testament.
This is the use of testament that's in last will and testament.
This actually, we find this several times in the Old Testament where someone will be dying and they will sort of give final words to their children or other descendants.
And often those have a prophetic nature.
Yeah, I mean, sometimes it's lessings and stuff too, but but not always.
Yeah, that there's this, there's this sort of wisdom imparted right of patterns and what's going to happen and who they're going to be and what's going to happen.
And there is within second temple Judaism of vast array of apocryphal, not canonical testaments of different figures.
Testament of Abraham, testament of Isaac, testament of every 12 patriarchs, right?
Right, right. Testament of 12 patriarchs is a very key and important one that people should read, but because that actually gets referenced and possibly even quoted at one point in the New Testament.
And our manuscripts for it are from Mount Athos.
Hey, that's where it was preserved, not in the Jewish circles.
So within this particular one that we find in Genesis chapter 49, which is a second of the last chapter of Genesis, Jacob or Israel is giving his testimonies.
And some of them are kind of harsh, you know, like Benjamin and Dan in particular get basically told they're the devil by their dad as he's tying.
But that's talking about things that are going to happen in the future.
Yeah, like really? Wow. These are dipping. These are your last words.
Yeah.
But I never liked you.
And we talked about how first born status is not necessarily the same thing as being the first born child.
Right.
So Jacob slash Israel's first born son is Rubin with Leia.
Rubin was not good.
Yeah.
And he was the ringleader that got rid of Joseph.
Right.
And he also slept with one of his father's concubines to try to take control of the family.
Yeah.
As one apparently does.
Should not do.
Yes.
That's one of the episodes of that in the Old Testament out of several.
And he's just and he and Simeon, who's the second son also masterminded the whole Let's go murder all the men of Shechem for violating our sister episode.
In disobedience to his father.
So Rubin and Simeon get left out.
Levi's next.
Levi has his own special destiny.
We know with the priesthood.
Yeah, right.
Right.
So that brings us to number four.
Note by the way, number four son of Leia.
Yeah.
Judah is one of the sons of Leia, not a Rachel.
Not the sort of favored wife.
Right.
So thick stake interesting turns.
And so he gets to Judah and offers this blessing to Judah that becomes critically important.
For what comes to be called the Messianic tradition and the rest of the Old Testament.
Yeah.
Okay.
So let's read it.
49 verses 8 through 12.
Judah, your brothers shall praise you.
Your hand shall be on the neck of your enemies.
Your father's sons shall bow down before you.
Judah is a lion's cub from the prey my son you have gone up.
He stooped down, he crouched as a lion and as a lioness who dares rouse him.
The scepter shall not depart from Judah nor the ruler's staff from between his feet until he comes to whom it belongs.
And to him shall be the obedience of the peoples binding his foal to the vine and his donkey's cult to the choice vine.
He has washed his garments in wine and his vestor in the blood of grapes.
His eyes are darker than wine and his teeth whiter than milk.
Which I mean, you know, I'm just imagining hearing this be the last thing my dad says to me, I'd be like,
wait, what?
I don't see how this applies.
But I like the scepter stuff.
I'm on board with that.
But I don't know.
Right.
This despite Judah himself not being perfect.
No.
Tamar.
So yeah.
So now I note on how you read it.
Right.
So you read the scepter bit, right.
The scepter shall not depart from Judah nor the ruler's staff from between his feet until he comes to whom it belongs.
Okay.
That is by all accounts what the text says.
Now, when I say it by all accounts, okay?
So the oldest Hebrew of Genesis we have, of course, which goes for the Dead Sea Scrolls, does not have vowels note, vowels notated.
Right.
Submitting languages are generally written without vowels.
And how things are vocalized, meaning what vowels you pronounce them with can change how things read.
Right.
I mean, you know, in English, the word net, words net, knit, and not all have the same consonants, but boy, that vowel makes a big difference.
Yeah.
Better, better, better.
Bitter.
Yeah.
So when you're translating from a Hebrew text that has no vowels into another language, you have to make certain choices.
Right.
And those choices you make will reflect a certain understanding of the text.
So the way the translators of the Septuagint, the Greek translators, the way the Aramaic translators who translated the Aramaic Targums, and the way the Syriac translators who translated the later Aramaic, the Syriac, read that verse was the way you just read it.
That the Septuagint will not depart from Judah until he comes to whom it belongs, until the person to whom it belongs arrives. Right.
Suspiciously.
Right.
When you look at the medieval Maseretic text, which is if you go and buy a Hebrew Bible, a Hebrew Old Testament today, that's what you will get.
And the reason it's called the Maseretic text is that they've taken the Hebrew text, which is that Hebrew text, the Hebrew itself is identical, literally identical to the Hebrew we found in the Dead Sea Scrolls in terms of the written letters.
But it's called the Maseretic text because these fellows, the Maserids, that's what it's named after, were scribes, they went in and put in vowel pointing.
Right.
They put in marks to indicate the correct vowels, and they put in these marginalia, these two sets of the Masura, these two sets of marginal notes about the text.
Right. So they preserved the text exactly as they found it, but then they annotated it for how they thought it should be interpreted.
And interestingly, by 1000 AD until he comes to whom it belongs becomes until he comes to Shiloh.
Hmm.
There's no explanation as to what that would mean.
Right.
Right. Because I mean, even even there, even rabbinic Jewish communities of the 11th century AD would say, well, yeah, this was talking about the divinic king.
So yeah.
Right.
So that dog don't hunt.
That's why we read it the way you read it. Right.
Even though if you pick up a given English Bible, some of them will have, some of them will have this and have the Shiloh thing in a football.
Some of them will have the Shiloh thing in this and a footnote.
Yeah.
They pretty much all preserve it in a footnote because it's kind of obvious what's going on here. Right.
That this promise of a specific Maseretic King has been edited out by the rabbinic Jewish scholars. Right.
But be that isn't me.
But so what we see here is that we see this this kingship language with the scepter. Right.
That is applied to Judah and his descendants.
But then specifically that there's going to be because the scepter is going to be there.
The ruler's staff is going to be there in Judah.
It's going to be a line of kings that is going to culminate in a singular king. Right.
There is going to be a it's not just this is prophesying that David's going to show up. Right.
That doesn't work because it says it won't depart. Right.
And and David is the first king from the tribe of Judah. Right.
Not the last. Right.
And there are promises made to his line that we're going to talk about here in a little bit.
So here we have this idea of the singular seed we've been tracking from Isaac to Jacob.
And now it's going to go to Judah.
And now we have this element of monarchy and and kingship being being brought in. Right.
And you even have this language of first your father's sons shall bow down before you. Right.
That's the first part. Right. Your father's sons the tribes.
Yeah, which kind of you know also suggest an elimination of them from this.
This line of the seed. Right. Right. Right. Right.
So so this is going to be the king of Israel first.
But then right.
His hands will be on the neck of the enemies. He's the one who's going to defeat those enemies.
Remember, that was part of the promise to Abraham originally.
The camp in the gates of their enemies. Yeah. Right. Right.
That means you've really got their city. Yeah.
And having your hand on their neck.
You get the idea. Right. You win.
Right. So so you have that kingship idea.
Now elements of this get picked get picked up.
We talked briefly in our Christmas slash astrology episode.
About the fact that in this text in this testament, there's this animal imagery associated with with each of the tribes.
And that's not unrelated to certain constellations. Right.
We have this lion language with Judah. Yeah.
Lion of the tribe with Judah. There is actually Orthodox iconography depicting Christ as a child.
Right. Usually laying on a mat, which then will quote this thing about Judah being a lion's cub.
Right. Right. Yeah.
Yeah. That icon is called who is crouched.
Yeah. That icon is called on opposite one, which I think is just the Greek word for that sort of lying down.
Yeah. Yeah. You often see this on the back wall sometimes of churches or of narthexes.
That's one place that I've seen it in a number of churches.
Right. Right. Yeah. And so there's, there's this rule over Israel culminates in somebody who's going to rule over then over all the nations through the defeat of the enemies.
And, and this person is then who comes, we call the mishiek, the anointed one, the Messiah.
This is that the promise, see the promise on the unique son is going to be a king.
And Christ himself, of course, well, this gets further elaborated. It gets picked up again in Zechariah 9 verse 9, which is an explicitly sort of messianic passage talking about the Messiah coming, writing on a, on a donkey's hole.
Yeah. So it's the Palm Sunday prophecy as we would. But here it is. But here it is again in Genesis 49.
Yeah. Right. Right. Zechariah is picking up on this imagery. Right. To say he's coming. Right. Don't forget about this. It's been a long time.
It had been probably a good 1300 years by that point.
Don't forget about it. And then that Zechariah passage, sort of this comes through that Zechariah passage into the story of Christ's triumphal entry.
Jerusalem in Matthew 21 verse 2, Mark 11 verse 4, wherever when he tells them to go and find the donkey, he says it's going to be tied to a vine.
Right. So he's, Christ is, is explicitly identifying himself as this figure by doing, by acting this out. Right.
And that's why it's totally clear to the crowds on that day that that's what he's saying. Right. Right.
And that's why they're all yelling, Jose and the son of David, because they know, hey, Messiah, right. He's doing Messiah stuff.
Right. So that all that gets drawn in here. And so we mentioned this very briefly in the past in, in our episode about the Theotokos, the Queen stood on his right hand.
But we'll, we'll talk about a little again here in terms of the Davidic monarchy, right, which is then connected to this.
We talked about there how the Davidic monarchy serves as kind of this icon then. Right. Right. Right.
Or a, as the language we used in our last episode is sort of the sign. Right. The coming of the first king from the line of Judah is then a sign of the ultimate king who's going to come. Right.
Right. The beginning of the fulfillment of this prophecy that's made to Judah.
And we're talking about that time. How there's this misunderstanding because of our Puritan ancestors in this country.
And by that, I mean the United States. We have listeners all across the globe.
Hello, New Zealand.
But in the United States, at least our ancestors are a bunch of Puritans who got, got thrown out of Europe for being heretics.
Are, are culturally ancestors.
Yes. Right. Right. Some of us are not literally listening. I mean, I'm sure probably I am on some level, but yeah.
I'm literally descended from some of the people who threw them out.
Yeah. Right.
So hey guys.
We've read, we've tended to read what goes on in first Samuel or first kingdoms chapter eight.
This whole thing where Israel demands a king.
We've, we've talked to read that as kings are bad. See the Bible says. Right. Right. Right. Yeah. Does it what king?
Is there once a king? God says no. Like yes, of course monarchy is bad. Right.
I mean, I have to admit that I myself have actually made that argument while I was yet ignorant.
Right. And, and it's interesting that even though so many of us imbibed that as children in Sunday school, it's sort of culturally abiled that.
Like it never crossed our mind. Well, wait, how does that work with the whole Messiah thing?
Yeah. Right. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. I mean, the problem, the problem isn't kingship.
It's the wrong king and and or the wrong kind of king. Right. A deformed type of kingship. Yeah. Right.
Right. So. So. Yeah. So it drew out of me 17. There are the commandments.
Right. As we talked about before where God says when you get into the land and you have a king. Right.
Where's the dudes at dose. Right. So basically saying look God knew that there was going to be a king. And so here's the commandment.
He didn't say you're going to get into the promise and you're going to want a king. You better not do that ever because you're not supposed to have a king.
He gives commandments related to kingship. Right. Right. We're keeping this a theocracy people. No, there was no.
So. And and even, you know, let's make the obvious point. At the beginning of the book of Samuel, when they ask for a king,
Samuel's the judge of Israel. Right. Right. He's the one who's ruling over a judge of Israel and is the prophet.
And the text says he's training his verses 19 20. He's training his son to take over.
When you have one person in charge and that passes on to his son. Right. I mean, what do you call that?
Yeah, that's basically primogeniture monarchy. Right. Right. So the situation of a monarchy is not that different. Right. The situation was Samuel. Right.
In that respect. Right. In that sort of just detailed respect. So so what is the difference and what is the problem there? Right. Since since
there's going to be a king. And he even says it. He's not just talking about David and the Davidate king because in verses 18 through 20 of that,
the positive command that Yahweh God of Israel gives for the king is that the king is to make his own copy of the Torah to study it and learn it.
So that the king's dynasties plural may be successful and maybe blessed. Right. So he's setting it up in view of a long term.
A whole set of things. Right. Yeah. Yeah. In those commandments. Right. Yeah. So, you know, what makes the the desire for Saul different from God's vision that he's imparting to them is
they want a king who's going to act like the kings in their area. Like they see that. They see a king who who conquers. Right. That's what they want. They want a conquering king.
You know, a human person to be their conquering king. But that's not what the kind of kingship that God had described to them. Right. And in in first Samuel,
first Samuel 8 verses 19 and 20, they used that language of we want a king to lead us out and bring us in. Yeah, that's, you know, that's military. Yeah, exactly.
Yeah, exactly. Lead us out to war and then bring us back. That's what we want. Right. And I was going to say I think it's as an interesting side comment on this. Right. I mean, within like within modern Orthodox circles,
there is sometimes a debate about monarchy amongst some people and some really kind of lionize it. See what I did there. And, you know, kind of a thing in and of itself,
but it's interesting that often the image that they have is exactly this image of monarchy. You know, the conqueror. Right. This military hero. Right.
Whereas God's image of monarchy is Christ, ultimately. Right. He's the image of what the king is supposed to be. Yeah, it's fascinating to me, you know, that, you know, people can say, well, look, the kingdom of heaven is ruled by a king.
And then they can kind of conclude from that. That means any kind of kingship must be the right way.
But but no, actually, you know, lots of kings were clearly unfaithful and I get judged by God for their unfaithfulness.
And, you know, it's because the kind of kingship that they practice was not the sort that God was talking about when he was talking about kingship.
So, let me just say, since in Deuteronry 1783 to 20, the primary job there of the king is to copy and study the Torah.
It really means that biblical scholars should.
So, when my administration starts, which should be any day now as people realize the truth, all those of you who have been kind to me will have favorite positions.
And when you come to your kingdom.
I'm somehow dubious that that will actually.
But so, yes. So, so the problem here, the rejection of Yahweh, the God of Israel here, is not that they want a human government with a single head.
Right. It was a representative of Yahweh on earth because that's what they had before with Samuel.
Right.
It's that they're no longer as they were called upon to do throughout the end of the Torah and Joshua and judges to they're not willing to have Yahweh lead them into battle and fight the battle for them and win the spoils and bring them back.
Right. Because they want to do it under their own power with a strong king to lead them.
Because prior to this, at some points, right, he literally was leading them into battle, not just sort of like inspiring them.
Like, oh, I really feel like God is with us today. Like they saw him fighting in the battle. He was literally leading them.
And so, I mean, what they're asking for is to replace him. They want to replace that role that God was was had.
And you say, why would they do that? Well, because sometimes when they were unfaithful and sinful as happened throughout the book of judges, they lost.
Right. Yeah. And he left them, you know. Right.
And they don't like them having to be responsible to God. Right.
They don't want to have to, you know, to keep the covenant to have God fight for them and to bring the victory.
They just want to have a man do it who's accountable to them. Right.
Because of course, once you have a human king, if you don't like him, you can just ax him literally and bring it a new one. Just ask the Purins.
There we go.
The whole circle.
And so that's the issue there.
That's the issue there.
And so then, of course, there's also when when David becomes king and what's normally called the covenant with David, these promises made to David about his line, are really then just the expansion of what was already said in Genesis to Judah.
And so when he comes and speaks to David, he's saying, look, you're the sign. You're here on the throne now. Right. And so reiterates the prophecy part, the promised part.
So interesting things to note, this is recorded twice in in second Samuel or second kingdom seven and in first chronicles or first chronicles 17.
It's first chronicles either way.
And there's some interesting things to note in both of them.
And then Yahweh, the God of Israel is speaking to David about this. He doesn't say at the opener, look, I have made you king.
Yeah.
Over my people Israel in both second Samuel or second kingdom seven eight and first chronicle 17 seven. He says, I have made you prince.
Second command, second and command at best. Right. Bringing out this sort of iconic or sign role, this preliminary fulfillment idea. Right.
And then when the promises made, there's an interesting difference between the two records in second Samuel or second kingdom seven verse 16.
He promises David that he will establish, he says, I will establish your house and your kingdom, meaning David's house and David's kingdom forever. Right. Right.
And so this, this record, right, this historical book is written at the time that Israel is going into exile. Right. So this is the earlier of the two.
And so it's focusing on it in this way to make the point that hey, yes, we're going into exile. Yes, everything looks about as bad as it can get the temples, but destroyed.
But number one, we had it coming. And number two, God did make these promises about David's life. Right. So, so it's not all over.
Then in first Chronicles 17 verse 14, which is written after the return from exile.
When the same thing is said, God says, I will establish you in or his descendant David's descended in my house and my kingdom, God's house and God's kingdom forever.
The indication that the kingship really belongs to God. Right.
But also this indicates that whoever this figure is, this ultimate king, right. David's the prince, he's the icon, he's the sign.
This ultimate king is going to make David's house and kingdom and God's house and kingdom, the same house and kingdom. Right.
Again, we talked about this in some detail in our episode, the Queen stood at the right hand from boy, it's almost been a year now, actually, I think since we had that episode.
I don't think so. We just celebrated our one year anniversary. So I think it has to be less than that. Almost been a year.
I think it was November, if I remember correctly, or early December of last year. So it's not that far.
It's closer to having been a year than to having not.
So, all right. Well, so having established all of that, we're going to go ahead and take another break and we'll be back with the third half of the show.
Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung will be back in a moment to take your calls on the next part of the Lord of Spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237-2346. That's 855-AF radio.
Big in Heaven, a collection of short stories available now on the Ancient Faith Book Store.
Sometimes poignant, sometimes funny, sometimes heartbreaking, sometimes convicting.
These stories of life in an inner city immigrant Orthodox parish are guaranteed to shake your assumptions and make you see your life and face in a new way.
They are not for the faint of heart, but they are very much for all who want to embrace the truth more fully.
And you didn't have to ask us over for help.
Cleaning, polishing, carrying, in or out. Any work in the church, the woman was a styled, a tovadesh you could count on.
No one knew her suffering. They never bothered to look into her eyes.
It surprised me that most of the church folks at St. Alexander the Whirling Derrish parish didn't even know her name.
It wasn't anything they thought about.
To find this book and others like it, you can go to store.ancientfaith.com
Again, that is store.ancientfaith.com
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits, the Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen De Young.
If you have a question, call now at 855-237-2346. That's 855-AF radio.
Welcome to the third and final half. That's right. We get that question a lot.
Did you say third half? It's because it's a show and a half.
Again, this is a reminder, though, that while we do love the voice of Steve,
his own pre-recorded voice does not know that this is also a pre-recorded episode.
There are no calls being taken for this particular one on Melchizedek.
Okay, well, we're now at the final, the third half of the show.
Now we're going to talk about Melchizedek's mention in Psalm 110,
which as you said a whole bunch of times is the most cited text from the Old Testament in the New Testament, right?
Yes, is Psalm 110 or 109 in the Greek number?
Yeah, right.
In case you're looking it up in your Orthodox study Bible, and you won't get confused.
Yeah, it is the most often quoted text, and usually, when it's quoted,
people don't even notice what we're going to be focusing on in this third half in that it's very clearly, right?
The first verse is what's usually quoted, and we've talked before about how, you know,
there weren't chapter and verse divisions.
And so, when a New Testament author quotes a line,
they're quoting the first line of a passage of a section of the scriptures,
and you're to understand the whole section, right?
So you quote the first line of a Psalm to reference the whole Psalm.
Yeah, it's basically kind of like hypertext, essentially.
And the line that everyone's heard, and probably the translation of most people have heard,
begins, you know, the Lord said to my Lord,
sit at my right hand until I make your enemies the footstool of your feet,
or something like that, the Lord said to my Lord, which of course, you know,
Jesus himself quotes that, right?
Right.
Right. Everybody quotes that, very clearly.
Yes, right.
Yeah, and it's the first the Lord is, of course, Yahweh, right?
So it's really Yahweh said to my Lord, sit at my right hand until I make your enemies your footstool.
But yeah, there's no Psalm number for them to reference.
There's no title to the song, right?
So you just quote the first line.
And that would still work today.
I mean, this show is evidence.
You could quote the first line of a song, and everybody automatically knows what song I'm talking about.
Sure, right.
Right.
So that's how it's, that's how it's referenced.
And that first verse, right, if we don't take the time to go and look up the whole song,
or we're not reading Hebrews, then that is very clearly a messianic thing, right?
Yahweh is on his throne.
The Messiah sits in a throne at his right hand, right?
So this is a messianic thing he has to do with the king.
And he's going to defeat his enemies.
Right.
But of course, deeper into the song, Melchizedek shows up again.
Yeah, there are more verses to the song, right?
Ladies and gentlemen, Melchizedek all of a sudden pops up, right?
And if you've been reading straight through the Old Testament, as we've all done many times successfully last week alone, right?
Then, you know, Melchizedek, who pops up for those three verses back in Genesis,
is a distant, faded memory by the time you get to solve 110, right?
And then all of a sudden mentioned, at all.
Boom, Melchizedek, right?
So why is he getting looped back in here to this messianic tradition?
I mean, you may have bought it earlier in this very episode when I told you that,
well, he's sort of an image of kingship, and that's how it's connected.
Hopefully, several of you at least bought it at least that much.
But now this, now we're getting to, as usual, in the third half, why we're talking about this,
that the scriptures themselves draw Melchizedek back into this messianic picture.
And this song is the main place they do it.
And then, this song gets sort of dissected and applied in 13 different ways once we get to the various texts that make up the New Testament.
So, as you mentioned, Christ quotes this verse himself, that first verse himself.
And one of the places where he references it is, he quotes it to the Pharisees that scribes were coming in badgering him with questions and trying to trap him.
Right? So he says, I have a question for you.
And so, in Luke 20 verse 44, for example, he asks them, you know, so this is, they all agree that this is about the Messiah.
Right? So, and they all agree that David wrote this.
Right. Right. So he says, so if it says the Lord said to my Lord, said it by right hand.
And if the Messiah is the son of David, that's one of his titles, that's who he is.
How is it that David calls him his Lord?
Right. Which the reason why that question is a question, in case it's not obvious to people, is that in, well,
I don't know, most of world history, almost everywhere, no one's son is their Lord.
There's always a relationship that always goes the other direction.
The son's Lord is his father.
You know, there's never a, you know, you done good son, now you're in charge of me.
Like, that's never a thing. Right? So that's why this question is a question.
How could he say that, how could David call him Lord, even though he's the son of David,
shouldn't David be above him? Right. Right.
And so this, this is testimony that the son of David is going to be greater than David.
Right. It was science. Something bigger.
But part of what Christ is doing there by pushing that rhetorical question in that way is,
is he is using an interpretation of this text that we also see in the vision of Daniel seven that we've also talked about before in the podcast,
which is this scene where the ancient of days comes to sit on his throne and the throne's plural are set.
Right. We have this sort of divine council, right, judgment scene that takes place today. That's where the son of man comes riding on the clouds.
Right. And the son of man is enthroned. Right. Well, if the son of David, if, if the Messiah is this son of man, this heavenly son of man,
well, that would make him greater than David. Right. Right. And we have this enthronement scene, sit at my right hand.
And within Daniel seven, that's in the context of we have these beasts. Right. And, and he's enthroned. And then there's this period of time before the beasts are judged. Right.
So there's this, there's this lapse. Right. And so in the second verse of Psalm 110, that's referred to. Right.
Right. The, the, the, the scepter, remember that scepter from back in Genesis 49. Right. It was hanging around a Judah.
Yeah. Right. Right. It goes out from Zion. Right.
Uh, goes out from Zion to extend over to extend over the nations. Right. So this is picking up that prophecy. Right.
That it's going to happen with this figure, but there is this element of ruling in the midst, right, of his enemies.
And that's the, that's parallel to the until I make your enemies your footstool. Right. This is verse two of that song.
In case you're calling it long, looking at your copy of Psalm 110 slash 109. Yeah. And so he is, he is enthroned.
He is ruling. He is ruling not only over Israel, but over the nations. Right. Cause it's gone out from Zion from Jerusalem.
But his enemies are still out there. Right. There's this period of time. Right. As we saw in Daniel 7, that's referred to as a long time. Right.
After the introverted to the set of man. Uh, this is the idea that was called referred to as the Messianic age. Right.
And, and this is what we're in now. Right. That there's this met what's the Messiah comes that starts this Messianic age. And then the end of days is at the end of that. Right.
And, and, and you know, this answers the question of why it is that don't, you know, despite Christ having defeated his enemies.
Why they are still around and messing with us. You know, and of course we're talking about the demonic powers here.
It's because this, this is part of the prophecy that he's going to rule in the midst of his enemies. He's ruling. He is ruling.
But the enemies are still around. So, you know, think about what that means in terms of like a battle.
You know, the battle can be won. But then there's a kind of route that occurs. Right. There's a retreat that's happening from, you know, the defeated enemies.
And often they try to burn and pillage and do all kinds of mischief as they go. And that's what we're living through. That's what the, you know, the current era is about.
Right. And this is why now I don't want to publicly shame or embarrass anybody.
But there are still folks out there every once in a while who think that A.D. means after death.
But it's after Christ's death. B.C. is before Christ is it? Now the big problem there would be that what would it be while during Christ's life? There'd be like 33 years of what D.C.
during Christ or. But I'm not a D.C. guy. Sorry. Yeah. I am. But anyway.
No, this is the year of the year of our Lord. Right. It is the year of our Lord. Whatever. Right.
Embedded in that understanding of time is this understanding of the Messianic age. Right.
That this is the period when Christ is ruling in the midst of his enemies. The year of our Lord, meaning the year of our Lord's rule. You start dating when the king takes his throne. Right. Right. Right. Yeah. I mean, the Roman period.
That's the way it was. You know, Tiberius six or whatever. I don't remember how long he ruled. But I mean, that's that's the way that that ancient chronologies always went. It always reset when there was a new emperor.
Right. Well, Genesis 14 that we just read in the 14th year of of Ketterlay Omer. Yeah. Right. Exactly. Everybody. Right. Yeah. Except now it's 2021. Yeah.
2024. So I have to throw in a sorry premillennialists. Right. Because it's been utterly clear to the church. It was utterly clear what was going to happen.
It's second temple Judaism that the coming of the Messiah would start this Messianic age that would then end with the end of days of the final judgment.
There would be this intermediate period in which the Messiah would rule over the world, but his enemies would still be there. That's not another period that's still in our future.
Yeah. Right. The millennium dog don't hunt with with the Bible with the way Christians have always interpreted the Bible with the way we figure out what year it is.
Like it just doesn't work. No. So it's a sorry, not sorry. I'll admit it. But so then keep it going through the song. Right. So it's describing this Messianic age.
Verse three. Right. The people, the people of the Messianic King offer themselves on holy mountains.
Now this is another place where the Hebrew can be read a couple of different ways. Right. Okay. But holy mountains is the way Saint Jerome reads it. And he had a cool lion for a pet. So I'm going with him.
But if you understand what's going on here, right. It talks about their garments, their clean garments. Right. And that they're offering themselves mountains make sense because these then are high places. And the idea that there are holy mountains plural. Right.
I mean, there's been there's been a change because remember the scepter goes out from Zion from Jerusalem, which was the one holy mountain with the one sanctuary. Yeah. I'm seeing like I'm seeing an alternative reading of this is in splendor of holiness rather than holy mountains or holy hills. Yeah. Yeah.
Does that I suppose does that depend on where you put the vowel points or exactly. Yeah. Yeah. It's vowel pointing. Yeah. And those vowel points again. Right. But in the context, right. We have them offering themselves. Right. This is sacrificial language. Right. And they're purification of themselves. It's sanctification of themselves with the garments. Right. Right. So it being sacrificial language splendor of holiness doesn't make a lot of sense. Yeah.
And then just the context of like it being sort of like at sunrise and then there's do like this. Yeah. Yeah. Right. And so this is this idea of living sacrifices that gets picked up in the New Testament. Right. But.
So that the people notice also it's your people.
Identifying the Messiah with with his people. They're his people. Right. Israel is the Messiah's people. Right. Yahweh's people are the Messiah's people. Right. But also this this extension that there's going to be all over the place. Right. The scepter going out from Zion and Jerusalem does not go and just crush everyone who's a Gentile. Right.
Right. It goes out there and makes a hundred other Jerusalem's where people the people are gathering and holiness for worship. Right. During this. This messianic period. Yeah. You know, echoing, of course, the thing that Christ said to the woman at the well, you know, that that. Right. You know, God's going to be worships in, you know, and spirit and truth in every place. Well, that doesn't mean in every place. Okay. But, you know, I got to I'm actually you. Okay. So not only in Jerusalem or on that mountain.
Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. It's spirited in truth as a response to it is talking about the Holy Trinity. Right. Yes. That I got. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. And it's as opposed to the other question she asks that we ignore where he says, where Christ says, you worship what you do not know we worship whom we know.
Because salvation is from the Jews, but the time will come when everyone will worship him in spirit truth. Everyone will know God through the revelation of the Holy Trinity. Anyway, sorry. I had to do it. I agree with you.
That's what I meant. So now we come to verse four of the salt. Yes. Yes. This is the one that actually does mention Melchizedek. Right. And here's where he pops up. And so this is important for how we understand verse three also.
Right. Because remember verse three, if we understand his holy mountains, this is the sacrificial language of this worship language on all these hills. Right.
So as for I have sworn it's usually I have sorted will not repent. Yeah. Meaning not changed my mind. Not. Yeah. Yeah. It's a usage of repent. That's a little bit older than like we tend to think every pant as meaning like I'm sorry for my sins or some version of that. Right. Which is not wrong.
But but you know, to repent means to change your mind. You know, that's all that really. And thus, that's why you get some language in the scriptures of God, quote unquote, repenting. It's not that God has sins that he has to repent of.
It's this notion that from the point of view of the person observing this that God seems to have changed his mind. Right. Or changed what he was going to do. He was threatening something. But then the person repents it so he doesn't do it. Right. Yeah.
So he's so he's sworn that you are a priest forever after the order of Melchizedek. Right. So here's where Melchizedek pops up. And again out of the blue. And there's this much of the order of Melchizedek where there's no order back in Genesis. Yeah, there's just Melchizedek.
Melchizedek doesn't show up with like a bunch of followers or a school or right.
So order here should be translated to literally we tend to think of order like an order of monks or an order. Yeah, the net has it is after the pattern of Melchizedek. Right.
There's an order of organization, the style, the type, the pattern, the the genus. Right. That's you're the kind that he was. Right. Right. Right.
So so there's there's a superficial right level at which we can we can immediately understand this. Well, this is saying that and this is this is part of we're going to go to more depth, but this is the beginning.
Not only is he a king, right. But he's also a priest. It's specifically he's serving as a sort of high priest. Right. That so he is in Zion. His scepter has gone out from there. And so he is sort of serving as the high priest over the people who are offering their worship in all of these scattered places.
Right. Then it's sort of being taken up by him as high priest. Right. In addition to being king. And so since he is both king and high priest, that's like Melchizedek who was both priest and king in Zion. Right. So that that's our first sort of superficial level.
So it's sort of like, oh, yeah, like that guy was right which is true. Right.
But so noting this now, especially in St. Paul's epistle of the Hebrews, he's going to go deeper. Right.
So I mean, you can see right away where he he's going to get the language of Christ is the great high priest from this. Right. How you get the Messiah and the high priest together. Right.
But also he's going to make a contrast between the priesthood of Aaron and the priesthood of Melchizedek. Yeah.
Yeah. What's that all about? Right. Well, part of it is that as he says Christ is not a leafite. Right.
So he would not be eligible to be part of the Aaronic priesthood.
And so he says no, right. Christ is in this with Christ's high priest. He's he's the high priest in this this other priesthood.
But also this is where he talks about and this is where as you were talking about where some people want to say Melchizedek is the quote unquote pre incarnate.
That's problematic, but Christ, right. And in Genesis, they're taking this a little too literally. So he makes some comparisons between Melchizedek and Christ. Right.
That Melchizedek kind of shows up out of nowhere. There's no genealogy of Melchizedek. Right. Right.
And he kind of disappears into nowhere. So his priesthood is in a certain way kind of eternal not in that it literally was, but in the sense that we're not told when it began and when it ended. Right. Right.
He's not enclosed within the text of the store. There is no story of Melchizedek. Right.
And in the same way, Christ's priesthood is not sort of limited and bounded the way Aaron's was.
And the erotic line was and we talked before in a previous episode. We were talking about sacrifice about how priesthood was separate was taken away from leadership and kingship within Israel.
Right. It's split. Yeah. Which was sort of a further limitation.
And so the priesthood of Melchizedek is the understanding of St. Paul's epistle to the Hebrews is understood to be this kind of limitless and eternal priesthood. Right. Of which the erotic priesthood was sort of a shadow.
Or icon is too firm or shadow even that Melchizedek would be the icon in this case.
So it's this this eternal unending priesthood. And it is for Hebrews a priesthood that is carried out not in an earthly sanctuary, but in the heavenly sanctuary.
And so this is another place where our understanding of the Messiah. If we understand that the Messiah is going to be the son of man, the heavenly son of man from Daniel seven. Right.
The heavenly son of man does what in Daniel seven. He's enthroned in the heavenly places. And he, as God's son, God the father's son, Yahweh the son presides over the divine counsel.
So that the kingship that the Melchizedek Messianic priest has is a kingship that's not bound. It's not you know limited to earth. It's it's actually the kingship, the presidency over, you know, the highest possible court that can can be the court truly of the heavens.
Right. And we've talked about when we've talked about theosis, when we've talked about st.hood, we've talked about that primarily from the king side in the past on this show. Right.
That that you know crisis the king and then he has his royal court. Right. And the divine counsel is like his royal court through which he administers right who he shares out of love. He shares his administration of the creation with them.
But there is also remember this priestly aspect that we haven't talked about as much. Yeah, that we're going to talk about a little more now, where remember as is reiterated in St. Paul's epistle to the Hebrews, when the tabernacle is constructed, it's constructed after the pattern of what Moses saw on the mouth. Yeah. Yeah.
He sends the mountain and goes into the divine council. And he's there. Right. With Yahweh speaking face to face with him with the angelic beings, right. The laws give it through angels.
And he then creates the tabernacle. The place where the priests serve. Yeah. Right. And this is the image as I say. And this is reflect. I mean, we just, you know, so we're recording this on the face of the exaltation of the cross on our calendar.
That's where we're speaking to you from. So this morning, and we just celebrated liturgy for the feast. And like this kind of thing is reflected all over the divine liturgy. But I just thought just now, for instance, about the prayer that gets said right before what's called the little entrance, which in the in the ancient church would have been the point at which the clergy and the people are really entering into the church.
It's not it wouldn't at the time. It would not have just been the clergy kind of leaving the altar and then coming back into it real quick. It was really their first entrance into it. And that prayer explicitly asks God to make that entrance be accompanied by angels.
Right. And there's all kinds of references then in the divine liturgy to angels serving alongside the celebrant who's there. Right. So, so like you said, there's this image of, you know, the royal court and the king on his throne.
And so forth. But at the same time, this is the priest Christ is the priest and the angelic beings serve alongside him the way that deacons and altars servers do, you know, and indeed that their vestments, those servers, vestments are designed to remind one of angels. Right.
But this is all going on that we still need to do episodes on the divine liturgy. We have to. But, but, you know, that this is all going on there as well. And it's, and it is, you know, mystically speaking, it is the same thing both are really the same thing.
These are just kind of two different angles of talking about it. It's two different images that are given in scripture of it.
Right. And, and they, they overlap and they're drawn together, you know, in St. John's Apocalypse. Right. And we've quoted this before when we were talking about the saints, right. He says that in the first resurrection, they'll come alive and reign with him during this period.
And that they will be priests. Yeah. Right. Those two things go together. Right. Right. And, and Christ as the second person of the Holy Trinity, the second person of Yahweh, the God of Israel, presiding over the council also means that he is the high priest who is leading the worship of that council, because that's what they do.
And he is the great high priest because he is God and man can both worship lead worship and receive worship, validly, unlike the pagan priest kings and God kings of Abraham's day. Yeah. I mean, that he is the only one that can do that.
Right. Right. You know, is justifiably able to do it. Right. Anyone else who does is an antichrist. Right. Right. The rest of the most literal sense you surpers in one way or another. Yeah. Right. And so that is the picture we're getting for verse three and four of the song of of Psalm 110. Is this image of earthly and heavenly worship being united in the figure of the Messianic king who is also a priest like Melchizedek.
Right. Right. During this Messianic age. And so the primary thing from the perspective of the Psalm, right, from from David's prophetic vision, the primary thing that characterizes the Messianic era between now and the end is the worship of the liturgy. Right. That's, that's the character of this age. And then outside of that, there are the enemies. And so in verses three and a half years,
that there are the enemies. And so in verses five and six of Psalm 110, we get the final destruction of those enemies. Right. The demonic kings and chiefs of the nations. Yeah. He executes judgment against the nations. That's how it begins. Yeah. And, and smashes their kings and their chiefs. And so those enemies are finally done away with. And then in verse seven, we have this image of him.
Stooping and drinking out of a brook. And the idea there is to, it's a pastoral scene of this final era of perfect peace with the enemies gone within the creation.
So Psalm 110 is quoted more than anything else. Obviously, because it gives this important right span, this important prophetic layout of of what's to come. And then once Christ comes to the New Testament authors.
The New Testament authors are then saying, this is what's now arrived. And so they go back to it again and again to characterize the age that's now begun.
So over the course of this episode, we sort of pulled a whole bunch of things together from all over the Old Testament based on how they're used in the New Testament and different things. And we've even pulled in some things from the last episode from Abraham and Isaac.
And a lot of times Christians get accused, especially by some of our Jewish friends, rabbinic Jewish friends, and even sometimes by non religious people that we just kind of go to the scriptures, especially the Hebrew scriptures, they just kind of pillage them for stuff that sounds a little bit Christlike.
And so, you know, Nietzsche said any stick of wood that shows up in the scriptures automatically becomes the cross.
And like we're just kind of, you know, plague fast and loose, right, and kind of constructing Christian theology, this sort of foreign edifice to it.
We're only doing that sort of aposteriority, right. We've received this Christian religion. And so we're now going back and looking for evidence of it in the Old Testament and lo and behold, when that's what you're looking for, you find it, right.
So to counter that, you're at the end of our third half.
I would like to offer an ancient text, which is called 11 Q 13 rolls off your tongue. Sounds like somebody's non personalized license plate.
This is one of the Dead Sea Scrolls. Okay. So the way the Dead Sea Scrolls are labeled is the first number is which cave they came out of. Right. Right.
So 11 Q 13 came out of cave 11. The Q is for cumeron, which is the place where the Dead Sea Scrolls were discovered.
And then the second number is just the order in which they found and identified them. Right. So this is 11 Q 13, it's sometimes called the Melchizedek document or the coming of Melchizedek.
This text was written around 100 BC. So this is 100 years before the birth of Christ by this incredibly fundamentalist Jewish group.
That's living out in the desert because they thought the Pharisees were too liberal. And this is actually their exegesis of the commandment about the Jubilee year in Leviticus 25.
Yeah. Right. So if you look at Leviticus 25, what gets commanded there is, it's called the year of Jubilee. And it's basically this sort of big economic reset, like all the debts are forgiven, all the captives released. Everyone has to go back, you know, everyone gets the land back that belong to their forefathers.
Slaves are free. Yeah. Yeah. Right. So I mean, it's, it's, I mean, we could have a whole episode about the Jubilee.
And we may. Yeah, we should. Yeah, it's a good, it's a great idea. But that's the context. So, you know, if you haven't read Leviticus 25, okay, welcome back. So, but yeah, this, as you said, this text is, this text is about that. This is their sort of commentary on that.
So I'm going to read it to you to everybody. And I'll just, you know, there are, it's fragmentary. So there's bits where the manuscript got damaged. Okay.
So where, where that happened, I'm going to, I'm going to say dot, dot, dot, just so you know that there's a break in what I'm saying.
And then also, you know, it quotes a number of places in the Old Testament. So when it does quote it, then I'm just going to mention what that reference is.
Okay. So as, as I read it here. Okay. So it's a little long, but please just, just, just bear with me. So listen this.
And concerning what the scripture says in this year of Jubilee, you shall return every one of you to your possession.
Leviticus 25, 13. And what is also written, and this is the manner of the remission. Every creditor shall remit the claim that is held against a neighbor, not exacting it of a neighbor who is a member of the community.
God's remission has been proclaimed Deuteronomy 15, 2. The interpretation is that it applies to the last days and concerns the captives.
Just as Isaiah said, to proclaim the Jubilee to the captives, Isaiah 61, 1, dot, dot, dot, just as, dot, dot, dot.
And from the inheritance of Melchizedek for, dot, dot, dot, Melchizedek who will return them to what is rightfully theirs.
He will proclaim to them the Jubilee thereby releasing them from the debt of all their sins, dot, dot, dot.
Then the day of atonement shall follow after the 10th Jubilee period when he shall atone for all the sons of light.
And the people who are chosen for Melchizedek, dot, dot, dot, upon them, dot, dot, dot.
For this is the time to create for the year of Melchizedek's favor.
And by his might, he will judge God's holy ones and so establish a righteous kingdom, as it is written about him in the songs of David,
a God has taken his place in the counsel of God's in the midst of God's, he holds judgment, Psalm 82, 1.
Scripture also says about him, over it, take your seat in the highest heaven, a God will judge the peoples Psalm 7, 7-8.
Concerning what Scripture says, how long will you judge unjustly and show partiality with the wicked, Psalm 82, 2.
The interpretation applies to Belial and the spirits chosen for him, because all of them have rebelled, turning from God's precepts and so becoming utterly wicked.
Therefore, Melchizedek will thoroughly prosecute the vengeance required by God's statutes.
Also, he will deliver all the captives from the power of Belial and from the power of all the spirits chosen for him.
Allied with him will be all the righteous gods, Isaiah 61-3, dot, dot, dot.
The visitation is the day of salvation that he has decreed through Isaiah the prophet concerning all the captives.
In as much as Scripture says, how beautiful upon the mountains are the feet of the messenger who announces peace, who brings good news, who announces salvation, who says to Zion your God reigns.
Isaiah 52-7. This Scripture's interpretation, the mountains are the prophets, they who are sent to proclaim God's truth and to prophesy to all Israel.
The messengers is the anointed of the Spirit of whom Daniel spoke after 62 weeks and anointed shall be cut off, Daniel 9-26.
The messenger who brings good news, who announces salvation, is the one of whom it is written to proclaim the year of the Lord's favor, the day of the vengeance of our God, to comfort all who mourn, Isaiah 61-2.
The Scripture's interpretation, he is to instruct them about all the periods of history for eternity and in the statutes of the truth, and then, dot, dot, dominion, that passes from Belial and returns to the sons of light.
By the judgment of God, just as it is written concerning him, who says to Zion your God reigns, Isaiah 52-7.
Zion is the congregation of all the sons of righteousness who uphold the covenant and turn from walking in the way of the people.
Your God is Melchizedek, who would deliver them from the power of Belial, concerning what Scripture says, then you shall have the trumpet sounded loud in the seventh month, Leviticus 25-9.
Before you go into talking about this, I just wanted to mention something that I noticed as I was reading it, which I kind of love.
There is this interpretation out there of Psalm 82 saying that this divine counsel that God stands up in the midst of is really just human rulers or the rulers of the people of Israel.
And I just wanted to point out that here is this Judean text from 100 years before the birth of Christ that explicitly says that this is about God judging the demon Belial and those who are allied to him.
I just wanted to point that out. This second temple Jewish text explicitly says that this is about God judging the fallen angels.
So I just wanted to point that out.
That the what we would call the quote-a-quote literal interpretation, the fact that every 50 years they were supposed to release their slaves and forgive their debts.
That's like the sign of the real prophecy which this is saying is about this figure they're calling Melchizedek coming, who is both the anointed one who gets cut off.
And called your God, like that's the last thing it says that that line your God is is Melchizedek is the Melchizedek.
Now again, it's this figure they're calling Melchizedek.
We're not saying this means that the man whom Abraham met is going to come back and do these things.
The point is like when it said that David is going to do X, Y and Z, they don't mean King David.
The point is that there is this figure who in himself is what David is in his fullness and that this figure is Melchizedek in his fullness.
Because it is the pattern, wherever the order, the sign.
And so this is Messiah, divine Messiah, who stands in the council of the gods, the renters judgment against Baleil, frees the people from their sins, permits their debts.
All the language we've been talking about today is all drawn together here, plus stuff we've talked about in the past as you just pointed out.
This was all being drawn together and understood 100 BC.
And so the New Testament authors are not making anything up.
Christianity is a continuation of this religion that already existed when Christ came.
But it's now shifted to now we know who that person is, who Melchizedek was the pattern of and it's Jesus Christ.
That's the only thing that's changed is that what was prophesied to happen has now happened.
We've now moved into this new phase, into this, into this new period.
So it's not us, a posteriori coming back and pulling all these things together.
This was all pulled together beforehand.
This is how the scriptures were understood by the people who took it seriously and studied it and were reading the Hebrew scriptures at the time.
Nothing new, very old.
Well, to wrap up this episode about Melchizedek, the thought that I had that to me ties it all together is, it's often the case that a lot of the things that we discuss that people could take a superficial image of them and kind of walk away and think,
you know, a lot of this stuff is a kind of beastiary, right?
It's a collection of weird and mysterious and strange things you find in the Bible, you know, and that is kind of antiquarian, exotic, you know, feeling about this stuff.
And of course, you know, Melchizedek is one of these kinds of figures like, whoa, who is this guy?
I mean, this is really strange and mysterious, right?
Of course, you know, we talk about giants and angels and demons and the various names of fallen angels.
And I think that it can be possible for some people to, you know, as the cliche goes, to miss the forest for the trees, meaning that we can get really caught up in looking at individual figures or stories or whatever it might be.
Which are, I mean, cool, you know, like this is really interesting, fascinating, fascinating stuff.
But if it's not finally all being referred back to Christ, then we're not only wasting our time, we actually might be harming ourselves.
You know, the Bible is not a collection of ancient texts that you can find weird, cool, mysterious things in.
I mean, that's probably literally true on some level, but that's not its point, right?
It's not a kind of book of magic spells.
It's not, you know, again, it's not a collection of curiosities and things to just sort of titillate the mind.
Right? It all points towards Christ.
And to me, this episode is one of the ones that, I mean, I think we, God willing, were doing this in every episode.
But I love where the last part where we ended on with this text from 100 BC, from the Kumaran community, talking about Melchizedek as being this messianic, kingly savior figure, right?
Who's proclaiming release to the captives and rescuing his people from demons.
And how, I was like, whoa, that is so Christian, right? It's so clearly Christian.
And yet this is 100 years before anyone was, or 130 years before anyone was being called a Christian, right?
That was not even a term at this period.
It's clearly about Christ. You don't even have to, you don't have to stretch it at all to see Christ in that.
This is, this is about him.
And that's the goal of everything that we're doing on this podcast is to direct people to Jesus Christ, to direct them to worshiping him, to direct them to being faithful to him, to direct them to knowing him better.
And I think this particular topic we discussed on this episode is especially about that latter bit. It's about knowing Christ better.
When people say, you know, I look at the Old Testament and I see Christ everywhere, that's not a stretch.
It's not a stretch. That's reality.
And so he've looked at one figure from the Old Testament, this image of Melchizedek, who, you know, as far as we know, it's a real person. Abraham meets him.
But he also, in himself, just as David does, he, in himself, is an icon of the one who is to come.
The one who is the prophet, the priest, the king, the Messiah, the Savior, the rescuer of captives, the messenger proclaiming the good news, the defeater of the demons.
He's an image of all of that as we heard summarized in this text from the Dead Sea Scrolls.
So again, at all points to Jesus Christ, that's where we should always end up in every single journey that we take.
Father? Yeah, so building off that a little, one of the most basic questions when you start studying the scriptures seriously is essentially whether the Bible is a thing.
And what I mean by that is obviously that we, of course, buy a Bible and it's a book, right? But in actuality, it's a collection of texts across centuries, you know, millennia, virtually.
That have been touched by countless hands, different authors, right? And especially when you take into account the fact that modern scholarship, you know, our 19th century German friends have done everything possible to try to make not just every book of the Bible, but every piece of every book of the Bible look as disparate from every other piece as possible.
Whether this collection we have actually constitutes anything, whether it's just put together by habit, whether it's just put together by historical accident, whether there's anything connecting it other than those series of historical accidents.
And I think this is a place of differentiation that you can clearly see between the Christian understanding of scripture and the rabbinic Jewish understanding of scripture.
Because on the Christian side, once you delve deep into the scriptures, and I hope this is what comes out on this show.
This is the thing that in this show, in this podcast, in the Bible studies I do, the thing I most want to try to bring people in touch with is the fact that once you start digging into the scriptures even a little bit,
you start to see that there is this, there are these structures that lie beneath the scriptures that connect the text to each other, the different parts of a text to each other, that connect the whole, there are ideas, there are realities that the text is an expression of and trying to draw those out.
The interesting thing coming at it as an Orthodox Christian is that it doesn't even really matter what canon of the Old Testament you use.
You're using the Hebrew Bible canon, the usual Greek collection, usual psilphonic collection, you can go get yourself an Ethiopian Old Testament with the extra dozen books.
Any of those you take, you will find the same structure, the same themes, you will find the whole thing in all of its parts when you see the links and tie them together all pointing toward the one person of Jesus Christ.
You can include or exclude Firsteenek, you still get the same Christ, you can include or exclude Third Maccabees, you still get the same Christ, it fits.
We don't have to go back and cut out pieces of the tradition we've received from our forefathers of the faith, I'm talking about the ones before the coming of Christ, we don't have to go and weed out pieces of that tradition in order to make ours hang together.
I don't think you can say that about the rabbinic Jewish view of the Old Testament.
I don't think there is a logical internal reason why Ecclesiastes is in and Tobit is out.
I don't see any cogent reason for most of those decisions, other than to obscure as much as possible those links and structures and themes that I was just talking about.
When we let the tradition we've received since Abraham, when we let that speak for itself, all of it orient us toward the Holy Trinity, God the Father, Jesus Christ, the Holy Spirit, Yahweh the God of Israel, all of it orient us toward that.
All of it orient us toward who Christ is and what he will do. All of it gives us the same picture of who Christ is and what he will do.
All of it gives us the same picture of how we find our salvation.
It becomes a unit in and of itself and that to me is the greatest argument, not only for the fact that the Bible is a thing, that the Scriptures are a thing, that they are a cohesive whole, but also that they are cohesive whole with the whole rest of the Orthodox faith, which also speaks with that same voice.
The same voice that the Apostle spoke with, the same voice that second-chemple Jewish teachers spoke with, the same voice that the teachers of ancient Israel who were faithful spoke with the same understanding that Abraham had and that Isaac had and that Jacob had and that David had and St. Peter and Paul had.
The fact that we find it in the Scriptures, regardless of our Christian tradition, we find it in our liturgy, regardless of our ancient Christian tradition, shows us that this is not just a construct, this is not just something we built over time, but this is an expression of a deep and eternal reality.
So that's what I wanted to focus on here at the end.
That's our show for today. Thank you very much, everyone, for listening. This was not a live broadcast, but we would still nonetheless love to hear from you, either via email at LordOfSpiritsatAncientFate.com, or you can message us at our LordOfSpirits podcast, Facebook page.
We do read everything, but can't respond to everything, it's true, we don't respond. We can't respond to everything, and we do save what you send for possible use in future episodes.
Some of those things I just don't respond. Join us for our live broadcast on the second and fourth Thursdays of the month at 7pm Eastern 4pm Pacific.
If you're on Facebook, you can like our Facebook page, join our discussion group, leave reviews and ratings everywhere, but most importantly, share this show with a friend whom you know is going to love it, or one that's going to hate it.
One that's going to claim I'm a pagan all over the internet. And finally, be sure to go to ancientfaith.com, stroke support, and help make sure we and lots of other AFR podcasters stay on the air.
And by my new book, Arise Oh God, and also make sure you pick up Father Steven's book, Religion of the Possils, you can get both at store.Ancientfaith.com. Thank you, good night, and God bless you.
You've been listening to The Lord of Spirits, with Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew Stephen Damick, and Father Steven DeYoung, a listener-supported presentation of ancientfaith radio.
And I beheld, and I heard the voice of many angels round about the throne, and the beasts, and the elders, and the number of them was 10,000 times 10,000 than thousands of thousands, saying with a loud voice, worthy is the land that was slain to receive power
and riches, and wisdom, and strength, and honor, and glory, and blessing.
Revelation chapter 5 verses 11 through 12.