Father Interest even Damick on the edge of Pennsylvania Dutch country in Emmaus, Pennsylvania, and with me is my co-host
Father Steven D'Young broadcasting from a gigantic pot of gumbo in the middle of Keaton Country in Lafayette, Louisiana
If you're listening to us live you can call in at 855 AF radio that's 855-237-2346
And we are gonna get to your calls in the second part of today's show
So what are we doing tonight?
Well, here's the question, what is a body?
Human beings are body and soul.
We take that as axiomatic.
What that means is foundational to Christian theology
and what exactly a body is is foundational
to how we understand and experience the world.
Our general conception of the human person goes like this.
And this is how we kind of see it in the modern world.
I am an immaterial soul.
soul and my soul is housed invisibly in
inside my body. My body is a kind of temporary material shell that changes into
case and I will lose it when I die when it will become a corpse and get put
in the ground. And from this common conception, theologically, God does not have a
body except when the Son of God becomes men. He now has a human body, but he did not
have one before. But what if this is wrong? What if I am in fact
body. And what if God had a body even before the incarnation? And what if bodies in general
are actually not what we think they are? So what does that mean? Well to understand that,
first we have to talk about God's body. That's actually the title for our show tonight.
Because God is first, He's the creator, He's the one whom we image. So if we're going to understand
bodies we begin not from our created experience and
our eyes, heaven, word, and try to figure out God from there. Now next time we're
actually going to talk about human and angelic bodies, and I know a lot of your
questions that have sent to us already have been about that, but just be patient
while we lay out the groundwork in this first episode because this is going to be
a two-parter, okay? And I'm going to warn you now that this one is going to be a
bit of a brain bender. So you will probably want to listen to it more than once.
uh
But this is what happens when you have to kind of reconsider such a foundational basic concept like this.
So let's ask the question, what is a body?
I mean, father Steven, what is a body?
And, and welcome, by the way, good to talk to you.
Well, and as you said, I think some people's brains after this may go into recovery mode
from taking in so many high level ideas, but we'll definitely did with mine actually.
and we were doing our preso-
So, but we're gonna, this is important and I think as we talk about it, we'll see why it's important and why it's worth the time to try to wrap our mind around it.
So, what we think of body, we think of, you know, meat like an object.
Yeah, the physical stuff that I'm sitting in, that is sitting in my chair right now.
Right, yeah, yeah.
And so, you know, we, and we even refer to sometimes the, you know, angelic beings as bodyless powers.
Right.
Say, God is a spirit and being a spirit means you don't have a body.
That's sort of our shorthand.
Those two things are opposite each other.
But that's not how ancient people understood bodies or what they meant when they talked about something's body.
Yeah, what they
when they talked about something's body was and
we came up with a couple of different phrases.
We'll see which one catches on and becomes a meme.
Yeah.
Those memes ready for bridging girls.
A nexus of potentialities or a collection of powers
or energies or abilities.
And I know that makes about zero sense
but that's why we're going to talk about this more.
I kind of like
So all you meme makers, I'm leaning towards Nexus of Potentialities because there's a lot of Star Trek possibilities there.
There are. Yeah.
So get William Shadner out.
Anything that will be a little bit of a good automatic.
Exactly.
But so what does that mean? Right?
That nobody has a sort of a Nexus of Potentialities.
Well, to give some examples, we'll talk about body part.
right? So when we talk about eyes we're thinking about the Gushi things in your
skull. Yeah eyeballs. When they're talking about eyes in the ancient world they're
talking about the power of sight. Yeah yeah this is a huge distinction. It's in
rather than talking about a kind of thing, an object, the term refers to
What you're doing, you know, it's dynamic versus as versus being a you know a thing to be put into a microscope and examined, you know
So yeah, so eyes refer to the power of sight not to
You know the what in my wife's family is the last part of the lamb that you heat
right. And likewise with ears, right?
It's not talking about your lobes. It's not talking about the tiny bones in your skull, your tympanum.
It's talking about the ability to hear.
Right? So when Christ says he who has ears to hear, let him hear. He's not saying, you deaf people, don't worry about it.
But the rest of you who have physical ears, you should listen to what I'm saying.
He's talking about those who have the ability.
to hear what he is saying, to hear it.
He's talking about the ability to hear.
And then, feet is a reference to the capacity for movement.
Right.
Arms, especially right arm, since most people are right handed,
is a reference to strength or power or might.
And face, a reference to a face is a reference to the ability to communicate.
Right. Right. Right. And I think it's important and we're going to talk about this more when we start talking about how these words apply to God.
But I think it's really important just to come to state right here that what we're not saying is they're not objects. These are metaphors.
And the objects are being used to set out these metaphors. Right. You know, like like saying, oh, you know, you need to have spiritual eyes or the eyes of faith. Meaning, meaning, okay, you understand things and see things. But it's like
having eyeballs, you know, that's that's not what we're saying because again, like
this is the show where we tell you that the things that you thought were metaphors are not metaphors. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. So yeah, our
you know, the the round gushy orbs in our skull
right those eyes are the instrument which we use to see
right the instrument through which we exercise that power. Yeah.
So
So in a sense, eyes include the eyeball in the sense that eyes need the eyeball to do the thing that they do.
For us.
Yeah, for us.
It's what we use to do that.
Yeah.
Not necessary, but that doesn't mean that something can't have the power of sight, the power of hearing, the ability to communicate without having a meaty, fleshy organ that we have.
Right.
rate.
So again, this is probably still super weird and confusing.
So yeah, and so to help with this, we're going to, again, we're talking tonight about God's body in particular.
Right. And so when we read in the Scriptures and we read things talking about some body part of God,
right that you know
God defeated Pharaoh with his strong right arm.
Right, right.
It's not a metaphor.
Right.
Or God's eyes go throughout the cosmos, right?
Go throughout the world and see everything.
Yeah.
Or when we read about, yeah.
I was just saying, yeah, like Moses speaking to the Lord,
I mean, this is the language in scripture,
face to face as a man speaks with his friend.
Right.
and the face.
of God is referred to all the time. And when someone says that they want to see God's face,
he doesn't say, don't be silly, I'm a spirit, I'm like a ghost, I don't have a face. He says,
I have a face but you can't see it and live. So, if I show it to you, you'll die. If I try
to communicate with you directly, you won't be able to bear it. And the problem, of course, is that
As modern people, when we see these references, like for instance, God in the Garden of Eden,
he's walking in such a way that they can hear him, you know, right?
It makes a sound.
There's that kind of thing.
This language is used for God.
And so because we have this idea that God doesn't have a body, God is immaterial.
And we're going to obviously, we're going to unpack what all of that means, okay?
kind of how we got to where we are now.
But what happens then is, as modern people,
who are faithful Christians, we want to believe
what the Bible says, we look at that and say,
well, that's metaphorical language for God.
God doesn't have an arm, he doesn't have a nose,
he doesn't have eyeballs, you know?
Like because we're used to thinking of a body
as being an object or a collection of objects,
then when those kinds of words are used to talk about God,
We said...
Well God doesn't have that. He's not limited like like we are you know, so it's just a metaphor
He accomplished this through some other means that
That the biblical writers were just trying to come up with ways of talking about and so yeah
And this is the came up with the term that's applied to that is anthropomorphism
Yeah, I suppose meaning a human right and and morph right form shape
So we're giving a human shape to God.
try to understand and better bring him down to our level.
Human beings can understand God, God is distant and remote and unintelligible and so we kind
of just explain him and describe him in human terms.
That's how people will generally talk about those references in the scriptures.
Right.
Exactly.
And we're here to say that's exactly backwards.
Yep.
That's right.
Exactly.
the reverse of the truth.
that the way the Scriptures see it is that humans are theomorphic, right? Humans are in the image and likeness of God.
Right.
So God is the paradigm, and then humans are a sort of weak and diminished, right, version.
our powers are a weaker or diminished version of his powers, not we take our powers that
just sort of project them.
a giant size and attribute them to him.
Yeah, you know, and correct me if I'm wrong about this, but like an obvious parallel seems
to me wherein, if I recall correctly, is Ephesians chapter five, that passage that gets read
at weddings in the Orthodox Church, where St. Paul talks about how men and women are, you
know, husbands and wives are supposed to relate to each other within marriage.
And then he says, but I am speaking of Christness.
church. And so a lot of times the way that gets read is people say, oh, oh, the relationship
between Christ and his church is like human marriage. But I've pointed out many times to
couples, you know, as I was preparing them to get married. So no, no, no, no, your marriage
is like the union between Christ and his church. Am I off base here?
or no, and thank you for choosing the least controversial possible
example you could have taken from Ephesians 5. Yes, this could have got a whole
different way. You're like, wait, what's up? What is he about to say?
But yeah, so God is eternal. So what we call seeing is sort of a very weak
a weak version of what it means that God is able to see.
Yeah.
And so what we...
call eyes is this weak material fragile subject to corruption,
version of God's eyes,
his ability to see his ability to communicate, his powers, his,
the divine energies, we have a human energy, which is obviously much weaker.
Right.
and write up but is in the image of the reality.
that is God. He's the original, where the icon of that.
Right. You know, yeah. Right. Much lesser version. Right.
And so going back to that example of God having a face. Right.
And if not to not he that he has a face. This is something that gets masked in most
of our English translations. All the time in the Old Testament we read about
estimate we read about the presence of God.
the presence of God in the temple, the presence of God in general.
So Jonah gets told to go to Nineveh to the Assyrians,
and he knows that the Assyrians flight people alive, so he's like,
nope, and it says that he flees from the face of God.
Because the word presence there was translated as presence is the word face.
You've flees from God's face.
And we talked about face representing this power of
communication. So when it says that Jonas is fleeing from the face of God, it doesn't
mean, well, God's over here in this particular geographical locale and he's running away
from it. It's more like he's putting his fingers in his ears and going, nah, nah, nah,
I can't hear you.
Yeah.
Right.
And taking off in the other direction.
But that.
that, that peer-revention you can't,
that where God says you can't see his face and live,
that's what's going on when the people of Israel
come to Mount Sinai, and they hear God communicating
in the thunder on Mount Sinai,
and they're terrified that they're gonna die,
and they say, Moses, don't let God talk to us directly,
we'll die.
They say, you go, right?
You go up there and, and interact and talk to him,
and communicate with him.
for us. So that language of face is actually probably the most prevalent one of these, even
though it's hidden by translation in the scriptures.
And again, it's so tempting, like Jonah fleeing from before the face of God. Like, oh, that's
a metaphor. Like, you know, but again, where exactly is God's face that he could run away
from it.
You know, so it-
It doesn't, it doesn't make sense in that way.
And, and again, nowhere in there does it say this is a metaphor.
Like you said, God doesn't say, well, I don't really have a face, but I'll just let you say that I have a face because it makes sense for you, you know.
And, and you know, this speaks to, you know, one of the sort of critiques of Christianity is that, that, you know, man makes God in his own image.
And...
But that's actually not the Christian teaching,
although some Christians effectively seem to think
that it is, right?
Because it's what we're talking about.
That we say, oh, well, we do use this human language
for God.
It's anthropomorphic language for God,
but he doesn't really have that, right?
So there's kind of an apologetic side to this as well.
You can say, no, no, no, actually, no,
this language that we use for God refers to something real.
And the human version of it is the kind of much
or lesser version of that.
So even though I understand sight by virtue of what I'm doing now,
you know, the things that I have that are there's eyelids
blinking on the outside of,
that's just a, you know,
small, you know, a sliver of what God is able to do.
I shouldn't assume that his sight is just like mine,
but bigger, right?
There's something else going on there, you know,
especially because he doesn't need eyeballs to do-
it right right you know he sees in some other way that I don't understand but he
nonetheless does see nothing can hide from him yeah he doesn't he doesn't need
and won't ever need the cheap Walmart reading glasses I need now that I'm
always breaking yes which I'm getting close to probably getting a set for
myself since we're about the same age so you get like five packs so when they break
you just move to the next one. Just flip yeah exactly.
So, yeah, so our powers, and this is key, I'm tempted to go down this rabbit hole, but
I won't.
I'm sure we'll talk about it more in the future.
But this is key to all kinds of things in terms of how we think about God, where understanding
that we're not, he isn't like us, right?
becoming like him.
Right.
And those are very different ways of proceeding.
Yeah.
To kind of summarize this piece of it, you know, when we talk about a body being a nexus of potentialities,
a collection of powers or energies,
you know, it's not a kind of object, it's rather...
the abilities that we have to do, you know, not just we, but the ability that anything that
has a body has to do all these things.
And God has these abilities, right?
Scripture talks about him this way.
So that's what a body is.
So if that's what a body is, then how does that differ from our concept of the body?
And then what do we do about the fact that we have all those languages, especially in
the New Testament, about flesh, right?
I mean...
I think most of us tend to think that body and flesh are just synonyms.
I mean, that's the way we use it in English, right?
That flesh is just kind of a nice poetic archaic way of referring to the same thing that
we mean when we have a, we talk about bodies.
So, so I know St. Paul makes this distinction.
Yeah.
What does St. Paul say about the difference between body and flesh?
And I know that in Greek body is soma and flesh is sucks.
those are the two words we're dealing with in Greek.
And this is the biggest place where you can easily go completely wrong with reading St. Paul is
missing the nuances of the way he uses, he distinguishes between his usage of similar words.
Yeah, right.
Right.
So when he talks about Judeans, it's usually translated in English as Jews, that's not the exact same
same group of people he's talking about when he talks about Israel.
He doesn't just use those interchangeably.
And this gets really granular to the point that St. Paul,
when he refers to dead, without a definite article,
is referring to a different group of people
than when he refers to the dead with a definite article,
even though both get translated as the dead in English.
So in most English translations, you can't even tell.
So this is how New Aussie could be.
So the same is...
true. I think we need a new study Bible father. The same is true with the way he uses body and
flesh. Right. We can read over it very quickly. And there is, for example, a Gnostic reading of Saint
Paul that reads these both the same. Yeah. Because as you'll see even just casually reading what
of St. Paul's epistles. And this is true outside of St. Paul's well.
very clear in St. Paul, but St. John and his epistles and other New Testament authors use
these terms the same way, basically.
Okay, so it's consistent across the New Testament.
Yeah, yeah, it's just St. Paul's sort of exhibit A, it's sort of the easiest place to see
it.
Right.
St. Paul has a lot of negative things to say about the flesh.
Yeah.
Right.
And its inability to inherit the kingdom of God, for example.
And add
It ties it, it's a tight very much to sinfulness and to the depassions and desires.
And again, if you read that as meaning, okay, well, our body is sinful and then our soul, which is this other thing,
is not, you can very easily go in a gnostic direction.
Yes.
Where the material gets opposed to the spiritual.
Right. Yeah. Yeah. And so body for St. Paul and for the ancients in general is this overarching
category of this nexus of potentialities. And we'll dig deeper into what he says in
1 Corinthians 15 next time. But there for example he talks about how angels and men and
animals have different types of bodies. All within that big cap-
category of body. They all have powers. They all have the ability to interact with the world. They all have these potentialities.
Flesh is then a subcategory. It's a smaller circle within the big circle of bodies is flesh.
And flesh is a type of body that for St. Paul and the other New Testament authors is weakened, is corruptible, is changeable.
is mortal. It's an even more limited version of the original human body.
Yeah, so it's, it's, it's the way the human, we're going to talk about Adam and Eve for just
a second, maybe we should introduce that. So Adam and Eve, they have the original human body and then,
and then it changes because of sin.
And God gives them this change.
It doesn't just sort of come out of nowhere.
For God for reasons.
Yeah, for reasons which we're gonna go into a lot more next time.
So, you know, write down the phrase garments of skin, everybody.
But this is not that episode, two weeks from today.
But just to cover this briefly though,
God gives them what are called
and scripture garments of skin,
which doesn't mean that he gives them nice leather suits.
It means that their bodies are altered.
So they now become fleshly bodies, right?
And I kind of like that as a sort of adverb,
or I don't know if it's adjectival,
yeah, I guess it's adjectival, but fleshly bodies.
And then they function in a fleshly way.
So it's not only just a kind of way
that their bodies changed as sort of a thing,
but also the way that they function.
Because again, a body is a collection
of powers and abilities and so forth.
And so what that means then is that our bodies,
when God gives mankind the garments of skin,
our bodies change in such a way as to become
limited and corruptible and deathly.
We're gonna talk next time about why
that was actually good,
from God's point of view.
So we're giving all kinds of teasers.
But, but I think it's really important.
understand that this change happens. It's not that they were exactly the same before. And now,
oh, boom, now you can die. That's not all that happens. You know, that they, again, if a body is a
kind of collection of powers and nexus of potential, potentialities, then that means that the powers
themselves change so they presumably lose some abilities and gain some abilities.
Weirdly there are there are powers that are lost. Yeah, they're lost completely and potentialities that are lost
There are powers and potentialities that are weakened
like the news the mind
and
So there are crises that are weakened and attenuated and then there are new potentialities that are gained
Like the mutability and
Mortality right that that are taken on
by them at the point of that change.
So if you think about a being's body
as sort of a circle that includes,
or like a bubble that includes all these powers
and potentialities, right?
The change that happens is that some of those leave,
some of those diminish, and then new ones
sort of come into the membrane.
right? Yeah. Now I sound like an
originist because I've got a spherical body
but that's a good that's a good
name drop for a lot of the
souvenirs out there. Yes, said
you're written condemnations to
it. Yeah, or I mean I can other way
and this is just a metaphor people
but it's just something that
occurred to me right now. But another
way of thinking about it is almost
that are if we could think of our
is having DNA. And again, I'm using body in that sense of the nexus of potentialities,
not DNA like the way we think of the modern idea. But DNA, of course, is the kind of code
that tells our flesh what to do, how to shape and function so forth. We could imagine
in a sense that the DNA of our collection of powers gets rewritten because now it does
different things, functions differently. Again, this is
just this is a metaphor.
I don't know.
Does that work in terms of rewriting the code?
I don't know, no metaphor really works.
But hopefully one of those at least, we'll get help people start to wrap their head.
And once you have that in mind, though, you can see that play out.
So St. John doesn't say the word took a body.
He says the word became flesh.
Right. Right. It's more specific than that.
Because just saying the word took a body wouldn't mean the same thing.
Right. He's talking about what are the incarnation
Christ being made man.
Um, and when when Christ after the resurrection, uh, says a spirit has not
flesh and blood as you see that I have. He doesn't say a spirit doesn't have a body.
Right. Right.
He says that has to be...
as it have flesh and blood.
So yeah, the human flesh and animal flesh is also flesh,
but we'll get more into that next time.
But flesh, a fleshly body is a type of body.
It's not synonymous with this is always what a body means.
Yeah, yeah.
And we're gonna go to a break in just a second here,
but another thing, we're just gonna give people all kinds
of hooks to save for next.
time because this is what we do on this show. But another one to think about is, you know,
when Christ rises from the dead, as you were just talking about, he still has flesh and
bone. So that means that his body still has flesh, you know, that there's something about
that is still quite human.
You know, and obviously we're gonna...
We're going to talk about that more the next time.
But clearly, it works in a different way after the resurrection.
He's no longer mortal, for instance.
Well, he technically wasn't before.
Yeah, we'll get into that next time.
Yeah, yeah, yeah, exactly.
Sorry, sorry.
Yes.
All right.
Well, all that being said, we're going
to go ahead and take a break.
And please call.
We would love to hear from you and talk to you
even though this is a very mind-bending version,
mind-bending episode of The Lower Spirit.
So let's let's go ahead and go.
break and we'll be right back into a second. Father Andrew Stephen Damick and
Father Stephen DeYoung will be back in a moment to take your calls on the second
half of the Lord of Spirits. Give them a call at 855-237-2346. That's 855-AF
radio.
Are you struggling in your walk with Christ? Do you want to rediscover your
reason for living.
person you are created to be. Renewing you, a priest, a psychologist and a plan gives
you the keys to unlock areas of your life that hold you back from fully experiencing the
renewal and transformation God has in mind for you.
Co-author by a priest and a psychologist, Father Nicholas and Dr. Roxanne Lowe, renewing
you combines principles of spiritual growth with psychological tools to help you become
your best self, fully connected with God's purpose for you.
To purchase this book, please go to STOR-
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits, the Father Andrew Steven Damick and Father Steven
to Young.
If you have a question, call now at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF Radio.
Welcome back.
This is the second part of the show.
And it's where we begin to take your calls.
We would love to hear from you.
You can reach us just like you heard
from the voice of Steve at 855-8F-Radio-855-237-2346.
And we would love to talk to you.
So all right, in the first part,
we talked about what is a body and also a bit about
what it means that God has a body.
And also we touched very briefly on what happens
to Adam and Eve's bodies.
after they sin.
But, you know, in trying to begin to rewrite the way that we think about the stuff and bring it into line with what the scripture says and which is embedded in this ancient way of thinking,
we need to talk a little bit about how it is we got to the way that we think now, right?
And actually the seeds for that are sown in the ancient world, right?
But it doesn't come from scripture.
It comes from
from pagan Greek philosophy, who, you know, they begin to ask the question, does God
have a body? And the answer that they come up with is, no, he doesn't. Right? So how
do they get to that? And what does that all kind of mean?
Yeah. So, and really what, what? I mean, we're particularly obviously talking about
a great philosophy here, but right.
When the Greek philosophers start to address this question,
what they're really doing is sort of philosophically dealing
with and encoding what was already the general pagan view.
We talked about this in a previous episode,
how after what is described as the Tower of Babel event
in Genesis 11 that we see in cultures all over the world,
that the most high
the creator god, the highest god, sort of becomes distant and is seen to be
disconnected and removed from the world and human beings interact with these
sort of lesser gods and spirits but not with the greater gods. And so the Greek
philosophers don't substanceively differ from that but they do speak about it
Obviously.
in a different and philosophical way
that will especially deal with it
in terms of having a body.
So if you look at, for example, Aristotle,
we were going in reverse order by talking about Aristotle
and then Plato.
How dare you, sir?
I know.
People are offended all over the place.
You know, you could have started with parminities
but then people would really fall asleep.
So I just remember priests,
ecratics like Thales who supposedly thought
everything was made of water.
That's what I remember from that bit of undergraduate
introduction to philosophy.
I'm not taking your bait, sir, and getting into that.
So, for Aristotle, we usually refer to Aristotle's quote
unquote, God, or quote unquote,
most high god is the prime mover because we're getting
kind of filtered through a
domestic theology
But the way he describes
this being like in metaphysics lambda is
He describes this being as noesis
Noesios as which is something like
thought thinking itself
Right. Yeah or just like pure thought
But key to that is the
idea that because it is the highest being, it is the being of beings, it is completely unaware
of anything else that exists because for it to think about anything other than itself,
it would have to lower itself. Yeah, yeah, there's this. Right, and so then this is the beginning of,
of like, you know, noctisism kind of branches off from this idea that the true
God, the unmoved mover is so pure, so perfect that it can't even pay attention to anything.
It just be perfect self-contemplation.
Because without that, then it's lowering itself.
Before we get too much deeper into that, which we certainly will, we actually do have
someone calling in.
So um.
We have Alec who is calling from Florida and he has a question about what happens to our body in the next life and this pertaining to theosis.
So Alec, can you hear us?
Yes, Father, is Alex from the Sonny Orlando, Florida.
Oh, Alex.
Alex with an X, excuse me.
Well, welcome, Alex, to the Lord of Spirits.
exactly is your question?
Yes, so it's a bit convoluted, I guess.
But the glorified saints, I would think, take part in the divine council.
So to an extent, I don't know how much they share in gods, I guess.
And their powers of omniscience are enhanced, their bodies are glorified.
Speaking of Christ's body as an example, first fruits.
And I was wondering if you could tie that into the concept of the news.
And to what extent
in the church experience and the church experience do,
say in their earthly life, achieve, you know,
these aspects of clairvoyance, you know,
knowing things that they can humanly know,
things of that nature.
Yeah, well that's a great question.
You know, I'll just say one thing
and then father Stephen can correct me,
or add to it whatever.
Oh, actually.
Actually, yeah.
Yeah.
So, you know...
And we're going to cover this a lot more in the next episode, but just to answer a little bit this time around.
Part of what happens, or I should say, what happens in theosias, this process of becoming adopted sons of God, and becoming more like him and participating in his glory, is that our body begins to reflect more the likeness of God.
likeness.
of God, right? And so that's why the saints have the abilities that they do is they're
actually they're becoming what human beings were meant to be, right? But that's not human beings are not
are not independently sort of powerful. It's their participation in God that makes them
what it is that they are and have these from our point of view what looks like
extraordinary abilities but actually is kind of ordinary for their normal, the rest of us are
abnormal, right? Yeah, yeah, exactly, exactly. So I mean, that is at least what I would say about that.
I don't know, Father, do you have anything you wanted to add or adjust or correct or whatever?
I'll add this is
and well I like to say we'll get into this a little more next time but
But this is pertinent here because I think what we're talking about tonight, what we're
going to talk about in two weeks, as we go on, hopefully you'll see if we do a good
job of explaining it, that this is the nexus where a whole lot of our theology and our belief
all sort of comes and fits together.
And so specific to theosis, we have these sort of different moments we think about or talk
about when we talk about theosis.
think about glorification and the transfigure
of the body, Christ's Transfiguration, some of the saints who have shown with the uncreated
light of God at the times of their deaths or at other times in their life.
And we also think about participation in the divine energies, right?
The energies of God, God's activities and His power in the created order.
And we have these separate things and the purification of the news.
We have all these things as separate.
This is really where those come
together, because if we come to participate in God's energies, right, we don't gain like
God powers, right? Like we don't get some power he has, but we participate in his, he
acts through us when we're imaging him. Right. And so that is transforming then of our powers,
and therefore of our body.
So the idea of transfiguration and glorification, that's where that comes together with the
idea of participating in the divine energies.
Because our body then becomes the instrument for God's energies and powers and activity.
Right.
Similar to nature.
Yeah.
So similar to the way that I was talking about that, you know, the the the Gushy things
in our skull, the Gushy Orbs.
the instrument we use for the power of sight, right? Yeah. We as persons become instruments
of God's love or peace in the world. Yeah. And then that's transformative. And for that
reason, it would, among others, the church is called the body of Christ, right? Right.
Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. That's what Saint Paul's getting at when he talks about
the body.
in 1 Corinthians 13, that the way in which Christ communicates to the world is through the church,
the way that Christ is brought to the world, his feet, his hands, right? That's the church.
We're going to flesh that out, pun intended. A lot more, sorry, I couldn't have myself.
Yeah, yeah, yeah, a lot more, a lot more in two weeks, but we just kind of realized when we
We are going over this.
or actually I should say Father Stephen just informed me look this is going to take a couple
episodes.
It's so, it was a great, yeah, right exactly.
So, does that, thank you, Father.
Yeah, thank God, thanks for calling in Alex.
Thank you.
Okay.
Yeah, so all right, let's talk a little bit more about the God of the philosophers, if
we can put it this way, right?
There's this idea that it's the unmoot mover that this God doesn't even pay it.
attention to anything other than itself, right?
You know, it does not communicate, does not see, does not hear, right?
So what the philosophers are denying is that God has body in this ancient sense of being this nexus of potentialities, collection of powers and abilities.
And as I was trying to imagine what that could be like, right?
Because there's
There's still some kind of interaction with the rest of creation.
You still have, it's the unmoved move, but it's moving.
I thought about the force and star wars.
It's not a perfect analogy, but the force and star wars is similar in that.
uh
It doesn't talk to you, although I mean, obviously depending on which one of the films you're watching, the force seems to have a will.
But the force doesn't step out and say, hey, Luke, I have something that you need to know.
That's not a thing.
But there's still a sort of influence there, but it's impersonal.
Would it be correct to say that the philosopher's God is not a personal God?
What do you think, Father?
well
Because we have this idea of prime mover,
we might be deceived into thinking that Pat means,
well, he's moving everything else.
Right, and he's sort of actively,
he's somewhere in some other realm
turning a crank and that causes everything else
to move, you know, starting with the sun moon and stars
and then working its way down.
Right.
But that's actually sort of the opposite of how it works.
the way it actually works is that
everything else sort of sees the
unmoved mover, sees thought
thinking itself and
motivated by love and sort of
awe of its perfection attempts
to imitate this sort of
impersonal but perfect to be.
Oh, I see. So it's almost an
unmoveed inspireer rather than
move or exactly. Does that, I don't know.
Yeah. They move out of, they move out of desire to be like it
and to be closer to it. So it's sort of like the whole cosmos
stands the prime mover and like must, you know, try to be
closer to it. And that's not a place where Aristotle differs
from Plato. So Plato has basically the same thing that he has
It's so good.
And the good is sort of in perpetual stasis.
Doesn't move, doesn't change, because it's perfect.
So how could it, right?
If it changed, it wouldn't be perfect anymore.
So the heavenly bodies, which are sort of the next,
most perfect thing, move in circles because going in a tight
circle is the closest they can get to imitating
that sort of perfect stasis.
Yeah, right.
And...
That's why Plato and the Tameas in particular comes up with this demi-erge, this lesser divine being,
who's going to create everything else. And he sort of looks at the good and looks at it
admiringly and sort of tries to create everything else based on that admiration and sort of
inspiration that it draws. So this is a God.
that doesn't have a body in the ancient sense
that we've been talking about, right?
It doesn't communicate, it doesn't act,
it doesn't speak, it doesn't hear,
it doesn't see anything else right outside of itself.
And that gets, as you mentioned already,
brought over into noctisism fairly directly.
Yeah, right.
When we found the Nakamadi Library,
sort of the biggest collection we found
of the Nostek texts, Plato's Tameas was in there,
as part of it, sort of as their old testament.
So yeah, this Plato, Gramps,
and you see in various Nostek systems,
they have this God with a capital G
who is remote and unknown and unknowable.
And then this whole series of emanations,
sort of working their way down.
until you get to material things in that direction.
Yeah.
Yeah, and it's easy to see then that this God of the philosophers,
who has nothing directly to do with us, you know,
It's really easy to see how people can
more of that into, for instance, deism, which is a little bit closer to us, right?
The deism is the idea that God created everything and then walked away from it, you know, the
cosmic watchmaker, right?
Wind up the watch and now just let it tick away.
And then there's not much distance from that to our disenchanted world, which is a major
theme of everything we talk about in this podcast. Because if God is
not present to us by means of his body, right? The body that we've been talking about, his
collection of powers, nexus of potentiality is the ways that he interacts with mankind. If he's
not present to us in that way, then it becomes all the easier not to believe that he's there at all,
or that if we do believe that he exists, he's kind of not an everyday thing. You know, he's out there
somewhere right?
And we wish once in a while that a miracle might happen.
Boom, oh, he stepped in, thank you God.
But this is the origin of the kind of disenchanted way of
understanding the world of secular materialism, because this is the
God that doesn't have anything to do with this.
This is the God that can't interact with us or you know,
won't, right?
However you want to perceive what, you know, what that is.
I mean, obviously play the
Aristotle are describing a God who can't interact with us because that would be against his nature.
Right? Modern man looks up, sees nothing, shouts at the sky, and gets no answer back, and so he
assumes, well, God, if you're out there, obviously, you don't care. You know? But they're just
kind of different permutations, different ways of essentially seeing God in the same way. I mean,
So this is kind of pastorally huge and theologically huge, right?
You know.
that the God of Abraham, Isaac and Jacob, the God and Father of our Lord Jesus Christ
is not the philosopher's God. The philosopher's God has nobody, he's remote, it,
I should really say it, really, right? It is remote and distant because he
you know implies this kind of personal reality. You know, and so we can't
know him and the idea that Jesus Christ would make him known as you know as
we're going to talk about it in a second here.
doesn't make any sense at all.
And the way that that kind of makes its way down through history
is that eventually you get what's referred to as the God of the gaps.
There's these scientific things happening that we can't explain.
So we'll just say, well, that's God.
But then as science gets bigger, then, well,
we don't really need the God of the gaps anymore.
So boom, secular materialism eventually
is kind of where that way of thinking goes.
And so it's interesting that there's a direct line between saying God does not have a body
and ultimately secular materialism, atheism, all of these modern problems that we have now.
Right. Right. And you sort of start with dasticism, you cut out all the middleman and you're left with
agnosticism. Yeah, right. Yes, there are a lot of middlemen along the way. I mean, I'm just sort of,
You know, just sort of, you know, scurrying over 15, 16, 17.
100 years of history there, but as one does.
Yeah, so this comes up as you mentioned in terms of how we understand who Christ is.
And it comes up at an event that I think a lot of people have probably heard of at least
vaguely.
Yeah.
But may not know what it was actually about.
on.
When we were reviewing this, I had only the barest outline.
I remember like, oh yes, this is something where someone
said something bad about St. John Chrysostom.
Right.
And if it's dealt with in terms of what it was about,
what you usually get is, well, this was really just
about church politics.
But we're talking about the synod of the oak, which is when
St. John Chrysostom was condemned and exiled for the first time
in 8402.
Right.
And you know, it is like there was a lot of church politics involved. This was motivated
by that. But that is, there was an actual accusation made against him of heresy at this
city. Right. Right. And so the, what we want to talk about here is the nature of that
accusation. Yeah, because that's very pertinent to everything that we've been discussing. And
But we'll stay from the outset that it was a false accusation.
Yes.
Yes, right.
Yeah.
But so if you've read anything about the Senate of the Oak,
you'll probably know that they accuse
St. John Chrysostom of being an originist.
Yes.
Now, originist is a very flexible accusation.
Right.
Yes.
It can refer to lots of things.
You could be saying somebody's a universalist.
You could be saying that they think that resurrected bodies
will be spherical.
You could be saying that.
right? That's my favorite. So, but in this case, what they were saying made St. John,
Christophe and originist was that they accused him and the tall brothers who he'd sort of given
aid and comfort to from Egypt. Yeah, we're a group of monks by the way, these tall brothers.
Yeah, right. He was accused of being an originist because they said he said that God didn't have a body.
Right.
They're saying that he said that.
Right, they accuse the Jockers' Ossum of saying
that God doesn't have a body
and a group of monks were sent who are referred to
as anthropomorphists because they believe
that God had a body.
Right.
And so sometimes, if anyone even gets
into the details of the accusation,
they look at it as kind of silly
because they say, well, of course,
God doesn't have a body because they're thinking of body
the mother.
sense. Yeah. Right. We've been talking about it. Right. So the accusation at the time actually
was an accusation about St. John's Christology primarily. Right. And I think it's important,
especially to know that part of the frame for this is that it's actually a guilt by association
accusation. It's not from something that he himself ever said or wrote, right? It's just...
you're from this town and they have bad Christology over there.
So you therefore must as well,
because we all know how people from Antioch are,
don't we, Nudge, Wink?
Right.
It's Antioch.
And there are other anti-Ikean writers whose Christology
was later condemned, like Theodore of Mopsu,
Ashtia, Theodore of Cyr.
And it was not coincidental that they were condemned.
alongside origin. Right. Because there is a connection that we're about to talk about. Yeah.
So the idea is they were condemned for a Christology that was an historian, meaning they were condemned
because they said that their view of Christ had some kind of separation between Christ's humanity
and his divinity.
And the part...
particular way that worked was based on a certain view of Christ as a divine person.
If you take, and again, we won't get into whether this is even actually what origin
believed, but origin was thought and said to have accepted this philosophical notion of
the divine nature.
That God has no body in this ancient sense.
and it's an ancient sense that God doesn't communicate.
directly to his creation or act directly in his creation.
That he had. Yeah. Now would it be correct to say, I know that, you know,
the word is developed a lot much later, but it would be correct to say that,
that these are the energies of God we're talking about is energies of God,
synonymous with the body of God.
I wouldn't say synonymous.
But there's certainly someone overlapped here.
Yeah.
Yeah, when we talk about God's powers and his, yeah.
Okay.
So, but so for him, God, capital G, they held that for origin,
God, capital G is like the God of the philosophers
and is disconnected.
And then for origin, they held, right?
They held the origin, said that then the logos
sort of a lesser divine being who served.
as an intermediary. So if you imagine for a minute that we're thinking about Christ, we have
Christ as humanity, but then you believe that divinity, including Christ's divinity, is bodyless
in this sense, is detached, is infinite, and you know, unaware and unable to interact with creation.
you end up
having sort of this human being, Jesus, who is in some way attached to or connected to
a divine person in some kind of unique way. Yeah. The forest. But, sorry. Right. But
Bidoclorians, I don't know.
It's really strong with the force.
Yeah, yeah.
It's so working.
But it's not one person.
Right.
Right, it's not one person.
And.
So that understanding of God is incompatible with Orthodox Christology, right?
You can't have, if God is that way, you can't have a meeting with a person.
And so that was the accusation, the incorrect accusations.
So yeah.
And if I recall correctly, Nistorius's solution to this problem, because this was his view,
the story of the solution to this problem.
is to say that the divine Christ is joined to the man Jesus by good will, right?
Is it was the Jew?
Evdo, you know, Evdo Keev, yeah, by good will, they're
conjoined by good will. So you have two persons who are conjoined and it's made
necessary for him to say this because he has this sense that God does not have a
body in this ancient sense of having a body. Right. Yeah. Right. So,
You
the way this ends up getting
resolved, surrounds, and now
we're going to use some fancy
Greek and Latin words. Okay,
everybody's not. We haven't
lost everybody. We still like
maybe five or six people listening
still. Yeah. Is there anybody
still hanging with us? This
should take care of it. Yeah.
And that's this phrase in Greek
any questions.
which both trades lay roughly two sort of lordly man.
Lordly man, yeah.
That phrase, and its original use was heretical.
Right, right.
Cause it came from a Paulin areas, right?
And so the a Paulin areas had a view
where the way you get one person for Christ
is that he sort of has some human
some human
aspects and then some divine aspects and when you put them all together you get one person. Yeah, or I'd the way about often heard it described is that you swap out his human soul or mind
for the divine logos and and if I recall correctly it was this
particular problem actually that was what inspired St. Gregory the theologian to say
What is not assumed is not saved in other words if there's any part of human nature that any elements of human nature that that the son of God
There's none of us.
in the incarnation, then that we can't be saved, right?
So if he doesn't have a human mind,
then our minds can't be saved and we're in big trouble.
Yeah, yeah, so you get sort of human parts,
God parts, stick them together,
and you have the Apollonarian Christ.
Right, yeah.
And so that obviously is wrong.
Right.
And St. Cyril of Alexandria,
when he was arguing against an historian,
was accused of at certain times of being in a party.
because he was insisted that there's just one person.
And so they said, oh, well, you must be in a pollinary.
And then you know, have pizzas if you say there's just one.
Right.
One subject.
And so he in rejecting that charge sort of condemned that term.
Nonetheless, that term got resurrected by St. Mark the Ascetic.
Right.
Or St. Mark the monk.
Yeah.
It's a ascetic, not aesthetic.
Yes, sir.
that he was just really good looking. Or an excellent dresser. Yeah, he was probably a terrible
dresser being a monk. Yeah, but he took this term and redefined it and reused it. Yeah. And he
used it to talk about Christ's body apart from the incarnation. Yeah, or before the incarnation, maybe.
Right. Well, both. Time. Time. Right? You know. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah.
outside of time. So yeah before gets tricky. Anyway, so yeah, to talk about to talk
about the divine person Christ who pre-existent. Yeah, yeah. So in this case then
you know that phrase Lordly Man, Lord obviously hearkening back to the Old
Testament reference to God to Yahweh. Right. The Lordly Man there is by way of
analogy because we're talking about
as much as he's not man. Yeah, exactly before he becomes man even. And apart, you know, whatever.
So it's not that there is this man, this lordly man who then joins with the human man,
right, right? Right. But to say that the divine person, the Son of God, the logos,
right, the word of God, had a body in this ancient sense, right?
right, meaning he had a will he has
energy, right? And this is this
understanding then becomes the source
of some of the later ecumenical
councils where we'll say that Christ
has two wills, divine will and a
human will, two energies, divine
energy, human energy, right? Because
he has these capacities, all right,
he has not cut off from creation
in his divinity. Yeah. Before,
before the
incarnation. Yeah. Yeah. All right. Well, before we go to our next break, we have another call that is
come in. And this is Greg, who is calling from Texas. So Greg, are you there? I am. Good evening.
All right. Well, good evening. And welcome to the Lord of Spirits podcast. Greg, what is your
your question or your comment.
I'm also engaged on your Facebook group.
I cannot thank you enough for the research and effort and everything you're putting out there is tremendously helpful to me who is not at all orthodox and not at all of an orthodox background.
I come from charismatic background, etc. So this is mind blowing to me and I love it. Thank you. Thank you. Thank you.
to me and I love it. Thank you. Thank you. Thank you.
Well, welcome. My question.
question. Let's call it the God body. What kind of God body do the fallen sons of God have?
And my question is specifically with an eye to the New Testament, I think it's a New Testament
idea, that the spawn of the fallen sons of God, you know, the spawn of the Necklim after they've
died, etc., etc. The demons are the unplanned spirits that are floating.
around, they seem to need or they seem to look for a physical body to inhabit. So that's
why I'm trying to get some more knowledge around what did they have, when they die, what
like what kind of body do they have, and why is there that need for them to quote unquote,
find a human body or a physical body to inhabit.
yeah we can't get away from giants father
who would want to write right
would walk to. Yeah, people get excited when you talk about giant. Yes. Yeah.
It's a great little giant episode once a week.
So literally listen to it religiously. Yeah.
So we're going to we're going to talk a little bit more about exactly what a
new gelica body is next time. But in terms of your question,
We talked about the five-ish right-fall.
of angelic beings, the angelic beings proper who fell still have an angelic body, though
its their fall has changed it in certain ways.
So that's what we'll be talking about more next time.
But the Nephilim, the giants who die, those are the spirits of dead folks, so they don't
have bodies currently.
their body went into the ground and decomposed.
And that's why those are the spirits who will possess humans, will indwell idols,
intempels, and are active.
They don't have a body, strictly speaking right now, and therefore can't really interact
outside of that.
Now, their bodies will be resurrected along with everybody else's on the last day, and
they'll go to there.
final condemnation. But we'll be talking about the bodily resurrection more next time too.
Yeah. Yeah. So does that help Greg? That helps tremendously. Thank you very, very much
for others. Again, keep up the great work. Thanks for calling in. All right. Well,
that wraps up the second part of our episode this evening. We're going to go ahead and go to
break. And when we get back, we're going to actually talk about the way that the Old Testament
talks about God's body. So let's go to break. Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen
even do you
young will be back in a moment to take your calls on the second half of the Lord of Spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF radio.
or Theroxie Live. I am pleased to announce today the release of my first book for Ancient
Faith Publishing, titled, Toolkit for Spiritual Growth, a practical guide to prayer fasting
and almsgiving. It seeks to provide a guide to the three basic and primary disciplines
of Orthodox spirituality. Through these disciplines, Christ opened for us a path that frees us from
the disordered way of life, has become normal for many, even though their hearts and minds
tell them otherwise. Please join me in exploring the three-legged stool.
of Orthodox spiritual practice, prayer, fasting,
nomsgiving, books now available at store.ancientfaith.com.
And the title once again is Toolkit for Spiritual Grove.
I look forward to sharing it with you.
God bless.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits,
the Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen
DeYoung.
If you have a question, call now at 855-237-238
four six. That's 855 AF radio.
Welcome to the third half of the Lord of Spirits here on Thursday,
January 14th of 2021. We're glad to be with you. All right, we've just been
bending your minds and definitely mine. I'm sure Father Stevens had this stuff
well in hand for years now, about talking about the body of God. And, you know, in the
The third part of the show, we want to...
specifically about some of the ways that the Old Testament shows that God does indeed have a body, right?
So, you know, let's talk about some of those. We have a few examples. There's actually piles of examples that we could give,
but we just selected a few that kind of show that God is interacting bodily with his creation with mankind.
And perhaps the most common kind of thing that we see, for instance in Genesis.
chapter 15 when it says the word of Yahweh came to Abraham in a vision or as it often gets translated
as the word of the Lord came to Abraham in a vision. So like he's seeing something, right? That's
a physical experience, right? That's actually a material experience, right? That's actually the
episode where he first receives the promises. Yeah. Right. So what's presented there is not that,
you know there was there was a movie with um
was it was it was it was an F. Marie Abraham I think maybe there was some Bible movie where he played Abraham I think it was him and you know he went out sort of looked at the desert outside of the CGI or and
there was sort of this voice on the wind that came and you know spoke to him and that was the word of the Lord coming to him. Right.
But it actually says the word of Yahweh appeared to him
In a vision and told him these things yeah, yeah
Yeah, there wasn't a. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. All right. We've got some more. Another one having to do with visions, right? So this is from
First Samuel or first kingdoms, I always get this mixed up chapter 3 verses 1 through 21.
The word of Yahweh was rare. There were not many visions. Samuel did not yet know Yahweh.
For the word of Yahweh had not revealed Himself to him.
and this is the part that really gets me.
Yahweh came and stood, calling as at other times.
He stood next to him.
Right, so yeah, so we're told there's this poverty
of the word of Yahweh and that doesn't mean like,
oh, there aren't prophets, right?
No, it's community anything.
We're told there's not many visions.
Yeah, meaning nobody's seen him in a long time.
He hasn't appeared to anyone in a long time.
Right.
and we're told that the reasons.
Samuel didn't know Yahweh the God of Israel yet,
is that he hadn't revealed himself to him.
Yeah.
And then there's this whole episode
where he calls out to him at night.
And Samuel keeps thinking it's Eli,
the priest calling him.
So he keeps running over and being like,
hey, what do you want?
Eli's like, I shouldn't call you,
go back to bed, kid.
Right. Right.
And this happens like three times.
And then finally Eli says,
Well, hey, maybe it's the Lord.
right? So next time, just ask him what he wants. And so that's when we get this, that, that,
you know, we come, the word of Yahweh comes and stands next to his bed and calls out to him
the way he had the other time. So this isn't again a disembodied voice. Right. Right. And then another
one, and this is very not disembodied. This is quite embodied. Jeremiah chapter one, verses 4-9,
And the word of Yahweh came to me and here we...
go, Yahweh stretched it his hand and touched my mouth. Yeah, stretched it his hand and touched
his mouth, you know, making him a prophet, right, giving him the words to say. But again,
he touches him. It's not a metaphor. Like it's an actual experience that he is having. And
then another one, this is probably one of the most famous and let's explicate this one a little
but that encounter at the oak of Mamra, right?
Where, where, yo.
way comes to Abraham and shows up as, you know, there's three men that show up and
talk to Abraham. So what's going on there? Yeah. One is identified as Yahweh. Right.
One of the men. The other two are angels. Yes. Right. And because we read, we read the
Bible and bits and pieces and individual stories, we don't necessarily get this connection
that this encounter at the oak
of of mammary, the hospitality of Abraham happens immediately before the whole
episode surrounding Sodom and Gomorrah. Yes, right. So the angels go down. Yeah. Right. So,
so Yahweh, these two angels come and Abraham has Sarah go and make them a bunch of food.
They lay out a spread and they sit and eat and converse.
Yeah.
And then we're told...
that Yahweh sends the two angels down to Sodom to get lot.
And he stays and talks to Abraham.
So again, this is not a disembodied voice.
There's someone staying there to talk to.
And conversing with Abraham.
And then as that unfolds, we get these two episodes.
And you can read these.
The first one where...
Yahweh talks to Yahweh. Right. Right. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. And then, um,
where he says, it says, you know, until the Yahweh said,
shall I hide from Abraham, what I am about to do, seeing that Abraham
shall surely become a great and mighty nation. And all of the nations of
the earth shall be blessed in him. But I have chosen him that he may
command his children and his household after him to keep the way of
Yahweh by doing
righteousness and justice so that Yahweh may bring to Abraham what he has promised him.
Right. So, which Abraham's over years. Right. So, Yahweh is standing there talking to him,
and then Yahweh talks to Yahweh. Right. Right. About him. Right. And then, even more tellingly, once
This lot is simply out of the way.
That's in Genesis 18, verses 17 through 19.
been in chapter 19 verse 24 after a lot is safely out of the city, which will then Yahweh
rain down fire on Sodom and Gomorrah from Yahweh from heaven.
Right.
Which, still standing on earth, calls down fire from Yahweh and heaven.
Which, underlines, by the way, and we haven't spent a lot of time on this, but underlines by
the way that the idea that God is...
a single unitarian monotheistic God is not a thing.
It's not a thing in the Old Testament.
Because here you've got Yahweh talking to Yahweh,
Yahweh calling down fire from Yahweh in heaven.
Like clearly at least there's two,
at the very least there's two, right?
You know, yeah.
Right, right.
And then okay, and then yeah, go ahead, go ahead.
Well, I was just gonna get that guy who gets pointed out
very clearly in over the
course of a few verses and Exodus, which I think you are about to read.
Right. Right. Exactly. So Exodus chapter 33, you know, Moses speaks to God,
face to face as a man speaks to his friend, I love that. And then later, God says,
no one can see my face and live. I mean, so like, well, which is it? God, you know,
can you speak to Moses face to face or can you not see your face? Obviously,
there is the face of God that Moses is talking to. And then there is another
other person.
whose face that no one can see and live.
Right. And these are, when you say later,
this is 12 verses later.
Yeah. Right. Right.
It's the same passage. Yeah.
12 verses later.
Yeah. You've been talking to be face to face.
You can't see my face and live.
Right.
Um, over the course of those two verses.
So, and as you said, there's
a hundred or more more examples we could give.
Right.
uh it very
the oldest part of just the old
Testament. And this kind of
gets summed up by St. John at
the end of the prologue to his
gospel. Yes, yes, where John
118, he says, no one has seen
God at any time. But the unique
God who is in the bosom of the
father has made him know. And
when St. John says that, he's
not like retconning the Old
Testament, right? He's not
saying, oh, hey, you know,
where you thought that.
That was God appearing to people or they saw God.
That never happened.
Right?
That's what he's saying.
He's saying the opposite.
He's saying the person that they saw, the person who they saw is the logos who I've
been talking about in this prologue.
Yes.
In the beginning.
That's the logos.
Yeah, and the logos was God.
That second Yahweh, the one who was standing there talking to Abraham, the one who Moses
talk to face to face.
the one who touched Jeremiah, the one who stood next to Samuel.
That's the word of Yahweh, as it said, in Samuel and in Genesis.
That's the logos.
Yeah. And we have, we actually have a very relevant question
specifically about this.
So Scott is calling from Alabama.
Scott, can you hear me?
I can't father. Thank you for taking my call.
Yeah, sure. So Scott, you have a question that's pretty much about what we were just talking about, right?
Well, I was worried you wouldn't take my call because this sort of is the answer I think for my question.
So long time listener, first time caller. Love the show. Yay.
As you're speaking of this and giving the examples from Jeremiah talks about the word,
but then you're talking about Yahweh, you're talking about imprevious.
episodes or maybe in some of your blogs you've talked about, the Lord, I guess Yahweh,
hiding his face or you can only see my backside, as he says to Moses, you've said before,
this is actually God's son that people are experiencing directly and having this direct relationship
with and so in this this episode I really was seeking some clarity on like who are we interacting
with we mutually in the Old Testament as we read, who are we interacting with and putting
ourselves in the mind of, are we interacting with God the Father? Are we interacting with
God the Son? I've never heard God the Son referred to as Yahweh. The We are wise would like
you to also talk about the Holy Spirit as you talk about the body.
Leave nothing out.
Hey everybody.
It's like the old time people gathered around their radio.
This is great.
We are absolutely.
You should see the kids.
They're actually bored.
But that's okay.
Oh, you'll understand this later, kids,
and you're going to love it.
Yeah, maybe.
Yeah, maybe not when you're teenagers
when you're teenagers, you roll your eyes.
But then you'll get older again, and then you'll dig.
That's right.
Yeah, go ahead, father.
Tackle this massive, trilogical question
and then he's back.
Yeah, and it's not to get. Let's just add some more
heresies people get it.
Gives me up.
So, so yeah, we're talking about, we're talking about as you
mentioned, you know, as we were already saying that this is,
this is God the Son, this is the logos who we see in the
in the Old Testament. So Yahweh is treated by the church, not
is a person.
personal name, but as a title.
And here's what that means.
Right.
Yahweh is not the name of one of the three persons
of the Trinity.
Right.
It's not the personal name of the Father
or the personal name of the Son
or the personal name of the Spirit.
Yahweh, I don't know how,
before I wanna go down this rabbit tail,
getting granular with Hebrew grammar.
But the word Yahweh is a form of the verb to be.
that in Hebrew, it's in what's called the Hifilbinyan, which means basically that it's causative.
So it literally means the one who causes things to be, you who causes things to be.
Or the create that we're not.
The creator.
Yeah, the idea of creation, that things are not and then he causes them to be, to exist.
Right?
And this is important in understanding a lot of places, especially the prophets in the Old Testament,
Where?
He will say, then you will know that I am Yahweh.
Right?
And it's like, well, they've known your name for a while.
Right.
But what he's saying is, for example, Israel will be destroyed and be bones in a valley.
But when I bring, breathe new life into those bones and bring them back to life, then you
will know that I am Yahweh.
As you will know that I am the one who causes things to be.
because only he could do that.
Right.
And so what that means is this is,
say, Dean, this is the area of Fugette tells us
that the titles of God, the names of God are his energies.
This is one of the powers, obviously, as the creator
that is possessed by all three persons.
So we could talk about Yahweh, the Father, Yahweh,
the Son, Yahweh, the Spirit,
or the Spirit of Yahweh, the Word of Yahweh.
way.
that's a perfectly appropriate way of speaking.
And we actually say it's hidden in our English translation,
some of which are extraordinarily bad.
But at the end of every vesper service in the dismissal,
we say the name Yollet and identify prices.
It depends on how it's translated.
We're both in Enochian, so most of our texts
have Christ our God, the existing one.
have Christ our God the existing one.
Yeah, and in Greek it's on, which is the Greek translation of, well sort of, of Yahweh, right?
But I've also heard it as Christ our God, He who is, you know, but it's really.
He who is Christ our God, sometimes which really confuses it, right?
But we're saying that, David, we're saying that's who Christ is.
We're saying Christ is Yahweh and that blessing at the end of every best per service.
Oh, uh.
So that's that but in terms of
and this is a good clarification to
it terms of the spirit and the father with bodies.
We're not saying that Christ has a body in this ancient sense
and the father and the spirit don't.
Right? We're not saying the father and the spirit
don't interact with the creation.
Right? God the father is not the God of the philosophers.
Right.
then we've got Christ as an intermediary.
They all do.
Right, and Genesis, you've got, for instance, a spirit of God hovering over the face of the water.
That's a movement, right?
That's a bodily action.
Right.
And one of the things that unites the three persons of the Holy Trinity is that they have one energy.
right so that they're united in these things.
So, and we'll be talking more particularly next time about the incarnation and the way in which Christ obviously,
because he also has human nature and a human body, how that then is different than the other two persons.
But it's not a case that Christ interacts with the creation and the other two persons don't,
or that they only do it through Christ, because we clearly see that's not the case in the scriptures.
So that makes sense Scott and Mrs Scott.
Sorry.
Scott and Megan.
Yeah.
Thanks.
Scott and Megan.
Okay.
It does.
It helps.
And I guess I hope you hear.
More clarity on this because God the father in my teaching.
What I've been taught has always been the originate creator and and maybe incorrectly.
I've been taught that he creates any...
and the world through Christ and through the Holy Spirit has metaphorically to arm.
So any further correction on that, I would love to hear in now and future episodes.
Yeah, well like Father said, they have one energy.
So it's not like God the Father operates independently of the Son and Spirit.
You know or or sort of uses them you know
right. Yeah. That that that
language is the through language
from and through and to and.
And yeah, it will get into that
in a future day. Yeah.
Because that could be a
topic in itself. The one state
Paul uses those prepositions
against that gets granular,
but we will get to that. Yeah.
All right. Well, thank you very
much, Scott and Megan for calling
in from Alabama. Great to hear
from you. All right.
We're gonna try to wrap this up with
some of my favorite stuff.
Yeah, we're going to talk about a little bit about paganism,
and also about worship in particular,
and how a lot of this plays out there as well.
So we've already established that St. John in John 1 is not talking about multiple gods.
He's talking about the one God Yahweh, you know, Yahweh the Father and Yahweh.
way the sun, right? That's what's going on there in the prologue, right? So how then, how
is this different from the way, and you know, we kind of touched on this a little bit when
I think it was Greg called in talking about giants, but how then is this different from
the way that pagans interacted with their gods? What kind of bodies do their gods have, right?
Like how does that work?
Yeah, just to take a little bit of the heat and hate mail off myself.
Father Andrew did just say that pagan worship is his favorite thing
What one of my one of my favorite topics?
Well, I am I am suspicious now because I am taking out I just just start a master of arts program and language and literature
Which I'm particularly looking at ancient pagan myths. So there we are. So yeah, who knows?
So, yeah, so when we're talking about pagan gods, ancient pagans believe that any given
god had a whole bunch of bodies.
And you can come at this from a couple of ways.
One of them is really granular and I'm not going to get into right now, maybe in a blog
post at some point.
And that's types of bodies that they believed their gods had.
Right. But for now, we're
about multiplicity in terms of one God having a whole bunch of bodies. Yeah. And which is totally a
thing in the ancient world people. Right. So, um, and this happens primarily through what we call
idolatry. This is an important part of how idolatry worked as a way of localizing a God. Right. Right.
But one God could be localized in a whole bunch of
of different places at the same time. Right. Right. And so as an example, one of the examples I use
is you look at Ray in Egypt, the sun god. Who, you know, is called raw in most
English sources. But I did look this up and it is Ray or re. I've seen it. I've seen it
in some languages that's re as well, which is interesting. Yeah. It's it's it's our e with like an
Umlao over it so I do love
Yeah. So in fact, it's probably not as
whom loud when it's over in E, but anyway, we digress.
Yeah.
The, uh, so for the Egyptians, the sun in the sky, right?
Like the actual solar disk in the sky is one of raised bodies.
But at some periods of Egyptian history,
in some sense the Pharaoh.
is Ray on Earth. And at the same time they've got temples to
Ray in different places that have statues that are bodies of Ray.
And sometimes these will get the names of a particular place,
this is why it's referred to as localization sort of attached to them.
And they'll look at these little different, but when someone went to
you can
communicate with or commune with or worship or sacrifice to
Rey in a particular temple. The sun didn't disappear out of
the sky. Pharaoh didn't cease to exist. Like this wasn't, it
wasn't that Rey was running around. It's sort of like, oh man,
I got to get over to the thieves. Right. Yeah, sacrifice it
12. I thought how they viewed it. They viewed it as having
multiple bites because again bodies it's not talking
about the physicality, it's talking about these points of communication, communion, interaction
with the world and with people. So there's tons of them. And because it's the peculiar form,
as we've talked about before on the show, that idolatry takes, this is human initiative,
going and creating a body for the God so that the human can interact.
with the God and communicate with the God and get the God to do what they want in
that particular place to sort of draw them down and trap the God.
Yes, a God trap.
Put them in that it's a death trap, a suicide rap, right?
Let me put them in the statue now they're localized.
So as we talked about also when you come
to the Torah and the Torah for Bids idolatry,
it's aimed at forbidding not just making a statue.
This is how many of our Protestant friends
interpret it is that it's idolatry is just
making a picture, right, or making a statue.
No, no, it's using the image in a particular way
to try to trap and provide a body for your God.
Right, and manipulate the God and exert power
control over the spirit that you're.
that you're worshiping.
Right.
And so what we see, that's why what we see in response
in the Torah is not just, hey, don't make statues,
except for the few I tell you to make on the Ark
of the Covenant and that kind of thing,
but other than that, don't make any.
Yeah, by the way.
Right.
It's not that it's what it's coupled with is,
you're only going to come and worship Yahweh
in one place.
That's going to be the tabernacle
and then with...
temple, there's just going to be this one place where you come to interact with Yahweh,
to commune with Yahweh, to hear from Him. And it's going to be the place it's referred
to all through the Torah as the place I will choose that God is going to choose that place.
Actually, first, it's the top of Mount Sinai. Right? Right. That it's the Babardaggle. But
it's the place where God chooses to come and be present. That's the place where God's
body is the place.
where he chooses to come and make himself present.
And that's the place where all of the Israelites have to come
to hear from him, to communicate with him,
to interact with him, to sacrifice him, to worship him.
Yeah, and if you think about that,
just even in a psychological way,
like there is a difference between
if you can summon someone to you
versus you have to go to them, right?
And idolatry is really about,
because you could set up your idolatrous time.
anywhere you like, you can, and the point is you're summing the God to you, but God, Yahweh is
saying, no, no, no, no, no, I've picked a place you come to me, right? And this helps to underline
what kind of God he is. He's not like, you know, and I mean, this is one of our frequent themes,
you know, who among the gods is like unto the old Lord, right? You know, like answer none.
And the fact that one place is chosen by him, and it's only one place, I mean,
such that it becomes a kind of a
polemic later against the Samaritan's,
like you guys are worshiping on the wrong mountain,
you know, all right?
You know, like that,
this is so important because it
underlines who God is that you have to go to Him, right?
Right. And this is,
this is why there was so much
appropriation towards the Samaritans because of that.
Yeah. It wasn't just like,
oh, hey, you guys are worshiping in the wrong place,
right? Yeah. Yeah. Yeah.
There, there it was. You guys are idolaters.
Look what you're doing.
right? That was idolatrous. That was, you know, heretical to go and build a temple there on Mount
Gharism and worship there. Yeah. Yeah. So and we see this connection between the body of God and the
temple in a bunch of places. One of the primary ones or at least one of the ones that I think of
of his primary because I wrote my dissertation
about the day of atonement.
Is the day of atonement?
Yeah.
because part of it that gets left out when we talk about the day of atonement
in our modern Christian world, we're almost always talking about the goats
because everybody wants to argue about atonement theories.
And so it's what's going on with the goats.
We miss sort of other key elements of the ritual.
A main one of which was the high priest, this was the one day a year
when he would go into the holy of Holies
where the Ark of the Covenant was.
before he did that, he would have to make a bunch of sacrifices for his own sins.
Then he could enter and as he entered, he was required to offer this huge amount of incense
to make this cloud of incense.
And the purpose of the cloud was to cover, and there's kind of a wordplay there,
because the word for cover is the same word as the word for atonement.
to cover.
the fact that Yahweh appeared there on that day.
And so if that smoke wasn't there to cover it,
he would see Yahweh and die.
Yep.
And so he did that, he had to offer the incense
so that he wouldn't see directly Yahweh when he appeared.
And then he would come in with the blood of the goat
that was Riyāweh and use it to purify
the Ark of the Cuff.
and it's covered so that, and then the rest of the tabernacle in later temple, so that God could continue to live in the midst of his people for another year without consuming them in fire.
And as I recall, the reason why this is done is because this is the day that God has chosen to make himself known.
It's not because doing this ritual makes God show up.
Right.
You're not doing the ritual to make God appear.
Because you can't do that.
That's the kind of God.
That's the day when God is going to appear in the temple.
He's going to appear in the Holy of Holies.
And so you have to do the ritual to make that safe.
Yeah.
And of course there's an interesting sort of modern analog to that.
It's not identical but as an analog which is, you know,
you know that we have the
the miracle of the Holy Fire that appears in the Church of the Holy Sepulchre on Holy Saturday.
Again, it's not that we've called him down, it's that this is the day, this is the appropriate day when...
And it's funny, like there's even that historical instance where the Holy Fire appeared,
even though the services were not allowed to be done at some point in history.
You know, it's still appeared and cracked one of the pillars nearby which I gather you can go see.
So, see, I've never seen it, but I've talked to people.
people who have, that God himself still chooses to appear.
Now, why don't they have to do a massive gigantic cloud of
incense, although I'm sure probably they do have some incense?
You know, in order to so so people don't see that happening,
it's okay to see it happening.
People see it happening.
Right. And that's because Christ's atonement has now has
now purified the world.
Right. He's done the covering.
And this is, you know, see the whole book of Hebrews.
Right.
Yeah right.
That's a lot of what what Hebrews is getting at. So it's now safe
To to approach God and you see you see it's the similar idea of
God's body and thrown in the temple and the visions the vision that Isaiah has what he called he's called to be a prophet
Where he sees him and thrown with the altar as his footstool. Yeah, here my lord send me. I love that bit and
And then Ezekiel sees a very similar thing, but then he sees...
got the all we have is chariot thrown in the temple, but then before the temple is destroyed, he leaves.
Right? That's what Ezekiel sees. And so when he leaves, the temple is destroyed.
And we'll probably get into this a little more in the next episode.
But as a semi-tease, the reason why we don't have just one place where we worship now
is
that any place where God's body is, say in a tabernacle, say on an altar, becomes a temple.
Yeah. Wow. Cool. Very cool. Yeah. Christ becomes the new temple. And, you know, yeah. And,
you know, and as the kind of the final tease, right, that I think would be helpful for next time
and two weeks is
So if the Son of God has a bodily existence apart from the incarnation, and then he also has a bodily existence by virtue of being human,
does that mean that Christ has two bodies?
Tune in next time, we'll talk about that.
But yeah, so you know before we close
Having gone through this bind bending experience now twice
me. For me, I wanted to just give some of my own impressions about this and then Father
Stephen, you can close us out. Yeah, I think one of the big takeaways for me, I mean, there's
two big takeaways. The first is the stuff we've just been talking about, which is how the
truth that God has bodily existence, the interact with the world that he has nexus, the potentialities,
you know, powers. What are
however you want to put it, that that is what he is what we're, whom we're interacting
with in worship. Like if he really was the God of the philosophers, then he wouldn't be
available. Like he wouldn't show up. He wouldn't reveal himself. He wouldn't do that,
right? And then connected to that, then my other big takeaway is how important it is that
we understand the biblical language about God's bodily
existence because if we don't, then we're not worshiping the God of Abraham, Isaac and Jacob.
We don't have a God who loves us. We don't have a God who cared enough to create us, right? The God
of the philosophers had to have not even an emissary if he's even aware of him, right? But this
kind of, you know, this demiors, this intermediary, right? And a number of heretics over time,
they accept that model and they identify Christ as being that.
intermediary, but he's not some lesser creator being that the unmoved mover was only kind of tangentially
connected to whatever. This is the God who loves us. This is the God who reaches out to us.
This is the God who touches the mouth of Jeremiah. This is the God who stands next to Samuel's bed.
We don't have to be embarrassed by that language. It's inscripture and it means something.
It may not mean exactly the same thing when I stand next to-
a bed, but that doesn't mean it didn't happen or that it's just some kind of metaphor.
It's not. Again, the scripture never says, you know, and Yahweh became present in a manner
like unto a man stands next to a bed. It doesn't even say that. Just that he stood next to the
bed, you know, or that he ate. I mean, how bodily can you get? How much more bodily can you
get? He ate with Abraham, right? And, you know, our, our February episodes are going to be
all about sacrificing worship everybody so hold onto your hats for those.
That's going to be really cool.
But it's astonishing, I know that I use that word a lot on this show, but it just really
is astonishing.
And it's okay to take this stuff seriously and not think that we're anthropomorphizing
God.
Again, remember, like we said at the beginning, it's the opposite.
We are theomorphized.
We are like God.
We're much smaller, lesser, corrupted, limited, imitations.
but we are like God, he's not like us, we're like him.
Right, we have to keep that in the right order.
So those are my big takeaways from this conversation, Father.
Yeah, so there's a place in the scriptures
where St. Paul talked to a bunch of those philosophers
we were talking about their God.
Yeah, the Euryopagus.
Yeah, I think you're vaguely familiar with that.
Yes, I'm a fan of the vagus.
one of my favorite things.
And when he speaks to them, he certainly repeatedly condemns idolatry.
But he also speaks to this philosophical notion of God that he's remote.
That the most high God has distanced himself and has now sort of gone.
and maybe we can content ourselves as much as we need with these idols and these.
these lesser spiritual beings.
But what St. Paul says to them in response to what they believe,
is that when God created all people,
the most high God,
the God of Israel created the whole world,
and he assigned to people there are a lot in places and times.
That he did this not,
well, first that he did it,
but also that he did this not
to push them away.
not because they were lesser than him
and he didn't think about them
or couldn't think about them
or didn't care about them.
Exactly the obvious.
He did this, St. Paul said,
so that they should seek God
and perhaps feel their way toward him and find him.
Yeah.
If he is actually not far from each one of us
for in him we live and move and have our being.
So he's telling them
This is a part
of the gospel, especially for these philosophers,
and how they're used to thinking about God.
That God not only knows you exist, right?
But he cares about you.
He wants you to seek him and he wants you to find him.
He's here with you, he's around you.
He's how you're taking your last breath and your next breath.
He's the one who's giving you life.
And not only for us.
into being but is maintaining your being.
And it's very easy for us in our sort of modern materialistic mindset, as we already talked
about, to fall into this kind of accidental agnosticism, where we don't doubt they got
exist, but he's off somewhere, at least most of the time.
And he's not here with us, he's not close to us, he doesn't care.
At least he doesn't care about the little stuff, maybe about the big stuff, maybe politics
for some.
he's involved but not with me in my life and the things I'm worried about and
paying my bills and all of these things. And the truth is that the God who created
the universe is the opposite of that. We're told by the Scriptures over and over
again that God has done all these things for us out of his love. He created us out
of his love. He created the cosmos out of his love. And he's done all of it so
that we would
seek after him and find him. We're told that if we seek it with our whole heart, we will find him.
And so that he can share his life, which is an eternal life with us in his kingdom that has no end.
And so this is something that should, it's not just, I know on our episode, we talked about the
saints. I talked about how we're never alone in terms of having the saints and the angels
around this and worshiping with us.
God's here too.
Christ is here.
with us too. The Holy Spirit is living within us, and it's not far off somewhere.
Well, that is our show for today. Thank you very much for listening, everybody.
If you didn't get a chance to call in during the live broadcast, we would love to hear from you,
either via email at Lordofspiritsatenthentfaith.com or you can message us at our Lord of Spirits podcast
Facebook page. We read everything but we
You can't respond to everything and we do save what you send for possible use and future
episodes.
Join us for our live broadcast on the second and fourth Thursdays of the month at 7 p.m.
Eastern 4 p.m. Pacific.
If you're on Facebook unlike me, like our Facebook page and join our Facebook discussion
group.
Leave reviews and ratings but most importantly share this show with a friend whom you know
is going to love it.
And finally be sure to go to ancientfaith.com, stroke support and help make sure we and
lots of other AFR.
podcast your stay on the air. Thank you very much and may God bless you always. We'll see you next time.
I'm Mimi Hogue and I'm Richard Barrett and this is the Byzantine chant podcast, a sacrifice of praise.
for him and the same.
When I bring, breathe new life into those bones and bring them back to life, then you will
know that I am Yahweh, because you will know that I am the one who causes things to be.
Because only he could do that, right?
Right.
And so, what that means is, this is, say, Dean, this is the area of Fugette tells us that
the titles of God, the names of God are his energies.
This is...
One of the powers obviously is the creator
That is is possessed by all three persons
So we could talk about Yahweh the Father Yahweh that's on Yahweh the Spirit or the Spirit of Yahweh the Word of Yahweh and
Yahweh
That's a perfectly appropriate way of speaking and we actually say it's hidden in our English
translation some of which are extraordinarily bad
But at the end of every Vesper
servant in the
missile, we say the name, you know, and identify Christ as y'all. It depends on how it's translated.
We're both an Edochians, so most of our texts have Christ our God, the existing one.
Yeah. And in Greek, it's it's all on, which is the Greek translation of, well sort of, of
of Yahweh, right?
But I've also heard it as Christ our God,
he who is, you know, or, but it's really he who is,
he who is Christ our God.
sometimes which really confuses it, right?
But we're saying that, Damon, we're saying that's who Christ is.
We're saying Christ is Yahweh and that blessing at the end of every best per service.
So that's that, but in terms of, and this is a good clarification too, in terms of the
Spirit and the Father with bodies, we're not saying that Christ has a body in this ancient
sense and the Father in the Spirit does.
right? We're not saying the father and the spirit don't interact with the creation, right?
The God the Father is not the God of the philosophers, right? And then we've got got Christ as an intermediary.
They all do. Right. I mean, in Genesis, you've got, for instance, a spirit of God hovering over the face of the water.
That's a very, you know, that's movement, right?
That's a bodily action.
Right. And one of the things that unites the three persons of the Holy Trinity is that
they have one energy. Right. So that they're united in these things. So, and we'll be talking
more particularly next time about the incarnation and the way in which Christ obviously, because
He also has human nature and a human body,
how that then is different than the other two persons.
But it's not a case that Christ interacts with the creation and the other two persons don't,
or that they only do it through Christ, because we clearly see that's not the case in the scriptures.
Does that make sense, Scott? And Mrs. Scott? Sorry.
Scott and Megan, yeah. Thank you.
Scott and Megan, okay.
It does, it helps. And I guess I hope to hear more.
clarity on this because God the Father in my teaching what I've been taught has
always been the originate to create to our and and maybe incorrectly I've
been taught that he creates any senses energy into the world through Christ and
through the Holy Spirit as you know metaphorically to arms. So any further
correction on that I would love to hear and now in future.
Yeah, well like yeah, well, like father said they have one energy. So it's not like God the father operates
independently of the sun and spirit
You know or sort of uses them
You know right, yeah, that that that language is the through language from and through and two and
Yeah, and we'll get into that in a future day
Yeah, because that's to be
the topic in and of itself.
The one state Paul uses those
prepositions against
that gets grand.
But we will get to that.
Yeah.
All right.
Well, thank you very much, Scott and Megan,
for calling in from Alabama.
Great to hear from you.
All right.
Let's move forward now.
And we're going to try to wrap this up
with some of my favorite stuff.
Yeah.
We're going to talk about a little bit
about paganism and also about worship in particular,
and how a lot of this kind of play
out there as well, right? So we've already established that St. John in John chapter 1 is not talking
about multiple gods. He's talking about the one God Yahweh, Yahweh the Father and Yahweh the
Son, right? That's what's going on there in the prologue, right? So how is this different from the way
and we kind of touched on this a little bit when I think it was Greg called in talking about giants
But
But how then is this different from the way that pagans interacted with their gods?
What kind of bodies do their gods have, right?
Like how does that work?
Yeah.
Just to take a little bit of the heat and hate mail off myself, Father Andrew did just
say that pagan worship is his favorite thing.
One of my favorite topics.
Topics.
Topics, yes, yes, yes.
Okay.
Yeah, well I am I am suspicious
Now because I am taking a I just just start a master of arts program and language literature, which I'm particularly looking at ancient pagan myths. So there we are. So who knows?
Yeah.
So, yeah, so when we're talking about pagan gods, ancient pagans believe that any given
God had a whole bunch of bodies. And you can come at this from a
a couple ways. One of them is really granular and I'm not going to get into right now, maybe
in a blog post at some point. And that's types of bodies that they believed their gods had.
But for now, we're going to talk about multiplicity in terms of one god having a whole bunch of
bodies. Which is totally a thing in the ancient world people.
So, this happens primarily.
through what we call idolatry. This is an important part of how idolatry worked as
a way of localizing a God. Right. Right. But one God could be localized in a
whole bunch of different places at the same time. Right. Right. And so as an
example, one of the examples I use is you look at Ray in Egypt, the sun God.
Whom, you know, is called raw.
in most places. But I did look this up and it is right or re I've seen it I've seen it
in some languages it's re as well which it's it's it's it's R E with like an umla
over it so I do love a little bit of them out yeah so it's probably not an
umla when it's over in E but anyway we digress. Yeah. So for the Egyptians the
sun in the sky.
right? Like the actual solar disk in the sky is one of Ray's bodies. But at some periods of
Egyptian history, in some sense, the Pharaoh is Ray on Earth. And at the same time, they've
We've got temples to ray in different places that have statues that are bodies of ray.
Right.
And sometimes these will get the names of a particular place,
this is what it's referred to as localization,
sort of attached to them.
And they'll look at this a little different.
But when someone went to communicate with or commune
with or worship or sacrifice to Rey in a particular temple,
the sun didn't disappear out of the sky,
ferro dincees to exist.
like this wasn't, it wasn't that Ray
was running around, it's sort of like, oh man, I got to get over to the
thieves mask.
Right.
Yeah.
It's not how they viewed it.
They viewed it as having multiple bites because again, bodies, it's not talking about
the physicality, it's talking about these points of communication, communion, interaction
with the world and with people.
Right.
So there's tons of them.
Because...
Because it's the peculiar form as we've talked about before on the show that idolatry takes,
right?
This is human initiative, going and creating a body for the God so that the human can
interact with the God and communicate with the God and get the God to do what they want
in that particular place to sort of draw them down and trap the God.
Yeah, it's a God trap.
and put them in that, it's a death trap, a suicide trap, right?
Let me put them in the statue now they're localized.
So as we talked about also when you come to the Torah
and the Torah for Bids idolatry,
it's aimed at forbidding not just making a statue.
This is how many of our Protestant friends interpret it
is that it's, idolatry is just making a picture, right?
We're making a stat.
you. No, no, it's using using the image in a particular way in a particular way to try to trap,
you know, and provide a body for your God. Right. And manipulate the God and exert power and
control over the spirit that you're that you're worshiping. Right. And so what we see, that's why
what we see in response in the Torah is not just, hey, don't make statues, except for the few I
tell you to make on the Ark of the Covenant and that kind of thing. But other than that, don't make it.
Yeah, by the way.
right. Right. It's not that. It's what it's coupled with is you're only going to come and worship
Yahweh in one place. That's going to be the tabernacle and then the temple. There's just going to be
this one place where you come to interact with Yahweh, to commune with Yahweh, to hear from Him.
And it's going to be the place it's referred to all through the Torah as the place I will choose.
Yeah, that God is
going to choose that place. Actually, first, it's the top of Mount Sinai. Right? Right.
That it's the Babar Dago. Right. But it's the place where God chooses to come and be present.
That's the place where God's body is. Is the place where He chooses to come and make
Himself present. And that's the place where all of the Israelites have to come to hear from Him,
to communicate with Him, to interact with Him, to sacrifice Him, to worship Him.
Yeah, and if you think about that, just even in a psychological way.
like there is a difference between if you can summon someone to you versus you have to go to them
right and idolatry is really about because you could set up your idolatry temple anywhere you like
you can see in the point that you're summoning the god to you but god Yahweh is saying no no no no
I've picked a place you come to me right and this helps to underline what kind of god he
He is. He's not like, you know, and I mean, this is one of our frequent themes, you know, who among the gods is like unto the old Lord, right?
You know, like answer none. And the fact that one place is chosen by him and it's only one place. I mean, such that it becomes a kind of a
a polemic later against the Samaritans, like you guys are worshiping on the wrong mountain,
you know?
Right?
You know, like this is so important because it underlines who God is that you have to go
to Him.
right? Right. Right. And this is this is why there was so much
appropriium towards the Samaritans because of that. Yeah. It
wasn't just like, Oh, Hey, you guys are worshipping in the wrong
place. Yeah, you digging in the wrong place. Yeah. Yeah.
There was you guys are idolaters. Look what you're doing. Right.
That was idolatrous. That was, you know, heretical, uh, to go
and build a temple there on Mount Garrism. Yeah. Uh, and and
worship there. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. So. And we see this connection
between the
body of God and the temple in a bunch of places. One of the primary ones or at least one of the ones
that I think of as primary because I wrote my dissertation about the day of atonement. Is the day of atonement?
Yeah. Because part of it that gets left out when we talk about the day of atonement
in our modern Christian world, we're almost always talking about the goats because everybody wants to
to argue about atonement theories.
Yeah.
And so it's what's going on with the goats.
We miss sort of.
other key elements of the ritual.
A main one of which was the high priest,
this was the one day a year when he would go
into the Holy of Holies where the Ark of the Covenant was.
Before he did that, he would have to
make a bunch of sacrifices for his own sins.
Then he could enter, and as he entered,
It was required to offer this huge...
of incense to make this cloud of incense.
And the purpose of the cloud was to cover,
and there's kind of a wordplay there,
because the word for cover is the same word
as the word for atonement.
Nice.
To cover the fact that Yahweh appeared there on that day.
And so if that smoke wasn't there to cover it,
he would see Yahweh and die.
Yep.
And so he did that.
He had to offer the incense.
so that he wouldn't see directly Yahweh when he appeared,
and then he would come in with the blood of the goat
that was for Yahweh and use it to purify the Ark of the Covenant
and it's cover so that, and then the rest of the tabernacle and later temple,
so that God could continue to live in the midst of his people for another year
without consuming them in fire.
right?
and their sins. Right. And as I recall, the reason why this has done is because this is the
day that God has chosen to make himself known, it's not because doing this ritual makes God show up.
Right. No, you don't. You're not. You're not doing the ritual to make God appear.
Because you can't do that. He's not that kind of God. That's the day when God is going to appear
in the temple. Yeah. He's going to appear in the Holy of Holy.
And so you have to do the ritual to make that safe.
Yeah. And of course there's an interesting sort of modern analog to that.
It's not identical, but as an analog, which is, you know, that we have the miracle of the Holy Fire
that appears in the Church of the Holy Sepulchre on Holy Saturday.
Again, it's not that we've called him down.
It's that this is the day, this is the appropriate day when you know
And it's funny, like there's even that historical instance where the Holy Fire appeared even though the services were not allowed to be done at some point in history.
You know, it's still appeared and cracked one of the pillars nearby which I gather you can go see. I've never seen it, but I've talked to people who have that God himself still chooses to appear.
Now why don't they have to do a massive gigantic cloud of incense? Although I'm sure probably they do have some incense.
you know in order to so so people don't see that happening it's okay to see it
happening people see it happening
And that's because Christ's atonement has now purified the world.
He's done the covering.
And this is, you know, see the whole book of Hebrews.
That's a lot of what Hebrews is getting at.
So it's now safe to approach God.
And you see this similar idea of God's body and thrown in the temple and the visions.
The vision that I...
what he called he's called to be a prophet. Yeah.
Where he sees him and thrown with the altar as his footstool.
Yeah, hear my Lord send me. I love that bit.
And then Ezekiel sees a very simpler thing.
But then he sees God.
Yahweh had his chariot thrown in the temple.
But then before the temple is destroyed, he leaves.
Right? That's what Ezekiel sees.
And so when he leaves, the temple is destroyed.
And we'll probably get into this a little more.
or in the next episode.
But as a semi-tees, the reason why we don't have
just one place where we worship now is that any place
where God's body is, say in a tabernacle, say on an altar,
becomes a temple.
Yeah
Wow cool
Very cool. Yeah, Christ becomes the new temple and you know, yeah, and you know and as the kind of the final tease
Right that I think would be helpful for for next time in two weeks is
So if the Son of God has a bodily existence apart from the incarnation and then he also has a
bodily existence by virtue of being human
Does that mean that Christ has two bodies?
Thank you.
Tune in next time. We'll talk about that.
But yeah, so you know before we close
Having gone through this bind bend to experience now twice me for me
I wanted to you know just give some of my own impressions about this and then and then father Steven you can you can close us out
Yeah, I think one of the big takeaways for me. I mean there's two big takeaways
The first is the stuff we've just been...
talking about, which is how the truth that God has bodily existence, the interaction of the world,
that he has a nexus of potentiality, powers, however you want to put it, that that is what we're
interacting with in worship. Like if he really was the God of the philosophers, then he wouldn't
and be a-
like he wouldn't show up, he wouldn't reveal himself, he wouldn't do that, right?
And then connected to that, then my other big takeaway is how important it is that we understand the biblical language about God's bodily existence,
because if we don't, then we're not worshipping the God of Abraham, Isaac and Jacob.
We don't have a God who loves us.
We don't have a God who cared enough to create us, right?
The God of the philosophers had to have...
not even an emissary if he's even aware of him, right?
But this kind of, you know, this demiors,
this intermediary, right?
And a number of heretics over time,
they accept that model
and they identify Christ as being that intermediary, you know?
But he's not, he's not some lesser creator being
that the unmoved mover, you know,
was only kind of tangentially connected to whatever.
You know, this is the God who loves us.
This is the God who reaches out to us.
This is a God who touches.
the mouth of Jeremiah. You know, this is the guy who stands next to Samuel's bed, right?
We don't have to be embarrassed by that language. It's in Scripture and it means something. It may
not mean exactly the same thing when I stand next to a bed, but that doesn't mean it didn't happen
or that it's just some kind of metaphor. It's not. Again, the Scripture never says, you know,
and Yahweh became present in a manner like unto a man stands next to a bed. It doesn't even say that.
Just to leave.
He stood next to the bed, you know, or that he ate.
I mean, how bodily can you get?
How much more bodily can you get?
He ate with Abraham, right?
And, you know, our February episodes are gonna be all
about sacrificing worship everybody.
So, hold onto your hats for those.
That's gonna be really cool.
But I mean, it's just, I don't know, it's astonishing.
I know that I use that word a lot on this show,
but it just really is astonishing.
And it's okay to take this stuff seriously
and not think that we're anthropomorphizing God.
We're not. Again, remember like,
we start at the beginning, it's the opposite.
We are theomorphized.
We are like God.
We're much smaller, lesser, corrupted, limited,
imitations, but we are like God.
He's not like us.
We're like Him.
Right, we have to keep that in the right order.
So those are my big takeaways from this conversation, Father.
Yeah, so there's a place in this group.
where St. Paul talked to a bunch of those philosophers
we were talking about their God.
Yeah, the Euryopagus.
Yeah, I think you're vaguely familiar with that.
Yes, I'm a fan of Euryopagus.
One of my favorite things.
And when he speaks to them,
he certainly repeatedly condemns idolatry.
but he also speaks to this.
philosophical notion of God that he's remote, that the most high God has distanced himself and
has now gone and maybe we can content ourselves as much as we need with these idols and these
these lesser spiritual beings. But let's say Paul says to them in response to what they believe,
is that when when God created all people and he the most high God,
God.
God, with the God of Israel, create.
He did the whole world and he assigned to people
there are a lot in places and times.
That he did this, not, well, first that he did it,
but also that he did this, not to push them away,
not because they were lesser than him
and he didn't think about them
or couldn't think about them
or didn't care about them.
Exactly the obvious.
He did this, St. Paul said,
so that they should seek God
and perhaps feel their way toward him and find him.
Yeah.
if he is actually not far from each one of us,
for in him we live and move and have our be in.
So he's telling them
this is a part of the gospel,
especially for these philosophers,
and how they're used to thinking about God.
Right? That God not only knows you exist, right?
But he cares about you.
He wants you to...
seek him and he wants you to find him. He's here with you. He's around you. He's how you're taking
your last breath and your next breath. He's the one who's giving you life and not only brought you
into being but is maintaining your being. And it's very easy for us in our sort of modern materialistic
mindset as we already talked about to fall into this kind of accidental agnosticism where we don't
don't doubt they had exist.
he's off somewhere, at least most of the time.
Yeah.
And he's not here with us, he's not close to us, he doesn't care.
At least he doesn't care about the little stuff, maybe about the big stuff,
maybe politics or something, he's involved.
But, but, but, with me in my life and the things I'm worried about and paying my bills and
and all of these things.
And the truth is that the God who created the universe is the opposite of that.
We're told by the scriptures over and over again that God has done all these things for us out of his love.
He created us out of his love. He created the cosmos out of his love.
And he's done all of it so that we would seek after him and find him.
We're told that if we seek it with our whole heart, we will find him.
And so that he can share his life, which is an eternal life with us in his kingdom that has no end.
Yeah, and so
So this is something that should, it's not just, I know on our episode where we talked
about the saints, I talked about how we're never alone in terms of having the saints and
the angels around us and worshipping with us.
God's here too.
Christ is here with us too.
The Holy Spirit is living within us and it's not far off somewhere.
Amen.
Well, that is our show for today.
Thank you very much for listening everybody.
you didn't get it.
chance to call in during the live broadcast. We would love to hear from you either via email
at Lordofspiritsatenthentfaith.com or you can message us at our Lordofspirits Podcast Facebook
page. We read everything but we can't respond to everything and we do save what you send
for possible use and future episodes. Join us for our live broadcast on the second and fourth
Thursdays of the month at 7 p.m. Eastern 4 p.m. Pacific. If you're on Facebook unlike me,
like our Facebook page.
and join our Facebook discussion group.
Leave reviews and ratings, but most importantly,
share this show with a friend whom you know is going to love it.
And finally, be sure to go to www.engshafethe.com,
Stroke Support, and help make sure we and lots of other AFR
podcasters stay on the air.
Thank you very much, and may God bless you always.
We'll see you next time.
I'm Mimi Hogue and I'm Richard Barrett and this is the Byzantine chant podcast, a sacrifice
of praise.
Singing a cry, a shouting the triumphant hymn and a say.