He will be a staff for the righteous, with which for them to stand and not to fall,
and he will be the light of the nations and the hope of those whose hearts are troubled.
All who dwell on the earth will fall down and worship him,
and they will praise and bless and celebrate with song the Lord of Spirits,
1st denoc, chapter 48, verses 4 through 5.
The modern world doesn't acknowledge but is nevertheless haunted by spirits, angels, demons, and saints.
In our time
many year into break free of the prison of a flat secular materialism to see and to know reality
as it truly is. What is this spiritual reality like? How do we engage with it well? How do we permeate
everyday life with spiritual presence? Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew Stephen
Damick and Father Stephen De Young host this live Colin show focused on enchantment in creation.
The union of the scene and unseen as made by God.
and experienced by mankind throughout history.
Welcome to the Lord of Spirits.
Welcome back to the Lord of Spirits podcast, Mary Christmas.
I'm Father Andrew Stephen Damick on the edge
of Pennsylvania Dutch country in Emmaus, Pennsylvania.
And with me is my co-host, Father Stephen D. Young,
broadcasting from the middle of Keijen country
in Lafayette, Louisiana.
And this is a pre-recorded episode of the podcast.
So even-
even though you're going to hear the voice of Steve telling you how to call in.
If you call during this episode, you're not going to get anybody.
Everybody's either having some kind of Christmas Eve dinner or at church or something like that.
So yeah, this is a pre-recorded episode, but we have tried to incorporate some of your pre-recorded
messages that you sent us.
So it's a little bit different, but this is going to be a great episode, and I think you're
going to enjoy this one.
This is our Christmas.
So in response to a Judean uprising, the Romans leveled Jerusalem and destroyed the temple in the year 70,
later renaming the city to Aliyah, Kapitalina, and refusing reentry by any Jews.
But less well known, however, during this period of Judean revolt from 8066 to 73,
is that the Romans also invaded Galilee in 8067.
During the first century the Romans level
and rebuilt a number of places in the Holy Land.
This was the Roman way of letting a local populist know that their rule and culture would dominate
and brook no competition.
A paradoxical benefit of this campaign of leveling and burying of settlements is that many places
have been preserved and are now being excavated by archaeologists.
And among those places are synagogues in the area of Galilee, where Jesus Christ was raised
and where He Himself would have entered for prayer and teaching.
So if we met...
from moment, Jesus, entering into one of those Galilean synagogues. We can see in our minds
the stone construction details like the names of donors and important community members
inscribed in mosaics, but there's something else in the mosaics that have been unearthed in our time
that may surprise and even shock you. When Christ entered to pray and even to preach in nearly any
Galilean synagogue in the first century.
Quite...
prominently displayed in Mosaic would have been an image of the twelve signs of the zodiac.
What can this possibly mean? We're ancient Judeans synchrotistically incorporating
pagan astrology into their synagogues? And if so, why didn't Jesus protest this?
Astrology means stars, and of course we all know that Christmas famously involves a star,
the star of Bethlehem. For this very special Christmas episode of the Lord of Spirits,
we're going to be talking a strong
So, Father Stephen, why would First Century Jews put Zodiac imagery in their synagogue?
What's that about?
Well, it turns out Jewish astrology is a thing.
Yeah, there's a Jewish astrology.
And not just sort of a some medieval thing that happened in Western Europe where Jewish
people sort of took on astrology as it existed in sort of alchemical.
circles or hermetic circles as an esoteric thing, but goes all the way back to ancient
Israel and basically all of ancient Israel's neighbors in the ancient Near East, having
a firm sense of what we would now call astrology.
And so we've read a bunch of times, we won't read it again because it's long, but we've
Read a couple times now in discussions.
about the Sun Moon and stars and angelic beings,
that quote from a follow of Alexandria
where he's talking about really this difference,
the difference between the nuances
between the Jewish view of the Sun Moon and stars
and therefore astrology and the more general pagan view.
But we may recall that in that quote,
he talks about how the Sun Moon and stars aren't sort of,
He calls them gods.
He doesn't hesitate to do that, but they aren't gods in the sense of being worshipped and
being independent powers in the heavens, separate from Yahweh, the God of Israel, but they're
lesser ranking officials in his divine government over the creation.
Yeah.
Both Jews and pagans have in common this idea that heavenly bodies are closely associated
with divine beings, but the
differences that you don't worship them if you're if you're the worshiper of the one true God,
and you're not subject to them either, right? Which is really important for what we're talking about
tonight. Yeah, well not in the same sense. There is, I mean, there is still that they are still part
of the government, right? Right. So, you know, in a lesser way, you're under their authority, but
but not they're not controlling your life.
Right. The language of the
to rule the day and the moon and stars to rule the night is all over the place in the old
testament. And we gloss over that rule verb very quickly, but it actually is there. And so
what Fylo really wants to hammer on is that they're not independent, meaning God rules and acts
through them. They don't sort of act on their own.
or have their own authority or control.
There is emissaries or XRX or ambassadors
or however you wanna put it.
Right.
And this isn't just talking about
the individual stars in the sun and moon.
For example, in the book of Jubiles,
which is one of the many Old Testament adjacent texts
adjacent tax in the
Orthodox Church, if you are Ethiopian, then it's in your Old Testament. Otherwise, it's a
Jason. Yeah. Jubilee's 1215. It says, all the signs of the stars and the signs of the moon and
of the sun are all in the hand of the Lord. And the signs language there is important. It's not
just the sun, moon, and stars, but the signs of the sun and the moon and the stars, their movements,
their positions, their tracks.
Yeah.
Now we're talking astronomy.
sort of, right? At least that's how we'd understand in the modern world is, you know, these
things moving around, or at least appearing to move around from our point of view. But
for ancient people, they saw them moving. I mean, they understood that they were in motion.
Yeah. And this is one of the big barriers for us as modern people trying to read ancient
Near Eastern texts. To put a fine point on it, we don't know much or care much about
Make sure to scroll.
We've kind of written off as, right?
We've written off, as we've talked about at the show,
as sort of materialists, we've written off a lot of ancient things
as silliness and superstition.
Astrology is probably exhibit A.
Right, right.
There's this, yeah.
I think that, just as, you know, we've talked about,
for instance, the modern view of ancient pagan gods is like,
oh, look at those ancient pagans.
They saw lightning and thunder and earthquakes and the ocean
and they made up gods to explain all that.
I think the modern view of ancient astrology is, oh look, you know, ancient peoples looked
up at the sky and they saw the stars and the sun and the moon moving around and they
assumed that they could sort of read some kind of, it's like fortune telling, you know,
like they could read something in there or they, since they saw them moving around, they
assumed well that they must have some direct influence on us and, you know, a modern
person that says, well, like, okay, yes, maybe some distant star is actually...
exerting gravitational force on you, but it's so microscopic, because there's no way it's going to determine your personality and the outcome of your life, and much less coming up with a horoscope that shows up in the daily paper.
It just becomes kind of a big joke, because of course we're scientific and we understand and know that you can't read the future by looking up at constellations.
But that's not the way that each astrology actually worked, right?
That's not what they understood themselves to be doing.
Right.
And when you look at any ancient Near Eastern text and just to take an example that we've
referred to before, we referred to back in the five-ish falls of the Angels episode when
we were talking about the fall of the devil and we were talking about the different accounts
of that in the Old Testament.
The one in Isaiah that refers to him as Hello Ben Chicarr that would later get translated
Lucifer, son.
of the morning. That the Hello Ben Chicare language and the way it's told in Isaiah seems to
draw on ancient texts about the fall of the God Enlil. So just to use those Enlil texts
as an example of this. On earth there's what we would call a political shift at that time,
where Babylon in particular takes political supremacy away from
Sumeria, and so there's this shift in the power base from one city to another, within Mesopotamia.
We would say there's a political shift. Then mythologically there are stories that the god Enlil of the cities that are losing power,
sort of falls as up in the underworld and is replaced in his position in the
Council of Gods.
by another god, by Marduk in this case.
And then there's also layered into the text,
various astrological signs that this has happened
where stars and constellations that are related
to these gods change their position in the heavens.
And these are seen to be signs of this shift
that has happened.
in the council of the gods.
Yeah.
And that even bleeds into the biblical account, right?
Because he's loosed to first Sunday the morning.
He's associated with the Morning Star,
which is the planet Venus, strictly speaking.
So that even that astrological connection
even comes over into the prophet Isaiah's reference to it.
But within these end little texts,
the writer and the reader moves back and forth
between.
these layers, sort of what we would call the political layer, the what we would call the mythological
layer or the mythical layer and the astrological layer back and forth. These are all interrelated
and mirror, they're like layered transparencies one over the other. Yeah, so it's like it's like
one sort of set of events that's playing out both in heaven and on earth at the same time.
Yes, yeah, in heaven, earth and the heavens.
Yeah, in all three.
Yeah, because it's all connected,
because it's all connected and we'll back it forth.
In our modern materialist view,
we of course have separated these things.
Yeah.
So we've got the political, the religious astrology
that we would assign to superstition, right?
Every separate these things.
And if you're a real materialist, you say,
only the political one is real.
Yeah.
the other ones are just sort of...
of imaginary and are being used to justify things in the political realm or explain things
in the political realm, but they're not real.
But for ancient people, all three of these are real.
And you have to have sort of all three transparency's layered over each other to look at it and
see the whole event and really understand what's going on.
Now, would they have understood it in a sort of positive sense, like there's this thing
going on between gods and so therefore we on earth are being deterministically
made to play this out politically?
Or, I mean, what exactly is that relationship?
Yeah.
Determinism in this case is like turtles.
It's determinism all the way down.
So this is something people miss and ancient myth.
The gods had their fates determined
just like everybody else.
so it's not like there
the ones with free will and in an absolute sense and we're just ants that they're stepping
on.
Yeah, I recall, so like, for instance in Greek myth, you've got the idea of the three
fates, right, who are measuring out these chords that are people's lifetimes and then cutting
them at the appropriate moment and that's what determines your fate.
It's fatalism, but that applies to God's and to men.
it's not
just us lowly mortals, right?
Because gods can die.
Gods can lose their battles.
You know, they can be cast into the abyss.
Yeah.
And in Norse mythology, you've got the Norenear
who are the same kind of thing, who are these three sort
of witches who determine the future, determined fate.
And all of the Norse gods are faded to die in Ragnarok.
and they can't sort of escape that.
In fact, a lot of the, a lot of Norr Smith
is them trying to escape that, fate.
They have this doom hanging over them,
which is also of course paralleled in the Christian story
because all of those demons do have doom hanging over them
coming at the end and are unable to escape it.
It's an interesting thing, actually.
I'm about to study Norr Smith much more deeply
as part of the MA work that I'm doing.
And it's an interesting point actually that almost all North Smith that we have.
So for instance, the Edas are one of the big sources of Norse mythology.
They're all written down and preserved by Christians.
And I kind of wonder sometimes like, you know, so a lot of mythology, as we've said,
is kind of demonic propaganda.
But I wonder sometimes like Snorrius Storelson, who is the guy who put down the Edas.
he's a 13th century Christian.
You know, did he kind of say, well, that's wrong. I'm gonna fix this. You know, was there a little bit editing happening?
I don't I don't know. I'm not a I'm not a textual critic of Norse miss, but
It's an interesting point though something something useful. Yeah, and and yeah spoilers. There was a lot of
editing
I've known that there was I'm just not sure exactly what the details are. Yeah, the most obvious example of that is pay a wolf
Where first
we have a, a, the Bale Wolf story, Grendel's descended from Kane. Right. Yeah. It's completely been.
There's biblical stuff in there. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. So, um, yeah. So this is, this is all layered
together. And the Bible is an ancient Near Eastern text. So what's true of those texts,
including this astrological layer is also true.
true of the Bible.
Yeah, welcome everybody.
Here's another surprising thing going on in the Bible.
Yeah, astrology in the Bible.
It's not just poetic language.
I mean, we've kind of talked about this a little bit before,
that the references to the Sun and Moon stars are not just poetic language,
but now we're kind of going deeper into the rabbit hole,
that there is actually astrology going on in the Bible.
And I think it's important again, I mean we've already said this.
but let's just underline that the astrology of the scriptures,
the astrology of Israel, is not the astrology of ancient pagans.
And it is also not, although it's related,
it's closely related, and it is also not
the astrology of the horoscope in your local paper.
I don't know if they even do those anymore,
but it's barely related to that, if at all.
So we should just kind of point that out.
When you heard that word astrology,
We're not engaging in secrets.
We're, again, we're looking, we're going to be looking closely at the scriptures and
seeing what's actually going on there.
So, all right.
Yeah, that's, I think that's some good preliminary ways to point it out.
And related to that, we got a question that was sent to us and recorded for us from Richard
Roland, who is a listener of this podcast and also is now becoming the co-host, the persistent
co-host of the Amman's School Podcast, thus continuing this idea that these are
really just one podcast with two different iterations.
So let's listen to the question that Richard sent us.
Greetings, fathers.
Christ is born.
I would like to hear your take on astrology
and its possible impact on one's personality traits,
characteristics, et cetera.
And here I'm not really talking about
or even interested in the modern horoscope,
but more in things like wear and medieval literature,
for instance, in Dante's Divine Comedy,
We're doing.
counter the idea that because the stars and planets are angels who do have some impact
and even influence on the world, there is some kind of a relationship there between us
and them, but not to the extent that either overrides our free will or takes away sort of
our personal responsibility.
I would love to hear this discussed from an orthodox point of view.
All right, so what about that?
I mean, Richard seems to be alluding.
He mentions that he's not talking about modern horoscopes, but he's trying to help us
You
figure out what's going on here. What is the sort of relationship between us and the stars slash angels?
And what does that have to do with free will? We've touched on that a little bit, but let's just kind of flesh that out a little bit, especially the difference between the pagan understanding and the understanding of the scriptures.
Yeah, and since we said we were doing this episode we've gotten a lot of questions about modern horoscopes. Yes, yeah lots of people sent us
questions about horoscopes and modern astrology and I hope that this episode actually helps with a lot of that.
Yeah, so we've already talked about a couple of distinctions.
One being that obviously we don't see the Sun Moon in stars as being gods that function independent of the creator of the universe.
right right and that is a separate
separate entities who control things of their own independent wills.
And that means the flip side of that, that what we are saying is that like all
angelic beings or spiritual beings, that these are beings through whom God can
work in his creation both in terms of governance as Philo talked about, but
but also the word angel.
means messenger, talked about how that's a job they do.
So that means that as angelic beings,
they can service messengers,
they can, God can communicate through them.
We lose the element of determinism
because that's not part of our religion.
Right, so like that's not the God,
the God we worship does not do that to us.
And so of course he's not going to do it to us.
through his divine beings.
Right, right, or through anything else.
Yeah.
Right. And so, yeah.
So it's not that all of these things are playing out in the heavens
and in the counsel of the gods and on earth,
according to some woven plan somewhere.
Yeah. God is not the feats.
Sorry, Calvary.
But...
Sorry, not sorry.
That's it.
But it's that just like humans, as we've talked about in the last couple episodes,
angelic beings are creations of God through whom God works and through whom he can communicate
to the rest of his creation.
And you see this explicitly in a bunch of places in Scripture.
real quick, shorthand one is at the beginning of the book of Revelation you have the seven stars
that are the seven angels of the seven churches. Right. Who add who are all each given a letter
to bring as a messenger to that church. Yeah. So right there you have this this connection of
of stars as messengers at a shorthand way,
but there's actually a much deeper biblical.
theology that you find in the scriptures regarding the Sunward and stars in particular
as messengers and agents of God.
Yeah, it's not just, again, it's not just a poetic image like, hey, you know, okay, there's
this association between angels and stars and so, you know, but again, it's watching
their motion and how they relate to each other in the heavens is incorporated into the
scriptures.
That I think is one of the big, I think that's one of the hurdles that we have to kind of get over is that again
it's not just like, oh, I think they're like stars, you know, it's it's
so once you take seriously that the actual stars are associated with angelic beings then what they're doing up in the sky becomes really interesting
but
maybe not on the way you think
Sorry, dispensation lists. Sorry. This isn't
And so
Is the east of Juliet is the sun?
Right.
This is it.
Yeah.
Yeah. Right.
A poetic thing.
Yeah.
And it's also not.
This is not some other version of the Bible code either to take it the other direction.
Right.
Yeah.
All right.
This is this is as we were saying with other ancient texts.
This is a layer of meaning that's there in the in the scriptures.
Right, it's not an overriding thing that then...
determines everything else.
So yeah, yeah.
Okay, so I know that we have,
so a really important passage that we want to look at
is from Psalm 19, or it's going to be 18
if you're looking at a Bible with a Greek numbering.
And verses one through six, I'm just going to read this for you.
And as you listen everybody, you may notice that the translation
here is a little bit different from what you're used to.
And we're going to talk about that, okay.
So just listen.
So there's a sub.
Again, Psalm 19 if it's a Hebrew numbering or 18 if it's a Greek numbering.
The heavens declare the glory of God and the firmament proclaims His handy work.
Day to day pours out speech and night to night reveals knowledge.
There is no speech, nor are there words whose voice is not heard.
Their line goes out through all the earth and their words to the end of the world.
them he has set a tent for the sun, which comes out like a bridegroom leaving his chamber.
and like a strong man runs its course with joy,
its rising is from the end of the heavens
and its circuit to the end of them
and there is nothing hidden from its heat.
And what's notable about that,
if you just read it whatever translation,
is there's clearly a sense of astronomy
at the very least going on here, right?
There's, okay, it's talking about the movement of heavenly bodies,
But there's something very specific here and I think...
think it and it's connected with that verse that probably sounds different from what you're
used to, especially Orthodox people, you're used to hearing their voice has gone out through
all the earth. And we're going to talk about that in just a second, but the way I read it was
their line goes out through all the earth. So Father, what is that about? What's that line?
And why like why are we saying voice most of the time?
Right. Well, so the just to drop back for justice.
It's important that we see this isn't just talking about you know that there are other texts for example
We get to Psalms 147 through 50 that talk about the Sun Moon and stars praising the Lord
Right
And we've talked about how you shouldn't really read those as purely poetic, but you can
Right, it's a possible reading, okay, but what what this says here in Psalm 19 is that they're they're pouring forth speech and revealing knowledge
So that's different.
That means there's actual content. There's actually, there's something being communicated.
They're saying that the heavenly bodies are seeing something to us.
Right. Not just like a general sense of joy or something.
Or, you know, creation, praise and God in sort of this vague sense.
But yes, so the word there that we translated line, which you will find translated
If you get most English Bibles, they'll have something like voice in the main text probably,
and then they'll have a footnote that says, you know, literally line.
They count at the bottom of the page.
Because what could that possibly mean so we're not going to?
Yeah, they sort of don't know what to do about it.
If you get a Bible that's pride in itself on being very literal, they'll just have line
there the way we did, because that's what it says.
and
So that word line is referring to.
I was going to say, sorry, it dropped.
I just looked up in the net Bible.
And this is what their note says.
I just have to read this because it's just proofed it.
What you're saying is, the M-T reads,
so that's a Maseric text.
The Maseric text reads, they're measuring line.
The noun, a cough measuring line,
makes no sense in this context.
That's what it says.
Makes no sense in this context.
In other words, they don't see...
it what we're about to say. Right. Yeah. Yeah. And there's a reason why because they're not
interested in and don't know about astrology, right? Because you know they've written that off
as irrelevant. But so what this measuring line here is referring to is what's called the
ecliptic. And that may not be a word you've heard either. I mean, I know the word eclipse.
right and it's not unrelated but
The ecliptic is the path, it sort of lines that you could drive.
If you were making an astronomical or astrological chart,
the ecliptic is the path that the sun follows over the course of the year.
Because it doesn't rise and set in exactly the same spot on the horizon.
Exactly the same spot.
Right.
It moves around.
It days get longer and shorter and yeah.
So there's this path of the sun through the sky, and that's called the ecliptic.
And if you have any doubt that that's what this is talking about in Psalm 19 verse 4, you
just have to read the next couple verses.
You said it's that for the sun, which comes out like a bridegroom leaving his chamber
like a strong man runs its course.
Yeah.
So it's talking about the rising and setting of the sun.
It comes out in a cool...
quote, quote, tent, you know. And so there is this, the line they're talking about is that
that path of the sun. And so the ecliptic that line, that region of the sky, is the region
where the different constellations that we would now call the zodiac enter and leave over
over the course of the year.
So it's their position relative to the path of the...
the path of the sun at that time of the year.
And this is, at some point inevitably,
we're gonna do an episode or five about the Book of Enic.
Yes, yes.
And there's a huge central portion of the Book of Enic
that's just about the calendar.
And the calendar you're supposed to follow,
then it talks about the different gates of the sun
at the different times of year,
It comes out over the gates it goes back into.
So this is sort of a key thing that everyone in the ancient world do about.
It could just reference something we haven't probably thought much about.
Right because I woke up this morning with an alarm clock and I still got up and I still
did the same things and I still walked out of the house at the same time on my clock without
any reference.
to when the sun was coming up.
I mean, I've noticed that it tends to be darker
when I leave, but that's about it.
That's about it, because our lives are governed
so much by mechanistic processes now
that the naturalistic processes of sunrise and sad
and so forth really don't govern our lives
and so we don't really notice them that much.
And indeed, we even attempt to control them
Bye.
something called daylight-saving time.
You know, it's, it's, it's, yeah, there's just so much that I think we're not seeing
because we're just not paying attention to it.
You know, it's happening, but we're just not paying attention because we've got our
attention on something else.
I can tell you what time my alarm is set for each day, but I couldn't tell you what time
the sun is rising or setting unless I, you know, ask Google.
Yeah.
the
And it's important when we take these six verses together,
this means that the Psalm is saying
that part and parcel of how the heavens communicate
what they're communicating from God
has to do with this path of the sun.
And the specifics of the movements.
Yeah.
You could say, well, a Psalmist poetry,
that it is.
But we're gonna get into it in a little bit and we're gonna see that when this
Text is cited later in the Bible
It's not just cited as sort of poetry and imagery. Yeah
But we'll get there and it's and this is interestingly specific and
Astronomical it's really like yes, you could just say you know the the poet is
Is taking an image and really running with it?
but he really has run with it at the very least, right?
Like this is not just throwing out, you know, astronomical imagery.
This is about specific astronomical events.
Yeah.
And that this is a means by which God communicates.
Right.
This is saying something.
And we find, because this is our Christmas episode, we find reference to this in our liturgical
hymns for the Nativity.
Yeah.
So I don't know if you want to read you could sing it.
I'm not going to sing for everybody.
Okay.
Yeah.
So this is the the nativity of
a politician.
And this is going to be the Christmas
him in the Orthodox church that
that everybody knows.
Whatever they do it in their particular tradition.
So there are little variations in translation
and we're going to talk a little bit about that.
But I'm just going to read to you.
this one. Theinativity of Christ our God has given rise to the light of knowledge in the world.
For they that worshiped the stars did learn therefrom to worship the O sun of righteousness
and to know that from the east of the highest, doubt it's come, O Lord glory to the.
And of course, it's that him, which is the source of the title of this particular episode.
So yeah.
So what's going on in here that has to do with this
ecliptic of Psalm 19.
Well, so we'll get into the Magi later on because of course, it will be in the third
half of the program that we get to our actual advertised topic.
They that worshiped us as our want.
Yes, right.
Exactly.
This is the podcast that is, wait for it.
So, but we have this element of the the the son of righteousness.
And this phrase that was translated as you read it from the east of the highest.
sometimes it's the Orient from on high.
Yeah, and we should note that son of righteousness there is S-U-N, not S-O-N, it's S-U-N.
So it's all astronomical here or astrological.
And the actual language that's translated from the east of the
the Hays is actually from the song of Zachariah, St. John the Four Hunters father at St. John's
ever.
Um.
That's where it's been picked up from. But what is it referring to? Well, the reason people
have trouble translating it into into English is that the word that's translated east there is
quite literally the word for east. It's the Greek word Anatoly. And the highest is literally just
a form of the preposition up, like high place.
Yeah, and I've seen this also translated as
Orient from on high and of course Orient is just another word referring to East
right and
So the word on a toly though also means the sunrise
Because that's where the sun rises is in the east right is in the east
In fact, that's how it came to mean east right the word actually refers to the sun rising
And so if you were going to talk about that
direction, you'd say over there where the sun rises, head that way, right? Or head of
the direction of the sunset, if you were talking about west. But so the point that's being
referred to here is it's not the sunrise in the sense of the event, it's the sunrise
in the sense of the location. So this would be, and that highest is really sort of just
a way of saying extremity. So this is talking about the one end of the ecliptic. This is talking
about the extreme of the ecliptic, which is the point of origin where the sun like a bridegroom
leaves his tent. And so, I mean, does that then connect with the fact that here we are around the
winter solstice. Is this the end? Is this the the the the point at which the the sun leaves? The bridegroom
leave this tent? Well...
Yeah, it's not it's not directly related to this ulcers.
Okay. All right. Good. Well, I figured there were some people can be thinking that we should throw that out.
Yeah.
No, it's not a little bit more.
It's the point in the sky. Right. That's the point of origin of the sun in the same way that the
magi come to know the point of origin of Christ. Right. That point of origin of the sun.
And this bribed room language related to the sun here, obviously that bribed...
language is something that's related to Christ and so the triparian is taking all
of that into account, right? But when it refers to the point of origin of Christ, it
refers to this point on the ecliptic. It refers to this sort of point of origin. So
this triparian, which of course comes later than the Scriptures, also has this
astrological layer of meaning in it. Yeah, this is Orthodox astrology now.
Now.
Right.
That's welcome everybody. Connecting to the to the bad job. So it's referring to that that place.
Yeah. But so as as I mentioned, we have this idea in in the song that's not just a poetic idea.
Right. You can try to write it off as a poetic idea that somehow the movement of the stars in relation to the
the ecliptic.
conveys knowledge. You know, the God speaks through it. It's just some sort of poetic thing.
But Saint Paul in particular takes this super literally.
Yeah. Now we're in Paul Inaestrology. Yes. Yeah. Yeah. So then the first example from our notes
is from the book of Romans and the first chapter, starting with
verse 18 and going through verse 20,
for the wrath of God is revealed from heaven
against all ungodliness and unrighteousness of men
who by their unrighteousness suppress the truth.
For what can be known about God is plain to them
because God has shown it to them.
For his invisible attributes,
namely his eternal power and divine nature
have been clearly perceived ever since
the creation of the world
and the things that have been made.
made so they are without excuse. I remember reading that verse, you know, when I was an evangelical
and I just read it as like, oh yes, you know, the creation has this amazing design and glorious,
you know, complexity. And so that means there must be a creator. And so I'm responsible for what I do
with that natural kind of conclusion to be derived from that.
But...
you're saying that Paul is actually saying something much more specific than just look at the
complexity of creation and you're responsible for thinking that there's a creator, right?
Right, and this also isn't just natural law. Yeah. Right. Hey, everybody knows from nature that
murder is wrong. So if you're a murderer, that's bad, even though you didn't have the Torah.
Right. Right. Yeah, I took, I took kind of a cheap shot at my Calvinist friends earlier. So
So as consolation, I offer you.
Romans 1 18 through 20. You have to explain that to everybody now. But this is a very popular passage.
I want my Calvinist friends. So this is talking about the fact that and this is still kind of vague.
We're going to see later in Romans say Paul's going to get more specific. But here,
say Paul is saying that that say Paul always lays out sort of his themes and the things he's going to do.
to talk about at the beginning of his epistles and then develops them over the course of the epistles.
So this is chapter one. Here's one of his themes that he's introducing here.
That there is actual concrete knowledge about God that is found by observe the observance
and perception of creative things which includes God's power, His divine nature, His attributes.
That's more than just.
there's some kind of God who created things, right? Because everyone St. Paul was writing to
thought there were gods who created things. Yeah, so there were no atheists. Right. He doesn't need
to address that. It's not a it's not a live question in the first century. Right, and so he's saying
he's talking to particularly former pagans in this part of Romans 1. He's going to turn to
Jewish Christians and
Romans 2, but he's talking specifically to former pagans here saying that the pagans are accountable
for, you know, Zon in chapter 1 to talk about specifics like idolatry and their religious ritual,
that they should have known that was wrong because they should have come to know at least about
It broads in some kind of broad strokes, enough about the true God.
to not do that. And so they're accountable for having, it's not that they, well,
they didn't know about Yahweh, the God of Israel. They had been assigned to these lesser spiritual beings.
Right. And they'd worship them, which they weren't supposed to, but they, how are they supposed to
know any better? St. Paul's saying, no. No, you, you had a way to know through created things. If
If you'd pay attention that there was
the true God, God most high, right? And that you shouldn't have been worshiping these other powers.
And so you're accountable because you could have known, but you chose to sort of suppress that
knowledge. Yeah. Now here he doesn't go into detail exactly how they should know or what exactly
they should have known or how they should have known it. But he says that it's revealed from heaven
against all of that ungodliness and unrighteousness.
And he says that they've suppressed the
to the
truth. You know, so there's there's this problem of like you knew the truth, but you you were hiding it. You
didn't want anybody to know. You hit it for yourself. Yeah, and you wanted to do some other stuff. And so
you did it. But you weren't it wasn't a sin of ignorance was a sin of deliberate deliberation. Yeah,
it was voluntary. Yeah. Yeah. But he does develop that later, right? Right. So and specifically in Romans 10.
Yeah, yeah, why don't you read
that one for us then. Okay, this is Romans 10 12 through 18. He says, for there's no distinction
between Jew and Greek, for the same Lord is Lord of all, but stowing his riches on all
who call on him, for everyone who calls on the name of the Lord will be saved. So I'll
just pause and do a little on the way through. Not the way I do it by Bible study, we don't
to be here all day.
But so he's
he's saying, look, there's one God and one Lord Jesus Christ over everybody whether you
used to be a Jew or used to be a pagan. Now you're a Christian. Everyone who calls on the name of
the Lord will be saved the same way. He says, how then will they call on him in whom they have not
believed? How are they to believe in him of whom they have never heard? How are they to hear without
someone preaching, how are they to preach unless they are sent?
So
This gets quoted a lot in evangelism circles.
Right?
These people can't call them the name of Lord and be saved unless they hear about who
Christ is and they can't hear who Christ is unless someone preaches it to them and they
can't have it preach to them unless someone's sent to preach it to them.
Yeah, so go out there and preach.
Yeah.
And then St. Paul says, quoting Isaiah, as it is written, how beautiful are the feet of
those who preach the good news, who preach the gospel.
Is this what they have not all obeyed the God?
for Isaiah says, equals Isaiah again, Lord, who has believed what he has heard from us.
So faith comes from hearing and hearing through the Word of Christ. So so far so good.
I think everybody gets what that's saying, right? That not everyone who hears actually is obedient to it.
Notice, St. Paul uses the word obeyed there, not the word believed.
Yes.
that it was true, but sorry to some people again. But so look you come to faithfulness, you come to
Christianity and the gospel by hearing it, you hear it through the word of Christ, the gospel
that's proclaimed. Then he says, but I ask have they not heard? So who's the the they here
is the pagan world out there.
Yeah, right?
The people who have...
heard the gospel. So he now he asks this question, have they not heard already? Right?
Implying have they not already heard the gospel? He says, indeed they have for their voice has
gone out to all the earth and their words to the ends of the world. Which is, and he quotes,
Psalm 19, Psalm 19. But that's that's the language we're more used to. Their voice has gone out
to all the earth. Why is he saved voice there and not lie?
like we said there about the classic.
He's quoting an already existing Greek translation.
Yeah.
Which, would you say got it a little bit wrong?
I think they had the same problem most English translators have.
They weren't sure what to do with the word.
But the meaning is still clear.
Yeah. Right.
Because if you go to Psalm 19, right,
Saint Paul is saying,
Hey, that knowledge that's communicated in Psalm 19 by the heavens,
by the stars.
The speech that's poured out St. Paul is saying regardless of how you translate that word
St. Paul is saying the gospel is the content that's being communicated the word of Christ
And we should emphasize that
Most the time when the New Testament quotes the Old Testament, especially the Psalms
like one line is quoted but the point is to isolate that one line and
Use it but rather to say
But I ask that they have not heard, and indeed they have for Psalm 19.
That he's essentially just referencing the Psalm by quoting that one line, although it's probably
the most relevant part of it for the argument that he's making. Yes, actually everybody has heard
the gospel, and they heard it because of these things that are observable in the sky.
Yeah. That's what he's claiming, that the gospel is being preached by the movements of the heavens.
Absolutely.
Which...
So how does...
I mean, I like, okay, you know, thinking about that sort of skeptically for a moment, or
just, you know, like, okay, so yes, let's say I did pay attention to where the sun rises
every day, and I do have this concept of the ecliptic and all that kind of stuff.
How do I get from there to the gospel?
You know, that Christ is God and man, and he is conquered as enemies, and here's what
expected of us.
How do I get there from that?
Right in five easy steps
God loves you and has a wonderful plan for your love. Yeah
So yeah, and this we're we're we're picking up
See again, this is as you said earlier
We're going further down a rabbit hole that we already gazed into in previous episode. Yes, right
It's a kind of...
We talked spiral-shaped podcast, just keeps struggling and getting deeper and deeper.
Yeah, yeah. Well, I would prefer to say an upward spiral than a downward spiral, but okay.
We talked about how the promise to Abraham was, the promises to Abraham were made in terms of
star language. Right. Right. Where we were talking about introducing the concept of theosis that
This sentence would be like the stars.
and that they would camp in the gates of their enemies
and this had to do with this replacement idea
of human beings,
demonized human beings,
human beings who experienced theosis replacing the fallen,
the fallen spiritual powers.
Well, now we're going further down that rabbit hole
into some of the particulars in how that was seen
and how that's reflected in the scriptures.
So, do word for it.
is do Hebrew word for today at least is Motsarot. Motsarot which doesn't have
anything to do with Motsarillo apparently. Nothing to do with Motsarillo
nothing to do with Motsaballs. Yeah. To my knowledge if someone knows there's
some connection to Motsaballs let me know but yeah scholars of
rabbinic Judaism. So that's the Hebrew word that roughly means
constellation.
Right. Right. One of the signs of the stars that we talked about in the book of Jubilee's earlier. And there are 12 of them. What do you know? Just like our 12 constellations in pretty much all the other
ancient Eastern understandings about what we would call the zodiac. What we may not have connected in our heads, though, but which ancient Israel and
Second Temple Judaism did connect is that there are also 12 tribes of Israel.
Yeah, so does each one of them have their own sign?
Yes.
Yep.
So, you can go everybody.
Hold on.
There is a constellation associated with each of the tribes.
Yeah.
Now are these the constellations that we would be familiar with, you know, like Orion and Sagittarius
and, you know, kind of help you?
Yes.
And they're roughly the same.
These are what we would associate with the Zodiac.
signs. And in many cases they're associated with the same animals. Yeah, right? So Judah with the
lion is kind of obvious. You could guess which one that is. And in some of the others. So
and this this imagery of those signs was directly connected to the 12 stones that were in the
high-prease E-Fod, his rest plate.
Yeah.
They can read about in Exodus 28, 15 through 21.
All right.
And that was part of the markings on them when you bore those into the tabernacle and then later the temple.
And this means there was likely, we've mentioned before I think that we don't know exactly how the Eurom and Thumum worked.
Some kind of a divination.
Yeah, yeah, that was if you had some really tricky case where you couldn't figure
out based on the written Torah what you should do. This was sort of your last
ditch way you'd go to the high priest and he would use the Yerim and Thumum to
determine what what God's will was. And we don't know exactly how that worked
but the fact that there were stones in his breastplate that were with these
others implies that there may have been some kind of astrological component of
this involved with the the urban
them are making that determination.
And then in Genesis 49, right,
there's all of this animal imagery.
What's going on there?
Yeah.
So the Genesis 49 is the testament of Israel
or the testament of Jacob.
But a testament is actually a whole genre of literature.
There are tons of these adjacent to the Bible.
It's like a temple of literature.
Yeah.
And if you haven't read it recently,
If you pull out your Bible and look at Genesis 49, you will see basically Jacob calls all his sons together, right?
And then he sort of lists them off, you know, by name.
It starts out, you know, gather together and hear you sons of Jacob and listen to Israel your father.
That's of course the name that God gives to Jacob.
And he starts off talking about Rubin and then Simion and Levi.
And it goes on and on and on.
And if you read closely, you'll see that there's
animal imagery that seems to be connected to these various
And of course, these sons are the origin of the 12 tribes of Israel.
Right. And so you get the lion imagery with Judah, you get serpent imagery with Dan.
That's not just sort of poetic stuff. It's prophetic in that he's talking about what's going to happen with these tribes.
So, for example, when he talks about his son Judah, he talks about the kingship coming from Judah.
and maybe one of our lent episodes.
so it's willing to talk about Palm Sunday
and the imagery there in the prophecy about Judah.
With Dan, that's been widely associated
the prophecy there with the Antichrist,
but it also talks there about a viper.
And so you have and Benjamin also,
but there's this.
Benjamin's a wolf, first 27.
Yeah, I mean, enough to leave as a deer.
I mean, it just goes on and on.
It goes on and on.
Yeah.
the car is a donkey.
And these are associated with constellations.
So there's this astrological layer here where that's being put into, it's called a testament
because Jacob's dying at the time.
And so these are sort of his parting words, sons, parting prophetic words.
But there's this astrological layer there associating these 12 tribes with those constellations.
which makes total sense.
If you go back again as we mentioned the promises to Abraham that is descendants are gonna be as the stars and
We're not just talking about kind of like an individual sort of ascension to be like an angel
Although that is certainly part of what we're talking about
but also there is this
this
Association with stars in a much more complex level now systems
you know, of constellations and so forth.
If that's how Israel understands...
it's identity that this is their destiny then it makes total sense then that they would have
this association with stars even on this level of zodiac signs in the sky. I mean this is cool
this is cool stuff that I had again no idea was in there you know but but here it is here it is
and then that would have been what's seen like when we we started out talking about these mosaics
and synagogues, this is what would have been there.
So, so when
Jesus walks into a synagogue and there's the zodiac.
It's the, you know, the zodiac of Israel.
It's the 12 tribes of Israel.
And there's zodiac, zodiac, zodiac signs.
You know, that's what's going on there, right?
Right, right.
And connecting that to their sacred calendar.
Yeah.
And how that relates to the, so by virtue of the stars,
the people are not only connected to the heavens, but also to time itself.
Yeah. Right? Is directly connected to their lives on this earth and
through the means of the sacred calendar. Part of something much bigger than yourself
And this is one of the ways they understood that that worked.
Yeah.
Cool.
And so there's
There's a very concrete example of taking that camping in the gates of your enemy's imagery
and applying it through the tribes to constellations in a place that we probably haven't read much.
Yeah, judges.
And that's in the song, yeah, the song of Deborah in judges five.
Yeah.
So there's this whole, this is a cool story for anybody who hasn't read it.
Yeah, it's one of the brighter spots and judges, which is largely dark and awful.
Well, for some, there are problems here too, but the biggest problem is that there's a man named
Barak who's chosen to be the judge of Israel and is sort of a wimp and doesn't do it.
And so God says a prophetess, Deborah, to sort of
go and take command of Israel's army, just sort of a baris barrack. And so they
have to make war against Cicera, this enemy general who ends up getting a
tent big driven through his skull into the ground by another woman named Jail.
So it's it's cool stuff, especially if you're like a teenage boy. Yeah, right.
This is great Bible.
I remember the 10 peg.
Yeah.
But so after this, the Teenage Boys quickly lose interest
because Deborah sings a song.
Yes.
But it becomes a musical Teenage Boys check out.
So, but there are details of the way in which she describes the victory that Israel has won that are important.
Okay, for what we're talking about.
today. All right. Rufrosa II verses in particular in judges 520 it says they
fought from the heavens the stars from their courses fought with Cicera. So
leading up to 5 verse 20 Deborah has gone through all the tribes has listed all
the tribes so she's sort of arraying the here's the forces right who are
opposing each other in battle. Here's all the 12 tribes.
who we've talked about are associated with these these 12 constellations and then on the other side
there's Cicera and his human army and the stars in their courses. Yeah so he's got right sort of a
bunch of rebellious he's got astral allies yes fighting on his side yeah and we know of course
who won but then in describing that victory later on in
chapter 5 verse 31 says,
thus let all your enemies perish, O Lord,
but let those who love him be like the sun,
when it comes out in full strength.
So when the sun comes out,
the stars disappear. It's the idea.
Right. The sun.
The sun shows up.
So she's saying, yeah,
yeah, you had these spiritual powers on your side.
We had our 12 tribes,
But oh yeah.
Now we had Yahweh the God of Israel.
And when he comes out on the battlefield, it's like the sun coming out in the sky because
all those stars disappear.
They all vanish, they all scatter.
They're all defeated.
And so what she's describing is this defeat by Yahweh the God of Israel of these spiritual
forces that ever raid themselves with Israel's enemies by that he's done.
as via through the tribes of Israel who are going to sort of supplant them.
And so this is still, this is a little deeper down the hole, but this is establishing a pattern
that's later going to find its fulfillment later on in the New Testament.
Yeah.
And so when we're reading Psalm 19 or 18 in the Greek and we read that line about their
line or their voice going out into all the world.
So there were to the NC Universe, our orthodox listeners who are attentive might have recognized
that as a prochemino.
Yes, right.
It's the prochemino that gets sung, you know, before the epistle for feasts of the apostles.
But of course, also it gets done weekly as well on particular days for Thursday.
But yeah, it's associated with the apostles, especially Peter and Paul, but kind of any
Apostle actually their sound has gone into the all the earth.
And it's sung as a communion hymn for feasts having to do the apostles as well.
So it's connected with this preaching ministry of the 12 apostles in particular.
Right.
And probably you usually read it as like, okay, yeah, there's sound that's gone into all the earth.
Yeah, those apostles, they really traveled long distances.
They really got the word out.
But that's not what this is talking about actually, right?
Right, because as we've seen, that's not what
But the psalm is talking about that's not how Saint Paul uses the psalm.
And so this is talking about, quite literally, the apostles having become stars.
And we say that even more directly, actually, when we talk about the fathers, when we do
the part of the father says that they've become like luminous stars upon the earth.
that the Apostle...
have now made this move and that's not just a general reference to theosis
because of course there's 12 apostles and Christ had told them they'd sit on
12 thrones and judge the 12 tribes of Israel who of course as everyone knows in
the first century in the Holy Land are associated with Zodiac signs and so
So this is now the apostles take...
over that function. Right? And so this is a fulfillment of the kind of move that Deborah was talking about in her song.
Oh man.
All right. Well connected with that, then we got another question. And this is from Ray Riek. And he left us this message.
Hi, my name is Ray Riek and near Hershey, Pennsylvania. I'm really enjoying the show and I've learned a lot.
My question tonight for you is this.
Vincent talked in some evangelical circles over the years and even sermons preached
regarding the real meaning of the zodiac.
Specifically, I'm thinking of the late Dr. D. James Kiddigey, but I'm sure there are
others.
He essentially said that the zodiac was the gospel written in the stars and reinterpreted
many of the astrological signs to promote that narrative.
Are you all familiar with this?
Is there any basis for it in historical Christian thought?
Thank you.
we will
We'll answer that when we come back from our break.
Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung
will be back in a moment to take your calls
on the next part of the Lord of Spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF Radio.
Introducing the new podcast on Ancient Faith Radio,
The filled with less show, living the
Christian life with simplicity and intention, featuring Molly Sabrett and Cynthia Damascus.
Each month, Cynthia and Molly bring you interviews and practical tips for developing and maintaining
a peaceful mindset, healthy body and productive life, all from an orthodox perspective.
Molly is an author, a blogger, and a podcaster for ancient faith ministries and the director
of content fulfilled with less.
Cynthia Damascus is an integrative nutrition health coach specializing.
in functional nutrition and lifestyle management.
Listen to their podcast today at ancientfaith.com.
That's ancientfaith.com.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits,
the Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung.
If you have a question, call now at 855-237-2346.
That's eat five.
5 AF Radio.
Welcome back to the second half of the show.
And despite what you just heard from the voice of Steve,
we're not actually taking calls because this is a pre-recorded episode.
So even if you are listening to this and it's live premiere on Christmas Eve,
don't call because we're not on the other end of the phone.
But we are very happy to have received some of your questions and comments.
And of course we finished off.
the first part of this episode with that question from Ray Rieke.
Yeah, well, the answer to his question is basically this part.
So, so you know, now we've looked at ancient Jewish astrology and explained how ancient
Israelites understood their relationship to the stars.
How exactly does that apply to the birth of Jesus Christ to the gospel?
This is our Christmas episode, so we should probably talk about Christmas a little bit.
So yeah, so yeah.
Yeah, so how does that apply?
How does that apply?
Well, I do want to drop just a note about the late Dr. D. James
Kennedy.
Oh, yes.
Yes, right.
Of course, mentioned.
You mentioned that question.
Yeah, yeah.
Who was a Presbyterian pastor in Florida
and had a television ministry as well that was very popular.
amongst us old folks. So he passed away probably close to 20 years ago now I think.
2007. 2007. Oh, no, not that one. Yeah. He had a being a Presbyterian. He very much enjoyed
St. Paul's epistle to the Romans and saw the things that we were just talking about in Romans,
about the stars and the constellations proclaiming the gospel.
kind of took that and ran with it and had a very, very developed, I mean, not just like
a general gospel presentation, but all kinds of events from the gospels and things all connected
to various astrological things in a very detailed and elaborate way.
Wow.
Presbyterian astrology.
Yes.
So he was a Florida man.
Yeah, and I think, I mean, obviously I agree.
with the initial insight started all that in Romans. I think that is what St. Paul is saying in Romans.
But I think it was a little like he discovered a hammer and all of a sudden everything looked like a
nail. You know, and so we need to sort of hammer that in. So yeah, we're going to be talking about
in this, in the second half now, since I'm going to say, yeah, he took kind of ran with it.
a little too far, what is, you know, how would you see the Gospels, the Gospel of Christ being
portrayed in the stars? How would that have been communicated? And we're going to give some examples.
Yeah, yeah. So, so to begin, we actually have one of my favorite quotes from one of my favorite
synths.
And
And it's a saint we just celebrated on the calendar and that's in Ignatius of Antioch.
Somebody should write like an Orthodox book about him.
Yeah, that's an idea.
And we can call it bearable.
It could be available from ancient faith.
It could make a perfect last minute Christmas gift.
Exactly.
That's very last bit.
Yeah.
Yeah, let me think about who should write that one.
So yeah, so sad Ignatius and probably I mean he wrote...
seven epistles, but the one that probably gets the most traffic and rightly so is his
epistle to the Ephesians. There's just a lot of cool stuff in there, but they're all amazing.
And this is from the 19th chapter of his epistle to the Ephesians, and he's talking
specifically now about the birth of Christ. Well, you'll hear it. So listen, this is what he says.
hidden from the ruler of this age was the virginity
Mary and the one born from her, and likewise the death of the Lord, three famed mysteries which
God worked in silence. How then was he made manifest to the ages? A star in heaven shining beyond
all of the stars and its light was ineffable, and its great newness brought about wonderment.
The remaining stars with the sun and moon became a chorus for that star, and it exceeded with
with its light, them all.
And there was confusion from whence did this great newness and strangers come to them.
By this, all magistrate was destroyed and every evil chain disappeared.
Ignorance was taken away. The ancient kingdom is destroyed utterly.
God appeared humanized in order to bring about the great newness of unending life.
And that which had been planned by God was given a beginning.
Therefore, they all were troubled because the destruction of death.
was being prepared. It's a cool passage and it goes right from Christ's birth up through the
resurrection which Ignatius talks about the resurrection over and over in his epistles because he's
on his way to be martyred and it's definitely on his mind and it's what's giving him so much
joy and hope because he knows that Christ has risen which from his vantage point happens just a
few decades before. You know because he's early first century when he's writing a second century
excuse me, early second century when he's writing this.
And so the resurrection comes up over and over again, but for him, it's always connected as he says this destruction of death was being prepared.
So, all right, well, let's talk about this.
He definitely talks about stars here.
But there's this interesting thing where he talks about all of this happening being hidden from the ruler of this age.
Right.
There are these, there are these three mysteries that he talks about.
And,
Right.
It's there of course fame to mysteries that God works inside.
So he uses a nice paradox there.
Yeah.
They're worked in silence, but they're famous.
Right.
And the three mysteries are, number one, the Theotokos and the Virgin birth, number two,
Christ divine identity that Christ is God himself, right?
And the third one is Christ's death and the subsequent defeat of death.
So those are the three mysteries that say any nation.
is talking about. And he's mainly here, and we're focusing on, because Christmas episode, on the
first two of those, right, that have to do with the incarnation, sort of directly. The third one,
which is the Christ's death and resurrection and the defeat of death, is what gets referred to by
scholars a lot in the Gospels as the Messianic secret, right? Right. Which is especially prominent in
at the St. Marks Gospel.
where Christ will heal someone or tell the disciples something and then say,
hey, don't tell anybody. Right? And yeah, that happens all the time. And they usually end up going and telling everybody. But
Right. Yeah, and and and and kind of the material and you know, I think sort of the
the materialist reading of that maybe seems like that the Messianic secret is a secret that he's keeping
from everybody except his disciples that you know, which is weird because like he's going around preaching
So it doesn't make sense if you think that the secret is being kept from human being.
Right. Right. Right. So who is it being? I mean Ignatius talks about the ruler of this age.
Right. From the ruler of this age. That's who it's being hidden from. And St.
Ignatius is using language from St. Paul, for example, in 1 Corinthians 2 verse 8, where he's
talking about Christ's identity. He says, which none of the rules
of this age knew, for had they known, they would not have crucified the Lord of glory.
Right. Which again, the rulers of this age, it's not Pontius Pilate and Caesar.
And I mean, they are, they are rulers, but they are not the rulers of this age.
They're the spiritual powers who stand behind Caesar and were motivating Judas and the Jewish authorities.
parties, which then makes sense when
and sitting, Nisha says, hidden from the ruler of this.
age was the virginity of Mary and the one born from her, etc. Like he can't be talking about
Caesar. Of course, Caesar knew nothing about it. Well, I say that it was hidden from him, you know,
like that doesn't make any sense. You're like, oh, we kept the secret from Caesar. Right.
Big whoop. Right. He was going on in Judea. If Caesar had known who Jesus was, I believe that he
was God. Why would he not have wanted him to die? It was good for Caesar. It was good for every human.
that Jesus died. If you're a demon, then Christ's death is the worst thing that ever happened to you.
Yeah, that's, you know, Ignatius says the ancient kingdom is destroyed utterly and again, he doesn't mean the Roman Empire.
He means the kingdom, the rulership of demonic.
say, say, Paul is saying if they'd known that he was going to use his death to invade
Hades and pillage it and destroy
it and buying the devil and take his authority, then yeah, the devil wouldn't have killed him.
Right? You would have said, peace in long life. Right? Right. But basically, he's killed, and so that's
opening up the gates of Haiti. Right. And so that's, and you see that motif over and over again in
the church fathers when they talk about Christ's death. St. John Chrysostom using this, you know,
imagery of like a fish hook.
right say Gregory the theologian does too, uh, that, you know,
hell or hidey's or the devil thinks they're getting this human body.
Yeah, it's being baited. He's being baited.
What's the hookest set? Then that's it. They're done for, right?
They're yanked. You know, and yeah, yeah, I can Chris Ostens
Pascal homley where it says that hell took a body on and met God.
Yeah.
And so that's related to this idea of the secrecy surrounding
that, right, that it's sort of the secrecy before an invasion, right, where they think,
you know, it's defeat in our moment of triumph, right?
That's, yeah, so that's the third mystery.
But so the ones we're talking about here are those first two.
And so the virgin birth that happens in Bethlehem, the event, and who Christ is, so the incarnation,
fact that he's got himself.
is kept from them. And the way St. Ignatius talks about that is the reaction of the stars
to this sign appearing in the heavens. So this sign appears in the heavens to announce the birth of Christ
from the Theotokos. And that's how the other stars find out that it happened. That's where it's revealed.
that's revealed to them by the sign in the heavens.
And when they see it, here's how we know it's talking about demons, they're all troubled,
and disturbed, and shaken, and there's this imagery of the sign, it's light,
sort of being greater than the rest, that imagery we saw about the sun in the song of Debra,
sort of causing all the stars to disappear. So they're troubled by it,
had disturbed by it because these are rebellious powers.
And then when it talks about the remaining, that remaining is not like the other ones other than the new one.
The remaining are the ones who aren't disturbed and troubled by it.
So these are like the elect angels.
Yeah.
The stars that remained after the other ones rebelled and left.
Right.
They rejoice for this chorus.
And then the other ones, rebellious powers.
But these are all stars.
These are all things going on in the heavens and
And that's where it's revealed to them.
And we see those events in the stars
that St. Ignatius is talking about,
in the gospels themselves and the accounts
of Jesus' birth.
Right.
Obviously in Matthew 2 verse 2,
the match I see the sign,
St. Ignatius is referring to,
and that leads them to know,
hey, a king's been born in Judea, let's go.
Right?
And, right.
And sometimes I think.
We kind of soft-pedaled it. Like Judea was not an independent nation. It was just a Roman province.
So, you know, Herod was the king. Herod's air being born was not a big deal that would cause
people to come from Mesopotamia. Yeah. Yeah. So the sign we're talking about was not just like
a birth announcement from the ethnarch of a tiny backwater Roman province, right? The sign we're
we're talking about was.
bigger than that, to draw people from that far to take a multi-year journey.
Right? So a king has been born in Judea. It's not a new king of Judea has been born.
Right? This is an astronomical event that signals something of apoccal importance to these pagan magi.
Yeah, yeah. Yeah. And then the other thing we see is...
in Luke chapter 2 where the angel appears to the shepherds and announces to them the birth of Christ.
And then it says in verse 13, 14, suddenly there was with the angel of maltitude the heavenly host praising God and saying,
glory to God on the highest on earth peace, goodwill toward men.
And you know, it's funny, again, you know, it's sort of rewriting my reading of scripture here, right?
I think many times I've read that is like, okay, so God.
sends this one angel and he kind of tells them the message and then he sends a bunch of other ones
to just really reinforce it. You know, like, hey, but what we're actually witnessing here is
the rest of the angels finding out and saying, oh yeah, you know, like there's this sort of
applause breaking out, so to speak, you know, it's news to them too. It's news to them too.
And this is the stars singing.
This is stars singing.
Yeah, the shepherds.
the stars singing which is also referred to in Job 38. And Job 38 is part of Job getting
bald out. Yeah, yeah. God is basically saying, look dude, what is the deal? How dare you bring
these complaints to me? Yeah. And so God is talking about sort of like, you know, you
You want ants?
for me, you know, your demand sort of demanding, I explained to you why these things have happened to you.
And he's sort of saying, what makes you think you could even understand if I did.
And so he's sort of asking a bunch of rhetorical questions, right?
So, okay, Job, so you're so savvy, you're so wise.
How about this?
Okay, do you answer these questions?
Do you know about this?
And so he's talking about, in verse 6 and 7 of Job 38, he's talking about the creation of the world.
And so, yo, I asked him to what were its foundations fastened?
The foundations of the earth.
Or who laid its cornerstone when the morning stars sang together and all the sons of
gods shouted for joy.
So this is the stars singing and the angels rejoicing here in parallel because, of course,
the angels and stars are the same thing.
this is talking about Star Singing and if you go on in Job 38
It's not just, again, using stars as poetic imagery,
but it refers to specific constellations in the Pleiades
and Orion.
It talks about particular constellations
that Job is asked about.
Yeah, and I think it's especially notable
that the scripture talks about two times when the stars sing.
Number one, this one from Job, where it happens
at the creation of the world, which...
again, for those of you who love J.R. Tolkien, and you read this Sumerrullian, the angels
sing at the creation of the world at the beginning of that.
So I just want to point that out for all you Tolkien nerds.
But the other thing is because Tolkien reads the Bible.
The other thing, of course, is this here in the Luke chapter 2.
So like this is a moment, the birth of Christ is a moment that is so world-shaking to use
Ignatius's language so stellar to you.
is an absolutely appropriate pun that it's appropriate now that the stars themselves should
sing again. So like this moment that is an announcement of the re-creation of mankind
is an echo of that original creation. And one of the things that I loved about that that
passage from St. Ignatius which just leaped out at me when we were going over this before and
And he says God appeared humanized.
in order to bring about the great newness of unending life.
And I mean, this is just essentially echoed
for those of you who know a little bit of Saint Athanasius
of Alexandria when he says that very famous line,
God became man that man might be divinized or deified
or might become God.
You know, that this event is the new life of mankind.
It's the new creation of mankind.
He's the new Adam.
right. It's just I don't know, it's just astonishing. It's just so beautiful. So beautiful. I mean, just to try to imagine, you know, when I was in seminary, actually, I went to a classmate who unfortunately got got rest of soul. He passed away pretty young from cancer.
And I remember when he first got to the seminary,
one of the things that often the seminarians would do
in the beginning days of those new school years
kind of go around.
the room and everyone would say their name and then what their home parish was.
And so he was from Palestine. And he said, my name is Yad Acher, and I'm from Beits Sahur.
And my parish is the parish where the shepherds heard from the angels. We're like, great, what?
So he was literally from this place that we're talking about now. And he and his family
worshiped at the church where this event happened.
It's just, I don't know, it's not a well-made.
And that's the positive side.
So Christ's birth and his appearance as man is a good news.
The beginning of the gospel, the beginning of this newness of
an ending life, of eternal life, because that which was
planned by God was given a beginning.
St. Ignatius says, edit the flips.
side is that the demons, this is revealed to them are all troubled because the destruction
of death was being prepared.
So for them, this is the beginning of the end.
Because death is their power.
That's what they have in their control, especially the devil.
This is D-Day.
It's the beginning of the invasion.
Right?
They're of their territory, sort of a divine insurgency.
And so we're...
And we see Herod going and slaying the infants.
This is the first counterattack.
This is their counterattack on the invasion that's beginning.
And when St. Matthew describes it, he's very obviously,
very clearly making this parallel between Herod and Pharaoh.
when Pharaoh at the beginning of Exodus slaves...
the first born of Israel. Herod Slays, the sons under two years of age. And because we had to,
because it's this show, remember Pharaoh is the persecuting giant of old. So, and Herod is,
in the sense that we've talked about it, is a giant here because how? Because he's imaging,
He's bringing the works of these evil hostile powers.
into the world by murdering small children.
Yeah, which is a very giant thing to do.
Yes, to try to destroy.
So he is participating in the works of the evil one here,
quite literally in that first counterattack.
Yeah.
Yeah, and to just kind of underline this idea
that we've been talking about now about these things
being hidden from...
from the angelic powers.
You know, if you go to church a lot,
if you're an Orthodox Christian, you go to church a lot.
If you're in, you know, so there's what's called
tone of the week.
So for all you Byzantine changes out,
or all you changes, Byzantine or not.
All you changes out there, people do church music.
There's the tone of the week, which begins being used
on Saturday night at great Vespers.
And the theotocans, so it's a hymn
about the theotocos or to the theotocos
that is a
pointed for tone 4, and it's the, in the resurrection tone of the week, tone 4, but also gets
used at other times as well for certain feast days.
It goes like this, and maybe you never thought about this very much, but now you're never
going to be able to hear it the same way.
So this is the, this is the translation that we use in the Antiochian Church.
It goes like this.
The mystery which was hidden from everlasting and was unknown of the angels, Otheotokos,
revealed through the two
those who dwell upon earth in that God having become incarnate in unconfused union of his
own goodwill accepted the cross for our sake whereby he raised again the first created
and had saved our souls from death. It's just a summary of what St. Ignatius says. It's
well it's just again a summary of what's in the Scripture.
Kind of from the flip perspective, right? Because it's through her that Christ is revealed
to those who dwell upon.
Earth and St. Ignatius was talking about how it was revealed to the stars.
Right. Not to the stars to the angelic beings. And it's through her that it's revealed to those
who dwell upon Earth. Yeah. Because the shepherds find her with the infant Christ.
The demons are being attacked and we're being rescued. And so when we say these things are mysteries,
we're saying that we're unknown even to the angels. We're saying that these are things that
along to gods.
What do we call internal counsel?
Now, there are two different words, both pronounced counsel.
And this causes great trouble for a lot of people
with the name of my other podcast.
They're spelled.
Yes, they're spelled different.
Yes, the whole counsel.
So when we talk about the divine counsel,
when we talk about God's counsel and angelic beings,
that is counsel, C-O-U-N-C-I-L.
Council, which is like your parish council.
So this is a body, a body, a deliberative body.
I hope the parish council is like the Ryan council.
And that was going to make it, I was, I was going to make a joke about only some
members being on parish council.
I guess I just did it.
But yeah.
So, um, the, uh, the other word council, COUNSEL,
refers to wisdom, like keeping your own counsel.
Right.
Like wisdom knows.
Yeah.
Now a counsel, C-I-L, my offer counsel, S-E-L, to someone, a counselor would be that S-E-L
spelling.
So when we say this is God's sort of internal counsel, we're using that S-E-L language.
Meaning we're talking about the Holy Trinity.
We're talking about this is something that is restricted to the Godhead.
the three persons who shared the divine nature.
The mind of God.
Then revealed at a certain time, right?
So we're talking about how the first two mysteries were revealed,
how they were revealed to the angels,
how they were revealed to those who dwell upon earth.
And then of course, the third mystery that St. Ignatius talks about
is still kind of a mystery,
still kind of a secret until the time of Christ crucifixion
and then is revealed through the resurrection
to everyone.
to the angels and to men. And then there is a fourth mystery that has still not been
revealed that is still held within the internal counsel of God. And that is the time of Christ's
glorious appearing. The reason I use that glorious appearing language for everybody
is that comes from St. Paul's pastoral epistles, so it's biblical language. But
But when we translate the green...
or a second coming that kind of implies in English
that Jesus went away somewhere,
like he's gone, like he's not here now
and he's going to come back and be here again.
And of course, that's not what we believe
as Orthodox Christians especially,
because most liturgies, we say Christ is in our midst,
and he is and ever shall be.
And there's that bit where he said,
there's that bit at the end of the gospel,
where he said,
low I am with you always.
even to the end of the age.
Wherever two or three of you are gathered in my name,
I am there in the midst of you, et cetera, et cetera.
So, yeah, so he's not gone somewhere.
But we don't see him the way the Apostle saw him.
And that's why St. Paul's glorious appearing language
that he will appear to us all, that we will all see him.
I think his better language to use in English to communicate it.
But when exactly that is,
knows the day or the hour, right? And that doesn't mean as some, as certain preachers
on television, the internet would have you believe, well, you can't know the day or
the hour, but you can't know the month in the year. No, nobody, nobody knows when at all.
Not even a ballpark figure. No, except that it hasn't happened in the past. Sorry,
No one knows and there's this verse that gives a lot of people a lot of trouble.
And the various people who used to try to prove various things where Christ says not only
just does no human know the day or the hour.
He says not even the angels or even the sun, but only the father.
And this gives people a lot of trouble, some honestly, some not so honestly because they're
trying to use it for some agenda.
the idea that Christ who's a person of the
Trinity who's fully God, is he saying he doesn't know, like how could one person of the Trinity
know something and the other two not know it, right? And so that that gives people a lot of fans.
But if you look at how the earliest readers, which would be the church fathers and early Christian
writers. How they read that, they didn't read that as Christ saying he didn't know.
They read that as Christ saying that it was not his to make known that it was not his to reveal it. Yeah, so so this is the same
Kind of mystery then as the ones that we were just talking about which now have been revealed except this one still hasn't as you see right and there's going to be a time and a place
When that is revealed to angels and to men
But it was not for Christ to do
before his ascension. That was not the point at which that was going to be revealed. It, like Christ's incarnation and his resurrection, is going to be revealed when it happens.
Yep.
Alright, so before we take our second and final break for this episode, we got a message
from Alex Radilescu who asked this.
Plus, fathers, my name is Alex and I'm calling from sunny or land.
Thank you for producing this illuminating, edifying, and entertaining podcast.
You touched on Satan not fully realizing Christ's identity in a previous episode, I believe.
Can you expand on how much Satan would have known as a former member of God's council,
with fallen from that position?
Especially in the light of the miracles that surrounded Christ from the earliest days of his conception,
and the prophecies which he fulfilled.
Thank you so much again for the podcast, and I look forward to hearing your latest episode.
the next episode.
All right, so this is obviously related to a lot of what we're
talking about. And I guess it raises for me the question of, you know, if the Satan is part of the
divine council before he falls, he knows the things that they know. Are there things that he missed out
on later? Right, after his fall, right? There seems to be the sense of hiding these mysteries from all
the angels, because even if you, even if you reveal it to the elect ones, then the rebellious ones
also
would find out. Is there something about being an angelic being, whether your obedience
are fallen, that they're sort of their access to knowledge is the same? I don't know. I'm
just trying to work this out. Help me out here.
Right. Well, this isn't something that was known by the members of the divine council.
Yeah. Okay. So there's that.
Yeah. The end for which man was created was known. And that provoked the devil de jealousy,
example. But these details...
were not known. Right. And until they happened to reveal to any of the angelic beings, so none of them
knew. Yeah, we have to again, angels are vast cosmic intelligences. Right. So their knowledge is not
sort of restricted by sensory organs like ours. I feel like that should be on a t-shirt now.
That's gonna be what it.
Yeah, yeah, we should just call them the the VCI is from now on
Right, but but they're not they're also not omniscient right there are created beings. They're finite
Right, so they don't know everything
right
But they they know far more than we do and they know it differently
They're not like taking in knowledge through their
Five senses right there
Yeah. So, so, so what would be sort of available to be known by any angelic being? Right. All angelic
beings would be able to know that. I know I'm just sort of repeating myself, but, but the point being,
the point being that if, if, if obedient angels can know it, they can't keep it secret from the
rebellious ones. Yeah. Yeah. So this, the, the, the, the image that Saini Nations is giving us is
the sign appears in the heavens.
Angels all go wait what and the sort of the elect angels go wait what yay and
The the fallen spirits or bellia spirits say wait what right no
This is bad, you know
Yeah, all right well fastening okay, well, let's go ahead and go to our second and final break
will be right back. Father Andrew Stephen Daymak and
and talk
or Stephen DeYoung will be back in a moment to take your calls on the next part of the
Lord of Spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF radio.
This is Father Tom Soroka, inviting you to join me every Tuesday.
evening at 9 p.m. Eastern 8 p.m. Central for ancient faith today live. We'll be discussing
issues that you care about from a distinctly orthodox perspective. That's every Tuesday
evening at 9 p.m. Eastern 8 p.m. Central here on Ancient Faith Radio.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits, the Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father
even to young. If you have a question
Call now at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF radio.
Welcome back.
This is the third half of our show.
And just a reminder that this is actually not airing live.
So this is a pre-recorded episode.
So don't call that number tonight.
But we'll get back with you live on our next episode.
next episode.
which will be in just a couple of weeks.
All right, well, so connected with all of that then,
cause it all shows out to be connected in the end.
We got this from our friend Matthew Nehmi
who wrote in and asked this question about this event
that actually just happened when this air,
so as is airing on the 24th of December,
just a few nights ago there was this big conjunction
in the sky that happened between the planets,
Jupiter and Saturn
and if I remember correctly.
And was visible even to the naked eye,
although unfortunately out here in Eastern Pennsylvania,
it was very overcast.
So I looked, you know, but I couldn't see a thing.
I had to look at other people's photos.
Were you able to see it?
Or did you look for it, Father?
I did.
I did not.
We've been getting rain.
You did not.
Oh yeah, well, there you go.
Yeah, but anyway, so there's this event that happened.
And Matthew wrote in to ask about that.
he writes this.
What?
What would the ancients have said about the whole planetary star thing happening on the exact date of the winter's solstice?
Would it have had good or bad connotations to them?
I'm reading that a great conjunction like this has happened only once since the birth of Christ in the 1200s.
And it didn't coincide with the solstice or equinox of which the ancients were obsessed.
So, yeah, I think just as a comment on that, I think that...
I think another one of these is supposed to happen in like
60 or 70 years or something like that.
But I don't know that it's going to happen on the solstice again.
I think that's maybe part of what is making it so relatively rare.
Yeah. So what about this?
I mean, are we seeing the star of Bethlehem here in 2020?
Is that what's going on?
Well, answer to that is no, because as we're going to talk about it this
third half, I think...
the sign in the heavens is something else,
and we're gonna talk about what that is.
But this kind of thing absolutely is the kind of thing
that ancient people took notice of.
Yeah.
And had various means for interpreting,
things like planetary alignments,
planetary alignments on particular days,
comments, anything going on in the heavens,
especially if it broke the regular pattern,
the cops.
or a meteor shower, or if it was rare, right?
Something that very, very rarely,
conjunctions that very rarely happen.
And there were very elaborately developed means
of interpreting these things
in the Mesopotamian world all the way up to
with Rome, they had the sibling books,
which were kept underneath a temple in Palatine Hill
only a particular class of
were allowed to go and reference them.
And whatever something like this happened,
or whatever there was some kind of military disaster,
or there was a plague,
any kind of disaster, or just anything weird in the heavens.
Those weren't separated.
Right.
Anything rare or odd or strange.
Any of those things that they needed to say,
okay, what's going on?
Is this good or bad?
What do we need to do?
Those priests would be sent to consult those books.
Yeah.
and those books would sometimes,
I mean, we're not, we don't have the books,
I'll explain why in a second.
But yeah, it's unclear whether these books
just had an excruciating level of detail
or whether the priests were really good with PR
and would just sort of come out and say,
hey, we looked in the books and this was all prophesied.
Yeah.
All right.
And I mean, it may have been books of vague prophecies
that you could sort of shape, you know,
the priest could sort of interpret how they
wanted to and then come up with something. So maybe a little of both. But they would say things
like we need to take a couple of slaves and bury them alive and then the disaster will pass.
I mean it was that level of stuff. And the reason we don't have them is that when the Western
Roman Empire was falling at the beginning of the fifth century and the barbarians were invading,
a bunch of the still pagan sympathetic citizens of Rome.
decided hey the gods are mad at us because we became Christians. So we need to go check the books,
the pagan books and see what we should do to make things right with them. So the barbarians will
go away and so the Christian governor of Rome burned them publicly. So that would not be an option.
I'm sorry, this is over now.
Yeah, we're not going back to that.
So, yeah.
But so yes, they did notice these things and they were things that there was a special class of priests or like the Magi in Mesopotamia in Persian religion who their job was to interpret these kind of things.
Yeah, and that's who they understand and interpret that's who the mad dyer that show up at at at Jesus's
Place of birth although what a couple of years later
right? Am I reading that correctly? Right. Two years ago. Because when they show up,
Herod kills everybody who's two years old and younger. And they're in a house. I remember there's
a detail that they're in a house probably. They're not still hanging out on the cave. Yeah. More
father Stephen Ruins, your Sunday school, it was two years later with the match I showed up. And
there's nothing that says there were three of them. Yes, there's three gifts. There's three
traditional names but yeah yeah and for those of you who don't know
the three traditional names of the Magi are Melcure, Caspar, and Balthazar. See, I knew that one off
the top of my head, so I'm very proud of myself. There you go. So, yeah, so if we're going to determine
what it is that they saw. Yeah, right. We need to have an idea of what it was that Christ, exactly,
that Christ was born.
And what might have been, you know, what, what's we have an idea of what he was born?
We could have a very good idea of what was going on in the sky at the time, right?
On any given date.
Yeah, fortunately, figuring out what's happening astronomically is just a matter of a lot
of complex math.
Yeah, basically.
So, which people more mathematically inclined than me have done, fortunately.
Yeah.
Right.
not me either.
Yeah.
So, we'll start with what year was Jesus born?
There is no year zero.
Here's another by the way.
Here we are, there's one BC.
There's one BC, and then there's one AD, right?
So zero would be like a point.
It would be like exactly midnight, right?
Yeah.
On that particular day.
and so
though
Our dating system in terms of BC and AD was worked out in the medieval period and isn't
accurate to when Christ was born.
Pretty much for sure.
Right.
Because by the time you get to that zero point, Herod had already been dead for a while.
so that wouldn't work because, you know, assuming that the biblical account is...
true. It's true. Which we do. Right. Right. You know, we're we're not saying let's debunk the Bible, the opposite actually.
Right. But then if Herod is dead, then that means that the events of the Gospels didn't happen because he's a pretty significant character in what's happening there. So he, so it couldn't, it couldn't be your, it couldn't be that zero point. You know.
You know, right, and you don't have to be, you don't have to be.
at Orthodox Christian or a Christian at all to realize that, you know, the New Testament
documents the Gospels have at least some valid historical information about when Jesus
lived, when he was born and when he died and when he was crucified, right? I mean, at least
that there are those people out there who claim Jesus never existed, but they're not scholars
Yeah.
If you have...
wanted to cheer for Bart Irman, which is a hard thing to do with a rare opportunity. He wrote a book,
did Jesus exist, where he just as an atheist who doesn't believe the Bible is true, who thinks that
most of the stuff in the gospels is not true, just goes and dismantles those people who, what
is Jesus did exist, pretty epically without any kind of Christian perspective coming into it,
from a historical perspective it's ridiculous.
Yeah. So yes, when Herod the Great is alive when Jesus is born, he has to die about two years after.
Yeah. And so this has been historically what scholars try to figure out exactly when Jesus was born.
The death of Herod, therefore, is their benchmark. Right. Because the gospel writers don't give us the year.
Yeah. And don't even try.
and, you know, a ruler.
dying is the kind of thing that makes it into records.
Right. Roman records, you know, just all that he says, you know,
Aaron the Great dying. Right.
Aaron the Great, calling him the Great is sort of like, calling Michael Jackson,
the King of Pop or something. It's, you know, it's very relative to a certain
time in place. Right. He's not Alexander the Great. Right.
There's a difference there in grades.
But...
So but his death is recorded.
Now even with that said though, his death is recorded
in ancient records in a certain way.
Because of course, they didn't have our BCAD system.
So for example, what Josephus tells us as a historian
when Herod died, he gives us a couple of benchmarks.
He says, well, he died around the time
This Olympiad was going on and he...
died around the time that these two Roman officials came to power.
The problem with that is those weren't the same time.
Those officials came into power who Josephus mentioned.
I don't want to go too granular on this, but the officials he mentioned came to power
like a year after the Olympia ended.
Even with the ancient records like Josephus, the ancient historians who talked about
here it's death. There are some big
in fall. Yeah. And because of that back in 1890, here come the 19th century
German scholars again. A German scholar identified the date of Herod's death,
quote-forwarded an argument that Herod died in 4 BC. And so based on that, a
couple generations of biblical scholars just said, okay, well that must mean
Jesus was born in 6 BC because it had to be two years before. Right. Right.
Thank you.
And so you will still see this a lot in,
this is the older scholarly consensus.
People who went to universities and studied this
at a certain time were just taught.
The Herodide in 4BC in Jesus was born in 6BC
because of that.
Now that causes some problems
with other parts of the biblical story.
Yeah, because we've got other sort of data points.
Right.
And...
And one of those is in Luke 3, verse 23, it says that Christ begins his earthly ministry
when he's in his 30th year.
So he's 30 years old.
Saint John's Gospel, when it describes Jesus' ministry, has his ministry being three years
long.
And that's been taken to be accurate.
So that would mean Christ was 30...
three years old when he was crucified.
Right.
Well, if he was born in 6 BC,
that would mean that Christ would have been crucified
and risen in 27, 80, 27.
Right.
And first of all, nobody says that's what he was crucified.
But more importantly, the gospel accounts all agree
that the
Saturday, the Sabbath day was the Passover. The Passover fell on the Sabbath. That Sabbath
was a high day. Right. It was the Passover. In the year that Christ was crucified, that's
why he had to be taken down from the cross so quickly, that's why the legs were broken
of the robbers, etc., etc., etc. Right. And so that doesn't work because because in the
CD27 it was it passed over to
not fall on a Sabbath. Yeah, so there's several problems with that making that
date gel. Now fortunately, we've had in the last 25, 30 years or so, people going
back to the question of when Herod the Great died. Yeah. This is one of the good
I sometimes kind of pick on biblical scholarship because I say well you know
people need to write dissertations so you get some of this weird
sometimes, right? But this is a place where it's good, right? People need to write
dissertations, so they're always going back and re-examining old
consensus. Right. Right. So we all had this consensus. You must have died in
4BC. Everyone just says that. But some people who had dissertations to do in
journal articles to write went back and said, hey, how firm is that date? Right? How
Do we really know that?
And again,
without going super granular about it.
If you follow through, like the way Josephus dates things
and the way he counts the years of people's reigns
and you look at the dates when the things
he refers to happen, you actually come to
Herod having died in 1 BC.
And if Herod the Great dies in 1 BC,
that means we have the birth of Christ in 3 BC.
Right.
Which then means that the crucifixion happens
in 8.
D30.
30 when Passover fell on on on a Sabbath day.
Yep.
Right.
So that all lines up them.
It all lines up.
And there's other thing.
I mean, like I said, you can go granular with it.
There are people who here it is supposed to have met and things he's supposed to have
built that wouldn't be possible if he died in 4 BC.
Yeah.
So it's a it's not just a well, there's alternate theory that he died in 1 BC.
There's a much better argument that you died of.
And it makes sense of data both biblical and extra biblical to date it this way.
Yeah, archeological, yeah, because you did a lot of building projects that helps with
things too, because you can figure out when things were built.
Yeah, yeah.
Okay, so we've got the year figured out, right?
Or we should say that a model that fits all of the available data very well.
Right.
Jesus is born in 3BC.
about and here's the one that everyone loves.
to argue about. And I actually wrote a blog post titled, no, Christmas is not
pagan, just stop it because of December 25th, right? Yes. So the dating of the
feast of the Nativity for December 25th is the claim being made that that is
when Jesus was born on that date.
Right.
Right, and there are some people
Right who respond to
Well, it's pagan, right?
That's good that comes from a pagan source that's that's a remake of a pagan holiday
There's some people who try to respond to that by doubling down and saying no Jesus was born on December 25
Yeah, yeah, and I should I should probably say that actually
You know even if you if you accept this idea that is derived from paganism that the data
is derived from paganism.
There are some people that their response to that is,
aha, checkmate Christians.
And then there's some people that are like,
Oh no, this was chosen quite deliberately
to crush paganism that exists.
Pagan festivals exist on it.
So there are both sort of anti-Christians and Christians
who both accept this idea that the date has something
to do with paganism and the question is just
whether that's good or bad.
Yeah.
But so but I just want to I just want to say that that there is a fundamentalist reflex
right where
Liberal theory or wacky theory comes along and we were spotted that not by a reality-based approach
Okay, what really happened where does the December 25th date really come from but with I have to defend the December 25th date
Yeah, because if I don't
of Christianity falls apart, which of course is not the case.
Right?
Right.
So so there are several problems with that whole hypothesis.
You talk about some of them in your article.
For example, a lot of the things that are pointed to
when these pagan feasts, they say, oh, look, here's these elements
of these pagan feasts.
That sounds kind of like Christmas.
Even though a lot of it is stuff that didn't come into the
celebration of Christmas until centuries later.
Yeah.
and it ends out a lot like Chris.
is geographically local to particular places. Right. Yeah. Oh, look, you've got Christmas trees.
They're spagan as well. I'm like, okay, Christmas trees.
You know, not everybody uses them and, you know, yeah. Chris Albert was German. And so he and
Queen Victoria had one. That's why people have Christmas trees today. Yeah. That's the, because
of Queen Victoria, it does not go back past that. No one in England had a Christmas tree before that.
Yeah, anyway.
So...
Yeah, yeah, and in many cases, what's that are valid? A lot of them are from the post-Christian
version of those pagan feasts. People tend to forget that things went both ways. That
especially in the late second and early third centuries when Christianity was waxing and
paganism was waning, a lot of pagan groups and cults.
and even philosophical schools started taking on elements of Christianity to try to appeal to,
you know, what clearly the masses were looking for in religion from their perspective.
Yeah.
That this seems to be where people are going, they're gravitating to these things in Christianity.
Well, we need to take those things on board in our pagan religion to keep these people.
And then there's another layer which we mentioned earlier when we were talking about Norse myths,
which is that a lot of the information that we have about ancient paganism.
is preserved and commented on and edited by Christians.
Right, and so yeah, so there's editing that goes on too.
Just try and integrate things.
So all that has to be taken into account.
So all that evidence in terms of the actual practices
kind of falls apart when you push on it.
You also have the basic issue of,
it presupposes that Christians
didn't have any kind of winter festival.
Yeah, so they needed one because they saw pagans had one
Pagans have one and we have all these people who used to be pagans that are now Christians and they're gonna keep
Celebrating the pagan festival unless we come up with something. Yeah, right?
Like it's the theory and the big problem with that is there were already a bunch of winter Christian festivals
Part of this is because
American Christianity is Puritan Christianity and so the only two feast days we
even kind of have left are Christmas at Easter.
Yep.
Right?
Like in the American religious consciousness, those are the only two Christian Vs.
Ed, for Puritans, Christmas wasn't even one.
But the original war on Christmas was being waged by Christians.
Yes.
That's right.
So there's only those two sort of in the popular mind.
But if you go into any, you know, if you go an inch deep into any traditional form of
Christianity, you find out there's a whole lot of feasts.
I'm sorry.
There's feasts of saints every day of the year.
But already you have, for example,
the Feast of St. Stephen on December 27th,
there's a strong argument,
and again, I won't go granular with it,
but that the reason St. Stephen's martyrdom
is so prominent in the book of Acts
is that it's actually explaining the origin of his feast day,
that his memory is martyrdom.
Already being celebrated.
Yeah, we're being celebrated already.
by the end of the first century.
Yeah.
And then he was being remembered.
Since he was the first martyr, right?
And the memories of martyrs, like the Maccabee in martyrs,
were already being celebrated by Jewish groups at this time.
So this wasn't like this huge new thing.
This was a lateral move for early Christians
from a Jewish background to commemorate him as a martyr.
And so he has this chunk of the acts of the apostles
devoted to him because it's explaining
Here's the origin of this feast.
But even if you don't want to go there, we know for a fact that the Feast of Theophany or
called Epiphany in the West, but centered around Christ's baptism.
Yes.
On January 6th.
Yeah, and that's actually, as my understanding of the liturgical history, that that feast
originally was a combination.
It was essentially a feast of the appearing of Christ, which then included both his birth
and his baptism.
Yes.
like that's the sort of a-
original Christmas as January 6th,
and the December 25th date is added a little bit later.
But the point being, yeah, the point being that Jesus's
birth was being celebrated, but on a different date,
again, not too far away.
I mean, it's just 12 days later, right?
Not in the winter.
But yeah, and then eventually they get sort of separated out
to be two different feasts.
Right. And so if, if they,
been worried about pagans still celebrating the pagan feasts, right? What you would expect
to see is a bunch of the pagan stuff being taken over by St. Stephen's Day and or the
often. You wouldn't expect them to add another day. Yeah. Right. You'd expect the pagan
things to be integrated into those, right? Which of course isn't what we see. So again,
that argument that it comes from paganism falls apart. So when you get at the beginning
of the 4th century.
starting in the West and then coming east, we know when Christmas, when the
piece of the activity was for celebrating in Constantinople because we have
St. John Chrysostom's sermons and he says hey this is the first time we're
celebrating this here.
That's the end of the holiday.
Yeah, thanks to Hobbily.
We know 401 and 402 is what it showed up in Constantinople as a feast but it started
earlier in the 300s in the early 4th century in the West.
So why does it show up then?
Right?
Paganism does not adequately explain it, because we just said, like a fall.
Especially because paganism is kind of on the wane, especially by that point, right?
It's starting to get...
It's almost, it may not be dead, but it's coughing up blood, right?
It's almost...
Right.
It's in its last gasp at that point in history.
And this really comes out of, though a bit indirectly, the Council of Nicee.
right and one of its decisions. The council and I see it did not say anything about what's in the Bible and what's not but they did.
Yeah, they didn't say a can.
They did say something about when we should be celebrating POSCA.
Yep. When we celebrate the Christian Passover. Right. That now gets called in Germanic languages Easter.
Right another false flag pig and his paint a cake
Right? I mean, I'll just point this out, right? So so so people will sometimes say, oh, Easter. Well, that's that's the name of a goddess blah blah blah blah. I'm like, okay, number one, there is only a handful of places in the world where it's even called that and they're all Germanic language speaking places. Okay, most are calling it some version of the word Paska.
Number two, it's really just about the fact that it fell at a certain time of year that
happened to have been named for that goddess.
So it just was kind of named after the...
month. And as I like to point out, if you celebrate the fourth of July, that does not mean
you are celebrating the divine Julius Caesar, after whom that month is named. You know,
as the fourth of July has as much to do with Julius Caesar as Easter has to do with the
goddess oyster, however you pronounce it. So just wanted to put that in there.
Yeah. As it aside, since we're in since we're in full debunking mode now.
Yeah, yeah.
Um, so...
At the time of the council, and I see there were different groups of Christians who were,
everybody was celebrating the Christian Passover, the death and resurrection of Christ.
Right?
Which happened at the Jewish Passover, and so they saw it as we're continuing to celebrate
the Passover, but we're celebrating it in this fulfilled sense, because there's been
a fulfillment of what was seen as sort of an icon or image in the deliverance of his
from Egypt, now has come to its fullness in Christ's delivery of humanity from slavery
to sin and death.
And so, but they're disagreeing on exactly when to celebrate it.
So you have Christians who are celebrating it basically at the same time as the Jewish
Passover.
Just whatever the Jewish Passover falls, that's when we celebrate.
Yeah, which could be any day of the week.
Right.
could be Thursday, could be, but just going by the Jewish calculation. You have other Christians
who it was determined that it happened on March 25th historically, and so they were doing it on
March 25th, whatever date that fell on. Sort of the way we celebrate a lot of other feasts,
Right, right.
And then there were questions who were doing sort of a very...
of what we're doing now either they were doing it on the Sunday nearest the Jewish Passover or the Sunday nearest the
25th or right they said it needs to be on the Lord's Day, right it needs to be on the day of the week that Christ rose but
You in that vicinity
right and so and so this all had to be settled right because it was determined hey
Christians need to all celebrate this together at the Council of Nicae and so they settled on the means of
calculating that they settled on which is room
slated to the way in which the date of the Passover was calculated by the Jewish community,
but slightly different and not done by the Jewish community.
Yeah, and so, and this episode is not about all of that.
All that.
Yeah, the point is that they came up with this, this dating and then out of that comes the
date of the annunciation.
March 25th.
So we have
these Christians who are used to celebrating on March 25th. And so what is proposed in the
deliberation of the Councils is that there was a Jewish tradition that the date of a prophet's death
would be the same date as his conception. Yeah, which is this idea called integral age.
that your age is exactly an integer basically.
Right. We won't get into go now the rabbit hole now of whether there's ever any evidence that there was such a Jewish tradition.
But they seem to think yeah, they seem to think that there was. Yes, that was set forth as part of the settlement. And therefore,
therefore if if the date that Christ was crucified as March 25th, then that would also have been the date of his conception. Right. Right.
And so that was the beginning of the celebration of what we now call the feast of the Annunciation or in Greek the evangelism of the Theotokos.
Yes.
And the archangel Gabriel comes and announces to the Theotokos that she's going to give birth to a son.
That was going to be celebrated on March 25th.
fifth and if you're using the the old Julian calendar because of that sometimes
Pascal falls on...
March 25th.
Yes.
Yep.
Right.
And you end up with what's called Keriopasca, which is this mix, this liturgical mix of
the adciation and Posca.
Yeah.
Mega, mega feast.
Combines like Voltron and you get, yeah, sort of the mega-sword of feast.
So, to mix my metaphor.
And I should add, since we just said all that actually, if you're interested in kind of a
little bit of the homework behind some of that. There's a
good article out there by Dr. William Tai, TIGHE, called Calculating Christmas, which appeared
a number of years ago in Touchstone Magazine, and you can find it online, actually. You can
just read it. And it talks specifically about this question of integral age and the
annunciation and the whole point is the one that we're about to make, which is if you know
that the enunciation is on March 25th, then nine months after a baby...
conceived, he's born so therefore December 25th. That's where December 25th comes from.
Right. Therefore December 25th. So that's where that date comes from. Yep.
And it's not based on a historical memory of the church that that's the calendar date that Jesus
was born on. Yeah. It's not based on that. It's a the surgical date when it's celebrated. Yeah. And
I'll say like, you know, even if it had been the keys that the church chose to pick something
replace a pagan feast, that's not syncretism. That's, you know, that's saying we're taking this,
you know, we're taking, we're reclaiming, yeah, we're reclaiming. Yeah, right. It's not the case
for Christmas as date. It's not. But the point is, that's not a problem and it's not syncretism.
It wouldn't be a syncretism.
It's really about conquest, really.
that the one who got is retaking what belongs to him wherever it.
I mean, the same thing happens, like for instance, where pagan temples where the the
altars would get destroyed by Christians and then a Christian altar would be set up and
then the place would be sanctified and they would put relics of scenes in there so as to
drive out the demonic presence, right?
So it's not syncretism.
But again, that's not what's going on in Christmas in any event.
date is really about the enunciation. It's related.
the Nancy right right and this is this is kind of important because we don't take
into account the fact that all the months and all the days and everything were
dedicated to and governed by these spiritual powers represented by the stars
and constellations we've been talking about. So you got to have a liturgical
calendar. So the Christian the Christian Festival calendar is reclaiming time
from the demonic powers.
Hi, Doc.
Rocus. I don't know she does either but just a case. Someone tell her maybe she'll listen to this one.
She's busy editing a really poorly written book manuscript right now by you.
So I could say that. But yeah, it's the reclaiming of time from the
but the same way you were going to click...
physical space as sacred space with those temples we're also reclaiming the
days and months of the year. For God and those are being given over to the
saints to take in from the powers that had them and given to the saints.
Like St Stephen. So but to our thrust here hey we're finally going to get to our
topic now. Right, that means that looking at December 25th, 3BC,
and trying to figure out what was going on to the stars isn't going to lead us to the
sign in the heavens. That's not going to do it. What will lead us to it, I think, interestingly,
is what I think is ultimately a bad interpretation of Revelation 12.
All right. Well, what's that all about then? This is a case where you do the math problem wrong,
but you still come up with the right answer, I think. You arrive at the correct answer through
through the wrong procedure.
So some folks, and by some folks,
I mean a few scholars and a lot of people on the internet have looked at
Revelation chapter 12
Which begins with St John saying he saw a sign in the heavens
right so
Boom okay something going on in the heavens and then goes on to describe
The woman standing on the moon clothes with the sun
The dragon at her feet, right? This is this
this apocalyptic description of the
of Christ and the dragon, the devil's attempts to destroy Christ and the church. And we'll
end up doing an episode at Revelation 12. I'm sure at some point. We've already talked about it
a little a couple of times in terms of the fall of Satan in the podcast. But so they say, well, if
this is a sign in the heavens, what if this is talking about astrological phenomena? Yeah, sure.
So natural question.
What if the woman is the virgin Virgo, right? And what if the sun means the sun's in this position and standing on the moon so the moon's in that position.
And things start to stretch a little, right? Like the dragon becomes like Scorpio because it's some of the Babylonian stuff. He's more of a dragon than a scorpion.
Yeah, so the job where maybe it's a bugging that needs to go on
Yeah, and it starts out strong and then it gets a little shake here and it's got it.
But what you end up getting described, and there's a star that appears related to the
constellation Leo, the lion Judah, right?
So you end up coming up with this conception and I think it's a little bit of work to get
it to fit Revelation 12.
But it just so happens that this sort of massive conjunction of stars, planets, et cetera,
at the side of the mood.
all happens in 3BC on a particular day.
Yeah.
And so this is why I say, I don't think that's a good interpretation of Revelation 12.
I don't think it works for interpreting that text to say that St. John gets to what we
now call the beginning of chapter 12 and says, oh by the way, do you want to know what
day Jesus was born?
Yeah.
And then sort of goes back to his other topics, right?
I don't think that works.
Yeah.
other people do, but I don't. But I think that going through all that has led us
to, hey, 3PC is the year Jesus was born and there is this conjunction that
happens in 3PC on this particular day that has all of this massive symbolism
regarding kingship, the tribe of Judah, all of these things.
And Ed is...
is exceedingly rare to happen at all.
One of the reasons I say a lot of people at the Internet
talk about this is there was a big fear
because this particular conjunction happened again in 2017.
And so certain people were super certain that,
well, hey, if this is what happened when Jesus was born,
then that means when this happens again,
he's coming back.
Yeah.
And that's just one of several apocalypse.
that I've survived over the course of my life.
See you under the world again.
Right, so that...
I have to go find.
Right, so I don't buy that, and I want to make clear,
I don't buy that as the correct interpretation of Revelation 12.
But it has gotten us to, hey, in 3 BC, that your Jesus was born,
this confluence of celestial things happened that would definitely be
the most prominent and rare thing that happened to you.
thing that happens.
that year for the Magi to notice and it's the kind of thing that they would have
noticed and would have clued them in that a king, a significant king had been, had been born.
And this happens to be a date, another point for this is that this happens to be a date that was
very significant for the Judean people. Yeah, so just to kind of underline the point that you're
you're making here, it's...
Yes, something really big did happen in the sky.
Like really big did happen in the sky in 3BC,
but that's not what Revelation 12 is talking about.
Yes, right.
Yes, God.
That's what I've say.
All right, good.
Yes, just to, yeah.
I just wanted to spell it out.
It keeps, like, way.
Very quick.
I'm not sure how to follow that.
OK.
But, but yeah.
So, but, but through that sort of biblical interpretation
chicaneery, right?
We discovered this astrological thing that happened.
Yeah.
And so the date that that fell on on the Jewish calendar that was being used
by the second temple Judeans at that time is
Tishri won the first day of the month of Tishri on the Jewish calendar.
This is a majorly
significant date on the calendar. First of all, it's New Year's Day. Right. So Rosh Hashana, right?
The Yav Rosh Hashana on the Jewish agricultural calendar. Right.
I don't want to go too...
who, gradually, are on this, there are actually two Jewish calendars.
We may talk about that at some point.
It's New Year's on the agricultural calendar.
Pascas New Year's on the Festival calendar.
Oh, fun.
And we still kind of have that in the Orthodox Church.
Yeah, that's a big rest.
Yeah.
We do have kind of multiple calendars going on in the Orthodox Church,
even just within a single parish.
Right.
This is the equivalent of the addiction on the modern Orthodox calendar.
And it's around the same time of year, not coincidentally.
It's New Year's Day.
This is also the day that David was coronated or crowned as king of Judah.
And so it became sort of the inauguration day for all the kings of Judah throughout
Judah's history.
So this makes it obviously a very messianically significant day.
Yeah, right.
Right?
The Messiah is the...
of David as we talked about last episode.
This is a majorly significant day.
This is also the day that Noah was born.
Oh man.
Based on, you can calculate his birthday
based on how old it says he was during different months
in the flood story.
So I mean, would the birthday of Noah,
but I mean, is that a liturgical commemoration
on the Jewish calendar?
Yeah, that was part of the understanding of that day.
All the things going on that other day.
Yeah, and Noah.
See again, we just read the story of the flood. We start with beginning of Genesis 6 and the Nephilim and stuff
because we get excited by the giant
but
when he's born
Lambic as this prophecy about Noah about how God's gonna save the world through him
Save the creation through him. So Noah really takes on he's this this savior figure and
And it's through him that the world's berseror of he becomes sort of the in the way that
was the father of that previous age. He becomes sort of the father of this new age.
Yeah. He is.
The begins after the flood. Yeah.
So there's some New Year connection there. Yeah. He's a new Adam. Yeah, right?
Yeah. And there's, when you read, again, when we do our inevitable series on First
Enic, there's tradition surrounding his miraculous birth where he's born sort of glowing and
talking and it's father sort of like wait a
see it.
Nephilim? Like what's going on here? Exactly. He's no
little giant. It has to be sort of reassured, right? He has
edict show up. You know, God says edict to go and tell him, no,
it's okay. He's really your son. And St. Matthew kind of
inverts that whole story with the story of Joseph, with
Joseph at St. Joseph the patrol sort of doubts first like his
when the Thaotokas gets pregnant, he's kind of like, you
Yeah, what's going on at it age?
comes to him and reassures him that it's not a human.
Not a son.
Yeah, so it's sort of inverted there.
But so yeah, there's all these Noah's birth traditions that could take it up in that
day.
So all of that is on that day.
And there's this major rare astrological Judah king-related event on that day in 3bc.
So all of this comes together.
for a pretty strong argument.
If you're good at pick a day, everything we've laid out
this third half, I think, other than Revelation 12.
They say really good argument for this particular day.
And that day on our modern calendar was September 11th.
There you go.
Which of course now has a bit of an apocalyptic significance.
Overtoed all its own.
For us Americans, yeah.
Yeah.
So, okay.
Okay, so are you saying then that there's this astrological astronomical event that occurs
some sort of major conjunction that they would have seen?
And that is the star that the Magi C and the E.
This is what the Magi C, this is what St. Ignatius is talking about, this is what St. Paul
is talking about.
Yeah.
And is this then the same angel who's...
speaks to the shepherds.
Is that what we should read this?
No, so that's a different angel making that announcement.
Yeah.
OK.
Gotcha.
Wow.
Well, it's been a wild ride.
But fun, as always.
All right, well, let's just offer some last thoughts.
Number one, one of the reasons I love doing this show
because I read the Bible in a new way that I did not before.
And honestly, it makes so many things kind of fit together.
But the other thing that I wanted to especially say is,
you know, we talked about pagan astrology
and syncretism and all that kind of stuff over and over again.
And I think that sometimes modern Christians understandable
fear of those things makes it so that we throw
the baby with the bath water so to speak, right? So we know that horoscopes are nonsense
and so therefore anything that looks like astrology is bad and not Christian. Well as we've seen,
that's simply not the case. I mean the Bible has astrology in it. It is a different character
for sure than pagan astrology and it's definitely a different character than the kind of modern
unfortunate telling type. Right?
And this is one of our persistent themes in this podcast is the things that paganism got right.
But then also commenting on the ways that they got those right things wrong. And to me,
this particular one really shows that. And I hope has opened up your eyes, listeners, to as Father
So Stephen is writing layers of meaning that are also pressed.
there and actually show how utterly rich the scriptures are. Just rich, so rich, so many layers upon
layers upon layers of meaning, and that it's not just stuff for us to hear and say, oh that's cool. I
mean, there are definitely moments that I was saying, oh that's cool because of this cool. But rather that
that as we marvel at the complexity and the glory and the beauty of the
a sponsoring revelation of God to men, that we would be drawn to love him and to worship him.
And one of the things that this also does for me is just seeing how all of these pieces
fit together so seamlessly is for me a reassurance of the truth of all of it.
It is more than any human being could ever design.
It really is.
And...
that what God is saying to us in all of this
has a very specific content,
which is that he has sent his son,
and he sent his son to defeat these evil powers
that were enslaved to rescue us from that bondage,
and to set us among the stars,
among his divine counsel.
So, glory to God in the highest.
I mean, that's what the angels say.
So that's what we say as well.
well in terms of my final thought.
When we talk about the fallenness of humanity,
and we're inevitably going to go into more detail about that
and how there's actually three falls of humanity.
When we talk about the fallenness of humanity,
we've got a pretty good luck in our understanding
of our fallenness of this separation
disjunction, this alienation between us and God. In fact, in some circles of American Christianity,
that's about all you've got in terms of human fallenness. But many of us have a little larger
view of that. We understand our fallenness in terms of not only the alienation between us and
God but the alienation between us and our fellow human beings, that...
that there are rifts and gaps and pain caused by sin
that separate us from each other.
And we understand that in Christ,
this the communion between us and God,
the communion between us and each other is restored.
But there's a third major element
of our fallenness in the scriptures
that we've lost sight of almost completely.
And that's the separation and the disjunction.
and the schism between us as humans and the rest of the creation.
This alienation that Adam receives between him and the ground from which his food is going to come.
The even more complete alienation that can experiences after he sins.
We don't go outside and hear the stars sing to us anymore.
We don't relate to them.
We don't relate to the...
animals. We don't feel the ground under our feet and we don't work it for most of our food.
We don't know or raise the animals that we eat or the animals that serve us. We're completely
disconnected and in this way, as in all three ways, secularism and materialism are the
day new mother the apex of the fallenness of humanity.
Secularism and
And materialism deny that God speaks and he acts and often even that he exists, denies
that the whole spiritual world that we talk about so much on this podcast exists, deny
that our departed loved ones still exist, to the departed saints still exist, it denies
and rejects the real communion between people that separated us as individuals and isolated
us.
And it's also separated us.
Modern materialism has separated us from the rest of the creation.
They're just rocks floating in space or gas balls that have nothing to do with us in our lives.
Trees are trees, rocks are rocks.
Concrete is better because it's smoother and it's man-made.
And we're completely alienated and separated.
But the truth is that part of what Christ does in our salvation is also
reunite us with
the rest of creation. He also reunites us with our departed loved ones. He reunites us
with the angelic beings in worship and in praise. And through theosis, he unites us with
them truly in his counsel and in the heavens. But he also reunites us with the earth that
we live on. He reunites us with the nature that surrounds us. We see the saints who are
even reunited with.
sometimes wild animals who come and serve them
and live with them.
And so a big part of what I hope this podcast
can help all of us do is try to break down
that barrier as well, that we would not only,
as we talked about in the last couple of podcasts,
get to know the saints, but we would also get to know
our fellow creatures.
that we would get to see how all of creation, all of God's creation is connected,
connected to us, connected with itself, and how God works His love and
communicates with us, shows His love for us, and works out of love to bring us
closer to Him and to work at our subit salvation through all of the creation,
including the stars in the sky and the sun in the moon. So I hope we've done a
little piece of that today.
a little piece of that beginning of that reunion where we could sort of take
our place again in the whole world of God's creation that He's made and He's
blessed us to be a part of.
Amen.
That is our show for today.
Thank you very much for listening.
This episode was not live, but in the future, if you would like to connect to us during
a live broadcast, you can call in.
You can also email us at Lord of Sp-
at ancientfaith.com. You can message us at our Lord of Spirits Podcast Facebook page.
We read everything, but unfortunately we can't respond everything, but we do save what you send
for possible use in future episodes. And join us for our actual live broadcast on the second and
fourth Thursdays of the month at 7 p.m. Eastern 4 p.m. Pacific. Don't forget to like our Lord of
Spirits Podcast Facebook page while you're at it. Leave a recommendation. Join our Divine Council
Facebook discussion group and then invite all you
your friends to both.
And if you leave a review on Apple Podcasts Facebook
or wherever you get your podcasts,
then that raises the visibility of the show
and gets more people connected.
And finally, be sure to go to www.engshadfaith.com,
Stroke Support, and help make sure we
and lots of other AFR podcasters stay on the air.
Thank you, God bless you.
Christ is born, glorify Him.
You've been listening to the Lord of Spirits,
with Orthodox Christian priests,
Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Steve.
even to young, a listener-supported presentation of ancient faith radio.
And I beheld, and I heard the voice of many angels round about the throne, and the beasts,
and the elders, and the number of them was 10,000 times 10,000, and thousands of thousands,
saying with a loud voice, worthy is the land that was slain to receive power, and riches,
and wisdom, and strength, and honor, and glory, and blessing.
Revelation chapter 5 verses 11