was 1963 and he was 83 years old.
As soon as they finished caring for his body, the bell rang for the exit of his self-poker.
In a little while, the self-poker was passing before his house.
His funeral took place on Holy Saturday.
His relatives informed the fathers of Kata Kalamana Sterry and asked them to serve 40 liturgies
for him, which they did.
May the memory of Constantin D.P. eternal.
Amen.
This sign was shared with you on ancient faith radio, that you may believe that Jesus is the Christ, and that believing you may have life in His name.
In 1892, a young man left his home in the coastal foothills of Lebanon and searched for a better life.
Coming to America with his newlywed wife, he found work as a traveling peddler before settling on a small farm in Central Nebraska.
Years later, personal tragedy and an unexpected midnight visit from a saint changed the course of his life.
seeing the desperate need of his fellow Orthodox Christians and heeding God's call
He would spend the rest of his life traversing the great plains as a circuit
writing priest, known to his thousands of parishioners as father Nicola Yanney. His legacy stands
alongside that of St. Rafael Halloweeny, his mentor as a Seminole force in the American Orthodox
Church of Ardae. Here is his grace, Bishop Basil. He was ministering to his own people who had
the Spanish flu, even though he was warned that it was dangerous and of course very inevitable.
He insisted on visiting them, not only caring to them the sacrament and anointing them,
You can fit.
preparing some of them for death of course.
But he also brought them grocery that they needed in their homes.
Apostle to the Plains, available now on store.
AncientFaith.com.
Again, that is store.
AncientFaith.
dot com.
Glory to Jesus Christ, glory forever,
you're listening to ancientfaithradio.com.
He will be a staff for the righteous with which for them to stand and not...
to fall, and he will be the light of the nations, and the hope of those whose hearts are troubled.
All who dwell on the earth will fall down and worship him, and they will praise and bless
and celebrate with song the Lord of Spirits.
1st Inoc, chapter 48, verses 4-5.
The modern world doesn't acknowledge but is nevertheless haunted by spirits, angels,
demons, and saints.
In our time, many year into break free of the prison of a flat, secular material.
to see and to know reality as it truly is.
What is this spiritual reality like?
How do we engage with it well?
How do we permeate everyday life with spiritual presence?
Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew Stephen Damick,
and Father Stephen De Young post this live Colin show
focused on enchantment in creation.
The union of the scene and unseen as made by God
and experienced by mankind throughout history.
Welcome to the Lord of S-
spirits. Good evening everyone. A
blessed feast to the ascension to
you. This is our 20th episode.
Welcome back to the Lord of
Spirits podcast where we walk in the
footsteps of well no not giants.
I'm father and your Stephen
Damick and Emma is Pennsylvania and
my co-host father Stephen D. Young
is with me from Lafayette, Louisiana.
And if you are listening to us
live, you can call in at 855 AF radio.
that's 855237
2, 3, 4, 6 and Matushka Trudy will be taking your calls tonight and will get your calls
in the second part of today's show.
So like I said, the Orthodox Church just began a celebration of the great feast to the
ascension of our Lord God and Savior Jesus Christ and that is what we're going to be discussing
tonight on the podcast.
As we saw last time with the resurrection of appearances of Christ, many treatments
of ascension also treat it as little more than an epilogue to the action of the crucifix
and resurrection. Some more diligent Orthodox examinations of the ascension show how this feast
demonstrates Christ's divinity and also how he elevates humanity to sit even upon the throne
of God. Tonight we are going to look at the ascension, especially as it culminates in the enthronement
of Christ, and we're going to start with footprints. Now we're not talking about the popular
footprints in the sand palm, nor about the variation that notes that the sand people run.
and single file so as to hide their numbers.
It turns out that within or just outside numerous temples
for worshipping various gods throughout the earth,
there are examples of something called a Petro-Somato glyph.
Everybody looked it up on Wikipedia right now.
What is that?
What is a Petro-Somato glyph?
Well, it's usually a footprint carved into rock.
So fathers Stephen take us back over 3,000 years
to Northway.
to a ruined archaeological site called Ain Dada.
So, yes, today's secret word is petrosomatic glyph.
So kids, whenever anyone says petrosomatic glyphs scream really loud.
Yes, I caught that one. I caught that reference.
So, yeah. Footprints.
Yeah, well technically there are a variety of petrosomatic.
Yes, right. There's various shapes.
Yeah, but anybody part
carved into rock. Yes, and I have to say I have to take credit right now because I
posted pictures of gigantic footprints in our Lord of Spirits Facebook group
yesterday and and everyone believed that we were going to be talking about
giants. And so I just have to say that I'm very very proud of myself because
to whom I was truly threw him off.
You've also deeply disappointed the Sasquatch enthusiasts.
Yes, yes, there are several people who wanted to talk about Sasquatch.
I'm like, you know, Sasquatch as big as he is does not have meter long feet.
Because that's that's the size of footprints we're looking at, right?
Right.
Which is about three times human size.
So that would make it the footprint of something about 15 feet tall indeed.
Yes.
Dun dun dun.
But not a giant, not a giant close.
Yes.
Right. Right. So the most common kind of petro-somatic glyph is footprints.
Right. As you were saying. And you find these outside of temples across time and across
the globe. So we have a couple examples and the one you mentioned to start out with,
That's it. Aindara which we're assuming that's a pronunciation
I don't know, I'm assuming it's Iane or something like that, but I can't do that too many times.
And we're going to do an Asian language in a minute too, and we'll totally get that one wrong.
But like the Lutheran say, symbolically, right?
Yes.
Well, plus there's no speakers of those languages, you know, actually around to correct your pronunciation.
So they're all gone, so we can guess.
Well, maybe.
Maybe.
I found that the modern people descended from those people are still pretty particular about how you love them.
They do have some opinions about how their language
sort of been pronounced 3,000 years ago.
But so the site in Aindara has unfortunately now been destroyed
in the current Syrian civil war.
And we're not going to get into who did it or why
because they're conflicting reports.
Yes.
But in the process, it's been destroyed.
But it was fairly well documented before that.
and there are lots of photos online.
and other places where you can see the remains of the temple and the giant carved cherubim and
all of those things. But one of the prominent features were these two
footprints, right, a right and left footprint, at the entryway to the temple sanctuary proper.
That as you mentioned are about a meter long, about three times.
human size. Right. And this is a temple to our old friend Bale, or Bale. And this is the Bale,
like Bale Haddad, right? Is that the one? Yes. Yes. Yes. Which doesn't mean like he's some guy
named, because like Haddad is a very common surname in Spanish these days. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah.
It's not actually related. But yeah. Yeah. This is the Ciro Hittite Bale. Right. If you want to be,
If you want to get fancy.
there is there is a whole book I just discovered and just ordered. This shows you the things that show up on my reading list.
That is just a catalog of all the different names for bail arranged in a flow chart of like hierarchy of places over time.
Right.
Now this is one to read out loud, you know, when you've got people over and you're sitting
around the fire, you know, relax it.
Yeah.
an ideal book like to take on an airplane when I don't want to be talked to because they
say, hey, what's your reading? And then you show them. And then you can fly in silence
for the rest of your trip. But so yes, this is this is that bail out of the bales. And
this this temple was built around the late 11th early 10th century BC. Yeah. And what
What yeah, I was just a 3000 years
plus or minus. Right. And the foundations and the base and everything so we could see the layout and all that were intact. Right. And part of what made it so important was that's within about 100 years or so of Solomon's Temple. Right. And if people want to take a look and see what this looks like while you're listening.
you can go to Wikipedia and look up iindara a-i-n space d-a-r-a and click the the the the article
that says archaeological site,
and you see some really great pictures
of the place that we're talking about right now,
including the footprints.
Yes.
But now to give you an idea,
since I claimed these were across time
and all around the globe,
if you go to Begonne,
I'm guessing that's how it's pronounced,
which is in Myanmar, aka Burma.
Right.
Begonne is one of the holy cities there,
which can
contains several temples. And at one of them, right at the entryway to the small shrine,
it's a Buddhist shrine, is carved into the stone, the right footprint of the Buddha.
Right. And also again, there is a Wikipedia article called something like Buddha's Footprints
or something like that. That's kind of fun. Yeah. And that's from the 11th century AD.
So we have kind of a symmetry.
there. Yes, right.
Yes, right.
Other side of the globe from the Northeast Syria.
Right.
So, why do we have these outside temples?
Well, these footprints sometimes joined with other footprints in the temple itself and
other depictions, whether in statuary or in frescoes or barley for what have you carving
in the walls. Trace a path that was walked by the God or divine or semi-divine
being or in the case of Buddha and lightened being. Right from the entrance of the
temple structure to the place where they were seen to be sitting. Right. That
That covers both the Buddha and Bale and whoever else.
Yeah, and I think it should be noted that especially if you start looking around for these things and you look at pictures of them
In some cases they are very realistic looking in terms of actually shaped like a human foot, although again very big
And then in other cases they're very stylized, right?
And in some cases it seems like the locals are saying
No, this is where this God or
you know demigod walked this is an actual
footprint that was left in the rock by this being. And in other cases, like, especially
the stylized ones, you can see like no one is saying that, right? It is deliberately
made to be, you know, beautiful or symbolic or whatever. And it's a footprint. They made
a footprint in the rock, either as you said, right outside the temple or inside the temple.
So there's some variation on this point as to whether or not there's a claim of some
some kind of
of divine intervention that happened at that particular place, right?
So that's just that's another kind of important point, I think.
Yeah. Also, some people just have weird feet, man.
That's true. Maybe in some cases, the bunions, you know, yeah,
the boot, the boot has a foot that has like flower petals and stuff, you know,
in grade in it. Yeah, I don't know.
So yeah, and so why
Why would this be embedded in the temple structure?
Why would you do this?
And it's because we tend to think of temples in very modern American terms.
I think of them as like worship spaces.
So we're going to do this worship activity.
Even if we have a concept of ritual, we're going to do this ritual activity.
and we need a space that will hold the number of people.
we're going to have, and then we need certain objects
to actually do the thing, and that's how we think
about the space.
But that of course wasn't the case in the ancient world
and the ancient world, the space itself is part
of the ritual and part of the liturgics.
Right.
Right, so it's not just a question of capacity
in accoutrements.
Right, it's a question.
Yeah.
How is what we're doing embedded in the structure itself?
Right. And, and you know, we still have that concept, right? So like if you walk into a theater,
it's designed to make theater possible, right? Or if you walk into a basketball arena,
and you see the basketball hoops up there in, you know, the kind of flooring that's down there and the seating that's around it,
all these things are designed to make basketball possible. It's not just, okay, we need a space to play this game in.
that the space and the way it's set up is
designed for what's happening.
Right?
So it's not like we don't have that concept.
And it's interesting.
I mean, this is kind of a rabbit trail somewhat.
But it's interesting to look at, for instance, where there's
actually a book which I've never bought.
But I think I kind of get the point from just the title.
The book is titled When Church Became Theater.
And it's basically about how church architecture altered
altered in the last couple of hundred years.
in many places from the traditional church architecture
to a theatrical style space and what that says and does
with regards to the kind of thing that happens
inside that particular place.
So this is something that we know,
but it's not something we tend to think about
when it comes to religious practices these days.
It's mostly about, like you said, capacity and decor,
for rather than a sense of...
setting up the space to do a particular thing in it and it's designed for that it's part of the ritual itself as you put it which I think was a good way to putting it.
Right, the space itself is doing part of the thing.
Yeah. Right. It's doing its part in the thing that's being done by the ritual.
And so this sort of path traced using these foot...
and using generally also the image of the God is setting up for what's going to be happening there.
So that path is the path that the God or the divine being walked in order to go to be enthroned
after having achieved some kind of victory. Right. And that's the broad strokes.
because we're trying to be broad so we include books.
both Bail and Buddha.
Right?
You want to have a lot of it?
Yes, they don't.
They don't.
But both of them walked a path, achieved a kind of victory,
and then ended up seated at the back of the shrine.
And portrayed in that way.
And so, yeah, so there's a variety of different forms
that that victory can take.
So if you...
you're talking about a Buddhist temple,
like in Myanmar, you're talking about achieving enlightenment.
Right, right.
And you go in there and you see the Buddha,
an image of the Buddha,
and he's in his enlightened state,
sitting in the, not that I'm an expert in Buddhism,
but he's sitting in the lotus position
and often has this sense of,
this is not the Buddha as he's going through his struggle.
This is the Buddha after he's achieved enlightenment.
You know?
Right, it ends.
So in the ancient world that we're talking about,
in the ancient Near East in particular,
so the world that the scriptures come out of,
it was not quite so placid,
and it was not sort of a spiritual victory in that sense.
No, right.
It was much more blood and guts,
with something, literally.
Yeah, and we've talked, of course,
especially in some of our earliest episodes,
And I think we've alluded to it since the...
but we've talked about what's called the succession myth, right? And just to kind of recap what that is,
that's in many mythologies you have, you know, a most high God, and then there's some
lesser God who goes and kills the most high God to send himself up as that.
Sometimes it becomes a little bit more complicated where you've got a father-son pairing that are in place, and
and another goes into set his own.
dad up on the throne and have himself as his right hand man. And that's what's being
talked about with Bale. Right? That this is his defeat as we've mentioned in the past
of Yam and Nahar, the ocean and river gods. So he defeats them, he walks this path, and
he goes and is enthroned. And when you know we were talking about this during the our
prep period, I was reminded of playing Warcraft III, the frozen, frozen throne expansion
where the bad guy at you know, although you're playing the bad guy.
I remember correctly. It's been so much.
Arthur's the champion you're playing there and you sort of he sort of falls and becomes possessed by.
There's a little village king. Yeah. Yeah.
And at the very end, the last thing that happens in the game is him having defeated all of his enemies.
He sits down and is enthroned and he's now, you know, the guy in charge.
I mean, this is a trope. You see it in a lot of literature, a lot of movies,
right, you know, that...
when someone wins they go and sit on the throne,
and that means that their authority has been set up, right?
Right, right.
And sometimes it's not so much they're having to fight
the last Most High God and give them the boot, right?
And replace them sometimes there.
And even bail is a little bit,
it's a bail kind of mixes the two.
But sometimes it's what's called chaos comp.
Yes, another word for everyone to,
this is today's second secret word,
our German word for today.
KS comp straight from the 19th century are fake people over the Germany of the 19th century.
Yeah, which comp means struggle, right?
You know, which you know probably a lot of people know that word comp because it's the
title of an autobiography by a certain very horrible person.
Yeah, mine comp.
Yeah, but it really poor really poorly written too.
Like it's not even like yeah, writing was not his forte.
I know he was a jail anyway.
Yeah, so chaos comp, the struggle against chaos.
And that's basically a god versus a chaos monster, right?
So there's, and this takes lots of different forms
and different kinds of mythology, right?
So you've got Odin with his brothers, Ville and Vé.
They go up against Emir, who is this sort of primeval giant.
They take him out.
In Greek mythology, you've got Kronos,
who takes out Uranos or Uranus,
who is sort of like the heavens, you know?
And then in Babylonian you've got Marduk versus Tiamat, who is a big dragon.
And kind of his mom.
Oh, yes, that's wonderful.
How do you could kill your own mom to make her Earth?
Yeah, so it does.
Yes, right.
So like I said, sometimes this chaos confresults in the creation of the world,
or the creation of humanity, or in some cases both in the Norse one,
it ends up, it results in the destruction of most of the giants.
to the Giants.
everybody. But when I think it's blood comes out of Emir's toe and floods the world,
though usually usually when it does create the world slash humans, especially the humans are
sort of an accidental byproduct. Right. It's like, I did it again. I made humans.
That may be our first Britney Spears reference. That's good. First baby last.
Never again.
So, right, so there's this notion of chaos comp that some
Sometimes is what preceives this walking the path to enthronement, right?
Right.
And so that's being traced there in the physical space of the temple in order to assist
with the sacrificial ritual that's going to take place there, then to play a part of it.
So yeah, as-
as a reminder with our sacred geography, right?
The reason you would have this traced
into the physical space is that when the ritual is in process,
that space and that time becomes the space
and time of the enthronement of the God,
of the victory and enthronement of the God.
And this is what's being reenacted
in sort of your typical.
your typical pagan ritual.
Yeah.
So we've talked about sort of the breakdown
of the liturgents of sacrifice
in one of our previous episodes on sacrifice.
But in terms of what is being participated in,
and you're just day to day pagan sacrifices
when you're doing on a day to day basis,
It's this sort of recapitulation.
of that victory and enthronement.
He's reenacted and participated in it again and again.
Right. And why, so why would the community want to do that?
Well, if you remember what we talked about when we talked about sacrifices,
so we had an episode called Eating with the Gods.
We talked about sacrifices.
You know, the point is that you're making the God part of your community,
you're offering the God hospitality,
especially in the most ancient versions of
that God is considered local to you.
So why would you keep recapitulating, participating in,
not exactly reenacting, because again, the understanding is
this is happening in a sense now by doing this ritual.
Why would you do that over and over again?
Well, it's basically like welcoming dad home, so to speak.
Right? You know, it's recognizing the authority of your God.
of your God. It's well
him, it's often there's a lot of flattery and stuff that goes along with it. But it's
really this, it's this affirmation of his authority within your community and his ability
to bind everybody together. So enthronement is not just like, oh, you won, you got the
throne. That's the center of the community's life is the throne of the God. Just as a throne
of your local warlord or your
King or whatever becomes the focal point of the community.
Right. So, so that's why this is part of the daily normal sacrifice.
You know, it's not a special occasion in that sense.
In the sense that this is something that, you know, only happens once in a
great while. It's something that you're, you're doing all the time.
You're constantly recapitulating, constantly reaffirming the authority,
the victory, the enthronement of their God.
And so that's why these temples are set up this way with these footprints
and other things that are...
that are involved as well.
And part of it is to keep him pleased.
Right?
Here's your big chair.
Oh, thank you.
Right, you're flat.
You're participating in his alleged victory.
So you're saying, yeah, Bill, you totally won, man.
You totally won.
Totally the best.
You're great, right?
Yeah.
And this understanding, here's a place
in the scriptures where this understanding lies
behind sort of what seems like it off.
comment, right? In Pergamon or Pergamos depending on the era in which you're
talking about the city, there was on the at the top of the Acropolis in the
city. So at the highest point in the city there was a gigantic great
alter to Zeus, right? And it's now in the University of Berlin. But the reason
at the University of Brooklyn.
in the museum is that it has these incredible sculptures, like human-sized sculptures on
the side, is this massive thing with massive steps leading up to the top of it.
And depicted in those sculptures is the Gigantomaki.
It's the victory of the Olympian gods over the giants.
And you went up the steps to the footstool of the throne of Zeus to make the offerings.
So.
This sat at the top of this high point of the city,
belching smoke of these sacrifices day and night,
towering over everything, celebrating this supposed victory of Zeus
over the giants, and when St. John attaches his sort of cover letter to the book of Revelation
to Pergamon, he refers to this as the throne of Satan.
Right.
And yeah, this is how
how he's making that connection, right? Zeus is part of the succession myth. He's the
devil claiming he won in his revolt when he didn't, right? This is his throne. They're
covering and buttering him up and offering him tribute. They're sureing him that, no,
he really did win. And he's writing to the Christians and talking about how they live
in the shadow of that every day as this persecuted Christian minority in the city. But it makes
It's perfect sense to come.
that in the throne of Satan if you understand what's going on there.
Yeah, right.
What's a pagan's understood was going on there.
Right. And another aspect to this, which I think is really important. I mean, I said earlier
that this kind of binds the community together, but also this is this underlies the notion of
founding of civilizations and cities and and peoples, right? This is a foundational myth.
and you know myth remember it within ritual theory myth is not
you know, just a story that isn't true. It's a story that everyone participates in and actually
shapes the community, right? So this is foundational. This is about the creation of this
city or whatever it is. You know, and so again, the throne becomes the focal point. That's what
it's all founded on, you know? So in Athens, right, Athena and Hephaestus, right, were the gods
who are assigned that air...
according to the Athenians. And so that land, the land they were working for food,
belonged to those gods, and those gods created the Athenians as this special race out of that
ground. Right. And so it was all bound together, right, in their minds. And what kept that bond going
was the ritual cycle of sacrifices. And this is why Christians opting out was not seen as an option.
Yeah
Right. And also, like just as a kind of side note, most kinds of paganism had this sense that their local gods had created them and that other gods had created other peoples.
It's within the worship of Israel that you have this idea that all of mankind has a single origin, which then implies that all of mankind has a single god.
Right. Right.
Yeah, which point Saint Paul makes an Athens?
Yeah, right.
from one man he made all the peoples of the world.
Right.
Talking about the most high god who's
which they would have argued with that.
Like no, no, we were made, no, no,
we were made by Athena and fate, no.
Right, and that makes us better.
Yeah, the Athenian democracy was not as democratic
as we might like to think.
No, last no.
Yeah, and then another thing that was celebrated,
another sort of aspect that was sometimes celebrated
that has some interesting biblic-
Ecos was the marriage of the God to the city as his bride. So that bond we were
just talking about, like the one that the Athenians saw in Athens. They would
talk about this in terms of Hephaestus having Athens as a bride. And the
goddess Athena being sort of a personification as feminists.
of the city itself, right? Right? Right? Or the city itself being a body of of Athena.
And so that that language is common all over the place in the ancient Near East and in ancient
Greece. I think we've said before on the show, ancient Greece was not the first Western civilization.
It was the last ancient Near Eastern civilization. Yeah. But this has some resonances then in the
the description.
especially the Old Testament, this idea, where you will see over and over again Zion and Jerusalem
and sometimes even Samaria the capital of the northern kingdom being referred to as the wife or the
bride of Yahweh, the God of Israel. Right, right. And then that's the origin of the language it gets
It's using the church that the church is the bride of Christ.
It comes from this notion.
of the community being married to the God.
And here's one, this is not, we ruined Sunday school.
This might be, we ruined, I don't know,
modern Orthodox myth, liturgical med-
Urban legends.
Urban legends, yeah, right.
So you'll often see in Orthodox liturgical texts,
the people of God being described as being a city.
So like in front of...
For instance, addressing God or sometimes addressing the Virgin Mary, I, the city, ascribe
to the appraise, whatever, whatever.
And a lot of times people, because they have this big shadow in their minds of, you know,
the Eastern Roman Empire and all that kind of thing, they assume that that city that's
being referred to is Constantinople.
So it's not.
The city is the church.
Now, Constantinople, in as much as it has been, Christian can be being that city, right?
But it's not the city of God.
You know, the city of God is the church.
And it's the city of God that addresses God,
and addresses the Virgin Mary and the saints and so forth.
It's not, it's, you know, there may sometimes be references
to Constance, or other cities, great cities,
in the Turgical texts, as they personify this.
But the origin of this language is a scripture, actually.
And other cities can participate in that reality.
but only as much as they are B-
being Christian, right? It's not just, it's not sacralized for all time as one
particular city here or there. There is a religion that kind of does that and
this isn't that one. There's a couple of them that do that actually. This isn't
that religion. And when we understand that the church is a police, that has all
kinds of ramifications that we're going to talk about probably in some future
episode yeah about to
Yeah, it's, yeah, police is being the ancient Greek word for city.
Although it's a bigger concept than that.
I mean, here in Emmaus, we pray for this city and every city.
Well, it may as if you walk around in its three square miles.
No one would call it a city in modern English, but it is a police in that sense.
You know, it's a community.
It's a people, right?
So yeah, yeah.
I love this.
And I love how I mean, we've talked about this many, many times.
but I just want to underline it in this case about how all these notions that are going around the each and near east about
What it means to have a devotion to your God and what the God's relationship is to the community
How all of that is fulfilled in the scriptures and shown to really be truly about the relationship of the people of God with
with Yahweh their Creator
So this is just a beautiful example of that
right the way it's
The the instinct that's still late into humanity that gets distorted
due to a lack of knowledge and due to demonic manipulation in the other nations
is sort of purified and restored and brought to its proper place within the
actual police of Yahweh, the God of Israel. And just to finish up this first half,
if you were to go to the Mount of Ascension in the Holy Land, right, you were
good.
to go to the site. It's no longer able to function as a church unfortunately. It's within
an Islamic compound. But if you go to the site of the original church of the ascension,
on the amount of ascension, ascension, what you will find there is in a stone the print
of Christ's right foot.
The Petro-Somato-Glyph. So yes, exactly.
All right, well that wraps up the first half of Lord of Spirits tonight. So we're going
I'm gonna go to break.
and as soon as we come back from break,
we're gonna take one of your calls.
Father Andrew Stephen Daymak and Father Stephen DeYoung
will be back in a moment to take your calls
on the next part of the Lord of Spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF Radio.
No one of books these days offer us techniques
for self-improvement.
But in the news...
This release from the ancient faith story, gratitude in life's trenches, Robin Phillips
takes a different tack.
He shows us that God made us where we are, in the pain and heartache of the present moment.
Instead of looking for a way to escape from hardship, we can cultivate an attitude of
gratitude, peace, and self-acceptance that will transform our experience of suffering.
Drawing on his own experiences and his work as a consultant in the behavioral health industry,
as well as stories of...
saints and sufferers, teachings of the fathers, and recent discoveries in neuroscience.
Philips shows us that the journey to personal well-being is one we can all travel, regardless
of the hardships we may face.
To find this book and others like it, you can go to store.angentfaith.com.
Again, that is store.angentfaith.com.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits, the Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father
Stephen De...
young. If you have a question, call now at 855-237-2346. That's 855-AF radio.
Welcome back to the second half of the Lord of Spirits on this feast of the
ascension and we're going to start taking your call. So we actually do have a
caller here right at the top of the second half. John from Atlanta, John, are
you there? I am father. Welcome.
Welcome, John, to the Lord of Spirits podcast.
What's on your mind?
I was hoping you'd slip up and say, West you hall, but OK.
Oh, West you hall.
Be that well in Old English.
Yes.
Thank you.
And Father Stephen is free to know me.
But I have wondered about this.
We read the 8th A.O.F. in Gospel Less.
And then this being ascension,
be ready.
today, uh, gospel from the Luke and uh, went in the oath, eight, uh, buried back to
the, he's the gardener and uh, don't touch me. I haven't yet ascended my father. Right.
And then we know 40 days later, he ascends to the father. And in this gospel, in Luke, he's
saying, handle me. And of
course, Thomas, he says, you
know, put your hand at my side
and feel the prince of the nails and all this and in this gospel from Luke at the ascension,
he says, he says, handle me and see.
And it makes it, long maybe wonder, if there's some ascension we don't know about that occurs
after he meets Mary Magdalene in the garden.
When he's saying, you can't touch me, I've just come from Hades.
And then later it's okay.
Yeah, so the one thing that I can say to that, because it just leaped into my mind right
off, is that the hymns that discuss St. Mary and Magdalene's encounter with the Lord there,
they actually give an explanation as to why he says that to her, which is that she, her
Your mind was on earthly things, it says that.
So that she was thinking, I mean, you can...
expand that whatever way you like, but that's what the hymns say. Right? So in other words,
that it's not that he can be handled after the ascension, it's that she's not her mind
is not where it should be. And so it's not, it would not be appropriate for her to embrace
him that way. Right? So that's the way that the hymns interpret it is, is that the change
is not that Jesus did something in changes so he can be touched later. It's that, it's
that St. Mary Magdalene.
state of heart is not appropriate to be able to do that. Now I can't say I totally understand
exactly what that means but that is what the hymns say is that she's thinking sometimes
you see a trans-aid carnaly which doesn't mean anything purine. It just means thinking
according to earthly things according to the flesh you know that kind of thing. So that's
the liturgical interpretation that I can remember off the top of my head. So Father did
Did you have something you wanted to add to that?
Yeah, let me try and connect those dots for you.
Okay.
Between the two things in terms of how you get from one to the other.
All right.
So yeah, it isn't like when Christ had just gotten back from Hades,
he was too hot to handle and too cold to hold or something.
It's the touch.
Is it really the best translation of the word that's used there?
Yes.
Hold her, grab onto her, like yeah.
And that's in that's in St. John's gospel. So it comes at the end of a whole a long piece that we read most of actually on holy Thursday night of
of teaching from Christ to his disciples.
And in that, he talks about, and this is one of the major themes of that whole back half of Saint John's Gospel,
is about Christ descending in the coming of the Holy Spirit.
And remember he teaches that you know it's to your benefit that I go right because then the Holy Spirit will come
And so the idea is he's saying don't cling to me because what what
Say Mary Magdalene is thinking is oh, I've got him back
Right I thought I had lost him but now I have him back and I want to keep him and I want to cling to him
right and that's why he's saying don't cling to me because
I still have to do this. I have to ascend. The Holy Spirit has to come. So it's sort of parallel
to what happens on the Mount of Transfiguration when St. Peter is like, hey, let's build a little
tense for you. Yeah, for you and Moses and Elijah. We'll all just stay up here. Right.
Right. And it's like, no. Right. Yes, this is this moment of joy. Yes, this is this wonderful
thing but we can't camp out here right there's there's something more
happening. There's something more coming. And, and that was the ascension and then what came after.
Is that makes sense, John? It does. Yeah, there's only one ascension.
Right. Just the one. Just just the one. That's the idea behind these. She was thinking
cardinally or in a worldly way, right? She was thinking of, oh, I've got him back. Right.
I wanted to stay here with me now.
Right.
Right. Yeah. Yeah. All right. Well, thank you very much for that call, John.
And we have another caller, Samuel from the God blessed Commonwealth of Virginia,
my natal state. Samuel, welcome to the Lord of Spirits.
Thank you, Father. You said something similar last time I called that is because
Virginia is a blessed land.
So when you were talking about the depictions of pagan gods
being thrown on mountains, mountain temples. I was wondering if you guys had any insight on
a particular example of that in today's popular culture. Okay. Are you familiar with Warhammer 40,000?
I bet Father Samuel is, I'm aware of it. Father Samuel, sorry, Father Steven,
We're talking to say
you know your father's yeah yeah I do know a father's Samuel in West Virginia. Yeah yeah as we both
which which West Virginia is the best Virginia but it's the rest of Virginia. So
so we're hammer 40k yes yes I am somewhat yeah was there some particular thing in their Samuel
that that you had in mind. I was thinking about how in that setting that humanity is ruled over
by an emperor who he...
around 15 feet tall and now sits on a throne on the highest mountains of
earth to hope and requires regular sacrifice. Yeah, how about that? Yeah, he's a
God Emperor. Right. Yeah, in return, he enables interstellar faster than light
travel. Well, there you go. Yeah, you'll see, I mean, you'll, once you see these
patterns from the ancient world, you'll start to see them in lots of places. Right? It just keeps
you getting repeated in culture, whether it's popular culture or classical literature, it's everywhere.
It's everywhere. So does that answer your question, Samuel?
Yeah. Well, actually, this emperor was said to have been born in the ancient near East.
Well, there you are. Right. Kells, please.
right. All right. Well, thank you very much for calling tonight. Samuel's good.
talk to you again. Yeah, I was actually reading Wikipedia's article,
Buddha foot for it's earlier today. How about that? Yeah, it's a fun article.
All right. Well, thanks for calling. All right. Well, next we have just say
I'm sorry. Go ahead. Go ahead, Father Steven. I don't want to bash a
caller after they get off the phone. But okay, Samuel clearly not a careful
listener. Oh, because I have made a blood for the blood god reference. Oh,
Oh, yes.
a lot of past episode. Right. And he apparently missed it or he would not own. Not everybody can be anyway. Yeah. Okay. Well, it's okay, Samuel. You live in Virginia. So you're, you're great.
We still have. We have Hannah calling. So Hannah, are you there? What's on your mind? I'm here. Thank you for taking my call. Welcome.
I have recently been learning and studying more about the actually natural family planning.
And you can't get very far in natural friendly planning without coming across the theology of the body.
Right.
And some things that have come up in the theology of the body is that what I quote is that the body and it alone is capable of making visible what is invisible.
The spiritual in the divine, it was created to transfer into the visible reality of the world, the mystery hidden from time and memorial.
in God and that's to be a
climate.
My question is, how well does this fit in with Orthodox theology?
Wow.
Do you have a few hours?
But you don't.
Well, we theoretically could, but we'd lose listeners
left and right after five hours.
Yes.
Yeah.
I've heard through my orthodox development.
different at different times,
hints about the body of man and woman being changed
after the fall.
Yeah.
And so I'm wondering how much we can really take
as signs of the divine from our fallen bodies.
Yeah, I mean, there is the problem
that we are in this state, right?
So human bodies get altered.
They, they, they
Now we talked about this in some detail in the body episodes.
You may recall earlier this year.
But they just to kind of recap, right?
So when Adam and Eve sin, God, and so that they would not be crystallized in evil, God
gives them mortality.
What the phrase, the garments of skin, right?
As some of the fathers interpret that phrase from Genesis.
they become mortal, they become...
corruptible. And the point of this actually was not God's, you know, being so mad at them,
he just had to punish them and give them this mortal state, but rather he was giving them the
ability to repent. And because you can't repent if you don't have a mortal body,
St. John of Damascus says this, it's, you know, it's, and he says it as a kind of sideways way of
talking about why it is that the demons won't repent because they don't have mortal bodies.
But also it's useful to remember that when you're parted from your mortal body
You don't then have the ability to repent because you don't have it anymore
It's your mortal body that gives you that ability so so right
We can't start with humanity as it currently exists now and then analogize outward from there to talk about the divine
That's completely backwards
Right human beings are created according to the image of God. So we are as we described it. Theomorphic
Weird.
you know, we're cheap imitations of God in sense, and we're in this sort of weakened state
of being mortal, which was given to us so that we could repent. So yeah, any theology of the body
has to take that into account. It cannot absolutize our current state and come up with a model for
understanding who we are in relation to God as a result of that. Right? Because this is, it's not
not just broken, it has a purpose.
This broken state we have has a purpose so that we can repent.
Father, I don't know if you wanted to add anything to that.
Yeah, a couple of things.
I think the quote you read is talking about the body,
quaw physical and material.
Yes, right.
It's not always the way we use body on this show, but it's part of it.
Right.
And so the sin, quaw non sort of fulfillment
of that quote you just read.
is of course the Theotokos giving birth to Christ, right?
It's through her human body that the mystery capital M of the ages, right?
Christ Himself is manifest in the world. It's through humanity taken from her body.
So that's sort of, that's the synchronon of that.
And that's what St. Paul is getting at, by the way,
when he says that woman will be saved by childbirth.
people come up with really bizarre world
understandings of that that like women having babies
makes them saved or something.
No, it's about the woman.
Right.
Because the word he uses there is not a woman.
The word for a woman.
It's the word for woman like womanhood.
Right? Like woman is a concept.
The same way that there's, you may know in Greek,
there's anthropos, right, which is...
of humanity, man, humanity kind of thing, and then on the ear which is just a man, right?
This is talking about woman is saved through child bearing.
So it's talking about womanhood, what God created women to be, we see fulfilled in the
Theotokos.
So that's the sort of core fulfillment of that.
But also humanity is both material and immaterial and humanity there.
for in Orthodox theology functions as the bridge between the spiritual world and the material
world to bring the two together. And that's sort of the basis of all of our sacramental theology.
Right? That God's grace comes to us through the created world and through matter and through
our physicality, right? So, Adam was created in the first place.
visible and invisible in order to serve as a priest and bridge those those
two realities and bring them both to perfection which of course as we know he
failed he failed to do but Christ then does that perfectly.
Hmm.
Does that help their Hannah?
It does.
Awesome.
Thank you.
So I'm waiting on the edge of my feet for talk of dragon.
Well, you're in luck. We're about to mention a dragon. Yes. Yes. Thanks for calling Hannah. Okay. I know we have some other
collars. Thank you. But we're going to move on and start talking a little bit about a dragon. So boy, that was just a
perfect segue we're gonna move on through fire and flames.
Yeah, to
that we're going to
We're going to leave the Pro-Devil propaganda
and go to the scriptures for the corrected version.
And we will see, this is an in joke
that only a handful of people will get,
but we'll see that there are continuities
and discontinuities with the scriptures.
So when we talked a little bit in the last half
about a
the way the creation myth kind of got worked into the victory stories of the gods,
particularly the creation of humanity, sometimes the creation of the earth.
And so when you read Genesis 1 and the first couple verses of chapter 2,
because why did they put the break there? Anyway,
There are some striking things that you notice over against it and probably the
The first one is that in Genesis 1 at least there's no element of chaos comp.
Right.
Yahweh doesn't have to fight anybody, there's no throw down between him and the forces of
chaos.
Right.
Chaos is there in Genesis 1 verse 2.
And he just founds the earth upon it.
Boom.
Right.
And he just kind of pauses it around.
Yeah.
He doesn't have to have a wrestling match with Leviathan with a dragon.
There you are, Hannah.
Uh...
you know, like there is a sense of God against Leviathan, right?
But it's mostly God pushing Leviathan around, right?
I remember you said at one point, father, someone asked about Leviathan
and he said, oh yeah, God plays with Leviathan like a cat.
Yeah, that's the way he's depicted in some of the Psalms.
That's amazing.
Yeah, and so there is these motifs from the Chaos Conf idea
idea in the surrounding countries get picked up.
places in the Old Testament and I'll do the quick list here so that people can
pause it or look it up in the transcript with such a thing materializes. But
that's in Psalm 74, Psalm 89, Psalm 93,
Job 26, verses 12 and 13, and Isaiah 51, verses 9 and 10. You see that imagery
sort of taken over and played with. In one case, like you mentioned, rather than
him fighting Leviathan, like he makes Leviathan as a sort of house pet to play with.
And another place he catches Leviathan like a fish.
Apparently he's a hobby.
Right, so that's this huge contrast.
Yeah, and it doesn't create the world when these things happen.
Right, no, this is something that happens later.
Right.
And in addition to there being no chaos comp, there's of course no succession myth.
There's no other most high god who, you know, he has to show up and defeat to take over.
And there's not anyone who he's worried about.
I mean, somebody has to go at it in Genesis 3, but he loses badly.
And there's not even a fight.
It's not like a Genesis 3 God has to fight.
fight the devil and beat him. Right. He just pissed that. Yeah, throws him out.
Get out. Tells him to buzz off, you know. Yeah. Yeah. And you know, there was, um,
so last night we're talking about, you know, shameless plug for your new book,
Religion the Apostles. We're talking about your book in a class that we're doing
here in Emmaus. And someone I was talking about the succession myth and, uh,
because that's in chapter four.
And someone brought up, I said,
They just said, what a beautiful contrast.
And I thought this was so, so beautifully brought this up.
What an amazing contrast where you've got in all of these pagan myths,
there's this divine father and son and often what's going down is the son killing
his father. But in the worship of the God of Israel,
you've got a perfectly obedient son who reigns alongside his father and works
alongside his father. You know, and it's a picture of humility.
and not of struggle.
Because I mean, if you're omnipotent,
why would you...
There's those who sting the struggle.
Right?
I mean, you know, like,
we see this in the Gospels, right?
Where, you know,
they're on the sea of Galilee
and the storm is picking up, whatever,
and Christ simply says,
peace be still.
And the disciples are like,
who is this that the wind and waves
just simply obey him?
You know, he doesn't have to like
cast a spell or wrestle against the demons of the water
the water.
or whatever, they just simply obey him, boom.
You know, what a contrast that is.
Yeah, yeah.
And it's, I mean, it's stark if you read the two side by side.
Yeah.
This is not even a similar story.
And this is what, for example, in Isaiah, when Yahweh says,
you know, before me there was no God.
And after me there will be no other.
This is what he's talking about.
talking about because we're talking
about Assyrians and Babylonians now in contrast, right?
There was no God before Yahweh who he overthrew,
and there's nobody coming along who's going to change
in the situation in the future.
Yep.
This is the way it is.
Right.
He's the creator.
And so we also see then in that story,
as we've talked about before in a previous episode
in Genesis 1 that the cosmos
as it's constructed, as it's put in order by Yahweh is this sort of giant temple,
right, with Eden as the sanctuary of that temple, and then Adam created by God as his image
in that sanctuary, in that temple. Right, which is a contrast with the way paganism works
in which man sets up a temple and creates an image of the God and puts it in there.
there.
Instead, you get God creates the temple, puts his own image,
which is human beings.
Right.
And so it's, and we're going to talk about this more
as we go on in this half.
Things are getting inverted, getting turned on the head.
So we've talked about that before in a previous episode.
So that was quick review.
But the element we want to focus on for our purpose tonight,
when we eventually actually directly
talk about the ascension in the third half,
you should have expected by the
now because that's how these things work on this show.
That's right.
The third half is inevitable, right?
Is the seventh day, the seventh day, which talk about things
that are treated as afterthoughts, right?
One of the most, even though I refuse to talk about it,
one of the things that most interested,
slashed, entertained me about some of the debates
about the length of the days of creating.
in certain circles, was that there were times where people were literally arguing for seven
24-hour days, not six, seven. So they wanted to say that God literally rested for 24 hours.
Yeah. Which I always said a little abuse. Right. Right. And it comes from this idea that,
And I think a lot of us were probably
raise with this notion, like God works six days and then rests.
Well, and because we tend to think of him anthropomorphically,
and we think, oh, yes, I too need a weekend.
Yeah.
You know, right?
And so that's what the Sabbath is about.
It's a weekend because God needed a break because he worked so hard.
So we need to take at least one day off, right?
But that's not what is meant by when Christ says that the Sabbath is made for man.
actually.
actually this God entering into his rest, entering into his rest. And so when the Sabbath
then is given to man, it's to do the same thing. Right. So what that means is that when
God completes his work in creation and then goes and rests, it's not because he needs
a break. He's got.
God does not need a break, right?
He does not need to take some time off.
Does not need a weekend.
Again, that's thinking anthropomorphically.
Right, and had the idea of Israel entering into his rest,
even if I just lie here, would you lie with me
and just get to the world?
Yes, because, oh, it's been so difficult, right?
Right, right, right.
This is REST like coming to REST like City
down like we just talked about in temples right and thrown. Yes. This is the end of the path. You get to
the end of the path. You've completed right. You've completed your victory. You have built your temple
and now you go and you go and sit down on your throne. You take your seat. And so joining God in his
rest is coming to be seated with him. Right. So when the Sabbath, when the Sabbath is given to man
man. And not man, you know, the Sabbath is made for man.
not man for the Sabbath. The Sabbath is made for man. That is God saying walk this path
to the place of my throne and sit here beside me. In other words, that the Sabbath being made for
man is actually an image of theoses. It's actually about becoming like God, becoming co-enthroned with him.
Right, so in the Old Testament by observing the
they are in the liturgical week and acting the promise to Abraham to become
like the stars right the promise to Abraham at the end that's why it's at the
end of the week they're looking forward to it at the end of the week that being
the goal and the destiny and so as as we were mentioning right and we're
gonna break down a little.
more here, right? The story we're told, the myth, the story you can participate in,
that we're told in the Old Testament is taking the pagan one and flipping it on its head.
That's how a pagan would have experienced it. Now, from our perspective, of course, this
is the true story, and the demons have taken that, taken that neck, flipped it on its head,
and so forth as a lie to the nations. Right. But in terms of reality. But a pagan
what it's weird is that
Okay, you've taken this story. We all know, I mean we disagree about the names of the gods involved, but we all know this story. You've taken it and flipped everything around.
And the main way to describe that flip overall is that the pagan story makes ritual and makes worship all human directed toward the divine.
the divine.
right, meaning it's the human who goes and makes the body for the God so that the God will
have a body and they can interact with each other. It's the humans who have to come in feed
and dress and care for and honor and celebrate and appease and please the God. Right.
So all of that motion is directed in that way, as opposed to God creating his own images.
you mentioned. As opposed to what we talked about in a previous episode, the showbred, right,
which is rather than them bringing food to God in the Tabernacle in the temple, God feeds his priests
during the service. Right, right. In the Tabernacle in the temple. Yeah, and you know, and then,
okay, just to extend it into the direct experience, everyday experience, really of Orthodox Christians,
at the very beginning of the divine liturgy, you know, the deacon says to the priest,
It is time for...
the Lord to act, right? And which is why I'm sorry for those of you who have this translation.
Sometimes you hear it is time to begin the service to the Lord. That is exactly backwards.
It's actually more accurate to the original though. I do. I'm actually a little bit.
Okay, that's fine. That's fine. I agree with you in terms of by preference. But yes,
right. Right. But yeah, but the point is that it is an action by, you know, the divine
and let her Jesus in action by God towards us, he's feeding us.
He's doing this work for us. It is it is a divine liturgy for the people. It is a public service
Right, I can hear Father Lucas Christensen whom I don't think we've referenced before in the show before
Hearing in his head he's saying that's right. It's not the work of the people. It's the work
Well, that's true. It's definitely not the work of the right
Yeah, yeah, resolved
but
But yeah, and so the idea is
the pagan gods need a bunch of things from humanity. Right. Right. Whether it's flattery and
praise, like, oh, no, bail, you're the best. Everybody you fought you won. Right. Or whether it's food,
whether it's to be dressed, whether it's to be cared for, right. They require all of these things.
And if not, they get pee-fish. They don't do what you want them to do. Yeah, you have to keep them
I'm happy.
Yeah, so there's all these.
demands opposed on humanity.
And so it's literally in there when you read
Samaritan religious texts, for example,
that basically humans were created to be
that God's slaves and served them, right?
Which what do you expect from demons
that are trying to enslave humanity, right?
In being honest, they're saying the quiet part out loud
to the Samarians.
But the reality is since God created
things, Yahweh the God of Israel created all things, everything belongs to him. He doesn't
need anything of yours. In fact, everything that you think is yours belongs to him anyway.
That's why we say the liturgy, thine own of thine own, we offer unto thee, right? Because
we don't actually have anything it all belongs to him. So he doesn't need anything. Rather,
whole perspective of Old Testament religion.
Of Old Testament religion is...
that God shares out of his love the things that are his with humans whom he loves.
The whole idea is that he moves outside of himself, right? He gets up off of
his throne. He creates the cosmos for us and puts us in it and then he sits
back down again. After he out of love has left his throne to do that, right? And
And this is, this is Old Testament.
This is what they, they,
understood in the Old Testament. Is it just a new thing that starts in the New Testament?
Right. So when Christ goes and feeds 5,000 people, right, he's enacting what Yahweh, the God of
Israel, has been doing all along for the Maddie and the wilderness, to the show bread, right? Any
showing that he's the same God. That's part of how that's revealed in the New Testament.
And so this changes like the context.
of praise in worship, right?
In Israel, praise in worship is primarily thanksgiving.
That's what's called the Eucharist, right?
It's giving because we're acknowledging all the goods that we've received from God.
It's not flattering.
It's not trying to meet God's needs.
Right?
For a approval like He's insecure, like bail is.
Yeah, and most like most, you know, even Orthodox prayers that specifically ask God for
or something, the usual new...
of structure that they take is to say God once you did this and then often
include a thanks. Can you please do it now again for us? Right? That's the way
that it goes. It's not like, oh, you know, like you said, it's not flattery. It's
not obsequious. Right? And we've all heard unfortunately from some of our
Christian friends, prayers that are sort of like, okay, I'm gonna butter God up for
for a few minutes.
that I'm going to read him my list of demands, right?
I'm going to try and get him good and buttered up and then I'm going to ask him for things,
right?
But that's not correct.
That's not right.
Right.
It's Christians, right?
No.
That's not what it's about.
He doesn't need your flattery.
You're not fooling him.
You're not tricking him.
Yeah.
Right.
So, you know, so part of them, the way that that gets expressed liturgically, meaning
ritual participation right in the in the Old Testament.
And then, frankly, also in the New Covenant as well,
you've got these two of the big feasts, particularly Passover,
which is a renewal of the Exodus,
and that is about the creation of the people of Israel,
and of course it's also about God's defeat of the Egyptian gods.
And then you've also got Pentecost, which is about the giving of the law,
so it's a renewal of the covenant.
And so these things are baked into the literature.
psychological cycle, it's a participation in creation as being always renewed by God, something that we receive from God.
Right? And so both of those acts, right? The Passover is an action by God.
You know, the giving of the law at the end of the 50 days is an action by God. Right?
And so our participation in those things is to renew our experience of them, our reception of them, you know, for me and my generation to do
to do this.
same thing to have the exact same experience that those who did it first. Right? So that's
just baked in to the way that we do this. And those two feasts were the creation of Israel.
Right. Before that there was no Israel. Yep. Exactly. Right. And afterwards there was.
It begins with Passover and it's completed in Pentecost. Right. Yep. Now as a tease. Right.
We've been talking about sort of this continuity between old and new testament, but now here's one of those points of discontinuity.
And that is that in the Old Testament with the Tabernacle in the Temple, right, God is dwelling there with the people and the people are near Him.
But not that many people could actually go into the Tabernacle or the Temple.
and only one guy once a year could go into the actual
holy of holy, the actual sanctuary at that time. So humanity was still kind of outside
though he had been brought near. And that's a tease for two weeks from today when we talked about
Pentecost. Indeed. It wouldn't be a Lord of Spirit episode if we didn't at one point say,
Well, we'll talk about that in a later episode.
Yeah.
But this one is soon.
Yes, quite soon.
Yeah, it's indeed.
Yeah.
So all right, so, okay, there's some cool structure stuff that goes on in the New Testament and some of the early fathers that we want to talk about how we participate in God's creation, his renewal of creation.
And the thing you pointed out, for instance, St. Aaron Ace of Lyon, who is
second century, or my blank is a third century.
Second century.
Yeah, yes, super early on, because yeah.
His spiritual father was St. Pauli Carp,
who is a spiritual son of the Apostle John.
Yeah, so it's gotta be a second century.
He talks about some of this stuff,
but he's getting it ultimately
as you pointed out in our earlier conversation
from St. John.
So why don't you talk about how that works out
in St. John's New Testament literature?
Right, well if you know one thing about St. Aaronnaeus,
it's probably annoying people pointing out
that they think he said Jesus was 50 years old when he died.
But it's two things about saying here in ASS.
The second one is probably you have some idea that he talked about what's called recapitulation.
Yes.
Which literally would mean to rehead to head again.
But anyway.
And that's the idea that he has theologically of in terms of the relationship between the Old Testament and the New Testament.
And on a general broader theological scale that of this renewal and recreat-
creation taking place and he gets that from St. John it's it's baked into the
Johanning literature in the scriptures and that's even at the level of structure
Yeah, so the
St. John's gospel and the book of Revelation and first John all have a similar structure in this way
Second and third John are kind of too short to have much of a structure
It's hard to structure a paragraph in a complex-
But I mean, I'm sure you give it a try.
Yeah, I'm sure you give it a try a few times yourself.
But the way they're structured is sort of like a spiral or a corkscrew.
Meaning it moves in circles or cycles, but it also progresses forward.
Yeah, right. So it's not just spinning its wheels sort of going around in a flat circle like time.
or the Wheel of Fortune.
It's moving forward, but it's moving forward in this circular path.
So in St. John's Gospel, it's structured around the three years of Christ's ministry
and each of those three years, he sort of goes through the festival cycle of Israel, the cycle of feasts.
And it progresses through three cycles of feasts.
In the book of Revelation, this is real obvious even if you just read the subject headers in your English translation.
your English translation.
because you get seven churches, seven lampstands, seven bowls, seven seals, seven trumpets, right?
They're sort of these repeating cycles of seven and each new cycle of seven sort of takes off from the seventh of the last cycle.
So the narrative kind of moves forward but it moves forward in these cycles of seven, seven because of the Sabbath.
that's part of what St. John is aiming at in the book of Revelation.
that we'll probably talk about more in a future episode.
But so what we want to kind of focus it on here because of what we've just been talking about,
the creation is sort of the primary point in view of the regular daily liturgics of the
tabernacle in Temple in the old covenant, is connected to specifically St. John's gospel
and the way in which in that, not just the back half.
that I mentioned earlier where we were talking about that question, but the
the passion narrative itself, which we also of course read on on Holy
Thursday because we read almost everything on Holy Thursday. Yeah, but it's
specifically the way that Saint John when he gets to describing Christ's passion
and death on the cross. He swirls in all of this language drawn from...
the Greek of the story of creation in Genesis 1 and 2.
And we see this in a bunch of places that we don't have time to develop them all right now,
but you see this with the Theotokos and this pearly makes with Eve where the Theotokos
goes from being referred to as woman over and over again throughout the gospel
to now be referred to as Mother in the same way that...
Eve's name is actually woman before Genesis 3, and then after the expulsion
prepared ice, her name has changed to Yvav from Isha, because she is now the
mother of the mother of all the living. And you see the opening of Christ's side,
like when he dies, like the opening of Adam's side, when Eve his bride is
created.
But specifically here, related to the Sabbath language that we've just been talking about,
in one of the interminable run-ins that Christ has with the Pharisees throughout the Gospels,
where they're after him about doing something or his disciples doing something on the Sabbath.
It comes up over and over and over and over again because they just don't get the Sabbath.
John 517 this time
says something very particular in that he says that his father is still working until
that very day and that he says, I am working. Christ is working. Right? Still. Right?
And that doesn't mean by the way, the until that very day doesn't mean that that's the
day he stopped. Yeah. Right. Right. What the listener understand who has questions about
Matthew, anyway.
So, meaning what?
Well, if our understanding of the rest of Yahweh at the end of creation is that God leaves
his throne, he works, and then when he's done, he is re-enthroned.
This is what Christ is appealing to.
The work is not done.
What work?
of the creation, the cosmos.
We talked before.
previous episode about how Adam and Eve's job was to continue putting things in order
and filling the world with life, to continue that work of creation and they failed.
And now Christ has left his throne in the heavenly places, has is now at work to bring that
to completion after which he will be re-enthroned.
When Christ dies on the cross and say
John's Gospel, he says, to tell us to tell us day, which is usually translated it is finished,
but that's the same verb that's used at the beginning of Genesis 2 to say that when God completed
his work, he rested on the seventh day. And so Christ says that now it is finished and then he rests
in the tomb on the seventh day. And so this is where the language that you'll hear in the orthodox
Church and Orthodox theology about the eighth day, the beginning of a new creation, the
beginning of a new cycle when Christ rises.
This is where that comes from, but that first cycle is completed by Christ, as he says
several times in St. John's Gospel, right?
Father, restored to be the glory which I shared with you before the world began, right?
Christ is going to return to the throne that He left and be enthroned again.
And with that, that ends the second half of the Lord of Spirits for tonight and we're
going to go ahead and go to a break and we'll get back to some of your calls.
We'll be right back.
Father Andrew Stephen Daymak and Father Stephen DeYoung will be back in a moment to take your
calls on the next part of the Lord of Spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
855 AFP
faint of heart, but they are very much for all who want to embrace the truth more fully.
And you didn't have to ask Russ Goulville for help, cleaning, polishing, carrying, inter-out.
Any work in the church, the woman was a stalled, a tallodish, you could count on.
No one knew her suffering. They never bothered to look into her eyes.
It surprised me, most of the church folks at St. Alexander the world in Derrish
parish didn't even know her name. It wasn't anything they thought about.
To find this book and others like it you can go to store.enginefaith.com. Again that is store.enginefaith.com
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits, the Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father
Stephen DeYoung. If you have a question call now at 855-237-2346. That's 855-
I'm David, I'm 19, 25 AF radio.
Welcome back everybody.
This is the third half of the Lord of Spirits.
And I see we have some callers that have been patiently waiting.
So first we're going to take a call from David.
David, are you there?
I'm here.
Welcome David.
Welcome to the Lord of Spirits.
What's on your mind?
So I was wondering if there was anything sort of tying into the Lord of Spirits.
tying into the
last episode about Christ's body.
There's anything to the idea why the reason is wounds
are still present after the resurrection is related
to Hebrews 9 and him re-entering into the heavenly temple
to sprinkle his blood as the once and for all
sacrifice as opposed to the annual day
of Atomans sacrifice.
Well, that's a great question.
I'm going to punt that directly to Father Stephen.
I don't think I have any follow-up to all this.
All right.
Okay.
Well, great.
Father Stephen, I am sending that directly to you.
Yes.
There we go.
All right.
Good night, everybody.
Right.
So, so, yeah.
Christ's wounds in particular are special, obviously.
Right.
But what I mean by that is, you know,
This is a...
like beetle juice, right, where you know you die in some particular way and you're sort of like
your spirit is that way forever or something, right? Obviously. So that's what I mean by special,
right? Right? Swords are different. And so he is, right? The lamb slaying before the foundation
of the world. Right?
And so his sacrifice has an eternal reality to it that enters into the time and space
of human experience at a certain point, but is an eternal reality.
And so what's going on in Hebrews, and this would take a lot of time to unpack, but
future episode.
What's going on in Hebrews is not that St. Paul, and I'm not going to go into all that now either,
St. Paul is not saying that there was this sort of, the way we tend to think of it,
that there's this sort of big transition, like yeah, the goat blood was doing it up until now,
But now, right, this thing happened, and so now, right, it's different.
different going forward. The reason the goat blood worked, right? What the goat blood
did, what the Rick Day of Atonement ritual did was bring the people of the old
covenant into participation in Christ's sacrifice beforehand. Right? So in Hebrews
Saint Paul is saying that his offering of his blood in the sanctuary.
This goes with him being slain eternally is a
eternal reality, right, meaning not just a
space-show temporal reality, but a reality that is
eternally capital-teacherous, but that enters into
humans' experience at various points in time.
And it enters into our experience too.
right? So we then celebrate the Eucharist where Christ's blood is right and drink his life.
And that's us now after the fact participating in that as we're cleansed by his blood.
Does that make sense David? Yeah. I was on it a little bit of something there. Yeah, that's pretty
cool. Okay well thanks for calling. Alright we have
one more caller we're gonna take right now and that's David so David are you
there? I am. Welcome David to the Lord of Spirits. What's on your mind? Yeah I guess
this is probably the wrong place for a pragmatic question. No. No those are
Father Andrews. There you go yeah right finally I something I can answer.
I guess the question is kind of an
a simple form.
how do we know what we are ritually participating in?
We make a lot of statements about
liturgical bodies and ritual participation
in them with us having physical bodies
and spiritual beings having other bodies.
How do you know what you're participating in
or what you're doing is active or passively participating
bleeding in some sense, but I'm not used to that mix.
sense. I think so. So let me see if I can restate your question in a way that makes sense to both of us.
So I think what you're asking is essentially, how do we know that it's working and what it's doing
when it's working? Is that what you're saying? Yeah, how do you know that it's working? How do you know
what you're doing is working? I guess how do you know what you're doing is right? Yeah, you know,
coming from a Protestant background, we're often taught that just by if you're
lusting after somebody or if you're greedy or if you struggle with X, Y, or Z,
Sin, well that's really what these people who are worshipping these gods were doing.
So by de facto you are worshipping ours or Nike or Aphrodite,
is there any validity to that?
So the short answer to that is yes.
right? Whenever we sin we are participating with demons and one way or another. It's not exactly
the same as a ritual participation in terms of actual worship but it's not totally dissimilar in
that both bring you into contact with and participation with whatever it is that you're worshiping.
Right? So when you do good you're participating in the life of God, right?
But there's
There's a way that you participate when you receive the Eucharist that is not the same
way that you're participating when you say, for instance, give food to the hungry, right?
It's the same God.
And you're still participating in his life, right?
So you know, to the epistemological question of how do you know that it's working?
How do you know what it is you're doing?
I mean, on one level, right, there is kind of this epistemological problem of how do you
know anything at all, right?
You know, there's ultimately most of the things that we know and act upon are just chains
of trust, right?
But the chain of trust that is the church is founded upon the revelation of God in Christ.
And it's renewed.
You know, so it's not only that we believe because someone told us who was told by someone
on back to the apostles, it's because God has revealed himself over and over again throughout
the history throughout human history.
industry. Right? So we don't only have to say, well, I hope that, you know, this long game of telephone that went from the apostles to me, you got it right, right?
Which is, I think the way that a lot of skeptical, secular-minded people would see it. Right? You know, well, it's just, you know, this big game of telephone throughout 2000 years. That's going to be wrong. Right? That's, that's not what it is.
And at the same time God reveals himself to us in various kinds of ways. Are they ways that would
satisfy someone who's looking for some kind of empirical experience? I don't think so because in the end like what
What exactly would that be right? So for instance someone could say well, I really feel like God is here tonight
And you know my the skeptical part of my brain says oh, yeah, what does that feel like and how do you know that that feeling is God?
Right, you know like like I've heard people say things like that
and
Ultimately, if we're going to be Christians, then what we look at first is the Holy Scriptures.
And if we're Orthodox Christians, we're looking at the Holy Scriptures within the tradition of the Orthodox Church.
And so when God shows up in the Scriptures, I mean, he shows up in lots of different ways,
it almost never does it describe how people feel, although the occasional bit of fear and trembling going on.
But it's not someone's like, oh, I really just felt a sense of peace and happiness, and that's how I knew God was here.
Right? That's not there.
Right, so there's actually
something much more spiritually objective about it. So, you know, I as a priest, if I go
and offer the divine liturgy, but I've had a terrible night and all kinds of things on my mind,
and I'm very worried, and maybe I was a jerk to my wife and kids. Am I still objectively offering
the Holy Eucharist? Yes, I am. And the people receiving it are still receiving it.
even though I might feel like garbage the whole time that I'm doing it.
It still is what it is.
So if we're looking for something that feels or seems supernatural to us, that is a wild
goose chase.
And it can be frankly spiritually deceptive because there are demons that will be happy
to provide you with a quote-unquote spiritual experience.
So I don't know if that's a little too roundabout way of saying it, but I think ultimately
we have to found it upon trust and faithfulness to Christ.
and believing the gospel. If we believe the gospel, then we are faithful in the following ways.
And sometimes we have to be faithful even if we don't understand or know it in a way that makes
sense to our analytical brain. Because the analytical brain, while useful, can only see certain things.
It can't see everything. And so we shouldn't expect it to be fed with the stuff that's going to prove,
for instance that God shows up on the altar when we ask him to.
So I don't know if that helps or hinders, but okay.
It provides a lot of clarity.
Okay, all right.
I don't know.
Father, did you have anything you wanted to add or actually or?
Not actually, but a lot of times we over intellectualize this stuff.
Yeah.
St. Gregory Palama said, you know, for every argument, there's a counter argument,
but you can't argue with life.
And so, you know, if I come to you and I say
Hey, you know, my car's not running.
It made this noise and I imitate the noise.
You and I could sit there all day arguing about what the right thing to do is to fix the car.
Right? We could go back and forth, we could debate it, we can hash it all out,
and we could do the same thing with theology.
What's the right way to worship? What's the right interpretation of this?
What's the, we can go back and forth forever.
This is exactly what St. Gregory Paulibos was talking about because he said it at the end of three debates with Barlin.
Bye.
But if I go to my car and I say, okay, this is what I think will help with the problem
and I do it, it will either help with the problem or it won't.
And so I think the most pragmatic level answered your question is fruit.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
If your habit of prayer and the worship you're engaging in and your pattern of being
behavior, the things you're doing in your life are drawing you closer to Christ and are
bearing fruit, you'll know.
And if you're doing things in your life that are making things worse and you're honest
with yourself, you'll know.
That being honest with yourself part can be very hard.
Right.
Yeah.
But sometimes we need some help from somebody else.
That's why, within our church, we have a spiritual father who's not me, who, when I'm
deluded, could put out to be like, yeah.
You think you're getting, you're not getting, right?
They're on their own track.
That's also why I have a wife.
I get it from both sides.
And my whole Dutch family.
But anyway, we have people outside who could check for fruit.
Right?
And help tell us when we're on the wrong track.
Yeah, and to add to that, this is also why we have,
you know, the experience of the saints saying,
okay, we have all this experience and this is what worked.
So maybe you don't...
No, we're trust yet that that's gonna work, but throughout all of these centuries, we've seen this work.
So do that.
You know?
It's like, you know, often if you've got kids, right, they're like,
you know, if they, they, you know,
they, they, they, they scraped their, their knee, whatever.
And you say, now you need to go clean that up,
or else it's gonna get infected.
And like, no, I mean, my own kids have done this. That's not gonna help.
I want a bandaid.
Like, no, no.
You've got to clean it up first, it's going to get infected.
And then you may have the band-aid, you know?
And they don't have the experience to know
that that's what needs to be done.
But I'm there, my mother is there.
She's there for that much more than I am to tell them,
look, this is what you're going to do.
You know, and that's what the saints do for us.
There's spiritual parents for us.
All right.
Well, thank you very much for that call, David.
Yeah.
Thank you.
I really appreciate it, Father.
You're welcome.
Okay, well...
So here we are in the third half of the show and now we're going to talk about the ascension.
Finally.
Yes.
We're going to talk about, we're going to start with the first place in which the ascension
is seen and described in the scriptures.
Right.
Which is in the book of Daniel.
In the book of Daniel.
That's right.
It's depicted in Daniel.
Daniel chapter seven verses nine through sixteen and skipping head just to touch, verses
and 27. And if you want to know why we're skipping because we don't want to get into who all
the beasts are and that they're not China and they're not Russia. No helicopters. People get
excited when we talk about the book of Revelation as well. And Daniel. Yeah, but this is Daniel,
and he's talking about the ascension. So I'm going to go ahead and read this because I think this is
really good to
just have in your head as we have this conversation. So everybody if you guys
are Bible pull it out to Daniel chapter seven. I'm starting with verse nine.
Sword drill. Yep. Oh, yeah. I got that reference. All right. Okay. So verse nine
of Daniel chapter seven. And this is Daniel describing his vision. As I looked,
thrones were placed and the ancient of days took his seat. His clothing was
white as snow in the hair of his head like pure wool. His throne was
fiery flames its wheels were burning fire. A stream of fire issued and came out from before
him, and a thousand thousands served him. And ten thousand times ten thousand stood before
him. The court sat in judgment and the books were opened. I looked then because of the sound
of the great words that the horn was speaking. And as I looked, the beast was killed, and its
body destroyed and given over to be burned with fire. As for the rest of the beasts, their
Dominion was taken away.
but their lives were prolonged for a season and a time.
I saw in the night visions and behold with the clouds of heaven there came one like a sun
of man, and he came to the ancient of days and was presented before him.
And to him was given dominion and glory and a kingdom that all peoples, nations and languages
should serve him.
His dominion is an everlasting dominion which shall not pass away, and his kingdom one that
shall not be destroyed.
This from me, Daniel, my spirit within me was...
anxious in the visions of my head alarmed me, I approached one of those who stood there
and asked him the truth concerning all this. So he told me and made known to me the interpretation
of the things, skipping head verse 26. But the court shall sit in judgment and his dominion
shall be taken away to be consumed and destroyed to the end. And the kingdom and the dominion
and the greatness of the kingdoms under the whole heaven shall be given to the people of
saints of the most high. His kingdom shall be an everlasting kingdom and all dominions.
shall serve and obey him." And that's the end of verse 27.
All right, so what's going on there? Well, so now that we've read that, let's point at a few
features. People probably notice some things while you were reading, right? But just to point out
a few things, and to fill in a little bit of the context that we left out. So it's not to be reading
all night. And that's so Daniel right before this sees the
the succession of beasts, right? And when he sees them in the vision, they come up out of the sea,
right? Which should have us thinking, low-tan, low-fifth, and beast from the sea, right?
Dragons. Yeah. Dragons, Hannah, dragons. So, and these are described by the angel who Daniel
asks to explain it to him as being a succession of
of empires that are going to come.
And so these are not any modern day contemporary countries.
It's not the EU.
This is, oh man, I know.
I know.
Sorry, Helllindsay.
This third eagle of the apocalypse.
This is the the Assyrians, or sorry, the Babylonians,
and then the Persians, and then the Greeks,
so you can see.
and then the Romans, finally.
And there's another vision in Daniel
with similar content of these four empires.
And so in the period of the Roman Empire,
something is going to happen, right?
Which Daniel is foreseeing.
And that's when this scene is convened.
Now it's interesting that we noted the viathan.
In the part we skipped where the angel explains to him
that.
part of the vision, he describes them as four kingdoms that will arise from the earth.
So the beast from the earth symbolism is more behemoth, right?
Behemoth, right?
So between the vision and the interpretation, you get these empires as a combination of both, right?
They participate in both of these sort of demonic forces.
And so in response to this, when we're...
the period of the Roman Empire, we read that the thrones are set or in the description
that the court will sit, and this is a description of the Divine Council.
Right. Right. So the Divine Council happens. Yahweh the God of Israel comes and takes his seat,
right, the ancient of days, surrounded by His Divine Council, note that His throne has
wheels. Yes, that's because it's a chariot throw.
this this is convened to deal with this last beast right to deal with this beast and
uh to judge it and to destroy it and in this context then this other figure arrives
uh the uh who's described as one like a son of man this like a son of man versus who
that looks like a human right there is throughout the book of Daniel uh maybe we'll do a whole
episode on the part of the video at some point.
in the future, but there is in the book of Daniel at several points a heavenly man. He's encountering these heavenly beings and several times this man who is there comes and talks to him.
So spoilers that's Christ.
But yeah.
Yeah.
So and so is this figure, right, who looks looks like a sort of man, this human looking one who's comes riding on the
clouds, it is brought before the ancient of days.
Yeah, who's described as looking like an old man, you know, long white beard, the whole
line yards.
Right.
And then the ancient of days, Yahweh, they got in Israel because he possesses this, gives
all of the authority and dominion to the Son of Man.
Right.
So he then has this power to rule over all the dominions, right?
territorial spirits who had been governing the earth are now subject to him he now rules everything but notice also in the description
Right of the in the explanation of the vision
It says that the kingdom is received by the people of the saints of the most high. Yeah, that's in jail
verse 27
Yeah, so it's both received by the Son of Man and by
The saints right the people made up of the saints of the most high
Okay. So those are just pointing out some features. So what those features would have
clued in to an ancient reader, right, in the ancient Near East, is that this is sort of
a remix, again, an inversion in many ways, of a story from the bail cycle. Yeah. Right.
right comes the old friend bail again
And that is the scene of his enthronement
which we've told a couple of the stories that a little more detail from the
bail cycle. This one we haven't gone through in the same detail. But so this story
involves Bale, the son and his father, L, who is depicted in Canaanite depictions of L as a very old man with a long white beard.
Right, right, so the Daniel language for the ancient of days is
basically saying the most high God who is the father is not L its Yahweh
Right and is taking the L imagery and applying that to Yahweh and I think it's important to realize that this is not syncretism
Right, this is not syncretism in the sense of like saying
Oh, we're gonna take this this L language and we're gonna, you know
We're gonna worship him. We're gonna change his name.
worshiping the same God. Just like Frans and we didn't mention this in this episode, but
you know the priests of Israel, the way that they're dressed, the way that God commands them to be
dressed, is basically the way that that bail idols were dressed, right? You know that that same
you know this idea that well that's the way you treat an image of your God, well actually where
the image of the one true God. And so, so the image
being co-opted not in a syncretistic way but to make an actually to make a
polemical point really. Right? And so this is another example of that. Right. And, and, and,
this is said, you know, all those things that you keep saying are true of L, aren't true of L.
Yeah. Right. They're actually true of Yahweh. And likewise, the imagery that's usually a
attributed to Bale, one of his primary titles as a storm god is the cloud writer.
Right. Right. He's the one who rides on the cloud. So not only is the real most high god,
not L its Yahweh but the real divine sun in the council. The one who really rides on the clouds
other clouds is this human looking one.
Son of man, right?
Who is the son of man?
who is the true son of God, who appears human, and who is also Yahweh, right? He doesn't have
a different name. Yeah, yeah. And another thing that's a big contrast is the relationship between
the two figures within each narrative, right? So in the bail story, bail shows up to L and
demands give me a palace, give me a temple to reside in so I can be enthroned.
is actually kind of afraid of bail because he remembers how he got in that position, right?
You know, he's like, uh, yeah, uh, he doesn't want to give it to him. You know, he's afraid of
setting him up and, you know, having him be powerful. And note, again, the contrast between the father
and our Lord, Jesus Christ, the Son of God who is simply approaches his father and his father
gives him the dominion.
There's no struggle, there's no rivalry. It's just love and humility. You know, it's completely different, completely different.
And here's where the bail story really goes off the rails. This is the fun part.
So since Elle doesn't want to give bail this palace temple,
Bill goes and talks to his wife who also happens to be his sister.
Yeah.
And Elle's daughter.
who is named a not. And a not as you might imagine if you're going to have, you know, the main goddess of an ancient
Eastern pantheon is a fertility goddess, seen as a fertility goddess. And there's sort of a parody there where you've got
Bale is a storm god, right, sends the rains and then those rains are received by the ground
and fertility brings forth.
Crops.
You've got a certain parallel there, that all seems nice, except a knot is also a goddess
of brutal warfare, who is described and depicted as wearing a necklace made of severed human
heads and a belt made of severed human hands.
So I hope if we ever have a Lord of Spirits Convention, that we have it in November, so
so that people can hit up the Spirit Halloween store clearance.
before it closes down and get there a not cosplay together, right? Because that would be great.
So it's lost a bunch of parents amongst her.
Exactly. Turn that off. So she goes and again this is kind of awkward but uses her feminine
and while on her own father to convince
him to give her brother, husband, what he wants in terms of the palace and L sort of
finally agrees. I think it is probably not coincidental the way the story of the beheading
of St. John the Forerunner can be errors this. But that's another future episode.
I'll leave that to Pedro.
So, but so, and then it says in the Bale's side, that Bale then has all all rule in the heavens
once he's been enthroned.
And now contrast this with all dominion in heaven and on earth in the Daniel story.
is Ellen Bale don't have control over the whole earth.
Yeah, they're local, relatively speaking.
And so, yeah, and so this is, but this is related to the way,
the whole kingdom of heaven language that comes up in the,
in the gospels, in particular, the synoptic gospels.
We tend to because it's translated with the word kingdom,
that's very reified, it's a noun, right? We think of kingdom as an object.
But the word is really more about the rule or dominion.
Yeah.
of the Shib even more of God, right?
It's about the extension of power and authority.
And so when we, for example, in exclamations and worships,
say, vying is the kingdom and the power and the glory,
we mean dying is opposed to anybody else's who may claim
that it's theirs.
Yeah, there's so much language in Scripture
and in Orthodox liturgical tradition
that is precisely expressing
I was going to use the word rivalry, but it's not rivalry because God has no rival, but it's offering these corrections
You know that like for instance, you know the earth is the Lord's and the fullness throughout the earth is the Lord's and not anyone else's
You know thine is the kingdom not anybody else
you know right right and
So then when we get to the New Testament
So if you understand Daniel's vision and you understand how
it's reworking and inverting this bail story and what's going on there in Daniel's vision.
When you read about, we're finally getting to the ascension, when you're at the end of the episode,
when you finally get to the descriptions of the ascension in the New Testament, in the gospels
and in Acts, you find that they're deliberately connecting what's going on to what Daniel saw.
Right.
right? Yeah, so then the most probably obvious would be in Matthew chapter 28
verses 18 through 20 and this is part of is it the whole thing? I don't think is the
whole thing but part of the first aothin on gospel and of course also some of
this is read at a baptism. So chapter 28 verse starting with verse 18 Jesus
came and said to them, all authority in heaven.
and on earth has been given to me, go there for, and to make disciples of all nations baptizing
them in the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit, teaching them to observe
all that I have commanded you, and behold, I am with you always to the end of the age.
This is what the Lord says right before He ascends into heaven. All authority in heaven and on earth
has been given to me. So He's entering into His rest. He's entering, He's going up to His enthronement.
right
And so because he's taking that position, he says, now you go out now and make disciples
of all nations baptizing them, teaching them to do all these things, teaching them to become
faithful. And I'm with you always to the end of the age, which is not an ironic statement
because he's about to ascend and go away somewhere. It's actually I'm going to go and be enthroned
and now you are going to participate in my rule. You are going to co-claim this. You're going
to do the thing that Adam failed to do.
by bringing the paradesal experience of God's presence into all the world and
driving out the demons who have been oppressing it. And that has been given to
me, we gloss over really quickly to get to the rest of it. Has been given to me
right by who, by the Father, which is exactly what Daniel saw. Yeah. The Father
giving Christ all authority and all dominion in heaven.
on earth. Yeah yeah. All right we got a passage from Acts. Father do you want to address that one?
Sure. So in Acts 1 verses 6 through 11, which also describes the ascension. This is,
Saint Luke has a brief description at the end of his gospel of the ascension. Very brief, but then
at the beginning of the Acts of the Apostles, he letches it out a little more. And so in Acts 1,
beginning in verse 6.
So when they had come together, they asked him,
Lord will you at this time restore the kingdom to Israel?
He said to them,
it is not for you to know times or seasons
that the Father has fixed by his own authority,
but you will receive power when the Holy Spirit
has come upon you, and you will be my witnesses
in Jerusalem and in all Judea and Samaria
and to the end of the earth.
And when he had said these things,
as they were looking on,
he was lifted up and a cloud took him out of their sight.
And while they were gazing into heaven as he went,
a whole
two men stood by them in white robes and said,
men of Galilee, why do you stand looking into heaven?
This Jesus who was taken up from you into heaven
will come in the same way as you saw him go into heaven.
So a couple of things there, right?
One of the most obvious and important ones
is that cloud that shows up.
So this isn't a reverse of the opening to the Simpsons, right?
Where just like Christ goes up into the sky
and then a cloud drips over
You can't see him anymore.
right? This is talking about the cloud taking him away is actually carrying him away. He is riding on a
cloud, which is exactly how Daniel sees him arrive in heaven. So same event. And you notice that
that kingdom language is here too, right? It's now when you're going to restore the kingdom to Israel,
Right, that's not saying...
Or are you going to give us your our own king now?
Yeah
Right are we are we gonna be an independent kingdom from the Romans again like we were with John here canis
Right, that's not what they're getting it right because remember kingdom is this this rule the power of God
Right, that's what Israel's been missing
Hmm, right? That's what Israel has has been missing
And so he says, look, you don't worry about...
Right? The big picture stuff. Here's your assignment. Right? And the assignment he gives them is actually how that dominion is going to be returned to the Israel of God, which is going to be them, right?
Church.
Yep.
Okay, now we've got one from Mark chapter 14.
This is again from the Ascension account.
And Jesus said,
I am and you will see the Son of Man seated at the right hand of power
and coming...
with the clouds of heaven. And in our pre-show discussion, Father, you pointed out that the verb
about them seeing him is a little odd and it kind of means from now on. So I am and from now on,
you will see the Son of Man seated at the right hand of power and coming with the clouds of heaven.
And again, this is his exact same imagery of the ascension as depicted in Daniel.
You know, he's the cloud rider. He's seated there at the right hand of power.
more.
If
everything that's about to proceed after that with the the apostles going out into all the world and the expansion of the church. All of this is about the extension of the rule of God into the world.
Yeah, Mark, of course, much more terse as always in his gospel. So yeah, yeah.
Yeah, and of course, right, this is also, if you want an old testament, verse that's talking about this, Psalm 110 or 10.
verse 9 verse 1, the Lord said to my Lord,
sit at my right hand until I make your enemies your footstool.
This is the most quoted Old Testament text in the New Testament.
Over and over and over and over again, right?
Christ quotes it to the scribes and the Pharisees.
A big chunk of the book of Hebrews is based on interpreting it.
It shows up everywhere.
And that's because this is the place where the Apostles and the New Testament writers found themselves
Right that Christ had ascended and was seated at the right hand of the Father and
Now was ruling for this period of time until the ultimate defeat of his enemies. Yeah
Cool
Okay, so the last thing we're gonna look at is from Revelation to
to disappoint all the Baptists.
Yeah.
Yeah, yeah.
Woo.
I was a disappointed Baptist once.
Revelation 20 verses 4 through 6.
Then I saw Throne's and seated on them
were those to whom the authority to judge was committed.
Also, I saw the souls of those who had been
beheaded for the testimony of Jesus and for the Word of God.
And those who had not worshipped the bee
store its image and not received its mark on their foreheads
their hands. They came to
life and rained with Christ for a thousand years. The rest of the dead did not come to life
until the thousand years were ended. This is the first resurrection. Blessed and holy
is the one who shares in the first resurrection. Over such, the second death has no power,
but they will be priests of God and of Christ, and they will reign with him for a thousand
years. Right. So obviously, this is the, I say obviously, obviously, if you've listened
all the way to this 20th episode of the podcast, you can see the
This is the Divine Council.
You know, these throes set up,
again, plural, notice again, it's plural.
And that, you know, these who have been,
these martyrs, those who have been beheaded, right?
They come to life and they reign with Christ.
They are given this authority to judge, right?
They are participating now in the ascension.
Because the ascension's not just a matter of going up,
It's a matter of this path.
This is where we started right with the big footprints, the path to the throne, the path
to the enthromant, the victory at the end of all the works being done.
And now these scenes have participated in that they have been doing the works of God.
They have walked of the same path with Christ, and they are now seated on thrones beside
His, and they reign with Christ.
And this is, as St. John says here, this is the first resurrection, this experience
of these saints, right? And they are priest as it says of God and of Christ,
reigning with him. What does it mean that they're priests? Well, priests basically have two jobs.
They offer sacrifices and they intercede for others. And we see them, especially there in
revelation, interceding before the throne of God. So this is the telos of mankind's possibility
You
that he joined Christ in his ascension
and that he reign with him, next to him.
They participate in those same works,
having participated in those works along the way,
having walked the path with the big footprints,
the path of God himself.
Right.
And St. John here, I mean, it's beyond doubt,
he's using the same language Daniel used
about the Therones being said.
Right?
And right after the passage you read is where the dragon is judged, just like the beast is judged in Daniel, right?
So St. John is describing the same scene that the prophet Daniel is. And so this isn't, you know,
Daniel's talking about one thing and St. John's talking about something else in the future.
This is part and parcel of the ascension in the enthronement, and
this is part and parcel of
He's drawing on what Daniel is talking about when he described how the vision was inter-
to him that when the kingdom is entrusted to Christ, when he receives the dominion, that
dominion is also received by the people of the saints of the most high, and they reign
and rule with him for this period of time in the midst of his enemies, right? And they
live to service priests and intercede, and they rule with him until the time comes for
the end.
All right, well, that's the end of our third half.
And just to give some final thoughts, you know?
So there are a couple of things that struck me
in this discussion.
One, of course, is like we were just talking about
where these visions that are,
that exist, that are seen in the Old Testament
and these actions by God in the Old Testament
are not just predictions of something that's gonna happen
the new customer.
some other time in the future. They are participating in the same reality. Right? So now there is a change.
I mean, we pointed out a couple of discontinuities between the old and the New Testament or things that are transformed along the way.
So what you get with the coming of Christ into the world is fulfillment of the old testament. And as fathers even loves to point out,
fulfilled does not mean there was a prediction. And then it came true.
So, um, nor does it mean like in the
case of the Mosaic Law, it's abolished, abolished, it's over. But rather full filled is what it actually says, it's full filled, it's filled up to the full, right?
So the cop has something in it, and then it's filled up to the full, right? In the end, right? So, so, you know, Daniel sees the ascension.
I mean, he's he's not predicting the future. He sees it happening.
He's participating in his way in his
if we need to talk about that way. And then St. John sees it as well, and he's also participating in
his own vision, even though if we think about it in terms of timelines, he's seeing it after it's
already happened, right? But he's not just seeing the event of Christ ascending into heaven, but he's
also seeing what that means in terms of his enthronement and the saints enthroned alongside him,
We're seeing John himself now as one of those as well.
Particip-
participating in the first resurrection.
Right?
So that was one thing that really occurred to me.
And the other one was I was really just struck by the Sabbath imagery, you know, that God enters into his rest after creating the world.
That Christ enters into his rest after completing the creation. Right?
It's not that the creation gets completed multiple times, once in Genesis and since one later.
They're again, they're participating in the same singular reality of the acts of God.
It doesn't work out in terms of chronological timelines and time travel and whatever.
It doesn't work out because that's not the way to understand the way that these things work.
But then also, I mean, this for me was actually a sort of almost a personal revelation really
because I'd never heard this before, but looking all this now, it's so clear that
The Sabbath that was made for men, it's
It's not, as we said earlier, it's not man needs a break so we can take the weekend off,
you know, or one day.
The Sabbath that's made for man is the ascension and the enthronement and the participation
in God's rule that was made for man.
That's what was made for man, right?
And so, you know, that's astonishing to think about on the macro level, right?
And if you think about it just in terms of your own...
daily quote unquote mundane life, right? You might think, well, that's not what I do on the weekend.
I don't, I'm not ascending into heaven and ruling with God. Like, well, actually, if you're going to worship,
then you are, you are, you're walking that path. You're going to the place where the Lord's enthroned.
you're participating.
in his rule. Right? And the beautiful thing is that the Sabbath is not just a day on the weekend.
Now that's one of the ways that we richly participate in it. Right? But really we're being
called to extend the Sabbath outwards so that all of our lives involve this. Now by that,
I don't mean that your whole week becomes a weekend. That's not what I'm saying. Again,
It's a very sort of material way.
reading this. But the point is is that we turn the world by participating in God, we turn the world
into participation in his rest, in his harmony, his creativity, his beauty, his rule, his love,
for all mankind. There's a reason why when a parish community is working well and it's at peace
and everyone's serving one another, that there is this warmth of love that's there. And the reason is
because the
people are actually experiencing this rest, this ascension, this enthronement, this rule,
this order, this beauty, this harmony of God.
That's what they're experiencing.
They're participating in it, and so it changes them.
And then they are sent at the end of the divine liturgy just as the apostles were sent to
go into all the world and to bring this Sabbath everywhere that they go.
.
It's not the only way of looking at the ascension, but to me it is now just a really an utterly
astonishingly powerful way of looking at it and then being inspired to participate in it.
So yes, we go to church and celebrate the feast of the ascension.
But in doing that, we're actually seeing on a day what it is that we do all the time
and what it is recalled to do every day and what...
our final destiny in Christ through faithfulness actually is. Father?
So when Daniel had his vision and that vision was recorded and given to God's people, and
when the gospels and the Acts of the Apostles were written and described Christ's ascension,
when Saint John received his vision.
and wrote the book of Revelation,
and they wrote about this reality
we've been talking about tonight.
They did it to people who were suffering.
Not people who are suffering from insecurities,
not people who are suffering
from sort of low grade inconveniences and minor problems,
but people who were suffering,
people who were enslaved,
people who...
had family members being killed, sometimes in front of them, sometimes tortured to death,
for trying to be faithful to God. And in all of these cases, what this vision proclaims very
powerfully is that regardless of who claims to be Lord, whether it's Nebuchadnezzar, whether it's
it's Cyrus or Darius, whether it's Anticus Epiphanies, whether it's...
it's Caesar, whoever claims to be Lord isn't. Whoever claims to be Lord is a
pretender and a fake, just like the gods they worship because the one who is
truly Lord is our Lord Jesus Christ. He is the one who has all dominion and
and authority on earth. The only thing the fake
lords can do.
is kill and destroy. There's sort of like Janice and Jambras, the magicians in Egypt,
right, who come to, this sometimes gives people problems because they're like, well, how could they
replicate what Moses did? Well, think about what they replicated, right, through Moses, all of the
drinkable water in Egypt is turned into blood, except for a very little bit, and the magicians show
up and turn that last little bit into blood and make it undrinkable.
Thanks!
And then Egypt is infested with frogs and vermin.
And they're like, hey, well, we could make more frogs and vermin.
So yeah, they can destroy, they can kill, they can't create, they can't do what God does.
And so in their anger and to try to prove that they're really Lord, they will come and
they will inflict suffering, they will come and kill the people of God, they will come
and attack them.
at the behest of the gods that they worship.
But what we see in the saints and the martyrs
is because they had had this same vision.
Like say, Stephen had this vision.
The vision we see described of Christ and Throne.
They would literally, in some cases, mock the people
who were torturing them to death.
They would make jokes as they were being fried on a rack
to that they were done on the one side.
It needed to be flipped over like Saint Louis.
They would ignore the sufferings. They were unimportant. Because the truth is that no one can harm the righteous man.
The person who loves Christ and belongs to Christ, the worst they could do to you is kill you.
and when that happens, you go to rule and reign with him,
including ruling and reigning over and eventually judging
that person who murdered you.
That's the promise that we have in this vision.
And so if we really understand what the ascension is about, this should give us a lot more
confidence in the way that we live our life.
This is where St. Paul got his confidence, despite the shipwrecks and the beatings and
the persecution and the hatred and the mocking he took.
He knew that for him to live was Christ and to die was gain.
And so we didn't have to-
be afraid of anything or anyone. Anything anyone did to him would ultimately work for his
benefit, for his blessings and his glory and blessings and glory that are eternal over
against sufferings that are temporary, even if they go on for our whole lives here on
this earth. So that to me I think is sort of a takeaway. If we really have this vision
before us.
Then all of a sudden we don't have to worry about who's president.
We don't have to worry about where there's certain bills past Congress.
We don't really have to worry about anything anymore because we serve and more importantly
are loved by the God who rules over all of it.
Amen.
Well, that is our show.
for tonight. Thank you everyone for tuning in and listening. If you didn't get a
chance to call in during the live broadcast, we'd love to hear from you either via
email at Lordofspiritsatinchandfate.com or you can message us at our LordofSpirits
podcast Facebook page. We read everything but cannot respond to everything. You guys
send us a lot of email. We love it though. We do save a lot of what you send for
possible use in future episodes. And I'm back off Facebook but never again is what
I swear the time before.
Join us for our live broadcast on the second and fourth Thursdays of the month at 7pm Eastern 4pm Pacific.
And if you are on Facebook like our page and join our discussion group,
leave reviews and ratings everywhere. Most importantly though, share this show with a friend whom you know is going to love it.
And finally be sure to go to www.inxupac.com slash support and help make sure we and lots of other AFR podcasters stay on the air.
Thank you very much and God bless you and happy Feast of the Ascension.
You've been listening to the Lord of Spirits with Orthodox Christian priests, Father
Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen De Young, a listener-supported presentation of
Ancient Faith Radio.
And I beheld and I heard the voice of many angels round about the throne and the beasts
and the elders, and the number of them was ten-
thousand times ten thousand than thousands of thousands,
saying with a loud voice, worthy is the land
that was slain to receive power and riches and wisdom and strength and honor and glory
and blessing.
Revelation chapter 5 verses 11 through 12.
you
This is becoming a healing presence with Dr. Albert Rossi.
In order to become a healing presence for others, we must first be healed ourselves through
an active relationship with the great.
Thank you.