For time, many year into break free of the prison of a flat, secular materialism, to see and
to know reality as it truly is.
What is this spiritual reality like?
How do we engage with it well?
How do we permeate everyday life with spiritual presence?
Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen De Young
host this live Colin show, focused on enchantment in creation, the union of the scene and unseen
as made by God.
and experienced by mankind throughout history.
Welcome to the Lord of Spirits.
Welcome back everyone to the Lord of Spirits podcast,
where we're going to be taking a voyage into the underworld.
I'm Father Andrew Stephen Damick and I'm a Aspensovania.
Joining me tonight is my co-host, Father Stephen D'Young,
from Lafayette, Louisiana.
And if you're listening to us live,
you can call in at 855 AF radio, that's 855-237-2346.
and
we will get to your calls in the second part of today's show.
Last time on Lord of Spirits, we introduced the idea of sacred geography,
including some mind-bending regarding what it means to be, that being is a verb.
Tonight we're going to be taking a journey into the underworld,
but first we're going to do a little recap to summarize and hopefully clarify some of our
points about what it means to be being and exactly what human consciousness
has to do with what we like to call objective reality and what all of that has to do with mantis shrimp.
Yes, you heard me. Mantis shrimp. There were a lot of questions from last time.
So I hope this out, Father Steven, when we say that human consciousness
produces the world, are we saying that the world is just the matrix, but where the computer?
No, no, okay. I feel like most of my leading questions at the beginning, you just say no.
So yeah, and as you said if people are listening live they can call in with any questions they
have.
If you're listening to us dead you probably don't need to listen you can just kind
of look around.
That's right.
I'd see the stuff that we're going to be talking about tonight.
Indeed.
Yes.
Look around.
Tell us what it's like.
Yeah, tell us where we're wrong.
So yeah, we talked about last time.
about the fact that the world that we live in,
so the world for me, the world for you, right,
is not just this sort of objective thing
that's out there.
Yeah.
But the world that I live in and interact with
is the product of my human consciousness
consciousness and uh...
certain tools that my human consciousness uses. We talked about language, art, music, and ritual
to construct that world. Right. Right. So some folks I think took that to mean like we're
all living in a hallucination or the hallucination or yeah. Yeah. Like if I just you know
So.
And I was trying to counter some of that with I don't have reference
titan a few times as quote about the brute facticity of reality.
Yeah.
You can close your eyes and wish really hard, but you're still going to hit that wall
when you walk into it, right?
Yeah, right.
Right.
And I think one like especially since we know we have a lot of fans.
We're also fans of the work of Jonathan Peugeot.
Hello Peugeotians.
Um, you know, he wrote an article a number of years ago called most of the time.
The world is flat.
Now Jonathan Peugeot is not a flat earther, but what he means by that is that your experience
of life in the world is that it's flat.
Like if you actually experience the world as being curved, you know, then that would be
very disorienting for one thing.
And you know, part of that of course is the experience of, you know, for instance the
sun coming up in the morning and going down in the evening.
Now from a quote unquote objective point of view, that's not what the sun does.
Earth turns.
But we don't experience the earth turning like I don't currently have the sensation of going however many thousands of miles per hour
The earth goes
Right, I feel like I'm stationary in fact here the sun is in the process of going down and
That is what my day
Consistent and it's not in illusion right. It's not an illusion
But it's what my actual conscious experience of the world is and and even like the human body has ways of
You know, you've got the what you call circadian rhythms, which of course, you know, if you
The last thing you do is you look at your smartphone
before you go to bed and you're throwing,
you know, you're throwing your circadian ripples off.
But, you know, that's an example
of part of what we're talking about, right?
And we're gonna even talk a little bit more about things
that we can't even detect even with like,
you know, equipment and so forth.
But that's what we mean is there's a sense of,
it's not just point of view,
it's what you're actually able to experience.
Not just what you imagine.
There's an actual interplay.
Right. So we talked about how a created anything, right, has an internal order, right, that
makes it what it is, and then it's part of a web of relationships. Right. And so when
I encounter people and animals and plants and things out in the world, I'm not encountering
like the totality of those being.
No, right. And I'm definitely not encountering what it is to be that being. Meaning when I see a bat, right?
Like I'm not, I still have no clue what it's like to be a bat. But also I'm not by seeing a bat taking
into totality even of the external right properties of a bat. Yeah, you can even detect all of all of the
the bats energies and the
world to say nothing of what what what bathecens right is I've seen in itself right certain
I'm seeing certain I'm encountering certain parts of that web of relationships
specifically how that thing relates to me yeah yeah right and and so and that's true of
everything and everybody who I encounter right right right I know my wife and knowing her more
intimately means I understand.
a greater part of that web of relationships, but I still don't know what it's like to be
her.
Yeah, right.
Right.
Like, I can't enter into her subjectivity.
Yeah.
I can't enter into her essence, as it were.
Right.
And so, okay.
So, we've already then kind of hinted at using these words, but just to connect it to a
piece of orthodox theology that if you're orthodox, you've probably at least heard of this.
You know, there is what's called the essence energy's distinction.
And often, you know, most of the time in orthodox theology.
We'll talk about essence and energies with relationship to God.
You know, we cannot know God in himself, right, in his essence,
but we experience him in his energies.
But I remember, you know, when I was in seminary,
I think it was Dr. Harry Boussales,
who was a great professor at C.T. cons, by the way.
I think he was the one who said to us one time,
he said, you know, you guys have essence and energies too.
And everyone was like, whoa, you know,
And you know that that that let me think about just think about
describing another person, the only things you can say about that person is the way that you experience them.
You know, he does this, he acts this way, he seems to have this kind of personality.
It's his operations to use the Latin-based term. His energies, you know, his working in the world, that is what you experience.
But his inner essence is not something that's knowable to you.
to you. You know, only God knows the
the inter-essences of all things, better than they know themselves actually.
So there is, you don't know them as they know themselves
and you certainly don't know them the way that God knows them.
And I think one of the problems of the modern
scientism, scientistic viewpoint is this illusion
of objectivity suggesting that there is this possibility
that we can know things as they truly are.
Or more likely that we just sort of reduce,
just all the things that we don't actually see,
we just assume that that's not even that's...
not even part of what it means to be that thing, right?
The thing is just the material in front of us or whatever, for instance, you know?
So, you know, the essence and energy distinction is exactly what we're talking
about.
It's exactly what we're talking about.
Right.
That's the separation between, right, that order, right, that being put in order is what
it means to be, as we said.
And essence in Greek is just the participle for being, right?
So that's that that internal ordering the the web of
relationships to everything else, that's where we encounter everyone and everything that we encounter.
So we don't know what it's like to be another person, we don't know what it's like to be a bat,
we don't know what it's like to be a tree, we don't know what it's like to be the earth, right?
I don't want to go too far down the pan-psychist trail, but...
That's where the sleep, but we don't know what it's like to be an angelic being,
we don't know who's in charge of one of those things.
Yeah
Yeah, we don't we don't know any of those things and we definitely don't know what it's like to be a mantis shrimp
Right right so we use the example of color and
Last time and I think some people got hung up on the details maybe but
Coming at it from we're gonna come at it from the other side
With our friend the mantis shrimp, okay, so
Mantis shrimp have these amazing eyeballs
That's a human and most other higher mammals have three sets of photo or
setters in their retinas. Right. So for us it's RGB, red, green, blue, and
everything that you see is some combination of red, and or green, and or blue.
Right. And you know, I used to do lighting design and theater and literally
everything that we did was the combination of red, and or green, and or blue.
Everything, everything right.
and birds have four which helps them see in low light.
Is it, are they an infrared? Is that what they can see?
Yeah, there it is. Like night vision goggles for you.
Nice. And mantis shrimp have 12 to 16.
So they can see, it's not just like, oh, they can see infrared and ultraviolet.
They can see more colors.
like beyond that that we don't have names for.
Right. And it's not just a matter of seeing 12 to 16 colors.
Because remember, we, we, we, the colors we see are, are basically all
combinations of three. So they can combine those 12 to 12 16.
Yeah. So. And we also, I also mentioned to you right before the show
started also that we have binocular vision. So each of our eyes produces
an image in our brain puts them together.
each of their eyes, they have two eyes, but each eye produces three images. So they actually have six images that their brains put together with all of those colors.
Yeah, it's a good thing that these things are only about the size of a small kitten.
Yeah, because otherwise, and because like there would be these vicious, vicious monsters that would be incredibly good at hunting.
and you know, and they are very aggressive by the way.
You don't want to keep one in your home aquarium
unless you have like a bulletproof glass.
because they literally can shatter the glass.
And if you keep anything else in the aquarium,
it will be attacked and eaten.
Yeah, yeah.
So apparently, yeah,
being able to see all the psychedelic colors
doesn't make you cool and peaceful.
How about that?
It just helps you be a better jerk and hunt.
But so, but the point of bringing up the mantis shrimp,
beyond turning this into a nature special.
David Attenborough coming in
doing the dais.
is that, right? So those other colors, right? Let's say, you know, rough estimate, there's
there's 48 other colors, right? That a that a mantis shrimp can see that I can't. Okay?
If the mantis shrimp had language, it could name those. And mantis shrimps could describe
them to each other, right? And talk about those colors. I can't, like I could make up names.
I could be like, okay.
Okay, the one right above ultraviolet is ultra ultraviolet.
But then if you say to me,
okay, Father Stephen, describe ultra ultraviolet,
I got nothing.
Yeah, all you can say is sort of positionally where it is.
Which is the same as,
which is the same as our, you know, the earth turning.
We can take photos of it.
You know, we can take video of it
if we put a camera out in space.
But we don't actually see that happening.
We have to imagine it happening.
But imagining is not the same thing as seeing it.
Right, and so if we say there's a handful.
of those colors that the mantis shrimp is the only creature that can see. And then let's
say we go and exterminate all the mantis shrimp because they're starting to grow and they're
looking like they're going to take over, right? So we go and exterminate all the mantis
shrimp. Those wavelengths of light that produce to those colors for the mantis shrimp will
still exist, right? Those wavelengths of light and radiation will be out there in the universe.
that color will know
longer exist because no one will see it. The color only exists because there's a conscious
mind that can process that wavelength of light into that color. The color is produced by
that interaction of the light that is there and the consciousness that is there. And so
this is what we're talking about when we talk about the world we live in. Sometimes the
word holographic is used by philosophers, but that will give people the wrong impression
again I think it's a ho-
in the world.
This is a simulation theory.
But that the world we live in and function in every day is therefore produced by the interaction
of our human consciousness with the world that's objectively out there.
Right.
And I think it probably, we, I don't know, correct me if this is wrong.
The only one who can objectively see all things would be the Lord.
Well, I don't know if that's the right way of putting it, maybe.
Yeah, yeah. So the problem is when we talk about the subject object distinction,
yeah, we're talking about created beings. Yes, right. And he's not. Yeah. Right. So yeah,
I can only imagine that God see, you know, like we talked about God seeing all things. Yeah,
yeah. God trans sends that subject object decision because God, for example,
does know what it's like to be a bat, even though he hasn't been a bat. Yeah, right. Right.
strictly speaking.
He knows the essence of all things. Yes
So relatedly
Why is all this important?
Point two of our brief review is space and time don't exist. There we go
Good night everybody. Yeah
The show is over before it began
Right. I know. These are the episodes of Star Trek, my wife hates by the way.
Okay, yeah.
Yeah.
A little shot after her.
Usually the writers just do a lot of techno battle.
Yeah, I just punt inertial stabilizers and yeah, heisenberg, compensators and all
that stuff.
Exactly.
So what does that mean?
Well, right.
Yeah, that's what is in time are our experience.
I don't want to just sit here and be like, hey man, let's blow everybody's mind, right?
because you're not all mantis shrimp looking at weird colors out there.
But space isn't made out of anything.
Yeah.
It's not a thing.
And time's not a thing, exactly.
See there is time.
Yeah.
So that's what I mean when I say they don't exist, they're not things, right?
So space and time are categories and are ways that humans, because they're finite, right?
Right, this is related to what we're just talking about.
We don't know.
things as they are in themselves, only how they present themselves to us, because we're
finite.
Yeah.
So in the same way, because we're finite, we're limited in terms of both space and time.
So this is what I was getting at last time when I was talking about how we tend to think
of the past ceases to exist and the future doesn't exist yet.
And there's this ever transitory moment that exists now.
Uh, could you see?
that times keep slipping into the future?
Yes.
You're just trying to make this as trippy as possible.
So, you're going to have your black lights and their posters.
Yeah.
So, that's not correct.
What we find, and this is why I've mentioned a couple of few times now,
booktand of St. Augustine's confessions his understanding of time consciousness.
So it's not how time works.
It's how human consciousness of time works.
How the human experience of time works.
Right, which I mean everybody's had the experience
of it feels like time flies
or that something is going very slowly.
And you know, and then I actually watched a video
about this just the other day.
It was the voice of Steve who showed it to me.
And you know, it was this guy talking about how
when something is really dull,
it seems like time goes by very slowly,
but when something is varying.
It seems to go by very quickly, but then when you try to remember those times later
That you remember the engaging time much more fully than you remember the the dull time because in the dull time
There was much less to remember right you did four memories. Yeah, right exactly exactly
And so like this is just one example and you could say, oh, well, that's just perception like well
That's that's what we're talking about
You know time is just perception right right time is just perception
So there's a bunch of qualifiers that's, and again, I don't want to just be like, hey, let's blow people's minds
But there's what's referred to as deep time
So let's say hypothetically
I'm just gonna throw this out and never pay it off, but let's just say hypothetically
That geologists are right the earth has been here for billions of years, okay?
While there were no created conscious beings on the planet
That saying billions of years is meaningless. There was no time
time.
because there were no conscious beings to experience time.
There you go.
Anyway, so I'll never pay that off because I hate talking about creation and evolution.
Sorry, everybody.
Believe it or not, this show actually is about the underworld.
But as with this, we're so massive setup.
Yes, we're getting it.
This is still just the recap.
But there were a lot of questions about this in our Facebook group,
Facebook group which is very helpful.
Right? So we kind of understand, we can see how you guys are hearing what we're saying,
and then maybe try to fill in some spaces.
So that's how it's written here before we take the next step.
Yeah, exactly.
And I say fill in space because there's no such thing.
Right.
So if you understand time in this way, and I know you have some people who identify as philosophy
nerds, so for those folks, this is the theory of time.
All points in time exist in the same sense that all points in space exist, meaning,
Right leg.
I don't sit here and say, well, Lafayette is real and Emmaus is not real yet or used to
be real, but isn't anymore, right?
If I get on a plane here in Lafayette and fly to Philly to come visit you, when I depart
Lafayette, Lafayette doesn't cease to exist, right?
And then like Philly, Delphi Airport comes into being and then it recedes and Emmaus
comes into being as I travel, right?
You would never say that about...
space. We understand the same is true about time. Right. Okay. So this gets to what we were
talking about in terms of ritual and one of the specific ways that ritual interacts with,
again, we're talking about that interaction between our human consciousness and the reality that's
out there, that really is out there. One of the ways that acts upon it is that ritual will cause a
a particular place and a particular
time to become not just sacred space and sacred time, but a particular sacred space and sacred
time.
So the burning of the incense in the temple made it paradise.
It became paradise in that space for that time.
Holy Thursday your local parish church even if it's in a storefront or even if it's
a cathedral or if you go to a monastery, becomes Galgotha for a period of time. And not just
Galgotha in terms of place, Galgotha in terms of time. So we say, today this is happening.
Yeah, which is why then the actions that people, let's say, for instance, you mentioned only
Thursday, you know, the cross is placed in the center of the church in the Byzantine practice.
and you know people come and venerate the cross.
It's not that that stands for the cross of Christ.
It is being the cross of Christ.
And think about iconography in the same way.
Iconography by the way that you interact with it is being the encounter of the saint
for you at that moment.
So that's why then the father say, well, the veneration shown to the icon passes to the
prototype.
because it's become...
I mean, the prototype is present for you at that moment,
like not just in a symbolic in the sense of this stands for this.
You know, it's not like a dollar signs,
you know, when a dollar sign stands for money,
but you can't spend it.
You know, it's not like that.
It's actually as present, this ritual participation.
So this is why all this matters.
I know it's all very mind-bending stuff.
Yeah.
So this is why it all matters.
Symbol doesn't mean one thing that allegorically represents it.
another. Right. Or analogically represents another. It's when two things are brought together.
One thing becomes the other. Yeah. And I'll throw out one more tease even though I said earlier,
I wasn't going to do this to everybody. But tease for a future relics episode. There we go.
Huzz time doesn't exist. Any given thing that exists in the world is itself throughout its
existence and is wholly present throughout its existence.
This is how relics work.
So say John Crassostum's hand is say John Crassostum.
Yeah.
Yeah, I mean, like I visited three years ago, I went on pilgrimage to Mount Athos and among
the probably several hundred relics that I have enter into the space of a week was the
hand of St. Mary Magdalene, which not only is incorrupt and flexible but maintains body
temperature.
So some relics
do this more obviously than others, right? Some of them it's very intense. Yeah, this is
why relics work. They're not. It's not a souvenir. It's not a talisman. It is the person.
And so when we're talking about God and God's eternity or God's transcendence or God's
ubiquity.
We're not talking about, for example, I know some people heard us and thought, oh, you're saying God is outside of time. That's sometime how it's said.
Yeah.
Like time is this bubble and the God is outside.
There's this bubble of time.
Looking down at it.
But outside is a spatial category.
So you can't be that's like saying you existed before time. Well, before is a temporal category.
Yeah
language that's used for this and it's used in the fathers and this is developed especially by
Father Duma True, Staneloi, whose last name I probably mispronounce every time I say it.
But right in and tell us from him exactly how that's it.
Yes, well we have a Romanian friend who may be messaging me already but
but he talks about how God's attributes are super not super but super essential.
Meaning essential.
Yeah, right meaning it's not that God is everywhere like you
just really big and spread out all over the place. Right. But that it's that that
spatial categories don't apply to God. So it's equally true to say that God is everywhere.
Right. That there's not a place where he isn't. And also to say that God is nowhere.
Yeah. It's saying there's not some particular place where we as humans can localize him.
Yeah. Right. This is that our finitude versus his
finitude.
Alright.
lack of finitude coming into play.
But so as we said, this is how the idea of sacred time
in space that we talked about last time works.
A particular time in place, a particular day
is made a sacred and holy day.
And that first time is when that spiritual event,
that eternal event first manifested itself
in.
human conscious experience, but then that reality is made present again and again,
ritually. Yeah, and that's a super important point because sometimes people say,
well, you know, why do you have all these holidays? You know, isn't every day holy or isn't
every place holy, right? And the problem there is when you say everything, you know, now on
one level, that's true, right? That that everything has become holy. It's all become dedicated to God.
But when when
people say, well, isn't every day holy, it's like saying, well, isn't every day your birthday?
Then that means we never have a party.
And then we're never actually celebrating my birthday, you know, which might be a good
idea.
I don't know.
My birthday is always a fasting day.
But let me, let me suggest the alternative approach to that problem, which is you could
have a party every day, every day, right?
So we could make every place and every time holy.
We could do that.
I'm not so good at it.
Yes, right.
I'm not so good at, but we could.
This is what St. Paul is getting at.
When St. Paul talks about some people
honor Sadduce and new moons, right?
The holidays, right?
The Holy Days.
And then some treat them like every other day.
We as modern people read that like,
oh, I don't have to do that stuff.
Yeah, you know, there was just kind of.
I would just be lazy.
Yeah, we just cut out the ritual participation.
Right.
We treat every day like Monday, right?
It would work there, right?
Yeah, but it's the ritual participation.
that actually makes our experience of it happen.
You know?
St. Paul is saying, though, some people celebrate these holy days,
there are other people who make every day a Sabbath.
Yeah.
And every day a celebration.
And that's one of the reasons why, by the way,
like I know this has been on people's minds,
especially this last year, where so many of us were limited
from coming to church.
You know, I've heard some people say well
you know, Paska happened anyway even though you weren't there.
And like on one level that is true.
It's it is true.
But on the on another level you have to you have to recognize that when you don't get
to richly participate in it in the way that you normally would,
that there is an actual poverty that has happened there.
Right? So, you know, whatever you think of the particular policies of your individual
church, you know, there is an actual loss if you're not
they're participating. If you skip church on Sunday for whatever reason, even for a really
good reason, it's still a loss. There's still something broken, fundamentally broken,
because you didn't get to richly participate in it in the fullest way. Now certainly you can
pray at home and that is a ritual participation, but it's not the same as, for instance,
receiving Holy Communion. It's simply not the same. It's not the same. You know, so
So this is what's behind all of that.
that right? That's why it's a horrible poverty when you can't be in church or when a church
is destroyed for instance. You know, so, you know, because I mean, you know, what would you
say if a church is smashed, say, well, every place is holy, what does it matter? It matters
because that place is used for that ritual participation. And now that's been prevented in some
way, right? Right? Yeah. So we have settled that so we can say that. Yeah. So that, yeah.
So that's therefore...
you. That's the catch up, right? That's what we're talking about last time with sacred
time and sacred space. So tonight we're going to be talking about the flip side of that,
which is profane space and profane word. And profane is a great word. It literally, it's
so profanum. It literally means that which is outside the temple. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah.
Outside the camp outside the holy the place that we've preserved under the bubble, right?
right right that's why people have that sense they shouldn't use profanity
inside the church is literally contradictory.
If you're going to cost, please go outside.
No.
What if you've cut in a foreign language?
Does it count?
Yeah, right.
In which languages count?
Can I cut in Klingon?
That's a language where every word sounds like a consort.
Yes, that's true.
Profane time and space.
Yes.
And so we've got a little bit of quick review here, too, just to pick up some concepts we've
already talked about on the show I think like several times.
And that's, we've talked about how when we sin, we're participating in the energies and
the works of demons, right?
And we're bringing those works of demons into reality, right?
This is another part of that.
We as human conscious beings, we bring that then into the world.
And when we do that, that not only transforms us, that breaks down that internal order,
right?
who we are and corrupts us, but it also
Through that web of relationships we have with the rest of creation leaves this sort of
metaphysical paint, this sort of stain on the created world where that has happened.
And so, with these places where demonic rituals, where events of great evil and things have
happened, there is this tape.
just as when we when we richly
purify a place and make it sacred space, it participates in another sacred time or sacred space.
When we do this with profane space, that space participates in that profane time and space.
Meaning it gives demons access to it.
It gives.
This is why people experience various kinds of quote unquote, we've already attacked this word,
but supernatural.
phenomena around places where these sort of horrible things have happened.
Right. Right. And I'm like, I'll give you an example where when I was in
seminary, a couple of my fellow seminarians met a guy,
half-pazardly out in public who, you know, one of the seminarians was wearing
his casking and he said, Hey, are you a priest? And he turned out to be.
And he said, you know, there's a problem at my house and he invited him over
And you know, he talked about sort of a feeling of evil and
and things moving around and all this classic haunted house kind of stuff.
And, you know, come to find out, it turned out that the previous owner had actually killed
himself in the backyard or something like that.
So the priest did a house blessing and then he also went out into the backyard and prayed
a memorial prayer for the person who had killed himself.
And there was this immediate change in the experience of the place that it, that it literally felt
lighter and earlier.
This is what the person who went there did this told me.
And so, that there's this, you know, that this action of suicide now.
sure that leading up to this suicide was probably a lot of darkness.
There's this taint, it became profane as a result, and so it needed to be cleansed.
Right.
And this is what's behind from the very beginning, and we talked about this back in our
Halloween episode, the church coming and rededicating these pagan sites, and making them sacred,
but burying the martyrs there,
dedicating churches and churches.
the lines there.
Or like the Parthenon in Athens, which we know of it as a temple to the goddess Athena,
but actually was a Christian church dedicated to the Théautocles way longer than it was
ever a pagan temple.
So we still have that one in Nashville that we have to take care of.
We won't talk more about that anyway.
But yeah, so what there isn't, so there's sacred space and there's gross fain space,
But there isn't is neutral space.
Yes, no such thing as neutral space.
There is no neutral ground.
There is no place that is not one or the other.
And so this is, as we talked about,
us going back to that Halloween episode,
this is part of our mission as Christians
is to go out and reclaim the Korean in order
and make it sacred and make it holy again.
Church it all.
Yeah.
not just ourselves in terms of repentance.
but also reclaiming the world around us, that we have a relationship to everything else.
So before we take our first break, can we do samples?
Yeah, let's do some examples.
Prove it's faces, name three.
So the first one is probably the one that's most familiar to people familiar with the Bible and or
or especially orthodox theology in Greek and that's the value of
Hennum aka Gehenna.
Right.
Yeah, because Geh means valley, right?
In here, right? Yeah.
It's like when people say Mount Fuji Yamma.
Like that's Mount Fuji Mountain.
Yeah.
Yeah, yeah.
Or China.
ATM machine.
Yeah.
Department of Redundancy Department.
So the and and hit him by the way was a guy. He shows up in Joshua. He was just
dude. Just some guy who lived there who it was named after. Oh man, but rotten luck. Yeah,
he got his name stuck on it, right? It's like me. What are the guys who Judas baptized?
You know, it's like I don't want to be a donatus, but seriously. Oh man. So,
Yeah.
The valley outside Jerusalem is one of the most infamous places in the Old Testament,
because it was there that the Israelites, meaning the people of the Northern Kingdom,
in particular, and even also the Southern Kingdom, came and sacrificed their children to Molec
by passing them through the fire.
Right.
And
God, I'm gonna say, condemns this.
Yahweh, the God of Israel, says, refers to them as his children.
He says, you have offered my children to Molech, right?
They weren't theirs to do with as they pleased.
But, so this is about the worst satanic ritual you can think of.
Right?
You want a topotic ritual, this is high up there, right?
Yeah, child sacrifice.
So, uh, good, it's done.
just that like these horrible things happen there so it's a bad place, right?
Because when you read there is in 2nd Kings chapter 23 there's just the
description of them doing this. But in Jeremiah 7 and Jeremiah 19 where the
Prophet Jeremiah is specifically coming at the Judahites before the exile.
This is one of the things that's going to finally prompt the exile so that God
I can purify the land from the people of Judah.
Yeah.
Wow.
Man.
And.
So when he talks about Jeremiah lays out what they've been doing, which of course they know, right, and this eating against them.
And then the language he uses, then, is that the what's going to come upon them as a result, is that their own bodies are going to end up in Gehanna.
And not buried there, but laying out in the open, being eaten by wild animals.
Yeah, which is buried, uncared for.
Yeah, which is, you know, like the worst possible
feet for a dead person in the ancient world.
Right, which is yeah. Yeah.
And if you read elsewhere in the Old Testament, not only is that of course a curse, but that's
how what's used to describe she-old, the underworld. Right?
That's the language. Right? So for example, in the Psalm, right, their bones are scattered
by the side of hell. Right? They're not buried.
They're just scattered out there to the wind.
when you read in Isaiah Jeremiah elsewhere, it talks about this is how
Shiolya was struck. So this judgment isn't saying, hey you specific people who
specifically did this, every one of you individuals is going to end up dead
and unburied in this valley. Yeah, no. At these GPS coordinates, right? It's what
And it's saying is, they have turned that place.
Gahanna into hell. They have turned to that place into she old the underworld. The abode of evil. They've invited the demons there. That's the place it is. And so that's where they're going to end up. That's where they're going to spend the eternity.
And you know, there is actually from the Germanic tradition, there is actually, you know, the Old English word, orc, which I'm sure we're familiar to a number of our listeners.
referred to
to a kind of demon in Old English,
referred to a kind of demon
that hung around in the underworld and ate corpses.
So it's literally this kind of thing,
that's what an orc is to an Anglo-Saxon person.
And of course, that actually shows up
in Beowulf and other stuff like that.
Well, in the Gospels, the Demaniac
running around in the tomb.
In the tombs, exactly.
He's basically being orcish.
The place of the dead.
Right, so that's what's going on.
this place has been has.
been made that, right, by what they've done there.
So another example, I don't think we've talked, you can
talk about this on this show. No, no, no, no, you're a
cinematic universe. Yeah, if you're a reader of Father
Stevens blog, the whole council of God blog, there's, there's a
a PC wrote called table and Herman that covers what we're about
to talk about. Yeah, there's this gateway to the underworld.
That's a particular mountain Mount Herman
which you can go visit. I don't recommend it because it's right by the
goal in Heights. It's not a safe area to visit, especially right now. But,
although I gather there's a ski resort there. There is no there is. I look this up actually.
I don't know. That's weird. So this this mountain is there. And if you if you do go there,
there are still all these ancient pagan shrines from all these different periods all over the mountain.
Yeah. There's something about that mountain. Back to the old Canaanites all the way up to
and the name
comes from Herum, which means band or forbidden, which is the same word as
Haram in the Arabic. So it's like the forbidden mountain, the cursed mountain. This
is where Azazel gets the other angels together to hatch their scheme in the
book of Enoch. There's on top of this mountain. And at the base of this mountain
There's an ancient spring that was...
considered a gateway to the underworld and featured a pagan shrine from the Canaanite period
all the way through to the Roman period where it became a shrine to pan.
Yeah.
Good old man.
And that area still referred to as Banius which Pee got turned into B. It was Panius but
now it's Banius.
That's because Arabic speakers can't say.
Yeah, there's a tendency to pronounce a Pee as what we were supposed to be as a B.
So there's this this game.
to the underworld and the place where this comes into effect is this is this is
near where Cecilia Philippi was and so that that famous moment in the
Gospels when St. Peter makes his confession as to who Christ is right and he
refers to the gates of hell not prevailing against the church he was standing a
few yards from this particular gate to hell. Gateway to the underworld. Yes. There
There was a-
one nearby. I feel like this is a major Paul Harvey moment, right? And now you know the
rest of the story. Good day. Good day. Yeah. So that's where my dad who was a big Paul Harvey
fan. So so at this place actually was the Byzantines came and built a church there. Right?
The rowing the Roman Christians came and built a built a church there and rededicated it
order to again make it sacred.
space instead of profane space. And then a third example, just because I people get excited
when we talk about about giants, I think they get ecstatic when we talk about werewolves.
Yeah. But this is not the werewolf episode, everybody. Sorry. No more tantalization on its
way. There is a mountain in Greece, Mount La Cale.
which basically means Wolf Mountain.
Yes, Wolf Mountain.
But it's actually named after a person.
A guy.
Yeah.
A guy named, like Hione.
And on top of that mountain is the oldest known Greek altar.
And here's how old it is.
It's so old.
How old is it?
Yeah.
It's so old that it was referred to in Greek as the Bemos.
Beamos is not a Greek word. It's not even an Indo-European word. It's the
Akkadian word, Beama, for altar, that was brought over into Greek. We talked
before about Kathercija being brought over from Kather in Akkadian. It's a general
truth that the very earliest layer of all religious vocabulary in Greek is
is actually a cadian.
comes from Semitic. Oh man. So you're saying you can't give me a word any word and I
show you how that word. No. Sorry guys. This is a Greek word. Yeah. Yeah. And so and then
on that altar they're doing human sacrifice. They did human sacrifices and you can read the Greeks
about this because they considered it a dark and evil place because of this. Yeah, right.
the great pagans that this fella, like he,
own, performed to you but sacrificed.
he would sacrifice there and engaged in cannibalism
because sacrifices are meals.
Yeah, which often goes with it.
And so it was cursed and became this sort of wolf and creature,
i.e. he's sort of the first werewolf in Greek thought.
So he becomes this sort of wolf like repacious cannibalistic
creature, possessed creature from having
participated in this ritual.
So even like I said, the pagan Greeks.
considered this this place of sort of darkness and evil that you didn't want to go around.
Um, right. Uh, it's been since Ben rededicated.
There's a shrine to St. Elias there now because of Elijah.
Yeah.
Because if you're going to fight demons up on top of a mountain, St. Elias is your man.
He has experience.
Yeah, exactly.
He knows what he's doing in this.
So even that space of being has been sort of re consecrated and taken over.
Yeah
All right, well, we're gonna go ahead and go to break
in just a second here.
When we come back, we're gonna actually start
taking some of your calls.
But in the second half of Lord of the Spirits,
we're gonna be talking about why is the underworld,
the underworld, and what is it under?
So let's go to break.
Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung
will be back in a moment to take your calls
on the next part of the Lord of Spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
Let's eat five.
5-A-F radio.
This is an ancient faith radio public service announcement.
Orthodox Christian Fellowship, OCF, is seeking qualified candidates to apply for two full-time
positions as part of their national ministry team, a communications manager and a ministry
coordinator.
Candidates should be Orthodox Christians and good standing with their parish-slash jurisdiction
who were interested in furthering the mission of OCF to provide
opportunities for college students to encounter Christ.
Full job descriptions and applications can be found at www.ocf.net slash join dash hour
dash team.
Inquiries about these positions or recommendations can be directed to executive director Deacon
Merrick Simon at Merrick M-A-R-E-K at ocf.net.
This has been a public service announcement of Ancient Faith Radio.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits, the Father of...
Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung.
If you have a question, call now at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF radio.
Thanks for that voice of Steve.
All right, we're going to be talking about why
is the underworld, the underworld,
and what exactly is it under.
But first, we're going to take one of your calls.
So I believe Brett is calling.
and he has a question about astral protein.
this this guy. You're
local to father, Steven,
aren't you? I don't I don't
like to make that claim or
not. I don't know. Take me
but I can go. So what's
your question there, Brett?
My question is since we've
been talking about time and
How does this relate to the concept of
of ask for projection that we know from either popular media or interactions with paganism,
neo-paganism specifically.
And what's the demonic influence of that and how it all relates in together with how we
experience time and place?
Is it a thing, basically, as well?
Is it a thing?
Like, is that, is it a thing, is it a thing, or like, is that a projection of thing?
I know the concept, but...
Beyond the concept is something that can actually be experienced.
Yeah, I mean, so before Father Stephen gets the well actually, I mean certainly we can see like there are visions for instance that some of the
Saints have had where they experience being in some other place where then they really are. Right that God gives them that experience.
I don't know if it's something that happens in other contexts for sure or not, so father, I don't know.
What do you say?
I'm not thinking Dr. Strange right now, like that's the injection.
As long as we're talking about it in terms of astral projection and not remote viewing.
Right?
Then we're okay.
If you want to know about remote viewing, go watch them in, who's staring at goats.
It's hysterical.
Major has daves.
I haven't seen that yet, but I can't tell you.
Is that a heroic character?
Yeah.
So now we definitely are coast to coast AFR.
Now that I brought that up.
Like for sure.
No, so what's usually termed aster projection, right?
So the way it's talked about a lot now is, is, and in terms of new age spirituality and
neopagodism and that kind of thing is that it's a technique by which one is able to usually
go somewhere else in the world.
That's why the connection to remote viewing, right?
to be present.
your consciousness be present at another place and or time than where your body is currently present.
But the Astral and Astral projection comes from originally it had a lot more to do with like
what you were just talking about Father Andrew the idea of like apocalyptic visions and that kind
of thing and and ecstatic experience because of course Astral refers to the stars. Yeah. Right so
So it was referring to this kind of...
transcending of time and space in the sense of having that kind of mystical vision.
So we have to say that does happen, right?
That happened to St. John, right?
In the book of Revelation, that happens to the prophet Ezekiel, the prophet Isaiah.
I mean, right?
Right.
So it's not just, basically this is an example of what we've been talking about, ritually
going the other way, right?
So we've been talking about ritual in terms of through ritual we make the
the time and space where we are to be a particular time and space, whereas the
ecstatic experience is an experience of the departing from the time and space
where I am and being in that other space, right. So rather than our ritual
experience and worship bringing paradise here, I leave here and go to
paradise right and I'm taken to paradise right in this sort of visionary
visionary experience. So that happens, but it is not something that happens when it's
happening legitimately by virtue of practicing certain techniques. Yeah, that's right.
Sorcery. Right. And so inevitably, we're going to do an episode on the news. And in that
episode, we'll probably talk about this and we'll talk about Kundalini yoga and all that
crazy stuff that people want to hear about.
The tuner-leaning serpent and all this.
you know, pineal gland stuff. But for now, this is something that happens sort of that is granted
to certain individuals by the grace of God in his timing in order to communicate certain things.
It's sort of God taking the initiative to bring certain realities into the realm of human conscious
experience rather than humans taking the initiative to
that you can enter into the place where God is,
which is what we're normally doing in worship.
Right.
So does that make sense, Brett?
It does. It makes perfect sense.
Thank you so much, fathers.
You could ask up to three follow-up questions at coffee hour.
Thank you for calling, Brett.
Okay, so we're going to take another call right now.
We have Matthew, who I think is calling from Germany,
or I'm not sure where exec is calling.
Matthew, you're there.
Yeah.
Where are you calling from Matthew? Yeah?
Yes, Fryberg in Germany. You are calling from Germany. All right. It has got to be late at night over there
Well, you know got a listen to the Lord of Spirit
Well, that's what I think
Good enough. Yeah
Yeah, all right, so so Matthew what is what is what is your question from over there in the Germanic lands?
Yes, so I know that you said before the main
between veneration and worship and an ancient understanding,
was that worship consists primarily of two things,
sacrifice and offering incense,
which is why you also said Protestants
really mostly participate in veneration
and why only God receives the sacrifice and the incense.
So this raised for me two questions.
Is it not offering incense to the saints?
when the horrible is slung before the icons is married and the other saying.
And second, if worship is primarily these two things,
then why was it such a big deal for the three youths about the statue of Nebuchadnezzar
or morticada, Heyman or the Jews before the bronze serpent, for example?
Yeah.
Because that would be veneration and not worship for say.
Well, that's a good question.
So, you know, to the question.
So the question of sensing icons, for instance,
when you sense an icon, you're not worshiping the icon.
You're not offering a sacrifice to the icon.
Instead, what incense is being used for
is for this purification function.
So incense is not a sacrifice that's used in the same way
as the sacrifices that are eaten, like the Holy Eucharist,
of course.
It's used in a different way to purify.
So you know, you know.
in our episodes on sacrifice,
especially the one we did on the day of Atonement,
we talked about purification a lot.
So you can go back and listen to that.
Excuse me.
So as to your other question about
why was it not okay for the three holy children to bow
before the idol that Nebuchadnezzar set up,
well, you don't want to venerate the image of a demon.
That's just a bad idea.
You don't venerate demons.
You know, you don't worry.
them either, right? So for instance remember in the Ten Commandments where the Lord said not to bow
down to them nor to serve them, that's actually two different actions. Don't bow in front of them and
don't offer sacrifices to them. So neither one is okay, right? So you know bowing in front of
something is an act of veneration and it becomes worship then when it becomes bound up in this question
of sacrifice. So I don't know if Father Steve, did you have anything you wanted to add or correct
or whatever? Yeah, I'll add yeah in terms of the purification with the incense, one of the reasons
This is why we have these sensings where we go.
around the whole church is that it's part of the ritual we're just talking about.
And maybe it's sacred space.
The space has to be purified in order to be made holy.
And so the incense in the censor, the smoke from the incense in the censor is performing
the function of the blood of a sacrifice, right?
So the incense was offered on the altar of incense.
And then, incense and coals from that altar were taken and put into a sensor.
and then taken out and used for this purification.
In the same way that the blood was drained
from a sacrifice that was being offered
and then the blood was used to purify,
the tabernacle of the temple,
the physical space to rededicate it and to cleanse it.
So that's what's going on with the smoke.
I would also point out that while obviously
eating food offered to an idol
is participating in the sacrifice.
And we see the book of Daniel too,
where they basically become vegetarians.
They won't...
the King's food because it was all offered to idols. But there are other ways of
participating in worship, right? So I've got a bunch of catacumins right now,
they can't receive the Eucharist yet in our church, right? Tell Holy Saturday
when they received it in the church. So they're still coming to liturgy, they're
still coming to like last night we had a pre-sanctified liturgy, right? They
come, they're not participating in the worship, right? They're not their
spectators.
Right to the worship that's happening
Right they're participating but how are they participating? Well, one of the ways they're participating is during Len is they're making prostrations
Right they're making prostrations. They're singing along with the prayers. They're praying along with the prayers
Yeah, right the context is super important, right?
So even if you're not doing the action right only the priest is actually doing the action of offering the sacrifice
right in one of these pagan situations right and then there are various ways that
people can participate in that. They might march in the procession with the sacrificial animal.
They might eat the meat afterwards. They might go and offer prayers to the God while the
sacrifice is going on. While that individual act that they're committing, the bowing
or the praying or the processing may not be worshiped in and of itself, by that action,
they're participating in the sacrificial worship that is going on in proximity.
Does that make sense?
Right.
Alrighty.
Well, thank you very much for calling Matthew.
We're honored that you are listening to us
in the middle of the night over there in Germany.
So, great to hear from you.
Thank you very much.
Alright. Well, why is the underworld the underworld?
And what exactly is it under?
I'm imagining that there was a group of people out there
there who thought finally they're going to talk about
vampires and werewolves. And we're talking about a totally different underworld. And there's like
a small legion of disappointed Kate Beckinsale fans. How man their eyeliners gonna start running when
they did this. So no, we're talking about the actual underworld, not the criminal underworld either,
but yeah, the only twilight we're gonna talk
about on here is the twilight of the gods.
Right.
The regions, the regions under the earth.
Right?
Yes.
Right.
That language is in scripture.
It talks about it as being the pit, right?
Or under the earth.
Or even the word, even the word shield,
grave, it doesn't refer to something that's sort of deep.
Right.
It is about depth.
You bury people in the ground.
Yeah.
In the holes in the ground.
And we talked about this when we set the way back
machine.
for the Neolithic era, that even then you see people being buried in the ground with grave
goods.
Yeah.
Meaning, both that they thought wherever this person's life went next, it was down there
somewhere and they were clearly not going to cease to exist because they gave them stuff.
Yeah.
You're going to need this in the world to come.
Right.
Yeah.
So this is universal.
Yeah, right, almost no culture does-
Are there any ancient cultures we know of that don't
of course what evidence were there where there be?
But everyone's bearing their debt as far as we know
in the ancient world.
Right.
This is, yeah.
And there's one exception in the ancient world
that you mentioned, maybe the Zoroastrianism.
Zoroastrianism where they have something called sky towers
where they would build these towers and put the bodies up there
to be animals, animals, animals and elements.
But yeah.
That was the Romans thought that was deeply deep
Yes, it's completely weird.
Everybody else thought they were complete wackos for that.
Right.
So that exception sort of proves the rule.
Everyone else thought they were Pizarro.
It was like Mirror Universe burial.
So in, you know, your cane and eye ancient near Eastern background, you have shield, the grave.
Right.
But it's not just referring to physical graves, obviously.
go in the grave. There's a
other beings there, right?
And so it's this realm of the dead,
and this is the place where the demonic beings are.
So going all the way back into Samaritan literature,
there are demons who are seen to sort of,
the way the demons show up as they crawl up
through cracks in the ground.
They come up out of the earth, right?
Or come up out of the sea, right?
But they're all below level, right?
That's, you have the mountain of God
then you have these things that come up.
up from below. And so in this understanding, in the ancient erysra understanding, when
you go into Sheol, you're going to the place where all those folks live and hang out.
Yeah.
Right. So it's much worse than Sartre. It's not just other people. It's, you know, these
Yeah, yeah, right. And and it's it's why why down there like what does that mean? Well, you remember last
time we talked about the mountain of God and all ancient peoples regarded the gods as living up on
mountains. This is the the inversion of that literally the inversion of that. It's it's what's down
there what's underneath right. You know the stars and the heavens that we've also talked about and
then this is then the inverse right yeah and one of the chief residents that that shows up a lot in
And the Old Testament are the Raphaim who we've talked about before.
are some of these dead giants. But these are not just in Scripture as the
spirits of these dead giants. We have eukaryotic ritual texts for when their
king died the Refaim they regarded as their ancient kings who were part
divine. Right? They they regarded them as dead giants. And they were worried
about their king who just died because these guys were going to come meet him
at the door when he got down there.
Yeah, head.
These guys were not nice-
guys, right? Yes, right? They remembered them like all of the demonic spirits and all of
these dead tyrants and all of these evil beings who they spent a good portion of their
trying time trying to ward off magically and ritually in this life and keep away from
them, right? Keep away from their crops and keep away from their children. That's where
they were going when they died. Yeah, yeah, it's pretty bleak, right? Yeah, and so you've
You know, this image of sort of demonic
torturing people down in hell, that's where, you know, which like is it's the cartoon hell, right?
That's it's the hell that Bill and Ted go to and Bill and Ted's both
that's that's um
You know the first movie was so much better than the second, but um
That's that's where this comes from it's it's this this image, you know this is a pagan. This is pagan hell the pagan
Christian hell not even ready.
Christian hell they got the medieval pagans they were converting in Western Europe. Yeah right right
So yeah, but that's not the only version of the underworld that there is right there's also right a much more complex
One you see in Greek myth where the term Hades is used
Right. Yeah, and Hades is the name of course of both a spirit
Right, a God, right, well gee, a spirit and the
that that spirit oversees. Yeah, which place of its dominion. Yeah, which went, you know,
sometimes people argue in like liturgical translations, so we used word, hate ease or the word hell
to refer to this. And I understand the argument in favor of hate ease,
basically because a lot of people have this image of hell, but at least
etymologically speaking and traditionally and historically speaking, both words refer to the
place of the underworld and both words refer to
the God that isn't charged down there. And you know just Hades just happens to come from Greek
and Hell comes from Germanic language. The one exception that's a little different is in the
Germanic world that that Hell is a feminine being. You know so if you're from either the Marvel
cinematic universe you remember that's Kate Blanchett right? So I was about to say that if there were
ritual by which you could make like the
century present. I think you would do it. But then I remembered that that's the SCA so you
probably already. Yes, no. Yeah, I could do that. Yeah, no. No. Yeah, and she and she is also
the same thing, right? There's a there's a God that is she all right. Right. Yeah, exactly. It's
both a God and a place in these historical usages, right? Yeah. Right. And so there's there's not
the sort of like slasher movie quality to Hades that there is to show.
right right the Haydys you get more images of sort of sadness regret for
getfulness woe sorrow yeah shadows darkness yeah it
presenting me right I cannot live I cannot die that's the reference someone
we'll get right and I notice that at our brief notes here you put teenage
Emo slash Goth Hell which is accurate at
to something we discuss, but I feel the need to distinguish between an emo and a goth.
Okay. Silver Sun pickups and Bauhaus are not the same thing. Okay. Not at all.
Oh, to me goth is a large German barbarian with an axe. Right. That's really what goth is.
But yes. Well, modern day goth would not survive that long. Right. Those goths. Right. Right.
But yes, this is this is you're appealing to the teenage
No one understands my pain
especially mom and dad. I write bad poetry that doesn't rhyme. Right. Kind of phase. Right.
And that's yes. It's every day is like Sunday, all silent and gray. Right. Everyone's
everyone's sad and depressed. And that's hate. Yeah. That's an yeah. So that's one angle of
Hades, right? Right. That it's sort of, and then Hades, right, the shades, the shadows
literally of people sort of.
go there and live this kind of shadowy for existence for as long as they're
remembered and that is their memory fades sort of so do they. Right and and
that's the reason why in a previous episode we mentioned the shrines that were
at various pagan cities to heroes where they would pour down blood to kind of
feed their memory and keep them alive because the hero would then still be
President of the city by means of sort of doing this, you know? Right. You got to keep them.
going. Yep. Yep. So, um, the, uh, I don't know, so having discussed it general, the, the,
right, the place. So this is, this is the underworld. This is that, that place, right, that is present
through in profane space. But this, this place has its own geography. Yeah. That's right.
This is sort of neighborhood.
in the underworld. Just like we talked about, you know, there's paradise, the garden, the
tensed it on top of a mountain, right? There is a certain geography, right? And really
a lot of the apocalyptic literature we've briefly mentioned, it evidently we're going
to have an episode of the Bokobianic, etc. are sort of tours of this geography, right?
Right.
both directions. So also, Hades, she, all the underworld.
has this geography and it's not just in general that like oh because these horrible things
have happened here these places become hell but specific places become specific places
in the underworld. There's a correspondence between these specific places and those specific
places.
Okay, yeah, so the first thing we're gonna talk about is the abyss.
which is of all the places in the underworld to be, it's the worst.
You don't want to go to the abyss.
That is a bad place, it's a bad place.
Yes, right.
Yeah, right.
Yeah, and it shows up.
It's in every ancient mythology and one way or another,
with slight differences in terms of the way that gets talked about.
But like in the ancient Near East, so this is obviously kind of ground zero for a lot of what we discuss.
It's down underwater, right?
right because the water is
So the sea is the depths of the sea is, right?
But that doesn't always play out in terms of sea like the Mediterranean.
Sometimes it does.
But for example, we've talked about the Opkalu stories.
These were sort of the ancient eryster version of the Titans or the angels who rebelled with Canes line.
In the Opkallu story, the Babylonian version of the story, they're imprisoned under
beneath the Tigris, that you frayed these rivers.
Yeah, in particular, at the bottom of the water.
So we kick a water down at the bottom.
Yeah, and you know some of my ancient ancestors
God blessed them and forgive them the bolts.
They, and actually a lot of people in Northern Europe
did this, you know, they had the sense
that gods were down there, not just under the waters,
but under kind of anything that's watery.
So like bogs, especially swamps.
and they would sacrifice things down into the bog.
including people. They would put various things down there, but including people, they would put them down in there.
The idea was to sort of send them to the gods, right? Because down there in the underworld, and something that's a pretty macabre,
you know, you're connecting with some really awful, awful gods if you're sacrificing to underworld gods.
Yeah, you're, yeah, like even a pagan has a sense that he's connecting with a demonic, horrible creature, you know.
Right, and surely to ward them off.
Yeah, right. Please don't come up out of there when you're connected with them. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah.
Yeah. Yeah. Yeah.
Yeah. So Joe fits into this, right? Yeah.
Yes. This actually isn't Ruins your Sunday school. This is I think vastly improves your Sunday.
Makes it way cooler. Yes. Right.
I think that that people still have this mental image that Jonah gets like eaten by a fish
like he's sitting inside the fish like Pinocchio in the whale.
in the Disney movie.
Like with a campfire or something.
Yeah, like just somehow enough to end down there.
Right at the bottom of the ocean.
Yeah, so here's what actually happens in the book of Jonah.
Leviathan, low tan, right?
The chaos seabodster eats Jonah and he dies.
Jonah is dead and it swims with Jonah's corpse down into the abyss.
It says it's between the pillars of the earth.
Those are the pillars that are...
holding up the dry land. So he's down in there under in the underworld. Right. And so with
Jonah praise, he's praying not just from shi'ol, he's praying from the abyss. From yeah. Right.
Out of the depths. Right. That's um out of the depths. I cried onto the yeah. I mean, that's
deliberate. That's deliberate. When it says again, like, you know, we're all about helping people who
are going to Orthodox Church services, parts of it light up.
Right, that's investors out of the depths of I cry it into the old Lord.
Lord hear my voice.
That's the depths we're talking about.
Right.
Way, way, way down.
And so it's death that vomits up Jonah.
When he when he comes back out and so when Christ talks about the sign of Jonah,
he's not just making this allegory.
We're like, okay, like, so imagine the tomb is a fish.
And there's three days.
So yeah, right.
Yeah, there's a three.
Yeah.
but it wasn't actually three. It's kind of on the third day. How does that work?
That's not what's going on there, right?
It's again very literal.
Our next episode, we're going to see that a lot of the things
that you thought were analogies and allegories
in the PASCA Easter Services aren't.
They're not.
Yes, I'll have to come up with another leading question
at the beginning where you just say, no.
Right.
This one's literal, too.
Yeah, right.
So um
This is also the little bit of irony in the episode where Christ cast the demons into the pigs.
Right.
They're by creating Devil'd Ham.
Boom!
Yeah, dad joke.
Is that, you know, they-
So that one's sinking everybody.
Devil'd Ham.
Okay. They plead with Christ.
to send them into the abyss, right?
And then he says, you know, they
said, they said this into the
pigs and said, so he sends them
into the pigs and the pigs
promptly run and jump into the
sea.
Yes.
And take them to the sink and take
them to the abyss.
Yeah.
Right.
So and just as reminded
everybody, this is where giants
show up in the New Testament
because those are giants.
There are just a lot of
spirits of dead giants.
Yes.
That's one.
But so as
As we mentioned with the the Apollo right the Abyss is the place where these rebellious
gods or spirits are imprisoned.
So you see the same thing.
The Greek version of this is Tartarus where the Titans are imprisoned.
And it's I'm sure we'll do a Titans episode at some point in the future.
Oh, that would be so fun.
And all the Robin and Wondergirl fans will be disappointed when they find out.
No, it's the Greek Titans.
I
just like disappointing nerds.
Yeah, and there's of course a reference to this
in the Bible in 2 Peter chapter two verse four,
four of God spared not the angels that sin,
but cast them down to hell,
just put a star up in and that,
and delivered them into chains of darkness
to be reserved into judgment.
So the word that's there for hell,
we looked this up in the Greek,
it's actually Tatarosa.
So it's the cast them into...
So like this sort of neighborhood of of Hades is there in in the New Testament
It's mentioned there in the New Testament
So it's not just a thing say Peter is here directly making that equation between the Titans and the angels who fell
With Kinsline and saying they're in prison right?
correcting the the pagan version of the story
but they're in prison in this place
Tardarus to to await the final judgment
So and and again the
Abyss and Tardis, these are just two different words for the same part of the underworld.
It's a pit, right?
It's the pit, which is the inverse of a mountain.
Exactly.
The direct inverse of a mountain, right, is an endlessly tall mountain has its opposite
a bottomless pit, right?
Right.
A mountain which stretches to the heavens, the bottomless pit.
And the biscuits are referred to a couple other places in...
scripture and revelation nine. There's the angel who has the key to the abyss shows up and he
unlocks it and lets those guys out to sort of ravage the world there at the end. Right? Yeah.
And then in chapter 20, same angel shows up again this time to imprison the devil.
Yeah, the furlough is over.
Yeah.
So everybody get back in.
Additionally, one of the rivers, we're going to talk about more rivers and
Hades, but one of the rivers in Hades, the Flengaston, is a river of fire that
runs down, all of the rivers run down into the abyss, run down into the pit.
But this is a river of fire that runs down into the pit, causing the pit to
become a lake or a lake of fire. Right. And the river of fire.
we see in Daniel, the lake of fire we see show up in the book of Enic or first scenic,
and then it shows up in St. Matthew's Gospel, shows up in the book of Revelation,
in St. Matthew's Gospel Revelation it's specifically the lake of fire prepared for the devil
and his angels. No not humans, although humans can end up there. It's not created for them.
It's created, this abyss is created to imprison those rebellious
spirits. Yeah yeah okay so that's not the neighborhood you
want to move into in the underworld. I mean, you don't want to be down there at all, but
the best part of the underworld in Greek myth was referred to as the Elysian Fields.
That's a bad place. Yes, the not so bad place. That's as good as it gets as the Elysian
Fields. And of course, there's, you know, this is referenced in scripture, not with that
term that I can recall. But so for instance, there's the Gospel where we read about the
Richmond and Lazarus and
Lazarus is in what is called the bosom of Abraham.
Right. So it's a colloquial way of referring to it because what you see
the Old Testament is the hope is that when they go into the grave,
they will rest with their fathers. Yeah, exactly rest with their fathers.
And so Abraham is sort of the patriarch, right? He's the first father
of the people. So if you're in the bosom of Abraham,
that means you're resting with the fathers with Abraham, Isaac and Jacob.
Yeah, and their righteous seed.
Yeah, and even pay, and even pagans had the same idea, you know, to go be with your ancestors.
You know, like this is sort of as good as it gets. It's not great, but it's as good as it gets.
But it's better than the abyss.
Yeah, way.
Yeah.
Right. And so the way this is described in the book of Enic when he sees Hades,
he sees that there are these three caves, these sort of three...
subdivisions of where the where the people are in Hades when Enic is sort of going on his
journey. At that point Paradise is empty. You see it but it's empty. But there are these
three caves and so in one of the caves you have the bosom of Abraham, you have the righteous
fathers, right? And there's a righteous seed. And apparently it's some kind of grotto or
whatever because there's a spring of water there. Right. There's a spring of water there.
That's what different.
It's from the other two parts for him, right?
Yeah, this spring of water to sort of refresh them and care for them while they're there.
And this is referenced obliquely in the parable of the rich man and Lazarus that you just mentioned, right?
Because in the one the one area the rich man is the other area Lazarus is the rich man asks for Lazarus to bring him some water.
Right, bring him some drops of water because there's water where Lazarus is in the bosom of Abraham.
right there's a spring so that's kind of a bleak reference to this idea and then so there's
there's that cave there's another cave which is sort of where the people are in a holding station
who after the final judgment in the book of Enic are going to end up in the abyss they're
going to be chucked in there with the rebellious angels yeah it's sort of the the abysmal waiting room
you know, like the
the DMV essentially. Yeah, they're waiting in the waiting room because they can't get out.
So then this raises the question of the third cave. Yes. So this in first Enek, he has the idea
in first Enek that that third group wasn't really righteous, but they're not really like demonically
evil.
either. Yeah, they're the the okay people. Right. And so they basically get
permahedis, right? They just get they're just in that cave forever. Yeah. Right. And
and isn't exactly great. Yeah. I mean, and this exists in pagan stuff too, like in the Greek
traditional, this is less or known. Like who knows this? There's something called the Asphodel Meadows,
which again, sounds like a neighborhood. We just moved into Asphodel Meadows, do you? Oh,
where everything is mediocre.
everything you watch the same VHS is over and over again.
Right. Yeah, I feel like I've just started watching WandaVision, which we of course we
referenced last time. And I feel like it's kind of an Aspidel meadows place.
I'm only halfway through so no spoilers. Okay. No spoilers. No spoilers. Yeah.
Yeah, it's not tell them about, don't tell them about Captain America showing up.
Yeah, so it's not it's not
Limbo in the later sort of sense of limbo like in the medieval Roman Catholic idea like it's not that but it's a limbo-ish
Kind of place that's it's it's the land of man
Yeah, you know, right? It's sort of it don't take kind of has a limbo like that right?
Yeah, like Virgil's hanging out and
Like all the pagans who he really likes and doesn't want to see in hell even though they were pagans, right?
Yeah
Like you can't bear to put the
there. But generally when they're talking about limbo's in most medieval
anthology, they're talking about the limbo of infants, that's unbaptized
infants, or the limbo of the fathers. And the limbo of the fathers refers to
like Abraham's bosom that place we were just talking about. Yeah.
Yeah. So these words kind of move around a little. Yeah. But so that that
kind of limbo, even though it's around that kind of idea is around in
paganism and it's around even in second-temple Jewish literature, like the
You
It doesn't really get picked up by Christianity.
That kind of idea of neutrality, right?
Does it really carry over?
Not a thing.
Yeah.
So I should just say here now that we've taken this little tour of the neighborhoods of the
underworld, that it will probably occur to a lot of our listeners to wonder exactly
exactly how all this fits into questions of eternal salvation and eternal
damn it.
and to that I'm just gonna say wait until next time.
So, all right, well, that being said then,
we're gonna go ahead and take our second break
and we'll be back with the third half of the Lord of Spirits.
Father Andrew Stephen Daymak and Father Stephen DeYoung
will be back in a moment to take your calls on the next part
of the Lord of Spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
That's 855 AF3
video.
Doxamut Online.
Tolkien, Enchantment, and the Christian Life.
An ancient faith event.
For the Christian, the enchanted or sacramental worldview is critical to a wholesome, full
life in Christ.
The work of fantasy author J.R.R. Tolkien provides a shaping for the imagination and soul that
contributes to this vision.
the hosts of Ancient Faith Radio's Aman Sule podcast and this special on-
event that explores how this shaping happens in partnership with the St. Basil Center for Orthodox Thought and Culture.
The webinar will take place on Friday, May 7th and Saturday, May 8th, and speakers include Dr. Cyril Gary Jenkins,
Father Andrew Stephen Daymak, and Richard Roland.
The cost is $30 and registration will close on Wednesday, May 5th at noon Eastern.
To secure your spot, please visit store.AncientFate.com slash Doxman.
That's store.com
AncientFaith.com slash Doxam.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits,
the Father Andrew Stephen Damick
and Father Stephen DeYoung.
If you have a question, call now at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF radio.
Welcome to the third half of the Lord of Spirits.
We're going to be talking very soon about some of the architecture in the underworld and also what happens when you as you cross over
But first we have Daniel calling from Tennessee. So Daniel, can you hear me?
Hello, I appreciate you're taking my call
Absolutely. What's your question Daniel?
Well, I have
Wondered about something ever since I was a young lad and that is that there was a denomination
I wish I didn't name it, but it teaches that there's...
I grew up a Catholic though. It teaches that people when they die, you probably have heard
this theory, people do not go anywhere told, but rather they die and they await the resurrection.
There seem to be scriptures that support that. For example, a joke said, I will wait till
my change comes. Though my, with the worms destroyed this body, get them out flesh, shall
as she got and so forth.
And the depth is always like it.
and unto asleep, and that supposedly the wicked when they are punished, they are not burned.
The punishment doesn't go on forever, but punishment is certainly final because they are consumed
in the lake of fire and are no more.
And I just wonder, should I hang up and listen to you or what would you like?
Well, you're welcome to stay on if you've got a follow-up question.
I'm gonna go ahead and punt this sort of father, Steve.
What exactly happens when you start?
There's two pieces there, right?
The first piece is what's sometimes called soul sleep.
And the second piece is what's often termed annihilationism.
And we don't believe in either one of those.
No.
No, okay.
Let's get that in.
Yeah.
So, soul sleep is based on...
In addition to the passage you mentioned, taking some passages of the New Testament very literally, right?
So, Christians passing away, dying is referred to as falling asleep in the Lord, right? So, taking that very literally.
One of the issues with that is, of course, that sleep isn't oblivion,
right? Yeah.
As Hamlet reminded us, right? You sleep per chance to dream, right?
Um, yes.
And so we continue to have conscious experiences while we're asleep.
So the idea of comparing it to sleep doesn't mean it's some completely unconscious state.
Like if you ever had surgery they hit you with the stuff and you're out.
Right, it's oblivious. Right, you close your eyes, you open them, you have no sensation of time passing.
right? It's that like a period of time has gone from your life, right? But that's not normal.
sleep. Right? That's right. And so that analogy doesn't necessarily mean that, right? Even if taken fairly
literally. So but it is also true. It is also true. And we need to push back against this and the
passage you quoted from Joe is an important one in doing that. That the idea that people die and
and go to heaven or hell for eternity.
That is a sub-Christian eschatology.
that is not what Christians believe.
Christians believe that we die and that when Christ returns, when Christ appears,
I should say, is the better language. When Christ glorious appearing happens,
that all of the dead are raised bodily and stand before His judgment see
and then go from then bodily to eternal life or eternal condemnation.
Right. We...
believe that in between, in the in-between period, that the conscious experience of Christians
doesn't cease, right? We're still finite, so we still experience things in terms of time
and potentially even space. And so that conscious experience continues, and that conscious experience
represents a foretaste of either, of either blizzard or
judgment, right, that is coming because our conscious state from our life continues until
the bodily resurrection. So the kernel of truth behind this whole sleep idea is that they're
at least holding on to the idea of the bodily awakening part, which is better than a lot of folks do,
Right, they have this bodyless eternity, right?
Which is a Christian.
But they're a little flawed in taking the sleep idea a little too literally and I'm saying that well then there's just oblivion
Between when you die and when you rise
So in terms of the annihilation question this goes back to something we were talking about last time and that we've talked about before and
See annihilation is the idea that the souls of the condemned just cease to exist requires an idea of nothingness
It opposes being and nothingness existed.
and non-existence. And that polarity just didn't exist in the ancient world. They didn't have zero.
The consular invention, I can't remember if that was invented in India in the fourth or fifth century.
So they didn't have a zero. So they wouldn't say, I have zero apples.
right they would say I am
not having apples. I am not performing the action of having. So when they talk about something
not performing the action of being, for them being is opposed to chaos. Existence is
opposed to chaos. Right. So in the same way that our being justified and being put in order
by God represents becoming fully human, the opposite of it, the chaos that comes from participating
and demons. What that does to a human is make them some human.
It makes them less human. It diminishes their humanity.
They descend into chaos.
And so the images we see of like weeping and gnashing of teeth,
weeping and gnashing of teeth is an image of being tortured.
It's an image of madness.
Yeah, insanity.
Right.
It's at lack of order, right?
Complete lack of order in chaos and destruction.
But so to cease to exist, to cease to be human,
didn't mean void.
to ancient people, right?
We can come up with the concept of annihilationism now,
but it didn't mean that to ancient people.
To them it meant this descent
into sort of this animalistic.
And so that behavior is what you see with demoniacs,
like in the gospels, right?
They're living in this subhuman way,
they're naked, they're running in the tombs,
you know, unable to be chained, right?
It's that they've become less than human now.
And so when Christ then performs an exorcism,
We see they're sitting peacefully in it.
the right mind and clothed right that order has been restored they've been made human again
in that that internal order so I know that was a ton I just dumped on you but yeah yeah I did
answers your question Daniel yeah Daniel hung up and took the call out the air so okay so
I'll just assume he understood yeah I nailed it so we're exactly so we're gonna take just one more
call and this is Michael who has a question or comment about giant.
Michael, are you there?
Hi there, father.
I really love the show.
Learned a ton.
I really appreciate it.
I actually just had a quick question.
I was recently read the Epic of Gilgamesh.
And it's the Gilgamesh and Enke do about two-thirds God.
Yes.
So I'm assuming they're clients?
And I was just, again, like, if you do something else.
And I thought, I want to try to think of all the Demi Gods
and all the other mythology.
Like, is it Killie the Giant?
Yes.
Is it the Giant?
Thank you.
Yeah, they're giants.
Yeah, so if you if you Michael, if you haven't listened to our Giants episode,
have you listened to the Giants episode, Michael?
I have.
Look, back in November.
Yeah, yeah, back in November.
Yeah, I might suggest relistening to it and you know, one of the cool things is actually just to put a little plug-up for this.
You know, you can sponsor people can sponsor our episodes for transcripts three written.
And so far every single one of our episodes has been sponsored for Transcript, which is
wonderful. And so you can read that episode if you don't want to spend the three and a half
hours, but why wouldn't you want to spend those three and a half hours listening to that
episode again? It currently holds the record for the length of any single episode on an
instant faith radio of anything. So how about hey, the night is young. Yeah, that's true.
We could keep that. That's right. Let's just keep it. But yeah, there you go. I will, I
will not just shine you on and give you an actual answer.
Yeah, there you go.
Which is yes.
Yeah.
They're all giants.
And there's, there's, there's a,
a Hercules, Samson stuff going on.
The people love it when I talk about Samson.
But you know who you are.
But yeah, they're giants.
And in fact, they're so firmly giants that among the Dead Sea Scrolls,
one of the Dead Sea Scrolls is referred to as the Book of the Giants.
Ready?
lists their names. Okay, so this is from the first or second century BC, okay? They list
Gilgamesh as one of the giants. So this is more than a millennium after the Epic of Gilgamesh
was written in a cadien. That's how firmly Gilgamesh is a giant and that memory was held.
Yep, yep.
That's right.
Susamic.
sense Michael? Yes, that answered my question. All right, well, thank you for calling. We're always ready to talk about giants.
Sister Ruall. Thank you all. That's a really appreciate it. Thanks for calling Michael. Okay, we're going to take one more caller
and it's Pedro from Wisconsin. Pedro, are you there? We can hear you. Welcome to the Lord of Spirits, Pedro.
Thank God, long time caller for some listener.
I appreciate you to take my question.
I am. Yeah, what's your question,
Pedro? Yeah, I wanted to ask about the
sort of the movements to the intermediate
state. What that looks like or I guess
maybe not looks like looks might be the
wrong word. I don't know this is kind of
what the third half of our show is about.
So yeah, what does it look like to a
mantish shrimp? That's the real question.
Or a bat.
So uh uh
sort of the nature of that, I guess, the journey, right?
You know, the departure of the soul, the, I guess, the,
the initial judgment and, and the role that, you know,
our guardian angel plays in that, the role that the saints play
in that, you know, we have a prayer complying where we ask
the Thelotokos to guide our soul when we depart.
And so I'm just sort of curious about what, what that's all about.
Yeah.
Well, we are going to talk about that a little bit in the third half, but particularly maybe
the questions about angels and demons and, you know, guiding along the way.
I don't know what do you think, Father?
Right.
There's our tradition has that there's a 40 day journey or journey corresponding to a 40
day period that the soul takes.
Yeah, it's not like 40, 24 hour periods.
Right.
And the soul is aided in that journey by the prayers of the faithful and by the prayers of
the saints.
This was an attempt by you to troche and horse toll houses onto my show.
You're a bad person and I hope you're ashamed of yourself.
We should add that Pedro, we should add that Pedro is is one of Father Stevens'
advisees in the St. Stephen's program.
So again, this is someone that we know.
And you should know better.
Frankly, it's okay Pedro.
We still love it.
I don't know if that helps at all but we are...
about to actually talk about crossing over that river.
So that should be pretty interesting to you.
Yeah, you know, that is, uh, that is helpful.
Okay, and I look forward to hearing the third half.
Alright, thank you very much for calling, Pedro.
Okay, further ado.
Yes, third half.
Exactly.
Alright, well, you know, when I saw that Giants call in there,
I mean, we do have that standing rule.
So yes, yes, yes.
Yeah.
And I want to add a rule about ass
projection calls, but just in general. Oh, and anything else
tangentially connected to major at games automatically,
especially if Ed himself calls in because I think he's dead.
So yeah, so now we're down to waterways. Right, right. I mean,
which we've already mentioned a couple. Yeah, I mean, you know,
most ancient mythologies in order to get into the end of
world there's some kind of water that you have to cross.
right so you know I always think about in Greek religion and by that I mean Greek
paganism you know when someone's being buried they put that coin on the tongue and that
coin is so that they can pay the ferry right so they can get across the river sticks and
make their way in.
Otherwise they just have to hang out on the shore which yeah yeah and I don't know what
Karen does with the money.
Yeah right.
I mean does he, what does he spend that? I mean who is he?
Yeah, I don't know. Yeah, he's just hoarding it somewhere. It's a good
So well the underworld is a place where there's hordes of gold coins and stuff as we know right and so you've got you got the River Sticks
Which you know if you fall into it you kind of
Dispers kind of thing
Diffuse
Unless you're a kill he's right. Okay, I think I get well he just got dipped dipped. Okay. Yeah, right. He was dropped
Right that made him immortal except we missed the heel that he was being held by
Bye.
which is a rookie mistake as somebody who's baptized some babies.
That's poor form.
You got to get a little bit.
So there's this idea that there's this potential destruction in entry.
So in the Egyptian stories, especially in the middle kingdom, this is the Sea of Reads.
If you're going to Grethor, because you're a Klingon and you died, you're on the road of the damned.
And uh
That's that that sales you there.
Because you died in dishonor.
So that's that's another river, right?
Or waterway that we have.
And then there's there's another one, the Akchur and River that actually sort of empties into a lake.
Notice the Akchuruzian lake.
Yeah, this is not one is not quite as well known.
I think at least here here in American culture as the River sticks.
but it doesn't get mentioned
in several places.
Yeah, it's actually more relevant religiously
than the River Sticks.
And not the River, the Lake, the Asher, the Lake.
And there is an actual lake in Northwest Greece.
Yes, right. We looked it up on the map.
In the Northwest.
Yeah, that you could go visit on holiday, if you'd like.
Again, why would you do that?
Yeah, I don't know.
It's like the people go skiing on Mount Hermann.
Bye.
How did you do that?
But it's actually been identified
with several different lakes, what in Italy?
And that's because as we've talked about,
various lakes can be being the atcherusia lake
at different times, the lake of the underworld.
And this water, like another river,
we're gonna talk about the,
well, we'll talk about it now, the leafy,
is associated generally with forgetfulness.
So in Plato's, Plato of course believed
the trail.
migration of souls more commonly known as reincarnation. And so this is where your soul would get dipped
in in Hades to sort of forget about the details, the detail memories of your former life.
You'd retain some knowledge of the world of forms like mathematical realities and these kind of
things, but your detailed memories of your past life would be wiped out. And if you were a
you could come back as a lobster or something.
So it's interesting to me that the bit of knowledge you keep is math.
I don't know how that works, but.
Well, Plato was big on the math.
He was probably a no-fagorean.
This was Aristotle's big critique of Plato actually was that he argued that first principles
could not ultimately be derived from mathematics because mathematics couldn't justify its own
first principles.
any one I
think. Yeah, free-graven cereal, the metaphysics lambda. But so Play-Doh has this, this
like performing this function of sort of purifying from the mind from the previous life, to
get a new one. And so then we start seeing it pop up in Jewish and Christian literature.
So one example of this is in the Greek life of Adam and Eve, where after Adam and Eve.
have been expelled from paradise. They repent. The Sun and the Moon offer incense and join
their prayers. It repenting with them and the stars and creation, repents. And as a result
of that repentance, Adam is taken and washed or baptized in that Jerusalem lake.
Right. That's just crazy. But fast. I mean, that's. Wow. Yeah. Right. Right.
and so there
And the most important work of this Asia that you've never heard of
is called the Apocalypse of Paul, which was translated into a variety of languages,
including Latin as the Visio Polly, and the Latin version became particularly
popular and important for medieval and Renaissance literature.
But in the Apocalypse of Paul, St. Paul is taken on a sort of, like we talked about,
this astral projection.
to our heaven and the heavens and the underworld to see everything.
And to reveal that through St. Paul.
And when he comes to the Atcherusia Lake, the city of God has been established on top of
it.
On top of the water.
That's the water is still in the habit.
The lake is now so still right again. It's this triumph over chaos right or
to even primordial chaos of the water.
It's now so flat you can build something on it.
And the city of God is built on it,
and those souls that are going into the city of God
are purified in the waters of the Atcherusian lake
on the way.
And there's a version of this.
There's very clearly a version of the same text,
but Saint Paul has been switched out
for the Theotokos.
Yes.
this apocalyptic vision.
And Dante actually refers to that in the inferno.
At one point, Virgil refers to the time
that the Theotokos came to visit.
Wow.
The version came to visit.
And he's referring to this version of the Visio Polly
that had the Theotokos.
Yeah.
And just to reference another piece of medieval literature
that I know that a lot of our listeners love,
in Beowulf, the house that Grendel lives in,
is early familiar, early-
similar to some of the language that's in the apocalypse of Paul. So there you go.
Because that's where demons live is the underworld. So the fifth and final river is the
the Kokidas, which is associated with woe and sadness and moracy and Robert's word and Manchester
England. All of that. So true.
But the importance. The
the rivers as we have these five rivers and unlike the four rivers that flow out from paradise,
that flow out from the mountain, these five rivers, one of which is a river of fire, pour down into
the pit. Yeah, right. Yeah, it's a big sort of pit. So it's a people flowing out and providing life,
right? It's sort of parasitic and taking that life and taking it away. Okay, so let's talk about
a piece of underworld architecture.
And with that, we're gonna complete our conversation this evening.
There's a palace down there.
What's that all about?
There's a castle.
Yeah.
Yeah, why would you build a castle in the underworld?
Although, you know, if some of you kids out there play Minecraft,
you can literally do that now.
You can build castles.
And they call it the nether in Minecraft.
But, I mean, when my kids, so my kids,
they do play Minecraft once in a while.
And I saw them building down in the nether.
I'm like, are you guys on the-
underworld? They're like, what? But it is. It's really kind of curious. So yes, there's a
castle. There's a palace down in the underworld. And it's kind of funny that it should be there
on the one hand, why would you want to rule in the underworld? Like, you know, there's multiple
mythologies, right, that where a defeated God gets kind of cast down into the underworld.
know it's like it's like in the medieval period you know your
You're defeated brother or uncle or whoever.
Because he's still royal blood, he's still family.
You give him some really terrible estate.
There were nothing grows.
And he's, you know, he gets to have a piece of desert
or something like that, right?
Or a bunch of other gods could spire and murder you.
Yes, right.
You end up there, but at least you're the boss.
Yeah.
You're the king of the trash heap.
You know?
Yeah.
Right, except one.
Right who
seems to he wins and he goes down there. Well, with bail, it's sort of the same thing,
but he there's a spin. Right. Yes. Right. There's bet to do that. Right. It's, right.
So bail, right goes up against goes up against yam the most high god and totally wins. Totally
wins. And then he just happens to end up in the underworld and just happens to run into
to moat the god of death and again totally
wins. Totally wins. And decides, hey, this is where I want to build my palaces down here
with the dead. Yeah, right. Absolutely. Believe it was, what's the live on the mountain of
the gods. Plus. Yeah. Those guys they didn't appreciate me anyway. I'm going to come down
here in the trashy. And so this is super important because there's actually, this is actually
referenced in the scripture.
bail ruling from the underworld.
It's referenced in Isaiah, it's referenced in Ezekiel.
And so in those stories, it's not only,
at next episode, we're gonna talk about some more of this,
there's literal ridicule directed at bail,
because bail is the devil in the Old Testament,
literal mockery.
Yeah, not a very ecumenical kind of language.
It's not just like, hey, we're gonna correct the record,
you actually lost, and that's how you ended up
the other world.
It's like, haha, like nice try with your lame claims that you wanted that to happen, right?
Like, your loser, you know, no time for losers. We are the champions, right?
That's it, right? Yeah, like it's a little...
Speaking of Zora Astrianism, yeah, we'll talk about that more next time.
So, what of the prominent features of this palace?
If you know one thing about this palace, or if you've heard one thing, whether it be
having heard it from reading mythologically or the way it's constantly referenced in our orthodox
himnography, is that it has brazen gates. Right. Gates made a brass, which is counterintuitive.
Right? Because if you put me to cage made of brass, I'm going to break out pretty fast.
Yeah, because brass is not that great as a
as a metal.
Right.
Like, it's not.
I, as a child destroyed many of brass lamp.
We'll put it that way.
Right.
Like, right.
Brass gates are not really good gates.
Right.
So it's kind of counter-intuitive, right?
Why it would be brazen.
And so to get into why, and what this is, why would it be brazen, Father Stephen?
We get to talk about giants.
Yeah.
Again.
Right.
So it goes back to the bronze age.
to the deolithic.
We're not going to go over this time.
No, no.
Yeah, it goes back to the Bronze Age.
So Bronze is, as everybody remembers, because we all took metallurgy, right?
Well, chemistry once put it back.
Bronze is an alloy of copper and tin.
And it's a good, strong metal.
It's great for making weapons out of and armor.
And it becomes the definition of technology in that period.
So this is what, two or three thousand years BC?
Right.
Alright, twat-
500 all the way up to, you know, the toward the end of the second line.
Yeah, yeah.
And, and, and, you know, just to give you some sense of what civilization was like at that
time, the copper that they used in this alloy came from Cyprus.
And as I learned today, that's part of the origin of the name of the, of the island of Cyprus.
Actually, I refers to copper.
I did not know that until today.
And the tin that's used comes from Afghanistan.
If you look at your map of the Middle East, these places are not right.
next to each other, it has to be shipped. So there's a lot of transportation happening. There's a
whole bunch of economy occurring in order to make these things, in order to make bronze, a lot of
shipping. I mean, a lot. We're talking big amounts of material in order to be able to make
weapons and armor. You know, those are the most important parts of bronze technology. But there's
those stuff like that. And then there's what's called the Bronze Age Clubs. Right. Well, in the
height of the Bronze Age era.
Right. Oh yeah right.
the old world order was so
connected. Right. Yes. I
love this example. Yes.
Hamarabi, for example, really
liked the Creighton style of
leather sandals that the
Maiceneans used. Right. He had
affection for them. And so he
got them shipped to him. So
he could wear his Creighton
sandals. Hamarabi, the Babylonian
But how about we're obviously important?
Ramarabi was one of the Martu, the Martu where this group who came from basically what's
now Western Syria, Lebanon, Northwest, Northeast Palestine, and Concord, Sumer and Akkad.
The Martu are referred to as the Amarites in the Old Testament.
So Amarites are...
Definitely.
Yeah, that's right.
So, Srebrenorg was the last of the Refereeim in his pal.
was Cihon king of the Amorites.
And what the Martus claimed to power,
including Amorabi, what they claimed to power
was that they held the secret knowledge from before the flood.
The knowledge that had come from the gods,
the secret knowledge that had come from the gods
before the flood, they still had it.
And so they themselves then have this, right?
Not just as giants, but this connection
to the pre-flood.
demonic spirits, that sort of their claim to power and fame. And so bronze is used after
the Bronze Age collapse once we get into the Iron Age, right? So we're not going to
talk about the dating of the Exodus because that's also something that borrows me to tears.
But the Bronze Age collapse probably happened after it, or was in the midst of happening.
But there's debate there too and it's sort of in mid.
Yeah, anyway, where exactly you peg the Bronze Age collapse is also a big debate because
it didn't happen.
It didn't happen in one day, right?
Yeah.
You see people's invasions, the Philistines receive people's.
Anyway.
So bronze after that becomes this symbol of that old world order.
Yeah, the ancient world.
Ancient wisdom.
Yeah.
Right.
And so when we get Goliath's armor, when we get Goliath's kit, sort of describe to us in
all this excruciating detail for Samuel or for
kingdoms you might wonder why, right? Who cares how much his broad spearhead
weighed? How, you know, and if you're learning Hebrew, you have to learn all
these weird words you've never seen before because most of them are Greek
loanwords. They're mycenaean loanwords describe his helmet, the Kobad stuff.
So because it's describing them, number one, it's all this Greek style mycenaean
stuff from before the collapse, but it's also bronze from before the collapse.
Wrinkle, I-
is really tall. So this is all hit hit. This guy's a giant, right?
This guy's a devil. This guy. Yeah.
Yeah, yeah.
Right. So that's the backing then for this idea that the gates of the palace of
Hades are made of brass because what is brass? Yeah, not bronze, but brass,
because what is brass? It is the the plethora of bronze world.
Right, it's the fake cheap imitation. It's shiny and pretty, but it doesn't do the job. So, so by just exactly, exactly.
So by describing the gates of Hades as being made of brass, the scripture and our liturgical tradition is basically saying that they're made a flashy junk.
Right. That pretends.
Yeah. That quote, quote, quote, quote, quote, secret knowledge is trash.
All the scare quotes, yes.
snake oil that they're from the demons are trying to sell you snake oil right right the con job yeah yeah right yeah exactly so yeah right and so from the perspective of the old testament and this is really where we're going to pick up next time this palace is the devil's palace this is where he's cast down he's thrown down to the dust to eat the dust of the ground that's the dust that Adam is going to return to he brews is going to refer to him and he was 214 is the devil is the one who holds the
the power of death that he is sort of the Lord of the dead, the ruler of this realm of
the dead, as we come to the close of the Old Testament. And this palace isn't just a
palace, but it's a fortress that's not really keeping people out, but keeping people in.
It's a fortress holding captives, those who, through sin have become captive to death
into the power of the devil.
Yep, yep, exactly.
So, right.
So that's our tour, kind of a real estate tour, as it were.
Of a...
Don't buy?
Yeah, do not buy any...
Yeah, right.
It's not like Minecraft, where there's valuable stuff down there.
You don't want to go there.
Yeah, so, all right.
So what does all this really mean for us?
I mean, again, this show is not just weird, cool, nerdy, Bible stuff.
It actually has a direct relevance to our lives.
and
I mean, God willing, we've mentioned some of those
relevance along the way, but I just want to, you know, in
terms of final comments, I think one of the most
important things to get from this is that the image of the
underworld as it's presented an ancient paganism, and then
it's picked up on in the scripture, right? The scripture
comments on it, it presents it the same image of the
underworld, you know, the afterlife. It is an image that
has no...
No hope, right?
You know, sometimes people talk about various religions, and they say, well, all religions
basically have the same goal.
Everybody's trying to get to heaven.
And there's just different ideas about how you get there.
That's nonsense.
Ancient paganism has no concept of getting to heaven.
A handful of super, super powerful important people might get elevated to go be with the
gods.
Right?
Once in a generation, maybe.
For most people, there is nothing like
that. There is just simply you go to Hades and if you're really bad, then you get to go be with
the Titans down in Tardarus, the Abyss, if you're, you know, really great. You get to be in the
Elision Fields, which again is not that great, but it's way better than being in the Abyss for sure.
And then ancient paganism and some and some Second Temple Judaism has this idea of a kind of
of neutralish space for the people who are just kind of, eh.
But in all those cases,
Is it still the sort of shadowy, forgetting, sad existence, barely existence, right?
That's what ancient peoples understood life after death was about.
That's what they understood it was about.
The difference that Christianity brings is to say not that that image is not true, but
There is a way out.
And that is a revolution. That is huge. It does not get hugeer when what everyone believes about the ancient world, about the ancient understanding of life after death, that this Messiah comes and says,
I'm going to lift you up out of the grave, which it's prophesied all over the old test...
or by the way, it's in the Psalms, it's in lots of places. But then of course comes in fullness and the New Testament.
That's huge, right? And this has connected very much even with the day-to-day experience of the Christian, where our day-to-day experience is about
the forgiveness of God, about repentance so that we can kind of conform ourselves to that forgiveness, to really truly receive it.
That's not an option for pagans. You know, I've said this many times in a lot of different places.
you
If you do something that makes your God mad in the ancient pagan world, then you have either
revenge to look forward to that the God is going to get you or you can attempt to appease
him.
Those are your options.
And you may not even be given the option of appeasement.
You just, you've had it.
But even if you don't particularly offend one of the gods, the hope for the afterlife
is not there is no hope.
There's no hope there's just the shadowy... eh.
existence, you know, and it might even be terrible, right?
But the difference with Christianity is to say that the grave is not the end.
It is not the end that the underworld is not the end
that there is something else. There is a possibility for hope
for being lifted up out of that. And not to give away too much, but
that's what our next episode is going to be about. Father Stephen, final thoughts?
Yeah, we on the show talk a lot about how the modern world and modern humanity has sort
of forgotten about ritual and lost sight of it.
But they haven't forgotten how to profane a time and a space.
They haven't forgotten how to create hell on earth.
If you're around for the 20th century, you should know that.
So
very good at that. And that's because as we said, there is no neutral space. You can declare
yourself secular all you want. You can deny spiritual reality all you want. When you
set out to create your utopia on earth, you're going to create hell. You're going to create
a place that's filled with demons. This was true in the ancient world when homerabi
or fair-
or Samarian Lugal built a kingdom on the back of thousands of slaves and human
sacrifices. This was true when Rome created a wasteland and called it peace. This
was true when Lenin tried it when Hitler tried it when Mao tried it. Any time
anyone tries it. This is the result. This is what happens when we try to create
parat-
under our own power is all we do is create corruption and evil.
Because the opposite, bringing paradise to earth and turning earth into a paradise,
isn't something we do by ourselves. It isn't something we do by techniques.
Not ritual techniques, not artistic techniques, not by tweeting the right hashtags
for your hashtag activism, not by voting,
not by holding up a sign in a row.
rally, right? God is doing it. God is in the process of turning all of creation into paradise,
into filling all of creation with His presence, into setting everything in order. He's establishing
justice. He's doing it. We don't have to try to do it ourselves through some technique.
When we try, we do the opposite. All we need to do is to get on board with and participate
in what God is doing.
What he's been doing.
since before I was born, what he'll still be doing most likely unless Christ appears after
I'm dead, maybe for a long time.
But we need to be a part of what God is doing, and we do that through the means we've been
discussing, right?
If you want to change the world, if you want to transform a little part of the world into
paradise, serve the liturgy, attend the liturgy, pray in your home.
Make your home a sacred space
through prayer
Make everywhere you go a sacred space make every encounter you have in every interaction you have
All of your web of relationships to the creation around you make those filled with love and mercy and gentleness and kindness
Right because when we do that
That's when God is acting through us and that's when actual change happens. That's when paradise actually comes to earth
Earth.
That's when space and time actually becomes sacred and everything is transfigured and transformed.
So that's my final thought.
Thanks. Well, that is our show for today. Thank you everyone for listening.
If you didn't get a chance to call in during the live broadcast, we would still love to hear
from you either via email at Lordofspiritsadanationfaith.com or you can message us at our Lord of Spirits
podcast.
Facebook page, we read everything but can't respond to everything but we do
say what you send for possible use in future episodes. And join us for our
live broadcasts on the second and fourth Thursdays of the month at 7 p.m. Eastern
4 p.m. Pacific. And if you are on Facebook you can like our page and join our
discussion group, leave reviews and ratings everywhere but most importantly
please share this show with a friend whom you know is going to love it. And finally
be sure to go to ancientfaith.com, stroke support and
and help make sure we and lots of other AFR
podcasters stay on the air.
Thank you very much, and God bless you.
You've been listening to the Lord of Spirits with Orthodox Christian priests, Father
Andrews
Stephen Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung, a listener supported presentation of Ancient Faith Radio.
And I beheld and I heard the voice of many angels round about the throne and the beasts and the elders
and the number of them was 10,000 times 10,000 than thousands of thousands,
saying with a loud voice worthy as the land that was slain to receive power and riches and wisdom
and strength and honor and glory and blessing. Revelation Chapter
5 versus 11 through 12.